<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>File:Introductory Physics fig 3.6.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>152</id>
    <revision>
      <id>904390</id>
      <parentid>900283</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-06-20T08:58:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Webaware</username>
        <id>27565</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>licensing</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Introductory Physics, figure 3.6 Copyright 1998, 2000, 2001, 2003 David J. Raymond, under GNU FDL

==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>szxwvo7csjh70j2a74rw1bsvepi3ana</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Introductory Physics fig 3.7.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>153</id>
    <revision>
      <id>904391</id>
      <parentid>900284</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-06-20T08:59:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Webaware</username>
        <id>27565</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>licensing</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Introductory Physics, figure 3.7 Copyright 1998, 2000, 2001, 2003 David J. Raymond, under GNU FDL

==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>aopl6wqoeucnkym9lzutrz2to1f7fh9</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Introductory Physics fig 3.9.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>154</id>
    <revision>
      <id>904393</id>
      <parentid>900287</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-06-20T09:00:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Webaware</username>
        <id>27565</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>licensing</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Introductory Physics, figure 3.9 Copyright 1998, 2000, 2001, 2003 David J. Raymond, under GNU FDL

==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>5hh24996yzmp7chbe79qil6qofam24e</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Introductory Physics fig 3.8.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>155</id>
    <revision>
      <id>904392</id>
      <parentid>900285</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-06-20T08:59:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Webaware</username>
        <id>27565</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>licensing</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Introductory Physics, figure 3.8 Copyright 1998, 2000, 2001, 2003 David J. Raymond, under GNU FDL

==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>omqn9tpk7denkm58al9gygmu652y5ap</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Introductory Physics fig 3.10.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>156</id>
    <revision>
      <id>904378</id>
      <parentid>900271</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-06-20T08:52:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Webaware</username>
        <id>27565</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>licensing</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Introductory Physics, figure 3.10 Copyright 1998, 2000, 2001, 2003 David J. Raymond, under GNU FDL

==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>10qpqeoqx2ot2jg2vb8w0g199llf3g2</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Introductory Physics fig 3.11.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>157</id>
    <revision>
      <id>904379</id>
      <parentid>900272</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-06-20T08:53:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Webaware</username>
        <id>27565</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>licensing</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Introductory Physics, figure 3.11 Copyright 1998, 2000, 2001, 2003 David J. Raymond, under GNU FDL

==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>nwh1osohp9mzsz3gzryglv3tva0n3d7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Introductory Physics fig 3.12.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>158</id>
    <revision>
      <id>904380</id>
      <parentid>900273</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-06-20T08:53:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Webaware</username>
        <id>27565</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>licensing</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Introductory Physics, figure 3.12 Copyright 1998, 2000, 2001, 2003 David J. Raymond, under GNU FDL

==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>3wnupc1w7b1nq1vx1k6fe0nysq3bl1j</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Introductory Physics fig 3.13.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>159</id>
    <revision>
      <id>904381</id>
      <parentid>900274</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-06-20T08:54:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Webaware</username>
        <id>27565</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>licensing</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Introductory Physics, figure 3.13 Copyright 1998, 2000, 2001, 2003 David J. Raymond, under GNU FDL

==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>q6iotrjakg7wi4wriq0fqgw84ymv663</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Introductory Physics fig 3.14.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>160</id>
    <revision>
      <id>904382</id>
      <parentid>900275</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-06-20T08:54:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Webaware</username>
        <id>27565</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>licensing</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Introductory Physics, figure 3.14 Copyright 1998, 2000, 2001, 2003 David J. Raymond, under GNU FDL

==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>pbwf7b81xhly4701z35iccisr97r9p7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Introductory Physics fig 3.15.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>161</id>
    <revision>
      <id>904383</id>
      <parentid>900276</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-06-20T08:55:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Webaware</username>
        <id>27565</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>licensing</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Introductory Physics, figure 3.15 Copyright 1998, 2000, 2001, 2003 David J. Raymond, under GNU FDL

==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>eda9uzs86q0ymvsy1wsr3cexr8r3yv8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Introductory Physics fig 3.16.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>162</id>
    <revision>
      <id>904384</id>
      <parentid>900277</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-06-20T08:55:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Webaware</username>
        <id>27565</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>licensing</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Introductory Physics, figure 3.16 Copyright 1998, 2000, 2001, 2003 David J. Raymond, under GNU FDL

==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>o3k4ejvkq5svblbkevrnaz5kedu0z94</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Introductory Physics fig 3.17.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>163</id>
    <revision>
      <id>904385</id>
      <parentid>900278</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-06-20T08:56:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Webaware</username>
        <id>27565</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>licensing</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Introductory Physics, figure 3.17 Copyright 1998, 2000, 2001, 2003 David J. Raymond, under GNU FDL

==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>5qkbeplcsm2oe1tx1bnua8cbztmwuh2</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Introductory Physics fig 4.1.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>164</id>
    <revision>
      <id>904394</id>
      <parentid>900288</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-06-20T09:00:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Webaware</username>
        <id>27565</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>licensing</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Introductory Physics, figure 4.1 Copyright 1998, 2000, 2001, 2003 David J. Raymond, under GNU FDL

==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>oarkno3nzizfihgx4k993e1p17ymtty</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Introductory Physics fig 4.10.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>172</id>
    <revision>
      <id>904395</id>
      <parentid>900291</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-06-20T09:01:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Webaware</username>
        <id>27565</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>licensing</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Introductory Physics, figure 4.10 Copyright 1998, 2000, 2001, 2003 David J. Raymond, under GNU FDL

==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>fyxp63fvk2yxawyp14vklsjon7ie47d</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Special Relativity/Spacetime</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>174</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2578645</id>
      <parentid>2578310</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-11-04T18:24:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>RobinH</username>
        <id>8141</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* A spacetime representation of the Lorentz Transformation */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Special Relativity}}

==The modern approach to relativity==

Although the special theory of relativity was first proposed by Einstein in 1905, the modern approach to the theory depends upon the concept of a four-dimensional universe, that was first proposed by Hermann Minkowski in 1908. This approach uses the concept of invariance to explore the types of coordinate systems that are required to provide a full physical description of the location and extent of things. 

The modern theory of special relativity begins with the concept of &quot;length&quot;.  In everyday experience, it seems that the length of objects remains the same no matter how they are rotated or moved from place to place.  We think that the simple length of a thing is &quot;invariant&quot;.  However, as is shown in the illustrations below, what we are actually suggesting is that length seems to be invariant in a three-dimensional coordinate system.

[[Image:Coord1b.gif]]

The length of a thing in a two-dimensional coordinate system is given by Pythagoras's theorem:

:&lt;math&gt; x^2 + y^2 = h^2 &lt;/math&gt;

This two-dimensional length is not invariant if the thing is tilted out of the two-dimensional plane.  In everyday life, a three-dimensional coordinate system seems to describe the length fully.  The length is given by the three-dimensional version of  Pythagoras's theorem:

:&lt;math&gt; h^2 = x^2 + y^2 + z^2 &lt;/math&gt;

The derivation of this formula is shown in the illustration below.

[[image:Coord2.gif]]

It seems that, provided all the directions in which a thing can be tilted or arranged are represented within a coordinate system, then the coordinate system can fully represent the length of a thing. However, it is clear that things may also be changed over a period of time. Time is another direction in which things can be arranged.  This is shown in the following diagram:

[[image:Coord3.gif]]

The length of a straight line between two events in space and time is called a &quot;space-time interval&quot;.

In 1908 Hermann Minkowski pointed out that if things could be rearranged in time, then the universe might be four-dimensional. He boldly suggested that Einstein's recently-discovered theory of Special Relativity was a consequence of this four-dimensional universe. He proposed that the space-time interval might be related to space and time by Pythagoras' theorem in four dimensions:

:&lt;math&gt; s^2 = x^2 + y^2 + z^2 + (ict)^2 &lt;/math&gt;

Where ''i'' is the [[w: imaginary unit | imaginary unit]] (sometimes imprecisely called &lt;math&gt;\sqrt{-1}&lt;/math&gt;), ''c'' is a constant, and ''t'' is the time interval spanned by the space-time interval, ''s''.  The symbols ''x'', ''y'' and ''z'' represent displacements in space along the corresponding axes.  In this equation, the 'second' becomes just another unit of length. &lt;!-- see discussion --&gt; In the same way as centimetres and inches are both units of length related by centimetres = 'conversion constant' times inches, metres and seconds are related by metres = 'conversion constant' times seconds. The conversion constant, ''c'' has a value of about 300,000,000 meters per second. Now &lt;math&gt;i^2&lt;/math&gt; is equal to minus one, so the space-time interval is given by:

:&lt;math&gt; s^2 = x^2 + y^2 + z^2 - (ct)^2 &lt;/math&gt;

Minkowski's use of the imaginary unit has been superseded by the use of advanced geometry that uses a tool known as the &quot;metric tensor&quot;.  The metric tensor permits the existence of &quot;real&quot; time and the negative sign in the expression for the square of the space-time interval originates in the way that distance changes with time when the curvature of spacetime is analysed (see advanced text). We now use real time but Minkowski's original equation for the square of the interval survives so that the space-time interval is still given by:

:&lt;math&gt; s^2 = x^2 + y^2 + z^2 - (ct)^2 &lt;/math&gt;

Space-time intervals are difficult to imagine; they extend between one place and time and another place and time, so the velocity of the thing that travels along the interval is already determined for a given observer.  

If the universe is four-dimensional, then the space-time interval will be invariant, rather than spatial length. Whoever measures a particular space-time interval will get the same value, no matter how fast they are travelling. In physical terminology the invariance of the spacetime interval is a type of '''Lorentz Invariance'''.  The invariance of the spacetime interval has some dramatic consequences.

The first consequence is the prediction that if a thing is travelling at a velocity of ''c'' metres per second, then all observers, no matter how fast they are travelling, will measure the same velocity for the thing.  The velocity ''c'' will be a universal constant. This is explained below.  

When an object is travelling at ''c'', the space time interval is '''zero''', this is shown below:

: The distance travelled by an object moving at velocity ''v'' in the ''x'' direction for ''t'' seconds is:  

: &lt;math&gt; x = vt &lt;/math&gt;

:If there is no motion in the ''y'' or ''z'' directions the space-time interval is  &lt;math&gt; s^2 = x^2 + 0 + 0 - (ct)^2 &lt;/math&gt;

: So: &lt;math&gt; s^2 = (vt)^2 - (ct)^2 &lt;/math&gt;

: But when the velocity ''v'' equals ''c'':

: &lt;math&gt; s^2 = (ct)^2 - (ct)^2 &lt;/math&gt;

:And hence the space time interval &lt;math&gt; s^2 = (ct)^2 - (ct)^2 = 0 &lt;/math&gt;

A space-time interval of zero only occurs when the velocity is ''c'' (if x&gt;0). All observers observe the same space-time interval so when observers observe something with a space-time interval of zero, they all observe it to have a velocity of ''c'', no matter how fast they are moving themselves.  

The universal constant, ''c'', is known for historical reasons as the &quot;speed of light in a vacuum&quot;.  In the first decade or two after the formulation of Minkowski's approach many physicists, although supporting Special Relativity, expected that light might not travel at exactly ''c'', but might travel at very nearly ''c''. There are now few physicists who believe that light in a vacuum does not propagate at ''c''.

The second consequence of the invariance of the space-time interval is that clocks will appear to go slower on objects that are moving relative to you.  Suppose there are two people, Bill and John, on separate planets that are moving away from each other. John draws a graph of Bill's motion through space and time.  This is shown in the illustration below:

[[image:Coord5.gif]]
 
Being on planets, both Bill and John think they are stationary, and just moving through time.  John spots that Bill is moving through what John calls space, as well as time, when Bill thinks he is moving through time alone.  Bill would also draw the same conclusion about John's motion.  To John, it is as if Bill's time axis is leaning over in the direction of travel and to Bill, it is as if John's time axis leans over.

: John calculates the length of Bill's space-time interval as: 

: &lt;math&gt;s^2 = (vt)^2 - (ct)^2&lt;/math&gt; 

: whereas Bill doesn't think he has travelled in space, so writes: 

: &lt;math&gt;s^2 = (0)^2 - (cT)^2&lt;/math&gt; 

The space-time interval, &lt;math&gt;s^2&lt;/math&gt;, is invariant. It has the same value for all observers, no matter who measures it or how they are moving in a straight line. Bill's &lt;math&gt; s^2&lt;/math&gt; equals John's &lt;math&gt; s^2&lt;/math&gt; so:

: &lt;math&gt;(0)^2 - (cT)^2 = (vt)^2 - (ct)^2&lt;/math&gt; 

: and 

: &lt;math&gt;-(cT)^2 = (vt)^2 - (ct)^2&lt;/math&gt;  

: hence

: &lt;math&gt;t = T / \sqrt{1 - v^2/c^2}&lt;/math&gt;.

So, if John sees Bill measure a time interval of 1 second (&lt;math&gt;T = 1&lt;/math&gt;) between two ticks of a clock that is at rest in Bill's frame, John will find that his own clock measures between these same ticks an interval &lt;math&gt;t&lt;/math&gt;, called '''coordinate time''', which is greater than one second. It is said that clocks in motion slow down, relative to those on observers at rest. This is known as &quot;relativistic time dilation of a moving clock&quot;. The time that is measured in the rest frame of the clock (in Bill's frame) is called the '''proper time''' of the clock.

John will also observe measuring rods at rest on Bill's planet to be shorter than his own measuring rods, in the direction of motion. This is a prediction known as &quot;relativistic length contraction of a moving rod&quot;. If the length of a rod at rest on Bill's planet is &lt;math&gt;X&lt;/math&gt;, then we call this quantity the proper length of the rod. The length &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt; of that same rod as measured from John's planet, is called '''coordinate length''', and given by

:&lt;math&gt;x = X \sqrt{1 - v^2/c^2}&lt;/math&gt;.

This equation can be derived directly and validly from the time dilation result with the assumption that the speed of light is constant.  

The last consequence is that clocks will appear to be out of phase with each other along the length of a moving object.  This means that if one observer sets up a line of clocks that are all synchronised so they all read the same time, then another observer who is moving along the line at high speed will see the clocks all reading different times.  In other words observers who are moving relative to each other see different events as '''simultaneous'''.  This effect is known as '''Relativistic Phase''' or the '''Relativity of Simultaneity'''. Relativistic phase is often overlooked by students of Special Relativity, but if it is understood then phenomena such as the twin paradox are easier to understand.

The way that clocks go out of phase along the line of travel can be calculated from the concepts of the invariance of the space-time interval and length contraction. 

[[Image:relphasesimple.gif]]

In the diagram above John is conventionally stationary. Distances between two points according to Bill are simple lengths in space (x) all at t=0 whereas John sees Bill's measurement of distance as a combination of a distance (X) and a time interval (T):

:&lt;math&gt;x^2 = X^2 - (cT)^2&lt;/math&gt;

Notice that the quantities represented by capital letters are proper lengths and times and in this example refer to John's measurements.

Bill's distance, x, is the length that he would obtain for things that John believes to be X metres in length. For Bill it is John who has rods that contract in the direction of motion so Bill's determination &quot;x&quot; of John's distance &quot;X&quot; is given from:

:&lt;math&gt;x = X \sqrt{1 - v^2/c^2}&lt;/math&gt;.

This relationship between proper and coordinate lengths was seen above to relate Bill's proper lengths to John's measurements.  It also applies to how Bill observes John's proper lengths. 

:&lt;math&gt;x = X \sqrt{1 - v^2/c^2}&lt;/math&gt; 

:Thus &lt;math&gt;x^2 = X^2 - (v^2/c^2)X^2&lt;/math&gt;

:So: &lt;math&gt;(cT)^2 = (v^2/c^2)X^2&lt;/math&gt;

:And &lt;math&gt;cT = (v/c)X&lt;/math&gt;

:So: &lt;B&gt;&lt;math&gt;T = (v/c^2)X &lt;/math&gt;&lt;/B&gt;

Clocks that are synchronised for one observer go out of phase along the line of travel for another observer moving at &lt;math&gt;v&lt;/math&gt; metres per second by :&lt;math&gt;(v/c^2)&lt;/math&gt; seconds for every metre. This is one of the most important results of Special Relativity and should be thoroughly understood by students.

The net effect of the four-dimensional universe is that observers who are in motion relative to you seem to have time coordinates that lean over in the direction of motion and consider things to be simultaneous that are not simultaneous for you.  Spatial lengths in the direction of travel are shortened, because they tip upwards and downwards, relative to the time axis in the direction of travel, akin to a rotation out of three-dimensional space.

[[image:Coord6.gif]]

::[[File:Examp.jpg|right|300x300px|What velocity would cause events A and B to be simultaneous?]]'''Example'''

::An observer records an event A next to herself then an event B a millisecond later and 600 kilometres away.  How fast would another observer need to travel in the direction of event B to record it as simultaneous with event A?

::The phase difference between moving clocks is given by: &lt;math&gt;T = (v/c^2)X &lt;/math&gt;
::The velocity needed to create a phase difference of 10&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt; secs is:

::&lt;math&gt;v =  \frac{10^{-3} \times 3 \times 10^8 \times c}{6 \times 10^{5}}&lt;/math&gt;

::This means that another observer who is travelling at 0.5c relative to the first observer in the direction of the line joining events A and B will consider that these events are simultaneous.


{{clear}}
====Interpreting space-time diagrams====

Great care is needed when interpreting space-time diagrams.  Diagrams present data in two dimensions, and cannot show faithfully how, for instance, a zero length space-time interval appears.

[[image:Coord8.gif]]

It is sometimes mistakenly held that the time dilation and length contraction results only apply for observers at x=0 and t=0. This is untrue.  An inertial frame of reference is defined so that length and time comparisons can be made anywhere within a given reference frame. 

[[Image:relsimul.gif|frame|left|Time dilation applies to time measurements taken between corresponding planes of simultaneity]]
{{clear}}

Time differences in one inertial reference frame can be compared with time differences anywhere in another inertial reference frame provided it is remembered that these differences apply to corresponding pairs of lines or pairs of planes of simultaneous events.

===Spacetime===

[[Image:Introductory Physics fig 4.1.png|frame|Spacetime diagram showing an ''event'', a ''world line'', and a ''line of simultaneity''.]]

In order to gain an understanding of both Galilean and Special Relativity it is important to begin thinking of space and time as being different dimensions of a four-dimensional vector space called spacetime. Actually, since we can't visualize four dimensions very well, it is easiest to start with only one space dimension and the time dimension. The figure shows a graph with time plotted on the vertical axis and the one space dimension plotted on the horizontal axis. An ''event'' is something that occurs at a particular time and a particular point in space. (&quot;Julius X. wrecks his car in Lemitar, NM on 21 June at 6:17 PM.&quot;) A ''world line'' is a plot of the position of some object as a function of time (more properly, the time of the object as a function of position) on a spacetime diagram. Thus, a world line is really a line in spacetime, while an event is a point in spacetime. A horizontal line parallel to the position axis (x-axis) is a ''line of simultaneity''; in Galilean Relativity all events on this line occur simultaneously for all observers. It will be seen that the line of simultaneity differs between Galilean and Special Relativity; in Special Relativity the line of simultaneity depends on the state of motion of the observer.

In a spacetime diagram the slope of a world line has a special meaning. Notice that a vertical world line means that the object it represents does not move -- the velocity is zero. If the object moves to the right, then the world line tilts to the right, and the faster it moves, the more the world line tilts. Quantitatively, we say that
:&lt;math&gt;velocity = \frac{1}{slope~of~world~line} . &lt;/math&gt;(5.1)

Notice that this works for negative slopes and velocities as well as positive ones. If the object changes its velocity with time, then the world line is curved, and the instantaneous velocity at any time is the inverse of the slope of the tangent to the world line at that time.

The hardest thing to realize about spacetime diagrams is that they represent the past, present, and future all in one diagram. Thus, spacetime diagrams don't change with time -- the evolution of physical systems is represented by looking at successive horizontal slices in the diagram at successive times. Spacetime diagrams represent the evolution of events, but they don't evolve themselves.

==The lightcone==

Things that move at the speed of light in our four dimensional universe have surprising properties. If something travels at the speed of light along the x-axis and covers x meters from the origin in t seconds the space-time interval of its path is zero.

&lt;math&gt;s^2 = x^2 - (ct)^2&lt;/math&gt;

but &lt;math&gt; x = ct&lt;/math&gt; so:

&lt;math&gt;s^2 = (ct)^2 - (ct)^2 = 0 &lt;/math&gt;

Extending this result to the general case, if something travels at the speed of light in any direction into or out from the origin it has a space-time interval of 0:

&lt;math&gt;0 = x^2 + y^2 + z^2 - (ct)^2 &lt;/math&gt;

This equation is known as the Minkowski Light Cone Equation. If light were travelling towards the origin then the Light Cone Equation would describe the position and time of emission of all those photons that could be at the origin at a particular instant. If light were travelling away from the origin the equation would describe the position of the photons emitted at a particular instant at any future time 't'.

[[Image:rellightcone.gif]]

At the superficial level the light cone is easy to interpret. Its backward surface represents the path of light rays that strike a point observer at an instant and its forward surface represents the possible paths of rays emitted from the point observer. Things that travel along the surface of the light cone are said to be '''light- like''' and the path taken by such things is known as a '''null geodesic'''.

Events that lie outside the cones are said to be '''space-like''' or, better still '''space separated''' because their space time interval from the observer has the same sign as space (positive according to the convention used here). Events that lie within the cones are said to be '''time-like''' or '''time separated''' because their space-time interval has the same sign as time. 

However, there is more to the light cone than the propagation of light. If the added assumption is made that the speed of light is the maximum possible velocity then events that are space separated cannot affect the observer directly. Events within the backward cone can have affected the observer so the backward cone is known as the &quot;affective past&quot; and the observer can affect events in the forward cone hence the forward cone is known as the &quot;affective future&quot;. 

The assumption that the speed of light is the maximum velocity for all communications is neither inherent in nor required by four dimensional geometry although the speed of light is indeed the maximum velocity for objects if the principle of '''causality''' is to be preserved by physical theories (ie: that causes precede effects).

==The Lorentz transformation equations ==
The discussion so far has involved the comparison of interval measurements (time intervals and space intervals) between two observers. The observers might also want to compare more general sorts of measurement such as the time and position of a single event that is recorded by both of them. The equations that describe how each observer describes the other's recordings in this circumstance are known as the Lorentz Transformation Equations.  (Note that the symbols below signify coordinates.)

[[Image:rellorentz.gif]]

The table below shows the Lorentz Transformation Equations.

&lt;TABLE BORDER CELLSPACING=1 BORDERCOLOR=&quot;#000000&quot; CELLPADDING=9&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD WIDTH=&quot;49%&quot; VALIGN=&quot;TOP&quot;&gt;
&lt;P&gt;&lt;FONT SIZE=2&gt;&lt;math&gt;x^' = \frac{x - vt}{\sqrt{(1 - v^2/c^2)}}&lt;/math&gt;
&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;/TD&gt;
&lt;TD WIDTH=&quot;51%&quot; VALIGN=&quot;TOP&quot;&gt;
&lt;FONT SIZE=2&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;math&gt;x = \frac{x^' + vt^'}{\sqrt{(1 - v^2/c^2)}}&lt;/math&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;/TD&gt;
&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD WIDTH=&quot;49%&quot; VALIGN=&quot;TOP&quot;&gt;
&lt;FONT SIZE=2&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;math&gt;y^' = y&lt;/math&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;/TD&gt;
&lt;TD WIDTH=&quot;51%&quot; VALIGN=&quot;TOP&quot;&gt;
&lt;FONT SIZE=2&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;math&gt;y = y^'&lt;/math&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;/TD&gt;
&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD WIDTH=&quot;49%&quot; VALIGN=&quot;TOP&quot;&gt;
&lt;FONT SIZE=2&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;math&gt;z^' = z&lt;/math&gt;
&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;/TD&gt;
&lt;TD WIDTH=&quot;51%&quot; VALIGN=&quot;TOP&quot;&gt;
&lt;FONT SIZE=2&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;math&gt;z = z^'&lt;/math&gt;
&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;/TD&gt;
&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD WIDTH=&quot;49%&quot; VALIGN=&quot;TOP&quot; HEIGHT=48&gt;
&lt;FONT SIZE=2&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;math&gt;t^' = \frac{t - (v/c^2)x}{\sqrt{(1 - v^2/c^2)}}&lt;/math&gt;&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;/TD&gt;
&lt;TD WIDTH=&quot;51%&quot; VALIGN=&quot;TOP&quot; HEIGHT=48&gt;
&lt;FONT SIZE=2&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;math&gt;t = \frac{t^' + (v/c^2)x^'}{\sqrt{(1 - v^2/c^2)}}&lt;/math&gt;
&lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;/TD&gt;
&lt;/TR&gt;
&lt;/TABLE&gt;

See [[Special Relativity/Mathematical Appendix#Mathematics_of_the_Lorentz_Transformation_Equations|mathematical derivation of Lorentz transformation]].

Notice how the phase ( (&lt;FONT SIZE=2&gt;v/c&lt;SUP&gt;2&lt;/SUP&gt;)x )&lt;/FONT&gt; is important and how these formulae for absolute time and position of a joint event differ from the formulae for intervals.

== A spacetime representation of the Lorentz Transformation ==

[[File:Rellorent.png|thumb|right|Spacetime representation of Lorentz Transformation for time]] Bill and John are moving at a relative velocity, v, and synchronise clocks when they pass each other. Both Bill and John observe an event along Bill's direction of motion. What times will Bill and John assign to the event? It was shown above that the relativistic phase was given by: &lt;math&gt;vx/c^2&lt;/math&gt;. This means that Bill will observe an extra amount of time elapsing on John's time axis due to the position of the event. Taking phase into account and using the time dilation equation Bill is going to observe that the amount of time his own clocks measure can be compared with John's clocks using:

&lt;math&gt;T = \frac {t - vx/c^2}{\sqrt{1 - v^2/c^2}}&lt;/math&gt;.

This relationship between the times of a common event between reference frames is known as the Lorentz Transformation Equation for time.

&lt;div class=&quot;noprint&quot;&gt;
[[Special_Relativity/Simultaneity, time dilation and length contraction|Continue]]
&lt;/div&gt;</text>
      <sha1>r3ocg0s7vb59m73gh8aft32hbe0cwdq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Waves/Waves in one Dimension</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>175</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2611071</id>
      <parentid>2611070</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-02-22T09:04:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>RDR</username>
        <id>769669</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">This page is missing a graph. &quot;Graphing this out we get [graph] From figure one we can&quot; There should be a graph where I placed the word [graph].  [[User:MicScoTho|MicScoTho]]

I think that

:&lt;math&gt;y=a\ \sin \left(\frac{2\pi x}{\lambda}  - \frac{2\pi t}{T} +\alpha \right)&lt;/math&gt;

is neater. It also allows to immediately identify that &amp;lambda; is the spatial period, and that its inverse, ''k'', together with the inverse of ''T'', f, are the spatial and temporal frequencies, respectively.

Along the same line the last equation (second line) in the page could read

:&lt;math&gt; 0=\frac{2\pi}{\lambda}\left(x - \frac{\lambda}{T} t\right) +\alpha&lt;/math&gt;

It direcly shows that the equiphase point moves with velocity ''c=&amp;lambda;/T''

[[User:RDR|RDR]]

Lets break this page up into smaller subunits so it is quicker to load and easier to navigate, etc. Keep up the great work, -- [[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

I'm just trying to wikify the source work, and it makes more sense to me to do each chapter as a page. I should do another few chapters tomorrow, and hope to be finished by Monday. After that, I'm going to leave it alone; I didn't do well enough at physics in school to edit this! -- [[User:Jimregan|Jimregan]] 02:15 20 Jul 2003 (UTC)

To clarify, the chapters listed are done so far as I'm concerned; I've done what I can with them, that is, unless someone can show me how to fix the ugly formatting as regards the image layout, the numbering of the problems &amp;c, in which case I'll gladly fix what I've done. -- [[User:Jimregan|Jimregan]] 02:32 20 Jul 2003 (UTC)

I was reading the introduction, and I know from my textbooks that the electromagnetic and the weak nuclear force are considered as one force called the electroweak force.  So there are only three fundamental forces.  Just trying to help.

Actually, there are four fundamental forces: gravity, electromagnetic, weak nuclear and strong nuclear. The electromagnetic and weak nuclear forces are unified, as electroweak, at energies greater than around 100 GeV. Many grand unified theories (GUTs) merge the electroweak with the strong nuclear force at higher energies. 27 Feb 2004

::Just a note: GeV = gigaElectronVolts.  Also: electricity and magnestism are two forces but because they unify at every energy level they are considered one.  Correct me if I'm wrong ... [[User:Dolphinn|Dolphinn!!]] 9:02 EST April 6 2007

== Merger ==

[[Waves/Sine Waves]] has some stuff about angular velocity, but is otherwise very similar to this page. I recommend that useful content from there be merged onto this page, with all the other math stuff. [[Special:Contributions/170.140.237.114|170.140.237.114]] ([[User talk:170.140.237.114|discuss]]) 14:20, 16 March 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>jvdnc429zhc6yiq5ezi867i92c4ljus</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Eric119</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>178</id>
    <revision>
      <id>152369</id>
      <parentid>27401</parentid>
      <timestamp>2004-04-25T03:05:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Eric119</username>
        <id>27</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&quot;...we who teach will be judged more strictly.&quot;

:--James 3:1b (NIV)

[[w:User:Eric119]]</text>
      <sha1>o6s9tlmihg8cwo7yjhnmdmvjt26eu95</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Waves/Reflection and Refraction</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>180</id>
    <revision>
      <id>551434</id>
      <parentid>152371</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-08-07T18:08:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[Talk:Modern Physics:Reflection and Refraction]] moved to [[Talk:Waves/Reflection and Refraction]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Lets break this up a bit so it isn't so long .. -- [[Karl Wick]]

== Total internal Reflection ==

Sir,
I would like to know in a physics point of view,keeping formulas &amp; mathematics aside why total internal reflection takes place.

RSVP to : adityavalluri@tatanova.com</text>
      <sha1>3occurjvtpqbzjh1e078kok5ymkn7pc</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:LouI</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>181</id>
    <revision>
      <id>152372</id>
      <parentid>1408</parentid>
      <timestamp>2003-08-13T19:48:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>LouI</username>
        <id>28</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>update for survey book</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">My normal use name is Lou Imholt.
I'm a semi-retired computer nerd (system engineer) with 35+ years experience, and an apprentice nanotechnologist starting in December, 2002.

I am still wraping up some loose ends I've left Wikipedia, but I have started to contribute ober here. I expect most effort to go into a new start up venture, the [[CACS:Computers and Communications|Survey of Computing]].

Use my talk page, or send an e-mail for comments, Thanks.</text>
      <sha1>t5cvna1oodhd8vbg0tnnvq53duir7ex</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:LouI</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>182</id>
    <revision>
      <id>152373</id>
      <parentid>72689</parentid>
      <timestamp>2004-11-29T08:59:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dysprosia</username>
        <id>32</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edit of 61.232.113.104, changed back to last version by 24.10.131.65</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Hey LouI, any work you contribute will be greatly appreciated. I think this thing will change education. -- [[Karl Wick]]
----
To whom it may concern:

I'm going to create a sandbox attached to me user page to try an experiment with pop up windows. It works in my browsers off-line but I need to try it within Wiki file structure. If it works, this would be useful in textbooks for glossary or footnote entries. I may wind up creating sub files for my sandbox, but I'll ask for it all to be removed after the trial.

Thanks ... [[User:LouI|LouI]] 04:46, 10 Aug 2003 (UTC)

----
&lt;strike&gt;Hi :) I've just noticed you changed the [[Study Guide:Shakespeare]] link to have a space inbetween the colon - it's not really common practice for namespaces to do so, (eg User talk:, Wikibooks:...)

Thanks :) [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 08:05, 2 Nov 2003 (UTC)&lt;/strike&gt;
I've just seen the discussion on Staff lounge, never mind. [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 05:22, 5 Nov 2003 (UTC)

== Loul...are you still interested in the Wiki-University thread? ==

I'm a new PhD student in Instructional technology, and I want to do my dissertation on open textbooks.

Can you give me an update on where things stand.  did they die?

Thanks!

John</text>
      <sha1>26f5pg93gxsakoagq6gfhitpi0e7zfb</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Organic Chemistry/Cover</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>183</id>
    <revision>
      <id>394461</id>
      <parentid>152374</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-03-10T16:33:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Robert Horning</username>
        <id>1227</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[Talk:Cover (Organic Chemistry)]] moved to [[Talk:Organic Chemistry/Cover]]: Moving to make a consistant naming convention for this Wikibook</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Splash page==
I decided to make this page a &quot;splash page&quot; or a sort of bookcover. Just the title, welcome comment, link to the contents and a pretty, ochem-related piece of artwork. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
::What a good idea! I'm going to do the same [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 09:16, 24 Sep 2003 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>1oh5rmzf0sk6n2k54swqvkz0qpuylaw</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:Cyp</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>184</id>
    <revision>
      <id>599627</id>
      <parentid>368738</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-10-01T21:28:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Withinfocus</username>
        <id>9615</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[en:User talk:Cyp]]

Hej/Miav/Hello/Meow/Aloha/?/Oi/Miado


Hey :) Thanks for picking up my arithmetic errors; my mental arithmetic is ''atrocious''! [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 21:10, 29 Sep 2003 (UTC)

Hi, nice job with all the puzzles! I'll see if I can find some more good and challenging ones. Btw: previously we first posted solution ideas to the talk page of a puzzle, but maybe it's better the way you did it and post directly to the solution page (incorrect / unclear solutions can always be edited later I guess). [[User:ThomasStrohmann | Thomas]]

:Thanks. Only saw the talk pages with solution ideas, after making all the solution pages... Think the solutions are probably correct, although the elastic one may not exactly have been the intended solution... [[User:Cyp|Cyp]] 18:01, 18 Oct 2003 (UTC)

Hello, the changes you made to the recursion section of primes is incorrect. Maybe i didn't explain recursion properly, and i'll try again. [[User:Xiaodai|Xiaodai]]

:I'm suppose I'm not actually sure what the definition of recursion is exactly... But I don't understand what the difference between iteration, and the example given, is. [[User:Cyp|كсηפ Cyp]] 12:50, 26 Oct 2003 (UTC)

::To define recursion, you first have to define recursion :) [[User:ThomasStrohmann | Thomas]]

----------
From the RfA page:
*[[User:Cyp|Cyp]] - Oh well, why not... Not that I've actually had any need for admin stuff in the Wikibooks section yet, but maybe I will some day... [[User:Cyp|Cyp]] 16:27, 18 Oct 2003 (UTC)
** Support. Corrects my errors, adds good stuff :) [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 01:54, 19 Oct 2003 (UTC)
**Make it so! --[[User:Maveric149|mav]] 22:46, 20 Oct 2003 (UTC)

You are now a Wikibooks admin. --[[User:Maveric149|mav]]

==Hebrew Wikibooks==
I want to promote the hebrew wikibooks, so i ask you to give me an admin premission in the hebrew wikibooks

--[[User:Mad dr|Mad dr]] 14:25, 14 Sep 2004 (UTC)

== Please delete http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Orbital_Mechanics ==

http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Orbital_Mechanics and
http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Physics/Orbital_Mechanics

I made a mistake in their creation.  One of them should have been under Aeropace Engineering, and actually there is already and astrodynamics one which is the same.

== SMW Guide ==

Hey, a lot of people are editing it wrong. Shouldn't you do something next time it happens? ( I took care of it.)--[[User:Nelson340|Nelson340]] 02:56, 19 Dec 2004 (UTC)

== [[Programming:Windows Programming]] ==

This book is in pretty lousy condition, and I would like to start a project soonish (within the next few weeks) to try and expand this book. I have started a basic outline [[User:Whiteknight/Windows Programming|on my user page]] to try and lay out the things that (I think) this book should cover. I see that you have been a contributer to this book in the past, and I would therefore like to get your input on the current outline, and see if there is anything that i should add, or anything that I should remove from it.

The outline can be found at [[User:Whiteknight/Windows Programming]]. --{{User Whiteknight Sig|Whiteknight}} 23:37, 12 December 2005 (UTC)

== De-Adminship vote. ==

A vote is being held to remove your sysop privileges.  The basis for this vote is lack of use of these privileges.  You may want to participate at [[Wikibooks:Requests_for_adminship#Cyp_.28_talk_.7C_email_.7C_contribs_.29]].  See also the discussion at [[Wikibooks:Staff_lounge#Removing_Sysop_Status]]. --[[User:JMRyan|JMRyan]] 23:13, 17 February 2006 (UTC)

== Your De-Adminship ==

Hello. I would like to inform you that you will have your sysop rights removed here on 1 Nov 2006 due to inactivity. If you would like to discuss the matter, please see [[WB:RFA]]. You can re-apply for adminship at a later date if you wish. Thanks. -[[User:Withinfocus|&lt;font color=&quot;#000000&quot;&gt;'''within'''&lt;/font&gt;]][[User talk:Withinfocus|&lt;font color=&quot;#7A7A7A&quot;&gt;'''focus'''&lt;/font&gt;]] 21:28, 1 October 2006 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>as6hk36x4hrcecoxviaa6dhl70xuae0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Cyp</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>185</id>
    <revision>
      <id>616004</id>
      <parentid>152376</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-10-18T04:09:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Guanabot</username>
        <id>5478</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>User-controlled Bot: table syntax updated</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[en:User:Cyp]]

{|
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#ff0000&quot; | &lt;font size=+10 color=#00ff00&gt;Cyp&lt;/font&gt;
|}

All my edits are also released under the proposed alternative licenses to the GNU, such as the creative something licence, or whatever they are all called, by the way, should this site decide to add an extra licence. &lt;Insert any required legal blah blah here.&gt;

See also: [[User talk:Cyp]]</text>
      <sha1>sea3i0gwccbpcw87qyq4rj8gcuxgnqd</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Help:Welcome, newcomers</title>
    <ns>12</ns>
    <id>186</id>
    <redirect title="Wikibooks:Welcome" />
    <revision>
      <id>1045554</id>
      <parentid>952977</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-12-05T19:43:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Redirecting to [[Wikibooks:Welcome]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">#REDIRECT: [[Wikibooks:Welcome]]</text>
      <sha1>jyecwjokv2dktnt7kiqa91nmwqbzkrf</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Wikibooks:Physics bookshelf</title>
    <ns>4</ns>
    <id>187</id>
    <restrictions>edit=autoconfirmed:move=autoconfirmed</restrictions>
    <revision>
      <id>2244409</id>
      <parentid>1944091</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-12-28T04:35:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Addihockey10</username>
        <id>410057</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Replacing raster images with vectorized equivalents - [[File:100%.png]] → [[File:100%.svg]] (semi-automated)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{deprecated bookshelf|[[Subject:Physics]]}}
{{bookshelves}}
{{bookshelf|Physics bookshelf}}
{{stages}}
{{info|Please see [[/Ranking discussion|the ranking discussion subpage]] to discuss the organization of this bookshelf.
An effort has been made to think about ranking the physics textbooks from most simple to most advanced. This page also collects related wiki links and external links (particularly non-wiki online physics textbooks).
}}
{{TOCright}}

{{Requested books}}

== Alphabetical ==
{|align=center 
! ||A-Mo|| ||Mu-Z
|-
| ||[[A-level Physics]]
| ||[[Multibody Mechanics]]
|-
| ||[[Acoustics]]
| {{stage short|50%|April 20, 2006}}|| [[Nanotechnology]]
|-
|{{stage short|25%|Jan 1, 2000}}||[[Astronomy]]
| ||[[Physics231]]
|-
|{{stage short|25%|Jan 1, 2000}}||[[Astrophysics]]
| {{stage short|75%|Jan 1, 2000}}|| [[Physics Study Guide]]
|-
|{{stage short|75%|April 25, 2006}}||[[Basic Electrical Generation and Distribution]]
| {{stage short|25%|Jan 1, 2000}}|| [[Physics with Calculus]]
|-
| {{stage short|50%|Jan 1, 2000}}|| [[Electronics]]
| {{stage short|50%|Jan 1, 2000}}|| [[Solid Mechanics]]
|-
| {{stage short|50%|Jan 1, 2000}}|| [[Engineering Thermodynamics]]
| {{stage short|00%|April 10, 2006}}|| [[String Theory]]
|-
| {{stage short|25%|Jan 1, 2000}}|| [[General relativity]]
| {{stage short|75%|Jan 1, 2000}}|| [[Special relativity]]
|-
| {{stage short|25%|Jan 1, 2000}}|| [[Introduction to Physical Science]]
| {{stage short|00%|Oct 30, 2006}}|| [[Statistical Mechanics]]
|-
| ||[[Kinematics]]
| {{stage short|00%|Jan 1, 2000}}|| [[Theoretical Mechanics]]
|-
| {{stage short|00%|Jan 1, 2000}}|| [[Marine Hydrodynamics]]
| {{stage short|25%|Dec 12, 2006}}|| [[This quantum world]]
|-
| {{stage short|50%|June 3, 2006}}|| [[Microtechnology]]
| {{stage short|00%|Jan 1, 2000}}|| [[Vibrations of Structures]]
|-
| {{stage short|25%|Jan 1, 2000}}|| [[Modern Physics]]
| {{stage short|75%|Aug 6, 2006}}|| [[Waves]]
|}

{{Requested books}}

== Categorized by subject ==

=== General ===
* [[Modern Physics]]

=== Mechanics === 
* {{stage|50%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[Classical mechanics]] - This will be a &quot;minimal standard course&quot; of classical theoretical mechanics.
*[[Mechanics]]

===Energy and Power===
* {{stage|00%|Feb 4, 2007}} [[Energy_and_Power:_Production%2C_Distribution%2C_and_Society|Energy and Power]] - This course will be an introduction to energy and power within a societal context.

*[[Nuclear Physics]]

=== Electromagnetism ===
* [[Electrodynamics]]
* [[FHSST Physics Electromagnetism:Magnets and Electromagnetism|Electromagnetism in the FHSST Physics book]]

=== Thermodynamics ===
* {{stage|50%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[Engineering Thermodynamics]]
* [[Thermodynamics]]
* {{stage|00%|2006-10-30}} [[Statistical Mechanics]]

=== Quantum mechanics ===
* [[Quantum Mechanics]]
* {{stage|25%|Dec 12, 2006}} [[This quantum world|This Quantum World]]

=== Relativity ===
{{Goodbook|box=width:300px; float: right;|title=Special Relativity|cover=Einstein_en_Lorentz.jpg|file=Specialrelativity.pdf|desc=[[Special Relativity]] is an introductory text for physics undergraduates and advanced high school students. It is also approachable by the educated layman. It is carefully designed to tackle the physics of simultaneity.}}
* [[General Relativity]]
* [[Special Relativity]]

=== Optics ===
* {{stage|25%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[Optics]] - Suitable for high school students.

=== Acoustics ===
* [[Acoustics]]
* [[Engineering Acoustics]]

=== Micro and Nanotechnology ===
*[[Microtechnology]] - handbook of microfabrication and microtehcnology
*[[Nanotechnology]] - handbook of nanoscience and nanotechnology
*[[Carbon Nanotube Cookbook]]

=== Study Aids ===
* [[A-level Physics]]
* {{stage short|100%|July 22, 2009}} [[A-level Physics (Advancing Physics)]]
* {{stage short|75%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[Physics Study Guide/Cover|Physics Study Guide]]
* {{stage short|00%|Jan 12, 2005}} [[Physics Exercises]]

=== History of Physics ===
* {{stage short|25%|Aug 4, 2007}} [[Galileo's Science]]

{{Requested books}}

== Categorized by audience and level ==


===Middle School===
*[[The Universe Made Simple]]
===High School===
*[[File:100%.svg]] [[FHSST Physics]] - A free high school student textbook on physics
* {{stage|50%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[GCSE Science/Electricity]] - A simple book for students aged 14 - 16.
* {{stage|25%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[Optics]] - Suitable for high school students.
* {{stage|50%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[Physics with transforms - new invention]] - A new mnemonic for learning classical physics formulas using Euclidean geometry. It also serves to geometrically correlate classical physics formulas together. For high school &amp; up.
* {{stage|50%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[High school physics]] - High school physics for the MTV literate.
* {{stage|25%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[SAT II Physics]] - Preparation for the College Board exam.
* {{stage|00%|29 June, 2007}} [[HSC Physics]] A physics textbook for Year 12 Australian high school students (Syllabus is closest to NSW)
* [[Physics - For dummies, rebels and humans]] - A free textbook for Physics - the ultimate goal being to teach the student how to learn by himself.
* [[Solved Question Papers - IIT JEE]]
* [[Solved Question Papers - AIEEE]]

===Hobbyist===
* {{stage|00%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[Waves]]
* {{stage|50%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[LearnElectronics]] More hands on experience.
* {{stage|50%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[Table of nuclides]] - Table with all nuclides 

===Undergraduate===
* {{stage|50%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[Physics Exercises]]
* {{stage|50%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[Electronics]] - Somewhat more advanced, for hobbyists or first or second year college level.
* {{stage|50%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[A-level Physics]] - For students taking Physics at A-level.
* {{stage|50%|Apr 12, 2008}} [[A-level Physics (Advancing Physics)]] - For students taking the OCR Physics B (Advancing Physics) course at A-level.
* [[File:100%.svg]] [[Physics Study Guide]] - Overview of equations, basic terms, and variables for algebra-based physics course. - Suitable for A level/ advanced highschool or first year undergraduate.
* {{stage|50%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[Physics with Calculus]] - Undergraduate textbook, first- and second-year level
* {{stage|50%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[Physics:Questions|Physics practice questions (with solutions)]]

===Advanced undergraduate===
* {{stage|00%|June 7,2008}} [[Mathematical methods of Physics]]
* {{stage|50%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[Modern Physics]] - A full-length undergraduate textbook. &lt;small&gt;''Includes [[Modern Physics:Electromagnetism:Contents|Electromagnetism]], [[Modern Physics:Quantum Mechanics:Contents|Quantum Mechanics]], and [[Modern Physics:Thermodynamics:Contents|Thermodynamics and statistical mechanics]].'' &lt;/small&gt;
* {{stage|50%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[Solid Mechanics]]
* {{stage|50%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[Introduction to Theoretical Physics]] - From First Principles to Newtonian Mechanics to General Relativity
* {{stage|50%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[Classical mechanics]] - This will be a &quot;minimal standard course&quot; of classical theoretical mechanics. 
* {{stage|50%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[Engineering Thermodynamics]]
* {{stage|50%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[Heat Transfer|Heat Energy Transfer]]
* [[Physics in the Language of Geometric Algebra. An Approach with the Algebra of Physical Space]]
* [[Basic Physics of Nuclear Medicine]]
* {{stage|25%|Dec 12, 2006}} [[This quantum world|This Quantum World]]

===Postgraduate===
* {{stage|50%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[Interpretations of Quantum Mechanics and Quantum Field Theory]]
* {{stage|50%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[General relativity]] - Post graduate / advanced undergraduate
* {{stage|25%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[Quantum field theory]] - Postgraduate
* {{stage|50%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[Supersymmetry]]
* {{stage|00%|Jan 1, 2000}} [[String theory|String Theory &amp; M-Theory]]

== Links and related pages ==
===Related Wikimedia Projects===
{{Associated Wikimedia|Physics
|Commons category    = Physics
|Wikinews portal     = 
|Wikinews category   = Physics
|Wikipedia           = Physics
|Wikipedia portal    = Physics
|Wikiquote           = Physics
|Wikiquote category  = 
|Wikisource          = Physics
|Wikisource category = Physics
|Wikiversity         = 
|Wikiversity school  = Physics and Astronomy
|Wiktionary          = physics
|Wiktionary appendix = 
|Wiktionary category = Physics
}}


=== Related books ===


=== Related bookshelves ===
* [[Wikibooks:Natural sciences bookshelf|Miscellaneous natural sciences]]
* [[Wikibooks:Engineering bookshelf|Engineering]]
* [[Wikibooks:Mathematics bookshelf|Mathematics]]

=== Other online resources ===

=== Wikinode: Other physics wiki ===
*[http://qwiki.caltech.edu/wiki/Main_Page Qwiki] is a quantum physics wiki devoted to the collective creation of content that is technical and useful to practicing scientists.
* [http://www.sklogwiki.org/SklogWiki/index.php/WikiNode SklogWiki.org] is a wiki for anyone interested in  thermodynamics, statistical mechanics and the  computer simulation of materials, especially liquids and soft condensed matter.


=== Offsite physics books ===
*[http://www.lightandmatter.com/books.html Physics book series] by Ben Crowell. 
*[http://kestrel.nmt.edu/~raymond/classes/ph13xbook/bookc.html A Radically Modern Approach to Introductory Physics] by David J. Raymond, GFDL license
*[http://www.phas.ucalgary.ca/phys323/fall/notes/optics.pdf Introduction to optics (PDF)] Lecture notes from the University of Calgary. Includes some nice images.
*[http://slacker.yosunism.com The Slacker's Guide to Physics: Electricity and Magnetism]
*[http://mitpress.mit.edu/SICM/ Structure and Interpretation Of Classical Mechanics] A Lagrangian and Hamiltonian mechanics text using computational tools online
*[http://alamos.math.arizona.edu/~rychlik/557-dir/mechanics/ Lagrangian and Hamiltonian Mechanics: A short introduction] Online at University of Arizona.
*[http://www3.baylor.edu/Physics/open_text/index.html OPEN TEXT physics books]
*[http://savannah.nongnu.org/projects/introphysics/ Introductory Physics] by Charles Edward Pax, published under the GNU General Public License (GPL). 
* ''Grains of Mystique: Quantum Physics for the Layman'' by Thomas Haberkern and N Deepak, copyrighted 2002, licensed under Open Publication License http://www.ndeepak.info/qp
* ''Lessons In Electric Circuits'' Copyright © 2000-2003, Tony R. Kuphaldt published under the &quot;Design Science License&quot;, which allows for free copying, distribution, and/or modification of this document by the general public. http://www.ibiblio.org/kuphaldt/electricCircuits/
*[http://www.anselm.edu/internet/physics/cbphysics/index.html Calculus-Based Physics I &amp; II] by Jeffrey Schnick
*[http://www.physicsforfree.com/essential.html Public domain, calculus-based physics book] in PDF format.

[[de:Regal:Physik]]</text>
      <sha1>ercjsnf4ezfmo6i7op491wfykvzq5ml</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Waves/Transverse, Longitudinal and Torsional waves</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>188</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2680126</id>
      <parentid>2679887</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-07-10T08:03:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jianhui67</username>
        <id>1013809</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/94.101.160.1|94.101.160.1]] ([[User talk:94.101.160.1|talk]]) to last version by 138.163.0.41</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{1DWavesTOC}}
===Transverse and Longitudinal Waves===

&lt;!--  Commented out because image was deleted: [[Image:Tranlong.png|thumb|right|Example of displacements in transverse and longitudinal waves. The wave motion is to the right. The longitudinal and transverse waves are in phase.]] --&gt;

With the exception of light, waves are undulations in some material medium. For instance, waves on a slinky are either ''transverse'', in that the motion of the material of the slinky is perpendicular to the orientation of the slinky, if you vibrate the slinky like a rope, or they are ''longitudinal'', with material motion in the direction of the stretched slinky, if you treat it like a spring. (See image on right) Ocean waves are simultaneously transverse and longitudinal, the net effect being (nearly) circular undulations in the position of water parcels. The oscillations in neighboring parcels are phased such that a ''pattern'' moves across the ocean surface. Some media support only longitudinal waves, others support only transverse waves, while yet others support both types. Sound waves are purely longitudinal in gases and liquids, but can be either type in solids.

Mechanical transverse waves require a material medium and propogate by means of vibrations of the medium perpendicular to the direction of travel. Examples are water waves, ripples, seismic shear waves, and waves in stretched strings as above.

&lt;!--  Commented out because image was deleted: [[image:Emwave.png|thumb|left|The periodic undulation of Electric and Magnetic field strengths in an EM wave]] --&gt;

Electromagnetic (EM) waves (such as light) are also transverse waves but they do not require a medium and thus can pass through a vacuum ([[Waves/Waves in one Dimension|see intro]]).They consist of oscillating electric (E) and magnetic (B) fields which are perpendicular to the direction of propogation while also being mutually perpendicular. EM waves are a disturbance of space itself, which can be thought of as being stretched and therefore being elastic and having a tension. The B and E fields are in phase as shown on the left.

The fundamental S.I. unit of length (meter) is defined in terms of the speed of light in vacuum and the definition of the unit of time, the second. The previous definition was in terms of the wavelength of a particular color of light in the line spectrum of Krypton 86. The modern definition is more accurate as well as being the same to all observers regardless of their relative velocity.

Longitudinal waves propogate by means of vibrations or disturbances in the medium that are in the same direction that the wave travels. Examples are sound (as above), seismic shock waves, slinky springs and part of the motion in ocean waves. Sound waves are a series of high-pressure compressions and low-pressure rarefaction (for this reason, sound is sometimes called a ''pressure wave''). While it might be convenient to think of individual molecules vibrating back and forth around an equilibrium position (producing areas of high and low pressure), the individual molecules in a gas generally move randomly, and it is only in large numbers that this pattern is visible. In longitudinal waves, the convention is to describe displacement in the direction the wave is going (the direction of propagation) as positive, and displacement against that direction as negative.

&lt;!--  Commented out because image was deleted: [[Image:dispress.png|thumb|600px|center|Graph of Displacement vs Pressure]] --&gt;

The pressure and displacement of a molecule at a point are &lt;math&gt;90^o&lt;/math&gt; out of phase, so that, for example, when a molecule is farthest displaced it is in a normal pressure area, while molecules in compressions or rarefactions have displacement close to zero.

Torsional waves consist of a twisting disturbance moving through a medium such as a wire or a rod.

----

{{1DWavesTOC}}</text>
      <sha1>ff1mndve1saw51vptdq70404dajg9wz</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Waves/Sine Waves</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>189</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2070274</id>
      <parentid>1445560</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-03-16T14:20:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>170.140.237.114</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Propose merge into first page, for less math redundancy</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{mergeto|Waves/Waves in one Dimension|Most if its content is already somewhere else|Talk:Waves/Waves in one Dimension#Merger}}

{{1DWavesTOC}}
===Sine Waves===

A particularly simple kind of wave, the sine wave, is illustrated in figure 1.2. This has the mathematical form:
:&lt;math&gt;h(x) = h_0 \sin ( 2 \pi x / \lambda ) ,&lt;/math&gt; (2.1)

where
:''h'' is the ''displacement'' (which can be either longitudinal or transverse),
:&lt;math&gt;h_0&lt;/math&gt; is the maximum displacement, sometimes called the amplitude of the wave,
:&amp;lambda; is the wavelength.tory Physics fig 1.2.png|Figure 1.2: Sine wave]] --&gt;&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 1.2''': Definition sketch for a sine wave, showing the wavelength &amp;lambda; and the amplitude &lt;math&gt;h_0&lt;/math&gt; and the phase &amp;phi; at various points.
&lt;/div&gt;


So far we have only considered a sine wave as it appears at a particular time. All interesting waves move with time. The movement of a sine wave to the right a distance &lt;math&gt;d&lt;/math&gt; may be accounted for by replacing &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt; in the above formula by &lt;math&gt;x - d&lt;/math&gt;. If this movement occurs in time &lt;math&gt;t&lt;/math&gt;, then the wave moves at velocity &lt;math&gt;c = d/t&lt;/math&gt;. Solving this for &lt;math&gt;d&lt;/math&gt; and substituting yields a formula for the displacement of a sine wave as a function of both distance &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt; and time &lt;math&gt;t&lt;/math&gt;:
:&lt;math&gt; h(x) = h_0 \sin [ 2 \pi (x - ct) / \lambda ] . &lt;/math&gt; (2.2)

The time for a wave to move one wavelength is called the period of the wave: &lt;math&gt;T = \lambda / c&lt;/math&gt;. Thus, we can also write
:&lt;math&gt;h(x) = h_0 \sin [ 2 \pi ( x / \lambda - t / T ) ] . &lt;/math&gt;(2.3)

Physicists actually like to write the equation for a sine wave in a slightly simpler form. Defining the wavenumber as &lt;math&gt;k = 2 \pi / \lambda&lt;/math&gt; and the angular frequency as &lt;math&gt;\omega = 2 \pi / T&lt;/math&gt;, we write
:&lt;math&gt; h(x) = h_0 \sin (kx - \omega t) . &lt;/math&gt;(2.4)

We normally think of the frequency of oscillatory motion as the number of cycles completed per second and is given by &lt;math&gt;f = 1/T&lt;/math&gt;. It is related to the angular frequency omega by &lt;math&gt;\omega = 2 \pi f&lt;/math&gt;. The angular frequency is used because it is directly analogous to the wavenumber, see above. Converting between the two is not difficult. Frequency is measured in units of hertz, abbreviated Hz; &lt;math&gt;1 \mbox{Hz} = 1 \mbox{ s}^{-1}&lt;/math&gt; and angular frequency &lt;math&gt;\omega&lt;/math&gt; is in units of radians per second.
(Not converting between frequency and angular frequency is a common mistake in many calculations)


The argument of the sine function is by definition an angle. We refer to this angle as the phase of the wave, &lt;math&gt;\phi = kx - \omega t&lt;/math&gt;. The difference in the phase of a wave at fixed time over a distance of one wavelength is &lt;math&gt;2 \pi&lt;/math&gt;, as is the difference in phase at fixed position over a time interval of one wave period.

As previously noted, we call &lt;math&gt;h_0&lt;/math&gt;, the maximum displacement of the wave, the amplitude. Often we are interested in the intensity of a wave, which is defined as the square of the amplitude, &lt;math&gt;I = h_0^2&lt;/math&gt;.

The wave speed we have defined above, &lt;math&gt;c = \lambda /T&lt;/math&gt;, is actually called the phase speed. Since &lt;math&gt;\lambda = 2 \pi /k&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;T = 2 \pi / \omega&lt;/math&gt;, we can write the phase speed in terms of the angular frequency and the wavenumber:
:&lt;math&gt;c = \frac{\omega}{k} \mbox{(phase speed)} . &lt;/math&gt; (2.5)

----

{{1DWavesTOC}}</text>
      <sha1>muyv42447n7s1cmqb7ifzml1u89s65n</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Waves/Types of Waves</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>190</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2070287</id>
      <parentid>661430</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-03-16T14:33:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>170.140.237.114</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Change some wording; velocity is v; what is k?</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{1DWavesTOC}}
=== Types of Waves ===

In order to make the above material more concrete, we now examine the characteristics of various types of waves which may be observed in the real world. 
==== Ocean Surface Waves ====

&lt;div style=&quot;float:right;margin:0 0 1em 1em;text-align:center;&quot;&gt; [[image:Introductory Physics fig 1.3.png|Figure 1.3: Wave on an ocean depth]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 1.3''': Wave on an ocean of depth &lt;math&gt;H&lt;/math&gt;. The wave is moving to the right and the particles of water at the surface move up and down as shown by the small vertical arrows. The particles move up, and gravity is the 'restoring' force. Water waves are also longitudinal, the water particles moving forward, then back.  The restoring forces are more complex, but involve the inertia of the mass of water surrounding. Think of water waves as superimposed transverse and longitudinal waves.  The net particle paths are nearly circular.  This is typical of waves that travel along the boundary (interface) between two substances, in this case water and air.
&lt;/div&gt;

These waves are manifested as undulations of the ocean surface as seen in figure 1.3. The speed of ocean waves is given by the formula
:&lt;math&gt;v = \left( \frac{g \tanh (kH)}{k} \right)^{1/2} , &lt;/math&gt; (2.6)

where &lt;math&gt;g = 9.8 \mbox{ m} \mbox{ s}^{-2}&lt;/math&gt; is a constant related to the strength of the Earth's gravity, &lt;math&gt;H&lt;/math&gt; is the depth of the ocean, and the hyperbolic tangent is defined as 2.7
:&lt;math&gt;\tanh (x) = \frac{e^x - e^{-x}}{e^x + e^{-x}} . &lt;/math&gt; (2.7) &lt;!-- what is k? --&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;float:right;margin:0 0 1em 1em;text-align:center;&quot;&gt; [[image:Introductory Physics fig 1.4.png|Figure 1.4: Plot of tanh(x)]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 1.4''': Plot of the function &lt;math&gt;\tanh (x)&lt;/math&gt;. The dashed line shows our approximation &lt;math&gt;\tanh (x) \approx x&lt;/math&gt; for &lt;math&gt;\vert x\vert &lt;&lt; 1&lt;/math&gt;.
&lt;/div&gt;

As figure 1.4 shows, for very small x, we can approximate the hyperbolic tangent by &lt;math&gt;\tanh (x) \approx x&lt;/math&gt;, while for very large x it is positive 1 for positive x and negative 1 for negative x. This leads to two limits: Since &lt;math&gt;x = k H&lt;/math&gt;, the ''shallow water'' limit, which occurs when &lt;math&gt;kH &lt;&lt; 1&lt;/math&gt;, yields a wave speed of
:&lt;math&gt;v \approx (gH)^{1/2} , \mbox{(shallow water waves)} , &lt;/math&gt; (2.8)

while the ''deep water'' limit, which occurs when &lt;math&gt;kH &gt;&gt; 1&lt;/math&gt;, yields
:&lt;math&gt;v \approx (g/k)^{1/2} , \mbox{(deep water waves)} . &lt;/math&gt; (2.9)

Notice that the speed of shallow water waves depends only on the depth of the water and on &lt;math&gt;g&lt;/math&gt;. In other words, all shallow water waves move at the same speed. 

On the other hand, deep water waves of longer wavelength (and hence smaller wavenumber) move more rapidly than those with shorter wavelength. Waves for which the wave speed varies with wavelength are called ''dispersive''. Thus, deep water waves are dispersive, while shallow water waves are non-dispersive.

For water waves with wavelengths of a few centimeters or less, surface tension becomes important to the dynamics of the waves. In the deep water case the wave speed at short wavelengths is actually given by the formula
:&lt;math&gt; c = (g/k + A k )^{1/2} &lt;/math&gt; (2.10)

where the constant &lt;math&gt;A&lt;/math&gt; is related to surface tension and depends on the surfaces involved. For an air-water interface near room temperature, &lt;math&gt;A \approx 74 \mbox{ cm}^3 \mbox{ s}^{-2}&lt;/math&gt;.

----

{{1DWavesTOC}}</text>
      <sha1>nf64a7tlsty6825q4fl4kz58v8vn0pw</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Waves/Sound Waves</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>191</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2134232</id>
      <parentid>1371045</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-07-05T14:54:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>94.196.223.161</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Sound Waves */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''''{{1DWavesTOC}}
==== Sound Waves ====

Sound is a longitudinal compression-expansion wave through matter. The wave speed is
:&lt;math&gt;c = ( \gamma R T_{abs} )^{1/2} &lt;/math&gt; (2.11)

where &lt;math&gt;\gamma&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;R&lt;/math&gt; are constants and &lt;math&gt;T_{abs}&lt;/math&gt; is the ''absolute temperature''. The absolute temperature is measured in Kelvins and is numerically given by
:&lt;math&gt;T_{abs} = T_C + 273.16^{\circ} &lt;/math&gt; (2.12)

where &lt;math&gt;T_C&lt;/math&gt; is the temperature in Celsius degrees. The angular frequency of sound waves is thus given by
:&lt;math&gt; \omega = ck = ( \gamma R T_{abs} )^{1/2} k . &lt;/math&gt; (2.13)

The speed of sound in air at normal temperatures is about &lt;math&gt;340 \mbox{ m} \mbox{ s}^{-1}&lt;/math&gt;.

----

{{1DWavesTOC}}'''''</text>
      <sha1>1662up1vpsfhj00ovt0eyu219if9oiy</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Waves/Light</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>192</id>
    <revision>
      <id>551347</id>
      <parentid>551245</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-08-07T17:58:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{1DWavesTOC}}
==== Light ====

Light moves in a vacuum at a speed of &lt;math&gt;c_{vac} = 3 \times 10^8 \mbox{ m} \mbox{ s}^{-1}&lt;/math&gt;. In transparent materials it moves at a speed less than &lt;math&gt;c_{vac}&lt;/math&gt; by a factor &lt;math&gt;n&lt;/math&gt; which is called the ''refractive index'' of the material:
:&lt;math&gt;c = c_{vac} / n . &lt;/math&gt;

Often the refractive index takes the form
:&lt;math&gt;n^2 \approx 1 + \frac{A}{1 - (k/k_R )^2} ,&lt;/math&gt;

where &lt;math&gt;k&lt;/math&gt; is the wavenumber and &lt;math&gt;k_R&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;A&lt;/math&gt; are constants characteristic of the material. The angular frequency of light in a transparent medium is thus
:&lt;math&gt;\omega = kc = \frac{k c_{vac}}{n} \approx 
\frac{k c_{vac}}{\sqrt{1+A}}(1+ \frac{1}{2}\frac{A}{1+A}\frac{k^2}{k^2_R})&lt;/math&gt;

so the frequency increases slightly with increasing ''k''. Typically, when ''k'' is near ''k''&lt;sub&gt;''R''&lt;/sub&gt;, the material becomes opaque.

Ultimately, this is due to resonance between the light and the atoms of the materials.

----

{{1DWavesTOC}}</text>
      <sha1>07u2pk9ykma0cu8svjlq5ukz4iwhpef</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Waves/Superposition</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>193</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1365844</id>
      <parentid>551350</parentid>
      <timestamp>2008-12-24T13:09:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ergzay</username>
        <id>154741</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Corrected formatting</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{1DWavesTOC}}
=== Superposition Principle ===

It is found empirically that as long as the amplitudes of waves in most media are small, two waves in the same physical location don't interact with each other. Thus, for example, two waves moving in the opposite direction simply pass through each other without their shapes or amplitudes being changed. When superimposed, the total wave displacement is just the sum of the displacements of the individual waves. This is called the ''superposition principle''. At sufficiently large amplitude the superposition principle often breaks down -- interacting waves may scatter off of each other, lose amplitude, or change their form.

''Interference'' is a consequence of the superposition principle. When two or more waves are superimposed, the net wave displacement is just the algebraic sum of the displacements of the individual waves. Since these displacements can be positive or negative, the net displacement can either be greater or less than the individual wave displacements. The former case is called ''constructive interference'', while the latter is called ''destructive interference''. 

&lt;div style=&quot;float:right;margin:0 0 1em 1em;text-align:center;&quot;&gt; [[image:Introductory Physics fig 1.5.png|Figure 1.5: Superposition of two sine waves]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 1.5''': Superposition (lower panel) of two sine waves (shown individually in the upper panel) with equal amplitudes and wavenumbers &lt;math&gt;k_1 = 4&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;k_2 = 5&lt;/math&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

Let us see what happens when we superimpose two sine waves with different wavenumbers. Figure 1.5 shows the superposition of two waves with wavenumbers &lt;math&gt;k_1 = 4&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;k_2 = 5&lt;/math&gt;. Notice that the result is a wave with about the same wavelength as the two initial waves, but which varies in amplitude depending on whether the two sine waves are in or out of phase. When the waves are in phase, constructive interference is occurring, while destructive interference occurs where the waves are out of phase.

&lt;div style=&quot;float:right;margin:0 0 1em 1em;text-align:center;&quot;&gt; [[image:Introductory Physics fig 1.6.png|Figure 1.6: Superposition of two sine waves]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 1.6''': Superposition of two sine waves with equal amplitudes and wavenumbers &lt;math&gt;k_1 = 10&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;k_2 = 11&lt;/math&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

What happens when the wavenumbers of the two sine waves are changed? Figure 1.6 shows the result when &lt;math&gt;k_1 = 10&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;k_2 = 11&lt;/math&gt;. Notice that though the wavelength of the resultant wave is decreased, the locations where the amplitude is maximum have the same separation in &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt; as in figure 1.5.

&lt;div style=&quot;float:right;margin:0 0 1em 1em;text-align:center;&quot;&gt; [[image:Introductory Physics fig 1.7.png|Figure 1.7: Superposition of two sine waves]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 1.7''': Superposition of two sine waves with equal amplitudes and wavenumbers &lt;math&gt;k_1 = 10&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;k_2 = 12&lt;/math&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;

If we superimpose waves with &lt;math&gt;k_1 = 10&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;k_2 = 12&lt;/math&gt;, as is shown in figure 1.7, we see that the &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt; spacing of the regions of maximum amplitude has decreased by a factor of two. Thus, while the wavenumber of the resultant wave seems to be related to something like the ''average'' of the wavenumbers of the component waves, the spacing between regions of maximum wave amplitude appears to go inversely with the ''difference'' of the wavenumbers of the component waves. In other words, if &lt;math&gt;k_1&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;k_2&lt;/math&gt; are close together, the amplitude maxima are far apart and vice versa.

&lt;div style=&quot;float:right;margin:0 0 1em 1em;text-align:center;&quot;&gt; [[image:Introductory Physics fig 1.8.png|Figure 1.8: Representation of the wavenumbers and amplitudes of two superimposed sine waves.]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 1.8''': Representation of the wavenumbers and amplitudes of two superimposed sine waves.&lt;/div&gt;

We can symbolically represent the sine waves that make up figures 1.5, 1.6, and 1.7 by a plot such as that shown in figure 1.8. The amplitudes and wavenumbers of each of the sine waves are indicated by vertical lines in this figure.

The regions of large wave amplitude are called wave packets. Wave packets will play a central role in what is to follow, so it is important that we acquire a good understanding of them. The wave packets produced by only two sine waves are not well separated along the &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt;-axis. However, if we superimpose many waves, we can produce an isolated wave packet. For example, figure 1.9 shows the results of superimposing &lt;math&gt;20&lt;/math&gt; sine waves with wavenumbers &lt;math&gt;k = 0.4 m&lt;/math&gt;, &lt;math&gt;m = 1,2, \ldots , 20&lt;/math&gt;, where the amplitudes of the waves are largest for wavenumbers near &lt;math&gt;k = 4&lt;/math&gt;. 

&lt;div style=&quot;margin:0 0 1em 1em;text-align:center;&quot;&gt; [[image:Introductory Physics fig 1.9.png|Figure 1.9: Superposition of twenty sine waves]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 1.9''': Superposition of twenty sine waves with &lt;math&gt;k_0 = 4&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\Delta k = 1&lt;/math&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;

In particular, we assume that the amplitude of each sine wave is proportional to &lt;math&gt;\exp [-(k - k_0)^2 / \Delta k^2 ]&lt;/math&gt;, where &lt;math&gt;k_0 = 4&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\Delta k = 1&lt;/math&gt;. The amplitudes of each of the sine waves making up the wave packet in figure 1.9 are shown schematically in figure 1.10.


&lt;div style=&quot;margin:0 0 1em 1em;text-align:center;&quot;&gt; [[image:Introductory Physics fig 1.10.png|Figure 1.10: Superposition of twenty sine waves]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 1.10''': Representation of the wavenumbers and amplitudes of 20 superimposed sine waves with &lt;math&gt;k_0 = 4&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\Delta k = 1&lt;/math&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;

The quantity &lt;math&gt;\Delta k&lt;/math&gt; controls the distribution of the sine waves being superimposed -- only those waves with a wavenumber &lt;math&gt;k&lt;/math&gt; within approximately &lt;math&gt;\Delta k&lt;/math&gt; of the central wavenumber &lt;math&gt;k_0&lt;/math&gt; of the wave packet, i. e., for &lt;math&gt;3 \le k \le 5&lt;/math&gt; in this case, contribute significantly to the sum. If &lt;math&gt;\Delta k&lt;/math&gt; is changed to &lt;math&gt;2&lt;/math&gt;, so that wavenumbers in the range &lt;math&gt;2 \le k \le 6&lt;/math&gt; contribute significantly, the wavepacket becomes narrower, as is shown in figures 1.11 and 1.12.

&lt;div style=&quot;margin:0 0 1em 1em;text-align:center;&quot;&gt; [[image:Introductory Physics fig 1.11.png|Figure 1.11: Superposition of twenty sine waves]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 1.11''': Superposition of twenty sine waves with &lt;math&gt;k_0 = 4&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\Delta k = 2&lt;/math&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin:0 0 1em 1em;text-align:center;&quot;&gt; [[image:Introductory Physics fig 1.12.png|Figure 1.12: Superposition of twenty sine waves]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 1.12''': Representation of the wavenumbers and amplitudes of 20 superimposed sine waves with &lt;math&gt;k_0 = 4&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\Delta k = 2&lt;/math&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;math&gt;\Delta k&lt;/math&gt; is called the wavenumber spread of the wave packet, and it evidently plays a role similar to the difference in wavenumbers in the superposition of two sine waves -- the larger the wavenumber spread, the smaller the physical size of the wave packet. Furthermore, the wavenumber of the oscillations within the wave packet is given approximately by the central wavenumber.

We can better understand how wave packets work by mathematically analyzing the simple case of the superposition of two sine waves. Let us define &lt;math&gt;k_0 = (k_1 + k_2 )/2&lt;/math&gt; where &lt;math&gt;k_1&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;k_2&lt;/math&gt; are the wavenumbers of the component waves. Furthermore let us set &lt;math&gt;\Delta k = (k_2 - k_1 )/2&lt;/math&gt;. The quantities &lt;math&gt;k_0&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\Delta k&lt;/math&gt; are graphically illustrated in figure 1.8. We can write &lt;math&gt;k_1 = k_0 - \Delta k&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;k_2 = k_0 + \Delta k&lt;/math&gt; and use the trigonometric identity &lt;math&gt;\sin (a + b) = \sin (a) \cos (b) + \cos (a) \sin (b)&lt;/math&gt; to find
&lt;math&gt;\sin (k_1 x) + \sin (k_2 x) = \sin [(k_0 - \Delta k)x] + \sin [(k_0 + \Delta k)x]&lt;/math&gt;  
&lt;math&gt; = \sin (k_0 x) \cos (\Delta k x) - \cos (k_0 x) \sin(\Delta k x) +&lt;/math&gt;  
&lt;math&gt;\sin (k_0 x) \cos (\Delta k x) + \cos (k_0 x) \sin(\Delta k x) = 2 \sin (k_0 x) \cos ( \Delta k x) .&lt;/math&gt; (2.17)

The sine factor on the bottom line of the above equation produces the oscillations within the wave packet, and as speculated earlier, this oscillation has a wavenumber &lt;math&gt;k_0&lt;/math&gt; equal to the average of the wavenumbers of the component waves. The cosine factor modulates this wave with a spacing between regions of maximum amplitude of
:&lt;math&gt;\Delta x = \pi / \Delta k . &lt;/math&gt; (2.18)

Thus, as we observed in the earlier examples, the length of the wave packet &lt;math&gt;\Delta x&lt;/math&gt; is inversely related to the spread of the wavenumbers &lt;math&gt;\Delta k&lt;/math&gt; (which in this case is just the difference between the two wavenumbers) of the component waves. This relationship is central to the uncertainty principle of quantum mechanics.

----

{{1DWavesTOC}}</text>
      <sha1>7at3nitricpci6atfxyt1a791ul248m</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Waves/Beats</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>194</id>
    <revision>
      <id>551352</id>
      <parentid>551262</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-08-07T17:59:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{1DWavesTOC}}
===Beats===

Suppose two sound waves of different frequency impinge on your ear at the same time. The displacement perceived by your ear is the superposition of these two waves, with time dependence
&lt;math&gt; A(t) = \sin ( \omega_1 t) + \sin ( \omega_2 t) = 2 \sin ( \omega_0 t) \cos ( \Delta \omega t) , &lt;/math&gt; (2.19)

where we now have &lt;math&gt;\omega_0 = ( \omega_1 + \omega_2 )/2&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\Delta \omega = ( \omega_2 - \omega_1 )/2&lt;/math&gt;. What you actually hear is a tone with angular frequency &lt;math&gt;\omega_0&lt;/math&gt; which fades in and out with period
&lt;math&gt;T_{beat} = \pi / \Delta \omega = 2 \pi / ( \omega_2 - \omega_1 ) = 1 / ( f_2 - f_1 ) . &lt;/math&gt; (2.20)

The ''beat frequency'' is simply
&lt;math&gt; f_{beat} = 1/T_{beat} = f_2 - f_1 . &lt;/math&gt; (2.21)

Note how beats are the time analog of wave packets -- the mathematics are the same except that frequency replaces wavenumber and time replaces space.

----

{{1DWavesTOC}}</text>
      <sha1>2ek49ddvt80yxrgtixm0zhp88wo59v3</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Waves/Interferometers</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>195</id>
    <revision>
      <id>551354</id>
      <parentid>551265</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-08-07T17:59:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{1DWavesTOC}}
=== Interferometers ===

An interferometer is a device which splits a beam of light into two sub-beams, shifts the phase of one sub-beam with respect to the other, and then superimposes the sub-beams so that they interfere constructively or destructively, depending on the magnitude of the phase shift between them. In this section we study the Michelson interferometer and interferometric effects in thin films. 

==== The Michelson Interferometer ====

&lt;div style=&quot;float:right;margin:0 0 1em 1em;text-align:center;&quot;&gt; [[image:Introductory Physics fig 1.13.png|Figure 1.13: Sketch of a Michelson interferometer.]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 1.13''': Sketch of a Michelson interferometer.&lt;/div&gt;

The American physicist Albert Michelson invented the optical interferometer illustrated in figure 1.13. The incoming beam is split into two beams by the half-silvered mirror. Each sub-beam reflects off of another mirror which returns it to the half-silvered mirror, where the two sub-beams recombine as shown. One of the reflecting mirrors is movable by a sensitive micrometer device, allowing the path length of the corresponding sub-beam, and hence the phase relationship between the two sub-beams, to be altered. As figure 1.13 shows, the difference in path length between the two sub-beams is &lt;math&gt;2x&lt;/math&gt; because the horizontal sub-beam traverses the path twice. Thus, constructive interference occurs when this path difference is an integral number of wavelengths, i. e.,
:&lt;math&gt; 2x = m \lambda , ~~ m = 0, \pm 1, \pm 2, \ldots \quad \mbox{(Michelson interferometer)} &lt;/math&gt; (2.22)

where &lt;math&gt;\lambda &lt;/math&gt; is the wavelength of the light and &lt;math&gt;m&lt;/math&gt; is an integer. Note that &lt;math&gt;m&lt;/math&gt; is the number of wavelengths that fits evenly into the distance &lt;math&gt;2x&lt;/math&gt;.

----

{{1DWavesTOC}}</text>
      <sha1>r2rpims03fmuz7umotldhg6iz9bam0c</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Waves/Thin Films</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>196</id>
    <revision>
      <id>551355</id>
      <parentid>551268</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-08-07T17:59:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{1DWavesTOC}}
=== Thin Films ===

&lt;div style=&quot;float:right;margin:0 0 1em 1em;text-align:center;&quot;&gt; [[image:Introductory Physics fig 1.14.png|Figure 1.14: Plane light wave normally incident on a transparent thin film]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 1.14''': Plane light wave normally incident on a transparent thin film of thickness &lt;math&gt;d&lt;/math&gt; and index of refraction &lt;math&gt;n &gt; 1&lt;/math&gt;. Partial reflection occurs at the front surface of the film, resulting in beam A, and at the rear surface, resulting in beam B. Much of the wave passes completely through the film, as with C.&lt;/div&gt;

One of the most revealing examples of interference occurs when light interacts with a thin film of transparent material such as a soap bubble. Figure 1.14 shows how a plane wave normally incident on the film is partially reflected by the front and rear surfaces. The waves reflected off the front and rear surfaces of the film interfere with each other. The interference can be either constructive or destructive depending on the phase difference between the two reflected waves.

If the wavelength of the incoming wave is &lt;math&gt;\lambda &lt;/math&gt;, one would naively expect constructive interference to occur between the A and B beams if &lt;math&gt;2d&lt;/math&gt; were an integral multiple of &lt;math&gt;\lambda &lt;/math&gt;.

Two factors complicate this picture. First, the wavelength inside the film is not &lt;math&gt;\lambda &lt;/math&gt;, but &lt;math&gt;\lambda /n&lt;/math&gt;, where &lt;math&gt;n&lt;/math&gt; is the index of refraction of the film. Constructive interference would then occur if &lt;math&gt;2d = m \lambda /n&lt;/math&gt;. Second, it turns out that an additional phase shift of half a wavelength occurs upon reflection when the wave is incident on material with a higher index of refraction than the medium in which the incident beam is immersed. This phase shift doesn't occur when light is reflected from a region with lower index of refraction than felt by the incident beam. Thus beam B doesn't acquire any additional phase shift upon reflection. As a consequence, constructive interference actually occurs when
:&lt;math&gt; 2d = (m + 1/2) \lambda /n , ~~ m = 0,1,2, \ldots \quad \mbox{(constructive interference)} &lt;/math&gt; (2.23)

while destructive interference results when
:&lt;math&gt; 2d = m \lambda /n , ~~ m = 0,1,2, \ldots \quad \mbox{(destructive interference)} . &lt;/math&gt; (2.24)

When we look at a soap bubble, we see bands of colors reflected back from a light source. What is the origin of these bands? Light from ordinary sources is generally a mixture of wavelengths ranging from roughly &lt;math&gt;\lambda = 4.5 \times 10^{-7} \mbox{ m}&lt;/math&gt; (violet light) to &lt;math&gt;\lambda = 6.5 \times 10^{-7} \mbox{ m}&lt;/math&gt; (red light). In between violet and red we also have blue, green, and yellow light, in that order. Because of the different wavelengths associated with different colors, it is clear that for a mixed light source we will have some colors interfering constructively while others interfere destructively. Those undergoing constructive interference will be visible in reflection, while those undergoing destructive interference will not.

Another factor enters as well. If the light is not normally incident on the film, the difference in the distances traveled between beams reflected off of the front and rear faces of the film will not be just twice the thickness of the film. To understand this case quantitatively, we need the concept of refraction, which will be developed later in the context of geometrical optics. However, it should be clear that different wavelengths will undergo constructive interference for different angles of incidence of the incoming light. Different portions of the thin film will in general be viewed at different angles, and will therefore exhibit different colors under reflection, resulting in the colorful patterns normally seen in soap bubbles.

----

{{1DWavesTOC}}</text>
      <sha1>3an6lvjyxpfjaatnew5hq7zlmxl7dac</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Waves/Derivatives</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>197</id>
    <revision>
      <id>551549</id>
      <parentid>551357</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-08-07T19:06:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{1DWavesTOC}}
=== Math Tutorial -- Derivatives ===

&lt;div style=&quot;float:right;margin:0 0 1em 1em;text-align:center;&quot;&gt; [[image:Introductory Physics fig 1.15.png|Figure 1.15: Estimation of the derivative]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 1.15''': Estimation of the derivative, which is the slope of the tangent line. When point B approaches point A, the slope of the line AB approaches the slope of the tangent to the curve at point A. &lt;/div&gt;

This section provides a quick introduction to the idea of the derivative. For a more detailed discussion and exploration of the differentiation and of Calculus, see [[Calculus]] and [[Calculus/Differentiation|Differentiation]]. 

Often we are interested in the slope of a line tangent to a function &lt;math&gt;y(x)&lt;/math&gt; at some value of &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt;. This slope is called the derivative and is denoted &lt;math&gt;dy/dx&lt;/math&gt;. Since a tangent line to the function can be defined at any point &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt;, the derivative itself is a function of &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt;:
:&lt;math&gt; g(x) = \frac{d y(x)}{dx} . &lt;/math&gt; (2.25)

As figure 1.15 illustrates, the slope of the tangent line at some point on the function may be approximated by the slope of a line connecting two points, A and B, set a finite distance apart on the curve:
:&lt;math&gt; \frac{dy}{dx} \approx \frac{\Delta y}{\Delta x} . &lt;/math&gt; (2.26)

As B is moved closer to A, the approximation becomes better. In the limit when B moves infinitely close to A, it is exact.

== Table of Derivatives ==

Derivatives of some common functions are now given. In each case &lt;math&gt;a&lt;/math&gt; is a constant.

{{:Engineering Tables/Table of Derivatives}}

The product and chain rules are used to compute the derivatives of complex functions. For instance,

:&lt;math&gt; \frac{d}{dx} ( \sin (x) \cos (x)) = \frac{d \sin (x)}{dx} \cos (x) + \sin (x) \frac{d \cos (x)}{dx} = \cos^2 (x) - \sin^2 (x) &lt;/math&gt;

and

:&lt;math&gt; \frac{d}{dx} \log ( \sin (x) ) = \frac{1}{\sin (x)} \frac{d \sin (x)}{dx} = \frac{\cos (x)}{\sin (x)} . &lt;/math&gt;

----

{{1DWavesTOC}}</text>
      <sha1>g0tmccgo094wdvrt481xfix0yjcr2bp</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Waves/Group Velocity</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>198</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1388650</id>
      <parentid>1297921</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-01-26T06:54:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>88.66.41.8</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Group Velocity */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{1DWavesTOC}}
=== Group Velocity ===

We now ask the following question: How fast do wave packets move? Surprisingly, we often find that wave packets move at a speed very different from the phase speed, &lt;math&gt;c = \omega /k&lt;/math&gt;, of the wave composing the wave packet.

We shall find that the speed of motion of wave packets, referred to as the group velocity, is given by
: &lt;math&gt;u = \ 0.1 \mbox{m}^{-1}&lt;/math&gt;. The phase speed of deep ocean waves is &lt;math&gt;c = (g/k)^{1/2}&lt;/math&gt;. However, since &lt;math&gt;c \equiv \omega /k&lt;/math&gt;, we find the frequency of deep ocean waves to be &lt;math&gt;\omega = (gk)^{1/2}&lt;/math&gt;. The group velocity is therefore &lt;math&gt;u \equiv d \omega / dk = (g/k)^{1/2} / 2 = c/2&lt;/math&gt;. For the specified central wavenumber, we find that &lt;math&gt;u \approx (9.8 \mbox{ m} \mbox{ s}^{-2} / 0.1 \mbox{ m}^{-1} )^{1/2} / 2 \approx 5 \mbox{ m} \mbox{ s}^{-1}&lt;/math&gt;. By contrast, the phase speed of deep ocean waves with this wavelength is &lt;math&gt;c \approx 10 \mbox{ m} \mbox{ s}^{-1}&lt;/math&gt;.

Dispersive waves are waves in which the phase speed varies with wavenumber. It is easy to show that dispersive waves have unequal phase and group velocities, while these velocities are equal for non-dispersive waves.

=== Derivation of Group Velocity Formula ===

We now derive equation (1.36). It is easiest to do this for the simplest wave packets, namely those constructed out of the superposition of just two sine waves. We will proceed by adding two waves with full space and time dependence:
:&lt;math&gt; A = \sin ( k_1 x - \omega_1 t ) + \sin ( k_2 x - \omega_2 t ) &lt;/math&gt; (2.37)

After algebraic and trigonometric manipulations familiar from earlier sections, we find
:&lt;math&gt; A = 2 \sin ( k_0 x - \omega_0 t ) \cos ( \Delta k x - \Delta \omega t ) , &lt;/math&gt; (2.38)

where as before we have &lt;math&gt;k_0 = (k_1 + k_2 )/2&lt;/math&gt;, &lt;math&gt;\omega_0 = ( \omega_1 + \omega_2 )/2&lt;/math&gt;, &lt;math&gt;\Delta k = (k_2 - k_1 )/2&lt;/math&gt;, and &lt;math&gt;\Delta \omega = ( \omega_2 - \omega_1 )/2&lt;/math&gt;. Again think of this as a sine wave of frequency &lt;math&gt;\omega_0&lt;/math&gt; and wavenumber &lt;math&gt;k_0&lt;/math&gt; modulated by a cosine function. In this case the modulation pattern moves with a speed so as to keep the argument of the cosine function constant:
:&lt;math&gt; \Delta k x - \Delta \omega t = const. &lt;/math&gt; (2.39)

Differentiating this with respect to &lt;math&gt;t&lt;/math&gt; while holding &lt;math&gt;\Delta k&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\Delta \omega&lt;/math&gt; constant yields
:&lt;math&gt; u \equiv \frac{dx}{dt} = \frac{\Delta \omega}{\Delta k} . &lt;/math&gt; (2.40)

In the limit in which the deltas become very small, this reduces to the derivative
:&lt;math&gt; u = \frac{d \omega}{d k} , &lt;/math&gt; (2.41)

which is the desired result.


----

{{1DWavesTOC}}</text>
      <sha1>hiqbkgzfpn153uya96cs9o9n1e3tkk1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Waves/1D Examples</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>200</id>
    <revision>
      <id>551361</id>
      <parentid>551305</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-08-07T17:59:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{1DWavesTOC}}
=== Examples ===

We now illustrate some examples of phase speed and group velocity by showing the displacement resulting from the superposition of two sine waves, as given by equation (1.38), in the &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt;-&lt;math&gt;t&lt;/math&gt; plane. This is an example of a spacetime diagram, of which we will see many examples latter on.

&lt;div style=&quot;float:right;margin:0 0 1em 1em;text-align:center;&quot;&gt; [[Image:Introductory Physics fig 1.16.png|Figure 1.16: Net displacement of two sine waves]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 1.16''': Net displacement of the sum of two traveling sine waves plotted in the &lt;math&gt;x - t&lt;/math&gt; plane. The short vertical lines indicate where the displacement is large and positive, while the short horizontal lines indicate where it is large and negative. One wave has &lt;math&gt;k = 4&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\omega = 4&lt;/math&gt;, while the other has &lt;math&gt;k = 5&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\omega = 5&lt;/math&gt;. Thus, &lt;math&gt;\Delta k = 5 - 4 = 1&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\Delta \omega = 5 - 4 = 1&lt;/math&gt; and we have &lt;math&gt;u = \Delta \omega / \Delta k = 1&lt;/math&gt;. Notice that the phase speed for the first sine wave is &lt;math&gt;c_1 = 4/4 = 1&lt;/math&gt; and for the second wave is &lt;math&gt;c_2 = 5/5 = 1&lt;/math&gt;. Thus, &lt;math&gt;c_1 = c_2 = u&lt;/math&gt; in this case.&lt;/div&gt;

Figure 1.16 shows a non-dispersive case in which the phase speed equals the group velocity. The regions with vertical and horizontal hatching (short vertical or horizontal lines) indicate where the wave displacement is large and positive or large and negative. Large displacements indicate the location of wave packets. The positions of waves and wave packets at any given time may therefore be determined by drawing a horizontal line across the graph at the desired time and examining the variations in wave displacement along this line. The crests of the waves are indicated by regions of short vertical lines. Notice that as time increases, the crests move to the right. This corresponds to the motion of the waves within the wave packets. Note also that the wave packets, i. e., the broad regions of large positive and negative amplitudes, move to the right with increasing time as well.

Since velocity is distance moved &lt;math&gt;\Delta x&lt;/math&gt; divided by elapsed time &lt;math&gt;\Delta t&lt;/math&gt;, the slope of a line in figure 1.16, &lt;math&gt;\Delta t / \Delta x&lt;/math&gt;, is one over the velocity of whatever that line represents. The slopes of lines representing crests (the slanted lines, not the short horizontal and vertical lines) are the same as the slopes of lines representing wave packets in this case, which indicates that the two move at the same velocity. Since the speed of movement of wave crests is the phase speed and the speed of movement of wave packets is the group velocity, the two velocities are equal and the non-dispersive nature of this case is confirmed.

&lt;div style=&quot;float:right;margin:0 0 1em 1em;text-align:center;&quot;&gt; [[Image:Introductory Physics fig 1.17.png|Figure 1.17: Net displacement of the sum of two traveling sine waves]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 1.17''': Net displacement of the sum of two traveling sine waves plotted in the &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt;-&lt;math&gt;t&lt;/math&gt; plane. One wave has &lt;math&gt;k = 4.5&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\omega = 4&lt;/math&gt;, while the other has &lt;math&gt;k = 5.5&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\omega = 6&lt;/math&gt;. In this case &lt;math&gt;\Delta k = 5.5 - 4.5 = 1&lt;/math&gt; while &lt;math&gt;\Delta \omega = 6 - 4 = 2&lt;/math&gt;, so the group velocity is &lt;math&gt;u = \Delta \omega / \Delta k = 2/1 = 2&lt;/math&gt;. However, the phase speeds for the two waves are &lt;math&gt;c_1 = 4/4.5 = 0.889&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;c_2 = 6/5.5 = 1.091&lt;/math&gt;. The average of the two phase speeds is about &lt;math&gt;0.989&lt;/math&gt;, so the group velocity is about twice the average phase speed in this case. &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;float:right;margin:0 0 1em 1em;text-align:center;&quot;&gt; [[Image:Introductory Physics fig 1.18.png|Figure 1.18: Net displacement of the sum of two traveling sine waves]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 1.18''': Net displacement of the sum of two traveling sine waves plotted in the &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt;-&lt;math&gt;t&lt;/math&gt; plane. One wave has &lt;math&gt;k = 4&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\omega = 5&lt;/math&gt;, while the other has &lt;math&gt;k = 5&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\omega = 4&lt;/math&gt;. Can you figure out the group velocity and the average phase speed in this case? Do these velocities match the apparent phase and group speeds in the figure? &lt;/div&gt;

Figure 1.17 shows a dispersive wave in which the group velocity is twice the phase speed, while figure 1.18 shows a case in which the group velocity is actually opposite in sign to the phase speed. See if you can confirm that the phase and group velocities seen in each figure correspond to the values for these quantities calculated from the specified frequencies and wavenumbers.


----
{{1DWavesTOC}}</text>
      <sha1>19kzjgeqbm2fw59h56bxkmwqqiuyc7s</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Waves/1D Problems</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>201</id>
    <revision>
      <id>825367</id>
      <parentid>825366</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-04-10T21:35:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Az1568</username>
        <id>37227</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edit of [[Special:Contributions/88.234.9.70|88.234.9.70]], changed back to last version by Guanabot</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{1DWavesTOC}}
=== Problems ===

# Measure your pulse r&lt;nowiki&gt;ate. Compute the ordinary frequency of your heart beat in cycles per&lt;/nowiki&gt; second. Compute the angular frequency in radians per second. Compute the period.
# An important wavelength for radio waves in radio astronomy is &lt;math&gt;21 \mbox{ cm}&lt;/math&gt;. (This comes from neutral hydrogen.) Compute the wavenumber of this wave. Compute the ordinary and angular frequencies. (The speed of light is 3&amp;middot;10&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt; m/s)
# Sketch the resultant wave obtained from superimposing the waves &lt;math&gt;A = \sin (2x)&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;B = \sin (3x)&lt;/math&gt;. By using the trigonometric identity given in equation (1.17), obtain a formula for &lt;math&gt;A + B&lt;/math&gt; in terms of &lt;math&gt;\sin (5x/2)&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\cos (x/2)&lt;/math&gt;. Does the wave obtained from sketching this formula agree with your earlier sketch?
# Two sine waves with wavelengths &lt;math&gt;\lambda_1&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\lambda_2&lt;/math&gt; are superimposed, making wave packets of length &lt;math&gt;L&lt;/math&gt;. If we wish to make &lt;math&gt;L&lt;/math&gt; larger, should we make &lt;math&gt;\lambda_1&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\lambda_2&lt;/math&gt; closer together or farther apart? Explain your reasoning.
# By examining figure 1.9 versus figure 1.10 and then figure 1.11 versus figure 1.12, determine whether equation (1.18) works at least in an approximate sense for isolated wave packets.
# The frequencies of the chromatic scale in music are given by 
:&lt;math&gt; f_i = f_0 2^{i/12} ,\quad i = 0,1,2, \ldots ,11 , &lt;/math&gt; (2.42) 
:where &lt;math&gt;f_0&lt;/math&gt; is a constant equal to the frequency of the lowest note in the scale.
## Compute &lt;math&gt;f_1&lt;/math&gt; through &lt;math&gt;f_{11}&lt;/math&gt; if &lt;math&gt;f_0 = 440 \mbox{ Hz}&lt;/math&gt; (the &quot;A&quot; note).
## Using the above results, what is the beat frequency between the &quot;A&quot; (&lt;math&gt;i = 0&lt;/math&gt;) and &quot;B&quot; (&lt;math&gt;i = 2&lt;/math&gt;) notes? (The frequencies are given here in cycles per second rather than radians per second.)
## Which pair of the above frequencies yields the smallest beat frequency? Explain your reasoning.
# Large ships in general cannot move faster than the phase speed of surface waves with a wavelength equal to twice the ship's length. This is because most of the propulsive force goes into making big waves under these conditions rather than accelerating the ship.
## How fast can a &lt;math&gt;300 \mbox{ m}&lt;/math&gt; long ship move in very deep water?
## As the ship moves into shallow water, does its maximum speed increase or decrease? Explain.
# Given the formula for refractive index of light quoted in this section, for what range of &lt;math&gt;k&lt;/math&gt; does the phase speed of light in a transparent material exceed the speed of light in a vacuum?
# A police radar works by splitting a beam of microwaves, part of which is reflected back to the radar from your car where it is made to interfere with the other part which travels a fixed path, as shown in figure 1.19.
## If the wavelength of the microwaves is &lt;math&gt;\lambda &lt;/math&gt;, how far do you have to travel in your car for the interference between the two beams to go from constructive to destructive to constructive?
## If you are traveling toward the radar at speed &lt;math&gt;v = 30 \mbox{ m} \mbox{ s}^{-1}&lt;/math&gt;, use the above result to determine the number of times per second constructive interference peaks will occur. Assume that &lt;math&gt;\lambda = 3 \mbox{ cm}&lt;/math&gt;.
&lt;div style=&quot;float:right;margin:0 0 1em 1em;text-align:center;&quot;&gt; [[Image:Introductory Physics fig 1.19.png|Figure 1.19: Sketch of a police radar]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 1.19''': Sketch of a police radar. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;float:right;margin:0 0 1em 1em;text-align:center;&quot;&gt; [[Image:Introductory Physics fig 1.20.png|Figure 1.20: Sketch of a Fabry-Perot interferometer]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 1.20''': Sketch of a Fabry-Perot interferometer. &lt;/div&gt;
# Suppose you know the wavelength of light passing through a Michelson interferometer high accuracy. Describe how you could use the interferometer to measure the length of a small piece of material.
# A Fabry-Perot interferometer (see figure 1.20) consists of two parallel half-silvered mirrors placed a distance &lt;math&gt;d&lt;/math&gt; from each other as shown. The beam passing straight through interferes with the beam which reflects once off of both of the mirrored surfaces as shown. For wavelength &lt;math&gt;\lambda &lt;/math&gt;, what values of &lt;math&gt;d&lt;/math&gt; result in constructive interference?
# A Fabry-Perot interferometer has spacing &lt;math&gt;d = 2 \mbox{ cm}&lt;/math&gt; between the glass plates, causing the direct and doubly reflected beams to interfere (see figure 1.20). As air is pumped out of the gap between the plates, the beams go through 23 cycles of constructive-destructive-constructive interference. If the wavelength of the light in the interfering beams is &lt;math&gt;5 \times 10^{-7} \mbox{ m}&lt;/math&gt;, determine the index of refraction of the air initially in the interferometer.
# Measurements on a certain kind of wave reveal that the angular frequency of the wave varies with wavenumber as shown in the following table:

{| border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! &lt;math&gt;\omega &lt;/math&gt; (&lt;math&gt;\mbox{s}^{-1}&lt;/math&gt;)
! &lt;math&gt;k&lt;/math&gt; (&lt;math&gt;\mbox{m}^{-1}&lt;/math&gt;)
|-
| 5 || 1
|-
| 20 || 2
|-
| 45 || 3
|-
| 80 || 4
|-
| 125 || 5
|}
## Compute the phase speed of the wave for &lt;math&gt;k = 3 \mbox{ m}^{-1}&lt;/math&gt; and for &lt;math&gt;k = 4 \mbox{ m}^{-1}&lt;/math&gt;.
## Estimate the group velocity for &lt;math&gt;k = 3.5 \mbox{ m}^{-1}&lt;/math&gt; using a finite difference approximation to the derivative.
# Suppose some type of wave has the (admittedly weird) dispersion relation shown in figure 1.21.
## For what values of &lt;math&gt;k&lt;/math&gt; is the phase speed of the wave positive?
## For what values of &lt;math&gt;k&lt;/math&gt; is the group velocity positive?
&lt;div style=&quot;float:right;margin:0 0 1em 1em;text-align:center;&quot;&gt; [[Image:Introductory Physics fig 1.21.png|Figure 1.21: Sketch of a weird dispersion relation]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 1.21''': Sketch of a weird dispersion relation. &lt;/div&gt;
# Compute the group velocity for shallow water waves. Compare it with the phase speed of shallow water waves. (Hint: You first need to derive a formula for &lt;math&gt;\omega (k)&lt;/math&gt; from &lt;math&gt;c(k)&lt;/math&gt;.)
# Repeat the above problem for deep water waves.
# Repeat for sound waves. What does this case have in common with shallow water waves?</text>
      <sha1>fiblapwffhrrt3rx8wesu0qasspjvws</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Waves</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>202</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2551411</id>
      <parentid>2551409</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-08-23T15:40:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>86.141.191.110</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{ModernPhysicsTOC}}

The wave is a physical phenomenon that is found in a variety of contexts, a perturbation in the medium. You undoubtedly know about ocean waves and have probably played with a stretched slinky toy, producing undulations which move rapidly along the slinky. Other examples of waves are sound, vibrations in solids, and light (photons have the particularity of sharing characteristics of both waves and particles).  

Despite the vast differences in these different types of waves, they all consist of a fluctuation around an equilibrium position caused by a restoring force, and can be described by the same types of mathematical equations.  Understanding these equations is a powerful tool because it will let you understand the basics of a wide variety of seemingly unrelated phenomena.  The purpose of this section is to describe the ''kinematics'' of waves, i.e., to provide tools for describing the form and motion of all waves irrespective of their underlying physical mechanisms.

In this chapter we learn first about the basic properties of waves and introduce the most common type of wave, called the sinusoidal(sine) wave. In fact just about any type of wave can be expressed as a combination of sine functions using a technique proposed by Charles Fourier.  Examples of waves seen in the real world are presented. We then learn about the superposition principle, which allows us to construct complex wave patterns by superimposing sine waves. Using these ideas, we discuss the related ideas of beats and interferometry. Finally, the ideas of wave packets and group velocity are introduced.
{{clear}}

== Waves in one dimension ==
#[[Waves/Waves in one Dimension|The Mathematics of Waves]]
#[[Waves/Transverse, Longitudinal and Torsional waves|Transverse, Longitudinal, and Torsional waves]]
#[[Waves/Describing waves|Describing waves]]
#[[Waves/Sine Waves|Sine Waves]]
#[[Waves/Types of Waves|Types of Waves]]
#[[Waves/Sound Waves|Sound Waves]]
#[[Waves/Light|Light]]
#[[Waves/Superposition|Superposition Principle]]
#[[Waves/Beats|Beats]]
#[[Waves/Interferometers|Interferometers]]
#[[Waves/Thin Films|Thin Films]]
#[[Waves/Derivatives|Derivatives]]
#[[Waves/Fourier Transforms|Fourier Transforms]]
#[[Waves/Group Velocity|Group Velocity]]

:[[Waves/1D Examples|Examples]]
:[[Waves/1D Problems|Problems]]
:[[Waves/1D Solutions|Solutions]]
:[[Waves/1D Terminology|Terminology]]

== Waves in two and three dimensions ==
#[[Waves/Waves in two and three Dimensions|Introduction]]
#[[Waves/Vectors|Math:Vectors]]
#[[Waves/Plane Waves|Plane Waves]]
#[[Waves/Plane Superposition|Superposition of Plane Waves]]
#[[Waves/Single slit Diffraction|Single slit Diffraction]]
#[[Waves/Double slit Diffraction|Double slit Diffraction]]
#[[Waves/Diffraction Grating|Diffraction Grating]]

:[[Waves/2-3D Problems|Problems]]

== Geometrical optics ==
#[[Waves/Geometrical optics Introduction|Introduction]]
#[[Waves/Reflection and Refraction|Reflection and Refraction]]
#[[Waves/Total Internal Reflection|Total Internal Reflection]]
#[[Waves/Anisotropic Media|Anisotropic Media]]
#[[Waves/Optical Instruments|Optical Instruments]]
#[[Waves/Fermat's Principle|Fermat's Principle]]

:[[Waves/Geometrical Problems|Problems]]

{{Subjects|Atomic, molecular, and optical physics|Acoustics}}
{{Alphabetical|W}}
{{status|75%}}</text>
      <sha1>psunfrvkp3nqy74ghj5o73dl0l0ko8f</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:Eric119</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>204</id>
    <revision>
      <id>152395</id>
      <parentid>4703</parentid>
      <timestamp>2003-10-12T00:18:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ThomasStrohmann</username>
        <id>47</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Hi!
I am glad someone filled in the things I was missing on the Calculus:Functions page, but I had a few questions about things I wasn't sure about.  I might have modified some of them, but I wasn't sure ''why'' you did what you did, so I thought I might ask first:

*In the definition of a function you referred to the formal definition of function (set of ordered pairs).  Most people would completely miss the point, unless we went in more detail, which I don't think is wise.  What do you think?
*&quot;in the world of real numbers&quot; is another (less) obscure reference.  Anyone familar with complex numbers would understand what was meant without the parenthetical clause, but someone who wasn't familar wouldn't care.  Of course, that is no reason not to be precise, so leaving it in would still be appropriate.
*In the example of adding, subtracting, etc. the functions f and g, you wrote &quot;def&quot; before the subtraction example.  Why?  What do you mean?
*I like the continuity section.  I was going to wait until limits to introduce it, but you tied it in with graphing effectively.
*I had left out a * 0 = 0 intentionally, since it is not an axiom of field theory (it can be proved easily).  Of course, I never titled the list as &quot;axioms of field theory&quot;, but rather as arithematic truths -- and a * 0 = 0 is certainly true.  Anyone reading it not familar with field theory would not notice one way or another.  So I am split in whether I think it should be included or not.  On second thought, the whole Algebra section is mostly redundant -- the only commonly missed fact is the distributive property (anyone who doesn't know a + 0 = a or a * 1 = a shouldn't be taking Calculus).

Conincidentally, my name happens to be Eric as well.

 -- [[User:IntMan|IntMan]]

Re: functions as ordered pairs -- Perhaps you're right. That little bit of information isn't necessary, as functions are rarely specified by giving a set of ordered pairs.

Re: complex numbers -- I hope people trying to take calculus have already been introduced to imaginary numbers in algebra or trig. Also, I remember that there is one method for solving differential equations that involves complex numbers (though I'm uncertain of the details), so if we think people won't know/remember them we should cover them in a review section (unless we are not covering that, but since there is a major section &quot;Advanced Calculus&quot; I assume we will be.)

Re: &quot;def&quot; -- It's just a typo. I meant nothing by it.

Re: continuity -- Thank you.

Re: a*0 -- Well, I thought a * 0 = 0 was an axiom, but apparently I misremembered. I definately agree that it should be removed.

[[User:Eric119|Eric119]] 20:47 22 Jul 2003 (UTC)

About the Hello, World! Page, Sorry, I was being rude.  Sometimes I do get carried away.  I was probably just in a bad mood at the time.  For example: using endl is just a preference because I don't like it when I write a program, and nothing shows up on the screen until the program exits.  The return 0, is the only thing I really have a problem with.  Point: You are right about the not having to return 0.  Counter-Point: But since it is standard pratice not to rely on the system to free all of your ram you've allocated, should it also be right to rely on the system to return the 0?

Josh:[[User:Mrquick|Mrquick]] 23:13 29 Jul 2003 (UTC)

Well, I suppose that's a style issue, too. The implicit &quot;return 0;&quot; is guaranteed according to the C++ standard. You could say it's better to explictly state that there were no errors. Or you could say that by default we assume the program did not encounter errors.

[[User:Eric119|Eric119]] 18:59 30 Jul 2003 (UTC)

----
About the [[calculus]] page: it didn't exist and was showing in red. See the [[Wikibooks:Staff lounge|Staff lounge]]. Apparently the database got confused and marked it as a nonexistent page with a history. Thanks for reverting it. [[User:Geoffrey|Geoffrey]] 23:31, 11 Aug 2003 (UTC)

----
Hi Eric, sorry I didn't realize before that you've put up a new puzzle. I've moved it to our new subcategories under 'Arithmetic Puzzles'. [[User:ThomasStrohmann | Thomas]]</text>
      <sha1>8zjlvui4yhhektwc4j27fuyiki1797m</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Organic Chemistry/Alkanes/Methane</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>208</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2613939</id>
      <parentid>2613938</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-03-04T14:04:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Stryn</username>
        <id>390608</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/182.185.175.99|182.185.175.99]] ([[User talk:182.185.175.99|talk]]) to last version by 98.210.210.193</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Organic Chemistry/Foundational concepts of organic chemistry|&lt;&lt; Foundational concepts]] | [[Organic Chemistry/Alkanes/Ethane|Ethane &gt;&gt;]]
----
'''Methane''', CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; is the simplest organic molecule. It is a gas at [http://www.wikipedia.org/wiki/STP standard temperature and pressure] and is a carbon atom with four hydrogen atoms bonded to it in a tetrahedral shape.


{|
|-
|
|-
| ''Methane''
|}

This is a flattened, two-dimensional representation of methane that you will see commonly. The true three-dimensional form of methane does not have any 90 degree angles between bonded hydrogens. The bonds point to the four corners of a tetrahedron, forming cos&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt;(−1/3) ≈ 109.5 degree bond angles.

[[Image:sp3.jpg]]
----
[[Organic Chemistry/Foundational concepts of organic chemistry|&lt;&lt; Foundational concepts]] | [[Organic Chemistry/Alkanes|&lt;&lt; Alkanes]] | Methane | [[Organic Chemistry/Alkanes/Ethane|Ethane &gt;&gt;]] | [[Organic Chemistry/Introduction to reactions|Introduction to reactions &gt;&gt;]]

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>pw3xnn4no3gnp2iz7sgq54ccwj83p3y</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Organic Chemistry/Alkanes/Ethane</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>209</id>
    <revision>
      <id>961121</id>
      <parentid>654661</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-09-07T18:33:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>removing all sub-pages from [[Category:Chemistry]], reformatting book main pages to use {{Subject}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Organic Chemistry/Alkanes/Methane|&lt;&lt; Methane]] | [[Organic Chemistry/Alkanes/Propane thru decane|Propane thru decane &gt;&gt;]]
----
Ethane is the second simplest hydrocarbon molecule. It is pretty much just two methane molecules attached to each other, less two hydrogens.

&lt;img&gt;

===Number of hydrogens to carbons===
This equation describes the relationship between the number of hydrogen and carbon atoms in alkanes:

:'''H = 2C + 2'''

where &quot;C&quot; and &quot;H&quot; are used to represent the number of carbon and hydrogen atoms present in one molecule. If C = 2, then H = 6.

Many textbooks put this in the following format:

:'''C&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;2N+2&lt;/sub&gt;'''

where &quot;C&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;&quot; and &quot;H&lt;sub&gt;2N+2&lt;/sub&gt;&quot; represent the number of carbon and hydrogen atoms present in one molecule. If C&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt; = 3, then H&lt;sub&gt;2N+2&lt;/sub&gt; = 2(3) + 2 = 8. (For this formula look to the &quot;N&quot; for the number, the &quot;C&quot; and the &quot;H&quot; letters themselves do not change.)
----
[[Organic chemistry|&lt;&lt; Organic chemistry]] | [[Organic Chemistry/Alkanes|&lt;&lt; Alkanes]] | [[Organic Chemistry/Alkanes/Methane|&lt;&lt; Methane]] | Ethane | [[Organic Chemistry/Alkanes/Propane thru decane|Propane thru decane &gt;&gt;]] | [[Organic Chemistry/Introduction to reactions|Introduction to reactions &gt;&gt;]]

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>52qooq0gw29adn1rdnzwpc326lmzutq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:Mrquick</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>211</id>
    <revision>
      <id>152402</id>
      <parentid>2070</parentid>
      <timestamp>2003-08-27T06:10:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dysprosia</username>
        <id>32</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">Hello and welcome! Is [[Programming:Perl]] going to be chapter in the Programming textbook? If not then a link to the Wikipedia article on the [[en:Perl programming language]] article would be best - the ''last'' thing we want to do is recreate Wikipedia here! :-) --[[User:Maveric149|Maveric149]] 09:16 22 Jul 2003 (UTC)

Welcome! It will be as soon as someone who knows Perl (not me) decides to write it.  Until that though, a link to Wikipedia would be acceptable; not a replacement though because a textbook is written differently than an encyclopedia. --Josh

:Ah - I see now. Good everything is self-contained within the single book - that's what I like to see. Oh and you could use the Wikipedia article to start such a chapter: just make sure to say &quot;From Wikipedia&quot; in the edit summary - a mention on the &quot;Authors page&quot; would also be nice (doing both of those combined with the fact that we are all part of the Wikimedia family should be good enough for the GFDL...). --mav

----
Re: [[programmingc:ch1_cpp]] (an impossible name to remember, btw) Are you using an automated HTML syntax coloring program? I &lt;font color=&quot;#0000FF&quot;&gt;do&lt;/font&gt; not like the colors appearing in the &lt;font color=&quot;#0000FF&quot;&gt;main&lt;/font&gt; text (not the programs); you shouldn't &lt;font color=&quot;#009900&quot;&gt;include&lt;/font&gt; that text in your syntax-colorer input.

Also, the namespace problem can be fixed by leaving out the .h from iostream. Only in ancient (nonstandard) compilers does &lt;iostream&gt; not exist (as opposed to &lt;iostream.h&gt;), and in all &lt;iostream&gt;-compatible compilers the file's contents are in std. If a compiler does not support the non-h syntax (and the other thirty-odd standard headers), it's not a good one to learn from. [[User:Geoffrey|Geoffrey]] 03:50 28 Jul 2003 (UTC)

I'll try that namespace thing... Yeah, that colored thing isn't that good.  I wrote something myself to do the conversion, having things colored in the text didn't bother me, as long as it was actually a command (but if the consensus is not to do it, I won't).  That &quot;do&quot; thing, I don't know why its not working?  Take, &quot;if&quot;, and &quot;while&quot;, they don't just turn blue in the text, my program searches for the accompaying paranthesis, but for some reason it won't do that for &quot;do&quot;.  I can't figure out why... Its probably due to some weird mistake I made when I programmed the parser at ultra high speed... so I'm writing a new parser... [[User:Mrquick|Mrquick]] 18:09 28 Jul 2003 (UTC)
----
I just wanted to call you attention to a discussion I hope I've started at the staff lounge regarding namespaces. No disrespect, but I'm recommending against your approach, and I think we ought to keep a record of the our reasoning, so the Lounge archive will do it. [[User:LouI|LouI]] 18:10 1 Aug 2003 (UTC)

----

Is there some way I can or an admin have the server email me my password now, instead of waiting for I think a half of a month.  I kind of forgot what it was :(. Josh

Lucky me, I figured it out, I didn't see the email myself a new password button. [[User:Mrquick|Mrquick]] 05:00, 15 Aug 2003 (UTC)

----
Hello :) Nice work in restructuring [[Computer programming]], but I disliked your choice of the suffix &quot;in programming&quot;, as it was very cumbersome for other titles.

By the way, if you've been active at the Wikipedia, the same syntax works here too. To create a tab indent, write a &lt;nowiki&gt;:&lt;/nowiki&gt;, to create bullets, use successive &lt;nowiki&gt;*&lt;/nowiki&gt;s, if you have an article in the form &lt;nowiki&gt;[[Namespace:Article]], you can just write [[Namespace:Article|]]&lt;/nowiki&gt; and it'll show up without the Namespace: part. Leaving a space as the first character of the line forces the rest of the line to be in fixed-width font, perfect for code.

Thanks :) [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 09:55, 20 Aug 2003 (UTC)

----

Hello, It seems I've dissappeared for a bit.  I just went off to college and the local college ethernet is down.  After one day viruses killed it.  Not fun.  I should become active again as soon as I have a permanent, or semi-permanent, internet solution.  Josh</text>
      <sha1>c1uymxokn450ejv02b3ycm5ifw9sdw9</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Optics</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>212</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2478935</id>
      <parentid>2478933</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-01-18T00:08:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Evan.oltmanns</username>
        <id>734596</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Update front graphic</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{B3D:N2P/Hidden begin|title=For how to help with this book, click &quot;show&quot;.}}
* Do add new material and examples and make corrections.  It all helps.

All help is welcome. 

{{Hidden end}}

&lt;!--Spacer--&gt;

[[File:Refraction_-_Huygens-Fresnel_principle.svg|350px|right]]

{{warning|The '''structure''' of this book is still '''being developed'''. 

The pages marked with a * are not currently accessed when reading the book in 'next page' order.}} 


{{stages}}

==Optics==

&lt;!--Many of the pages have closely related free/YouTube.  This is by design.  Many students find the video presentation helpful with learning this material.--&gt;
''about this book''

==Contents==
*[[/Light/]] {{stage|50%}}
** [[/Nature of light/]] {{stage|25%}}
*** [[/Waves/]] {{stage|0%}}
*** [[/Evidence for wave properties of light/]] {{stage|0%}}
*** [[/Evidence for light as a stream of particles/]] {{stage|0%}}
** [[/Features of a wave/]] {{stage|0%}}
* [[/Propagation of light/]] {{stage|0%}}
** [[/Fermat's Principle/]] {{stage|25%}}
** [[/Refraction/]] {{stage|25%}}
** [[/Total internal reflection/]] {{stage|25%}}
*[[/Fibre optics/]] {{stage|25%}}
*[[/Images/]] {{stage|25%}}
** Images {{stage|0%}}
*** Real images {{stage|0%}}
*** Virtual images {{stage|0%}}
** Curved mirrors {{stage|0%}}
** The mirror equation {{stage|0%}}
*[[/Lenses/]] {{stage|0%}}
** Introduction  {{stage|0%}}
** Refraction at a spherical interface {{stage|0%}}
** A lens {{stage|0%}}
*** Locating the image {{stage|0%}}
*** The lensmaker’s equation {{stage|0%}}
*** Converging and diverging lenses {{stage|0%}}
* Optical instruments using lenses {{stage|0%}}
** Single-lens systems {{stage|0%}}
*** A magnifying glass {{stage|0%}}
** Compound optical systems {{stage|0%}}
** The refracting telescope {{stage|0%}}
* Interference and diffraction {{stage|0%}}
** Wave phenomena {{stage|0%}}
** [[/Huygens’ Principle/]] {{stage|0%}}
*** Introduction {{stage|0%}}
*** Interference {{stage|0%}}
*** Diffraction {{stage|0%}}
** Summary of formulas in this chapter {{stage|0%}}

*Small angle approximation {{stage|0%}}
**Small angle approximation {{stage|0%}}
*Derivations for the Module 7 exam {{stage|0%}}
**Derivations for the Module 7 exam {{stage|0%}}

X-ray optics {{stage|0%}}

[[/Authors/]]

==External Resources==
*[http://diffractive-optics.org/ Diffractive optics] papers and patents. 
* Also available [http://d4ap.com/optics/] and [http://leakway.org/optics/] news and events.
*[http://grin-optics.org Gradient-index optics] reviews, theory and ideas

{{Subjects|Atomic, molecular, and optical physics}}
{{alphabetical|O}}
{{status|0%}}
__NOTOC__ __NOEDITSECTION__
[[de:Optik]]
[[es:Física/Óptica]]
[[fr:Optique]]
[[nl:Fysica/Optica]]
[[pt:Introdução à Física/Óptica]]
[[sv:Fysik A/Optik]]</text>
      <sha1>hc1wv1jpm15mpda5dk996pgaiwks2yy</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Wikibooks:Textbook planning</title>
    <ns>4</ns>
    <id>214</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1967988</id>
      <parentid>1967968</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-11-06T23:06:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Reference links */ fixed link</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Historical project page}}

Note: See also [[Wikiversity]] page for discussion of Wikiversity / WikiU.
----
The following areas were [http://mail.wikipedia.org/pipermail/textbook-l/2003-July/000164.html recently suggested in the mailing list] as important to resolve in regards to the [[Main_Page|textbook project]].

When applicable, list your username to vote for (a) particular opinion(s).
(This is a &quot;vote&quot; only in the sense of a show of support; no decision has been taken to count votes in any particular way, or even at all, to make final choices.)
Write arguments for your position after the list of options; also add more options if you like.
If there's not a list of options, but instead a list of points needing discussion, then you can list more points or give sublists of options for a particular point of discussion.
Et cetera.

== Name of the project ==
* &quot;Open Textbook Project&quot; -- http://www.opentextbook.org - [[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
* &quot;Free Textbook Project&quot; --
* &quot;Wikimedia Textbooks&quot; -- [[User:Kpjas|Kpjas]]
* &quot;Wikipedia Textbooks&quot; --
* &quot;Wikibooks&quot; (mav owns the urls and plans to transfer them to Wikimedia) -- [[User:maveric149|mav]], [[User:Toby Bartels|Toby Bartels]], [[User:Kpjas|Kpjas]], [[User:LouI|LouI]], [[User:LittleDan|LittleDan]], [[User:ThomasStrohmann|Thomas]], [[User:Dhum Dhum|Dhum Dhum]]
* &quot;Wikitext&quot; -- [[User:Toby Bartels|Toby Bartels]],

The URL could also be http://wikibooks.wikimedia.org/ (owned by the Foundation already). -- [[User:Toby Bartels|Toby Bartels]] 08:14 27 Jul 2003 (UTC)

We should avoid entering the philosophical debate between &quot;open&quot; and &quot;free&quot; in our name. -- [[User:Toby Bartels|Toby Bartels]] 08:14 27 Jul 2003 (UTC)

We should continue the tradition of having &quot;wiki&quot; in our name since that is what defines us the most - even more than the free license. --[[User:Maveric149|mav]] 19:44 28 Jul 2003 (UTC)
:I agree completely with that one. [[User:Dhum Dhum|Dhum Dhum]] 20:11 5 Aug 2003 (UTC) 

We should not limit ourselves to being a textbook-only shop - all non-fiction books should be allowed. --[[User:Maveric149|mav]] 19:44 28 Jul 2003 (UTC)
:Or even fiction books, that would be interesting [[User:LittleDan|LittleDan]]
::If you are talking about stuff like Huck Finn with annotation and wikified words going to encyclopedia articles, then yes. But we should ''not'' be in the business of creating our own fictional worlds. That is a different project. --[[User:Maveric149|mav]] 17:24 1 Aug 2003 (UTC)

== Types of content that are to be covered ==
* Traditional textbook content -- Presumably everybody supports this!
** Do realize that the effort may be futile, no matter the resulting quality. One would need to make a snapshot for some unusually brave (solidly tenured) professors to try, then supply an errata list and print many copies. A live wiki is too unstable to teach a class from. --[[User:AlbertCahalan|AlbertCahalan]] 20:29, 13 Feb 2005 (UTC)
** ''Non traditional textbooks'', there are some subjects (especially in science on post-graduate levels) for which there are no traditional textbooks. In such a book its dynamics are not a problem. --[[User:Iztok.jeras|IzI]] 18:07, 25 August 2005 (UTC)
* Possible other book content:
** How-to directions like cookbooks -- [[User:Toby Bartels|Toby Bartels]],
*** Well, the envisioned Wikibooks' Cookbook might turn out to be a general book about cooking in different cultures with historical background and some conscious consumerism threads
*** The Cookbook is doing very well. It does suffer from problems with: [http://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Deletionism deletionism], case-sensitivity and the Cookbook: prefix ruining normal wiki ease-of-use (&lt;nowiki&gt;normal [[easy linking]] is unusable&lt;/nowiki&gt;), lack of [[Special:Specialpages]] specific to the Cookbook, and a sidebar [[Main_Page]] link that doesn't go to the main page of the cookbook. --[[User:AlbertCahalan|AlbertCahalan]] 20:29, 13 Feb 2005 (UTC)
**Manuals to use certain things (such as a software program) 
***Should be textbook-oriented in presentation. --[[User:Maveric149|Maveric149]]
**A broad travel guide covering the entire world. -- [[User:Dhum Dhum|Dhum Dhum]]
***The people at http://www.wikitravel.org are going to fill that role. Our focus here should be in ''instructing'' students - travel guides are informative (like an encyclopedia), not instructive (like a textbook). --[[User:Maveric149|mav]]
**Other non-fiction works
**Fiction books. [[User:LittleDan|LittleDan]]
*** Something like a &quot;[[w:cliffs notes|Cliff's Notes]]&quot; possibly? --[[User:Neolux|Neolux]] 15:28 1 Aug 2003 (UTC)
***Absolutely ''not'' newly-created fiction (that is a different project; &quot;Wiktion&quot;). But we should have public domain fiction of already established works (with annotation; such as the works of Mark Twain). We can also have ''Cliff's Notes''-type extensive summaries of works. That would be neat. --[[User:Maveric149|mav]] 17:20 1 Aug 2003 (UTC)
***Fiction study that does not go very deeply into criticism.  Major themes that are universally accepted seem to be the order in textbooks I've dealt with. --[[User:Jdl32579|Jdl32579]] 12:57, 14 Jun 2004 (UTC)
* Remixes and compilations of free content (Wikipedia, ...). Sometimes all the knowledge is already freely available, all it has to be done is to organize it into a book (thought its not that simple). --[[User:Iztok.jeras|IzI]] 18:07, 25 August 2005 (UTC)
* I really favor -footnotes-, similar to those found along with biblical texts; I find myself having the need to use 'symbols' [e.g. (†), (‡), and (*)] to use for reference-''like'' footnotes.[[User:RekonDog|RekonDog]] ([[User talk:RekonDog|talk]]) 10:10, 23 August 2009 (UTC)

== Key policies ==
* While a name hasn't been settled, we'll need a sort of &quot;Wiki&quot; policies for our developer interaction separate from any policies that affect the texts themselves:
* A proposed outline of [[Wikibooks:textbook considerations|textbook considerations]] is available for Wiki development and discussion.
* A short outline proposal for a description of processes is open for comment or update at [[Wikibooks:textbook development process|textbook development process]].

== Timetable for setting things up ==
* As it gets done
* Schedules are for proprietary encyclopedias. [[User:LittleDan|LittleDan]]

== Resources and techniques useful in creating educational content ==
* [[Textbook Figures and Diagrams]] -- I've created a page for the discussion of resources to support the creation of figures and diagrams for wiki textbooks. --[[User:StevenBrewer|StevenBrewer]] 14:11, 17 October 2005 (UTC)
* photographic images
* diagrams
* maps
* chemical/mathematical formulae
* Javascript quizzes
**Practise problems in traditional format
* Flash quizzes
** I could make some, however, Flash is [en:Proprietary]. It's something we should think about before we dive in head-first. [[User:KirbyMeister|KirbyMeister]] 20:14, 7 May 2004 (UTC)
* Java applets
* cookies
* flashcards: free version of [http://www.flashcardexchange.com/ Flashcard Exchange]
* [http://www.studystack.com/ flashcards, matching, wordsearch, and hangman from StudyStack.com]
* Request Tracker (List of requests) - Some of us can make useful drawings/diagrams/photos in subjects that we wouldn't be qualified to write textbooks for

== GNU GPL Server Software to draw ideas from==
* '''Moodle''' - PHP software that aims to make quality online courses (eg distance education) easy to develop and conduct. Learning and development are guided using a social constructionist philosophy. 
[http://moodle.org/sites Implemented on thousands of sites and in 30 languages].
See [http://moodle.org website] and [http://sourceforge.net/projects/moodle development site].

* [http://lon-capa.org/ lon-capa] might be a better model to support on-line courses.  You can create extremely rich interactive problems and easily integrate many different kinds of resources. --[[User:StevenBrewer|StevenBrewer]] 14:11, 17 October 2005 (UTC)

== Potential changes that need to be made to the software ==
* Compiling many pages into one large document:
** A standard book structure (sections) could be created that could be easily translated into LaTeX and further into PDF (with a table of contents and a cover picture). --[[User:Iztok.jeras|IzI]] 17:47, 25 August 2005 (UTC)
* Automating navigation links within textbooks:
** [http://mail.wikipedia.org/pipermail/textbook-l/2003-July/000088.html Mav's suggestion] on the mailing list for modular URLs -- [[User:maveric149|mav]],
** It would be nice if when one comes to the end of a textbook page which one had accessed by clicking on a table of contents entry,  one could go on to the next page of the book without having to go back to the table of contents and select the next page from there. On other websites one often sees this done with ''NEXT'' buttons; or ''PREVIOUS'' for going backwards. -- rew 
**Mav's suggestion as [http://mail.wikipedia.org/pipermail/textbook-l/2003-July/000099.html modified by Toby] -- [[User:Toby Bartels|Toby Bartels]], [[User:Maveric149|mav]] (I very much like Toby's improvements)
**WikiGroups has already been developed with another php/GPL wiki; [http://mail.wikipedia.org/pipermail/textbook-l/2003-July/000222.html] - this will allow us to have one TOC/Index per Wikibook but I think we can tweak that software to make it possible to have more than one TOC/Index per book (the trick would be to add the TOC/Index's name after a ? to every link on the TOC/Index page - then when you click on a link to a module, the WikiGroup code on that page will know which %trail% to dispaly. Those links in turn would have the TOC/Index's name after a ? but only for links in the %trail%). 
** Karl's idea to [http://mail.wikipedia.org/pipermail/textbook-l/2003-July/000102.html nest URLs] in a way that reflects the structure of the book
** [[meta:Wikibooks extension|Yet another proposal]] from [[User:Magnus Manske|Magnus Manske]]
** In a related note an automatically generated index (cached!?) would make any textbook more useful [[User:m.linger|m.linger]]
* separation of books' contents from each other and from meta information (or rather a means to filter thing out) 
**This should be possible when categories are implemented for Wikipedia.
* Wikipedia namespace moved to Wikibooks: or something like that when the name is settled

== Proposal ==
The project '''wikibooks''' does not seem to be enjoying the same sort of growth that the original '''wikipedia''' did.  There are probably a number of reasons for this.  I shall give a few reasons I think are important and then follow up with some suggestions for the action that could be taken to remedy this.

1) Wikibooks requires a different logon to wikipedia.  IMHO it would be better for the project if existing wikipedia developers could be automatically part of wikibooks.  This would allow more free movement of labour from wikipedia to wikibooks.  A strong motivating factor for people developing in wikipedia is the racking up of credit in the form of edited articles.  Why not allow create a contributions page that gives credit to all material worked on in any wiki project?

2) Wikibooks is not interconnected in the same way that wikipedia is.  There is a clear need for a different structure to the books as they are meant to be (at least eventually) printed and should therefore have a linear style.  However, if links were made in such a way that they could deleted without interfering with the quality of the text then we could have the same interconnection that wikipedia has without that necessarily causing problems with the style of the books.

* We need a way to designate sections as being developer areas (but within the actual text itself) We could produce a special heading &quot;Developer's notes and links&quot; which has a template (to ensure consistent usage.

* We need a special link type that represents a temporary link for development purposes.  This would allow the developer links and comments necessary to speed up development.  But at the same time would allow these links to be removed with ease when the wikibook is downloaded.  (Of course links just to wikipedia should be fairly easy to remove automatically although it might help if they appeared in a different colour to remind developers that that material reffered to will not be available to the readers of printed versions.

3) Also links can be made from relevent pages of wikipedia to wikibooks.  This should draw in much more labour to liven up wikibooks.  This is one thing that I can implement on my own. So I shall start introducing a section on some selected wikipedia pages entitled &quot;relevent wikibooks&quot;.  I may also start links to wikibooks in the main text of some articles in wikipedia.  However, without 2) we may find that people learn to ignore links to wikibooks as they are deadends.

Please comment on these proposals.
[[User:82.43.185.179|82.43.185.179]] 11:44, 27 Aug 2004 (UTC) (Barnaby dawson)

At least one wikibook is interconnected in the same way that wikipedia is. The [[Cookbook]] is highly self-connected. If anything, some connections need to be severed. At the bottom of most recipes you will find a Categories link. This should list all the categories in the cookbook. Unfortunately, it lists all sorts of other random unrelated stuff. Cookbook info is drowned out by the noise. --[[User:AlbertCahalan|AlbertCahalan]] 20:40, 13 Feb 2005 (UTC)

Is #2 really the case?  I tend to think that Wikibooks should be created to best serve the user.  If that best way is by creating a non-linear book, so be it.  Let's use the medium we have and not be tied to an old communication medium. [[User:Liblamb|liblamb]] 05:28, 14 Feb 2005 (UTC)

Learning a new topic needs to be linear (at least to an extent). For example, learning about ionic bonding in chemistry before learning about the periodic table would be very difficult. Coming back to a topic you have already learnt is when non-linear content is generally more useful (which is where GOOD appendices and indices come in).
[[User:m.linger|m.linger]] 02:06, 06 Jul 2005 (UTC)

:Maybe the most important thing is increasing the ability for this 'free movement of labour' from wikipedia. There is vast untapped potential for all those experts to get interested in and excited about wikibooks. The two best ways, which I think have been floated around as nebulous proposals for some time, are as mentioned above - automatic or connected logon for existing wikipedia editors, and very simply, far more links to wikibooks for the click-happy wikipediholics! Is there anywhere on Wikipedia fairly heavily trafficked by people with the technical knowhow that could support or rubbish these suggestions? [[User:Mark Lewis|Mark Lewis]] 22:21, 14 Jun 2005 (UTC)

== Internationalization ==
Yes, please!

== Participants in textbook planning ==
You who are reading this, and anyone else.
* [[User:maveric149|maveric149]]
* [[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
* [[User:Toby Bartels|Toby Bartels]] [I'm not active, although I still like my suggestion listed in [[#Potential changes that need to be made to the software]].]
* [[User:Kpjas|Kpjas]]
* [[User:Cyp|Cyp]] (Only made one real edit so far.)
* [[User:Neolux|Neolux]]
* [[User:LouI|LouI]]
* [[User:Mrquick|Josh]]
* [[User:LittleDan|LittleDan]]
* [[User:ThomasStrohmann|Thomas]]
* [[User:Emperorbma|Emperorbma]]
* [[User:Zanimum|Zanimum]]
* [[User:Jdl32579|Jdl32579]]
* [[User:Frankie Roberto|Frankie Roberto]] - mostly interested in [[Linguistics]] and planning issues
* [[User:209.182.169.166|209.182.169.166]] 17:24, 16 Dec 2004 (UTC)
* [[User:Yann|Yann]]
* [[User:Nct|Nct]]
* [[User:Everlong|Everlong]]

See also: [[Wikibooks:Wikibookians]]

=== Reference links ===

* [[Wikibooks:Files to be harvested|Reference works to use to build books]]
* [[Wikibooks:Media]]
* [[Wikibooks:Boilerplate request for permission]]

--[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]] 02:15 30 Jul 2003 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>77xx2zed1vsoswnbu0gc874p6hppk2f</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Computer Programming/Tools</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>215</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2064254</id>
      <parentid>1493225</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-03-04T19:34:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Avicennasis</username>
        <id>314063</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WP:AWB/T|Typo fixing]], typos fixed: specfically → specifically, ie  → i.e. using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Computer_Programming_Navigation|Tools}}
__TOC__

==Wikify==

Wikify is a program written by Josh Ferguson specifically designed to turn a standard text file into a html/wiki format.  It is being used to do the color syntax highlighting for the C++ code in the C++ section of this textbook.

Author's Statement:
Wikify can not yet wikify itself, due to the fact that it has html codes in it, which confuses itself.  I plan to rewrite it soon so it can wikify itself.  Right now though, it works good with simple code.  And it can be modified to work with other languages by changing the variables in it.  Later on I'll probably move all the important variables into text files so it will be more easy to change things for other languages (i.e. by changing the text files, or extension checks), etc...

The code was written really fast, so the code isn't perfect, even though the author stubbornly maintains that it is close.

Code Snapshot as of 7-22-03
----

The escape sequences in the code give the wikiscript problems, so here is a link to it.  Click on it, and it will take you to a page, where you can click on it, and it will come up.

This should be compilable by any standard C++ compiler.

[[Category:Computer Programming|Tools]]</text>
      <sha1>c1rjy7fkz0edrpv3uqhu5mkzvo0evvu</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>BASIC Programming</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>217</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2714212</id>
      <parentid>2713945</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-16T09:37:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Syum90</username>
        <id>1499881</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Undid revision 2713945 by [[Special:Contributions/205.202.225.189|205.202.225.189]] ([[User talk:205.202.225.189|discuss]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''BASIC''' was developed in 1963 at Dartmouth College in Hanover, New Hampshire as a teaching language. The acronym BASIC stands for '''B'''eginner's '''A'''ll-Purpose '''S'''ymbolic '''I'''nstruction '''C'''ode.

== Programming Preliminaries ==
Anybody can write a program. A background in mathematics or science is not required. Patience, practice, and an interest in the subject matter should suffice, along with the required software and hardware.

Understanding programs can appear daunting at first, but their reliance on logical operations allow for easy learning of commands which you will commonly see in many programs.

A program itself is merely a series of commands in the order in which they are to be executed. That is to say, that the first line is the beginning of the program!

All programs a user uses from day to day, including browsers (Internet Explorer, Firefox, etc.) and operating systems (Windows, *nix and MacOS) are separate sets of lines of code, which aim to fulfill tasks. the amount of code is dependent on how simple the task generally, and different types of code may be used for the advantages they give. BASIC is considered an excellent starting point for moving onto other languages, and can be useful for simple programs.

=== Programming Languages ===

Programming languages allow people to give instructions to a computer with commands that both the computer and the programmer can understand.  Different programming languages use different commands and different rules for entering those commands; similar to the way people speak different words to each other with the same meaning.  One person may say &quot;hello&quot;, while another says &quot;hola&quot;, which, although express the same thought, appear different.

Similarly other human languages, such as French and Spanish, are similar to each other, as computer programming languages can be also.  Programming languages that are similar are usually referred to as related languages.  Once a person learns a programming language, it is easier to then learn other programming languages especially those related to the first one, as many similarities in structure are shared between languages, especially those with a common ancestor.
 

The language taught here, BASIC, is easier to learn than others as its commands are similar to English and has a simple set of rules for entering them.

== Beginning BASIC ==
''Section for chapters detailing the basics of BASIC; i.e. data types, control structures...''
#[[BASIC Programming/Beginning BASIC/Your First Program|Your First Program]]
#[[BASIC Programming/Beginning BASIC/PRINT, CLS, and END|PRINT, CLS, and END]]
#[[BASIC Programming/Beginning BASIC/Variables and Data Types|Variables and Data Types]]
#[[BASIC Programming/Beginning BASIC/User Input|User Input]]
#[[BASIC Programming/Beginning BASIC/Documentation|Documentation]]
=== Control Structures ===
#[[BASIC Programming/Beginning BASIC/Control Structures/IF...THEN...ELSEIF...ELSE|IF...THEN...ELSEIF...ELSE]]
#[[BASIC Programming/Beginning BASIC/Control Structures/WHILE...WEND|WHILE...WEND]]
#[[BASIC Programming/Beginning BASIC/Control Structures/FOR...NEXT|FOR...NEXT]]
#[[BASIC Programming/Beginning BASIC/Control Structures/DO...LOOP|DO...LOOP]]
#[[BASIC Programming/Beginning BASIC/Control Structures/GOTO|GOTO]]

== Intermediate BASIC  ==

#[[/Random Number Generation/]]
#[[/Subroutines and Functions/]]

== Advanced BASIC ==
#[[/External Libraries|External Libraries]]

== Further reading ==
* [[Chipmunk Basic help|Chipmunk Basic Wikibook]]
* [http://freebasic.net/wiki/ FreeBASIC manual and wiki]
* [[Gambas|Gambas Wikibook]]
* [http://qb64.net/ QB64 website]
* [[Programming:Visual_Basic_Classic|Visual Basic Classic Wikibook]]

{{Subjects|BASIC programming language}}
{{alphabetical|B}}
{{status|50%}}

[[ja:BASIC]]
[[nl:Programmeren in BASIC]]</text>
      <sha1>p53w28sks9rrxxh4ehset36p3bei964</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Pascal Programming</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>218</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2704441</id>
      <parentid>2506130</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-09-27T03:14:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Wickorama</username>
        <id>176370</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Remove resource site that no longer exists and was not captured by Internet Archive</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Pascal is an influential computer programming language named after the mathematician [[Wikipedia:Blaise Pascal|Blaise Pascal]].  It was invented by [[Wikipedia:Niklaus Wirth|Niklaus Wirth]] in 1968 as a research project into the nascent field of compiler theory.

== Contents ==
* Standard Pascal
** [[Pascal Programming/Getting started|Starting up]] {{stage short|00%}}
** [[Pascal Programming/Beginning|Beginning Pascal]] {{stage short|25%}}
** [[Pascal Programming/Variables and Constants|Variables and Constants]] {{stage short|50%}}
** [[Pascal Programming/Input and Output|Input and Output]] {{stage short|50%}}
** [[Pascal Programming/Boolean Expressions and Control Flow|Boolean Expressions and Control Flow]] {{stage short|25%}}
** [[Pascal Programming/Syntax and functions|Pascal syntax and functions]] {{stage short|25%}}
** [[Pascal Programming/Enumerations|Enumerations]] {{stage short|75%}}
** [[Pascal Programming/Sets|Sets]]
** [[Pascal Programming/Arrays|Arrays/Lists]] {{stage short|25%}}
** [[Pascal Programming/Strings|Strings]]
** [[Pascal Programming/Records|Records]] {{stage short|50%}}
** [[Pascal Programming/Pointers|Pointers]] {{stage short|25%}}
** [[Pascal Programming/Files|Files]]
* Extensions
** [[Pascal Programming/Units|Units]]
** [[Pascal Programming/Object_oriented|Object Oriented Programming]] {{stage short|25%}}
** [[Pascal Programming/Libraries|Exporting to libraries]]
** [[Pascal Programming/Foreign_function_interfaces|Foreign function interfaces]]
*** [[Pascal Programming/Objective_Pascal|Objective Pascal]]
** [[Pascal Programming/Generics|Generics]]
** [[Pascal Programming/Miscellaneous|Miscellaneous extensions]]
* [[Pascal Programming/Preprocessor|Preprocessor functionality]]
* [[Pascal Programming/Cheatsheet|Syntax cheat sheet]]
* [[Pascal Programming/Appendix|Appendix]]

== Alternative resources ==
{{Wikipedia|Pascal programming language}}
* http://www.taoyue.com/tutorials/pascal/index.html
* http://wiki.freepascal.org/

{{Subjects|Computer programming languages}}
{{alphabetical|P}}
{{status|25%}}
__NOTOC__ __NOEDITSECTION__

[[de:GNU-Pascal in Beispielen]]
[[es:Programación en Pascal]]
[[fr:Programmation Pascal]]
[[ko:파스칼 프로그래밍]]
[[it:Pascal]]
[[he:פסקל]]
[[nl:Programmeren in Pascal]]
[[pl:Object Pascal]]
[[pt:Pascal]]
[[uk:Pascal]]</text>
      <sha1>cok2mkjvg49hi1bd546ud1xxpk2z8bq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Organic Chemistry/Foundational concepts of organic chemistry/Atomic structure/Octet rule and exceptions</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>220</id>
    <revision>
      <id>961216</id>
      <parentid>644909</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-09-07T18:35:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>removing all sub-pages from [[Category:Chemistry]], reformatting book main pages to use {{Subject}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Organic Chemistry/Foundational concepts of organic chemistry/Atomic structure/Filling electron shells|&lt;&lt; Filling electron shells]] | [[Organic Chemistry/Foundational concepts of organic chemistry/Atomic structure/Molecular orbitals|Molecular orbitals &gt;&gt;]]
----
The '''octet rule''' refers to the tendency of atoms to prefer to have eight electrons in their valence shell.

The main exception to the rule is hydrogen, which is at lowest energy when it has two electrons in its valence shell. 

Other notable exceptions are aluminum and boron, which can function well with six valence electrons; and some atoms beyond group three on the periodic table that can have over 8 electrons, including sulfur.  Additionally, some noble gasses can form compounds when expanding their valence shell.

The other tendency of atoms with regard to their electrons is to maintain a neutral charge. Only the noble gasses have zero charge with filled valence octets. All of the other elements have a charge when they have eight electrons all to themselves. The result of these two guiding principles is the explanation for much of the reactivity and bonding that is observed within atoms; atoms seeking to share electrons in a way that minimizes charge while fulfilling an octet in the valence shell.
----
[[Organic Chemistry/Foundational concepts of organic chemistry|&lt;&lt; Foundational concepts]] | [[Organic Chemistry/Foundational concepts of organic chemistry/Atomic structure/Filling electron shells|&lt;&lt; Filling electron shells]] | [[Organic Chemistry/Foundational concepts of organic chemistry/Atomic structure/Molecular orbitals|Molecular orbitals &gt;&gt;]]

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>ohbv9x1hausei5k5uauw0wppt35vwwk</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Organic Chemistry/Foundational concepts of organic chemistry/Acids and bases/Proton donors and acceptors</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>221</id>
    <revision>
      <id>961220</id>
      <parentid>654504</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-09-07T18:35:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>removing all sub-pages from [[Category:Chemistry]], reformatting book main pages to use {{Subject}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Organic Chemistry/Foundational concepts of organic chemistry/Acids and bases|&lt;&lt; Acids and bases]] | [[Organic Chemistry/Foundational concepts of organic chemistry/Acids and bases/Electron donors and acceptors|Electron donors and acceptors &gt;&gt;]]
----
The first and earliest definition of acids and bases was proposed in the 1800's by Swedish scientist Svante Arrhenius, who said that an '''acid''' was anything that dissolved in water to give up '''H+ ions''',Such as hydrochloric acid and a '''base''' was anything that dissolved in water to give up '''OH- ions''' such a sodium hydroxide.

The '''Brønsted-Lowry definiton''' of 1923 broadened this idea a bit:

:an '''acid''' is any '''proton donor''', and a '''base''' is any '''proton acceptor'''.

The focus of this definition is on donating and accepting protons, and is not limited to aqueous solution.

The Brønsted-Lowry definiton of acids and bases is one of two definitions we commonly use. The second definition deals not with protons but with electrons, and has a slightly different emphasis.
----
[[Organic Chemistry/Foundational concepts of organic chemistry|&lt;&lt; Foundational concepts]] | [[Organic Chemistry/Foundational concepts of organic chemistry/Resonance|&lt;&lt; Resonance]] | [[Organic Chemistry/Foundational concepts of organic chemistry/Acids and bases|&lt;&lt; Acids and bases]] | Proton donors and acceptors | [[Organic Chemistry/Alkanes|Alkanes &gt;&gt;]]

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>1ci5bfk4zxttqbfifmmprjuemz9w0hk</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>