<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>Help:FAQ/Administration</title>
    <ns>12</ns>
    <id>813</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2018915</id>
      <parentid>1966973</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-01-18T04:59:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>moved [[Help:Administration FAQ]] to [[Help:FAQ/Administration]]: Subpages enabled.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{wikibooks help}}

''See also:'' [[Wikibooks:Administrators]]

==How do policies get decided?==
:[[Wikibooks:Policies and guidelines]] describes how Wikibooks arrives at its policies and guidelines through a process of discussion and consensus.  Discussion takes place on the [[Wikibooks:Mailing lists]], on [[irc:#wikibooks|IRC]], and in the various policy pages which form part of the &quot;Wikibooks:&quot; namespace. For recent policy discussion on wiki, try looking at [{{fullurl:Special:RecentChanges|namespace=5}} recent changes].

==What is an Administrator? What is a sysop?==
:An Administrator is simply a [[Wikibooks:Wikibookians|Wikibookian]] who can access the few restricted Wikibooks software functions: deleting modules and uploaded files, protecting and unprotecting pages and blocking and unblocking IP addresses.
:&quot;[[w:sysop|Sysop]]&quot; is a more technical designation which deals with the a special user account itself, due to historical and to the Wikimedia software the &quot;flag&quot; that gives an Administrator its special privileges is called ''sysop flag'' that is why Administrators are sometimes called  sysops (even if the definitions aren't equivalent).
:The Administration tasks and rules are (still to be) defined on [[Wikibooks:Administrators]], they are not of a technical nature and are defined more as several managerial task that must be performed by a selected groups of users that needed or requested the access to be able to perform them to the good of all the community.

==How can I become an Administrator?==
:It's easy. First, you need a user account. Then, make useful edits over a period of time. In this way, you prove to the community that you are here in good faith. Then, add your name to [[Wikibooks:Requests for adminship]]. Voila! Be sure to read [[Wikibooks:Administrators]] and [[Wikibooks:Deletion policy]], and use your new &quot;powers&quot; with caution.

==Who monitors the conduct of an Administrator?==
: Administrators monitor each other; all administration tools are completely reversible by any other admin (including [[Special:Log/Delete|page and media deletions]], [[Wikibooks:Protected page|lockings]], and [[Special:Ipblocklist|IP bannings]]). In rare cases [[w:User:Jimbo Wales|Jimbo Wales]] has to step in. In any case, the GFDL license grants you the [[MeatBall:RightToFork|right to fork]], but all forks must be on your own servers, in accordance to [[Wikibooks:Forking policy|policy]] (the fixed policy regarding fork is still under discussion you are welcomed to express your views).

==How can I unban an IP?==
:Administrators can go to [[Special:Ipblocklist]] and click on &quot;unblock&quot; as required.  Developers can unblock multiple IPs at once.

[[Category:Wikibooks FAQ|Overview]]</text>
      <sha1>63ec11zpy9q0ipqisw5koljgo2r9514</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Help talk:FAQ/Administration</title>
    <ns>13</ns>
    <id>814</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2018917</id>
      <parentid>475925</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-01-18T04:59:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>moved [[Help talk:Administration FAQ]] to [[Help talk:FAQ/Administration]]: Subpages enabled.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Initial text adapted from [[en:Wikipedia:Administration FAQ]] --[[User:Maveric149|mav]] 08:58, 24 Aug 2003 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>0j8atdix6gw6191dqr22ldb1025oa1c</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Help talk:More editing FAQ</title>
    <ns>13</ns>
    <id>815</id>
    <revision>
      <id>479386</id>
      <parentid>152952</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-06-06T07:43:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[Wikibooks talk:Editing FAQ]] moved to [[Help talk:More editing FAQ]]: more suited to help namespace</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Initial text adapted from [[en:Wikipedia:Editing FAQ]] --[[User:Maveric149|mav]] 08:59, 24 Aug 2003 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>a2nu5nxa2sx4tnfrr04zyxq81wt90nu</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Help talk:FAQ/Contributing</title>
    <ns>13</ns>
    <id>816</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2470638</id>
      <parentid>2231542</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-12-31T05:33:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Maximilian.Klein.LRMI</username>
        <id>849601</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* wording nitpick */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">
==Source of initial text==
Initial text adapted from [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Contributing_FAQ Wikipedia:Contributing FAQ] --[[User:Maveric149|mav]] 08:59, 24 Aug 2003 (UTC)

== Linking to wikipedia? ==
As a new user, I upgraded the [[perl]] book to link to all first-occurrences of foreign comp-science words to wikipedia ( ie. &lt;nowiki&gt;[[w:foo|foo]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;.) Today I find someone of high stature has reverted all of those links. Please advise on when a wikibook should consult with a wikipedia entry and when it shouldn't. I feel discouraged, a lot of time has been needlessly wasted. [[User:EvanCarroll|EvanCarroll]] 19:14, 23 September 2007 (UTC)

== wording nitpick ==

This is super minor, but while browsing the page, the wording about the GIF patent question leapt out at me.  Instead of saying  &quot;&quot;Consult an attorney for more legal advice,&quot;&quot; it would probably be better to delete the word &quot;more.&quot;  It seems like, to me at least, including the word &quot;more&quot; suggests that the answer is in fact trying to give legal advice, which we probably shouldn't be giving the impression of. [[User:Maximilian.Klein.LRMI|Maximilian.Klein.LRMI]] ([[User talk:Maximilian.Klein.LRMI|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Maximilian.Klein.LRMI|contribs]]) 05:33, 31 December 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>d41ml2i70tkm8716naehc3sl7w3c735</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Help:FAQ/Problems</title>
    <ns>12</ns>
    <id>819</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2141839</id>
      <parentid>2141834</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-07-15T19:38:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Recent Runes</username>
        <id>66908</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Help - a page I am interested in has been deleted! */ add instructions</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{wikibooks help}}

''Note: If you're trying to get help for a specific technical problem that isn't answered by the FAQs, try asking in the [[WB:TECH|Reading room]].''

==How do I report that something isn't working properly?==
:If you think it's a bug in the software, you can send a bug report to the developers. See [[Wikibooks:Bug reports]] for directions. It may also be a problem with your browser; see the next question.

==My web browser and Wikibooks aren't playing nice!==
:Report at [[Wikipedia:Wikipedia:Browser notes|Browser notes]]. Include a description of the problem, the name of your browser, the version number, and the [[w:operating system|operating system]] you are running.

==How do I know if the problem is in the [[m:MediaWiki|MediaWiki]] software or my browser?==
:If you have another [[w:web browser|web browser]] installed, you can try to reproduce the problem in both. Failing this, you can describe your problem at the [[Wikibooks:Staff lounge|Staff lounge]] and ask other Wikibookians if they are having a similiar problem. If no one else is, it's probably a problem with your particular browser setup.

==Some, but not all, images don't show up. What's wrong?==
:Usually this is caused by ad-blocking software; uploaded files are distributed into random subdirectories, and 1/256th of all images on the server end up in http://www.Wikibooks.org/upload/a/ad/, which trips off some advertisement-blocking proxies. Configure your proxy to allow this directory, and you should be fine.

==Is it possible for a vandal to delete all Wikibooks pages?==
:Not really. Not even [[Wikibooks:Administrators|administrators]] can permanently and totally delete pages. Any other users could remove the text of a page, but any other user could restore the text from the history archive. If someone did an extensive attack, they could be blocked from further editing by the admins. Moreover, there are periodic backups kept of the server itself. For more on this topic, see [http://www.c2.com/cgi/wiki?WikiWipeout this discussion of &quot;wiki wipeouts&quot;] at the original [[en:Wiki|Wiki]].

==Help - a page I am interested in has been deleted!==
When you try to go to the page, you should see a notice saying who deleted the page and the reason why. If you disagree with the reason given or think the administrator made a mistake you can contact them directly on their talk page or make a general request for the page to be undeleted [[Wikibooks:Requests_for_deletion#Undeletion|here]]. (Select &quot;Add New Entry&quot; in the '''Undeletion''' section.)

[[Category:Wikibooks FAQ|{{PAGENAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>ok76zm0d8cc8582lsqh3j9p2biu5syf</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Help:Database download</title>
    <ns>12</ns>
    <id>822</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1985491</id>
      <parentid>1985486</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-12-02T01:48:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>{{Wikibooks help}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Wikibooks help}}

This page explains how to download an XML dump of the entire en.wikibooks.org site, or of one specific page. If you are trying to download the entire site, please use the XML dump instead of a web crawler.

== What is MediaWiki? ==
The [[Wikimedia:Home|Wikimedia Foundation]] hosts Wikibooks on servers running the free software [[MW:MediaWiki|MediaWiki]]. MediaWiki is a PHP script that provides the wiki to web browsers and stores the pages in a MySQL database. MediaWiki was developed for our sister project, [[Wikipedia:Main Page|Wikipedia]]. It is now used by all wiki projects hosted by the Wikimedia Foundation, including Wikibooks itself.

To learn more about MediaWiki or to download a copy, visit:
* http://www.mediawiki.org

== How is Wikibooks copyrighted? ==
Contributors to Wikibooks own the copyright to their contributions, but they all grant permmission under the [[GNU Free Documentation License]] and the [[Wikibooks:Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License|CC-BY-SA 3.0]] license for copying, modifying, and reusing our textbooks and other content. Some embedded images and media are under [[Commons:Commons:Licensing|other free licenses]]. Some copyrighted content is used under &quot;[[WB:FUP|fair use]]&quot;. For more information, see the page [[Wikibooks:Copyrights]].

== How do I download my copy? ==
Because Wikibooks is free documentation, you are allowed to copy our content from our MediaWiki server to your own computer. You might want to download a machine-readable copy designed for human modification, that is, the '''Transparent Version'''. Or you might want to load a copy of en.wikibooks.org into your own copy of MediaWiki as a mirror. Our XML dumps fulfill both purposes.

== Understanding different formats ==
* '''Wiki markup''' is the format in which authors write pages for MediaWiki. This is what you see when you use the &quot;Edit this page&quot; tab on Wikibooks.
* '''HTML''' is the format that web browsers understand. This is what you obtain when you use the &quot;Save Page&quot; function of your web browser.
* An '''XML dump''' is a format from MediaWiki that contains the complete wiki markup of a page, plus additional information about the page such as its title. ''Thus an XML dump is the best format for copying the wiki markup from Wikibooks.'' You can also reimport an XML dump into your own copy of MediaWiki.

== Downloading the ENTIRE site ==
The site http://download.wikimedia.org contains an entire site dump for en.wikibooks.org. To download the entire collection of textbooks:
# Visit http://download.wikimedia.org
# Look for &quot;enwikibooks&quot;
# Pick an XML dump and download it

Note that &quot;enwiki&quot; is the English Wikipedia, and does not contain any part of &quot;enwikibooks&quot;.

== Downloading some pages ==
The [[Special:Export]] feature allows you to download one or more pages from Wikibooks. To download some pages:
# Visit [[Special:Export]]
# Follow the instructions to submit a query
# Save the resulting XML to disk

... or just use [[Special:Export/Main Page]] to quickly get the XML dump of the [[Main Page]], for example.</text>
      <sha1>chqr2s46an9v5e8zgo50hhcjaqrhbmd</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Help talk:Database download</title>
    <ns>13</ns>
    <id>823</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1985488</id>
      <parentid>1967513</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-12-02T01:48:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>moved [[Wikibooks talk:Database download]] to [[Help talk:Database download]]: Moving to help namespace.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Initial text adapted from [[en:Wikipedia:Database download]] --[[User:Maveric149|mav]] 10:00, 24 Aug 2003 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>59z7v6fvms466ns845sz5mjto6tm44j</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Wikibooks:ISBN</title>
    <ns>4</ns>
    <id>833</id>
    <revision>
      <id>152970</id>
      <timestamp>2003-08-24T10:58:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Maveric149</username>
        <id>7</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">test</text>
      <sha1>jrwjerxiekdtj9k82lg930wpkr6tq6r</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Spanish/Sound Files</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>838</id>
    <revision>
      <id>532458</id>
      <parentid>490469</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-07-22T07:46:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">*[http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Image:SpanishL1D1.ogg Diálogo 1] Dialogue 1
*[http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Image:SpanishL1D2.ogg Diálogo 2] Dialogue 2
*[http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Image:Spanish_alphabet.ogg Alfabeto español] Spanish alphabet
*[http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Image:SpanishNumbers.ogg Los números de 0 a 20] Numbers 0 to 20
----
[[w:Wikipedia:Media#Audio|Audio Help]]

[[Category:Spanish]]</text>
      <sha1>hyuac44wc1pn5obyc5551a46h6831zj</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Wikibooks:Requests for permissions</title>
    <ns>4</ns>
    <id>840</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2712786</id>
      <parentid>2711462</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-13T01:49:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jusjih</username>
        <id>10882</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Requests for permissions */ /Jusjih</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">__NEWSECTIONLINK__ {{Discussion Rooms}} {{Requests for permissions/Archives}} {{shortcut|WB:RFP}} [[Category:Wikibooks administration|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[ca:Viquillibres:candidatura a administrador]]
[[de:Wikibooks:Adminkandidaturen]]
[[eo:Vikilibroj-Diskuto:Administrantoj]]
[[es:Wikilibros:Candidaturas a bibliotecario]]
[[pl:Wikibooks:Przyznawanie uprawnień]]
[[pt:Wikibooks:Pedidos de administração]]

All rights available on Wikibooks are handled here, including [[Wikibooks:Reviewers|reviewer]], [[Wikibooks:Importers|importer]], [[Wikibooks:Uploaders|uploader]], [[Wikibooks:Administrators|administrator]], [[Wikibooks:Administrators|bureaucrat]], [[m:CheckUser|CheckUser]], [[Wikibooks:Pseudo-bots|pseudo-bot]], and [[Wikibooks:Bots|bot]] flags. A nomination must demonstrate how the project will benefit from granting the rights.

;Nominations
: To nominate a user (including yourself), add their username to the appropriate section below. Please explain why you feel the nominated user would be a good choice. All registered Wikibookians may comment, and provide arguments in support or opposition. For the bot flag, technical information about the bot may be requested. See the specific requirements for each type of access on their respective pages.

;Outcome
: Consensus does not need to be demonstrated in granting reviewer, importer, and uploader flags. Administrators may use their best judgement in granting those. All other tools require community consensus and can only be granted by bureaucrats. Access to CheckUser is governed by [[meta:CheckUser policy|CheckUser policy]]. After about one week, if there is consensus to grant access, then a [[Special:ListUsers/bureaucrat|bureaucrat]] will make it so and record the fact here. If not, a bureaucrat may refuse to grant the rights and the request will remain until a consensus is reached.

= Removal of permissions=
{{message box|image=Symbol comment vote.svg|message='''Note:''' You may request removal of ''your own'' rights at [[meta:Steward requests/Permissions]]. Requests to remove others' rights should be placed here, whether due to inactivity, or abuse.
}}
=={{usercheck|MiszaBot}} (-Bot)==
{{closed|1=Removed - if the bot reactivates we need full visibility of the edits given the situation re. its operator, etc. [[User:QuiteUnusual|QuiteUnusual]] ([[User talk:QuiteUnusual|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/QuiteUnusual|contribs]]) 07:02, 26 June 2014 (UTC)}}
As a logic consequence of the bot's reported dysfunction since late March and in face of an alternative offering by [[User:Whym|Whym]] to run [[User:Whym|ArchiverBot]] in the same function, the bot flag should be removed from the previous bot ([[User:Misza13]] hasn't registered an email but the bot account has one). I see no problem in running the two procedures in parallel but this one should be closed before we resolve [[User:Whym|Whym]]'s request.  --[[User:Panic2k4|Panic]] ([[User talk:Panic2k4|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Panic2k4|contribs]]) 01:18, 26 June 2014 (UTC)
* {{support}} Sure, perfectly reasonable to take away the old bot's bit (say that three times fast).  Though I don't think the old bot is ever going to do anything again, so it's mostly a formality, not to leave an extra bit lying around.  --[[User:Pi zero|Pi zero]] ([[User talk:Pi zero|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Pi zero|contribs]]) 01:25, 26 June 2014 (UTC)
* {{support}} Even though this is in the wrong section. If someone does wake MiszaBot up again, we want to be aware of that if ArchiverBot is active. [[User:Chazz|Chazz]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Chazz|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 03:23, 26 June 2014 (UTC)
:: Fixed (wrong section, moved disc. up to the removal header).  --[[User:Panic2k4|Panic]] ([[User talk:Panic2k4|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Panic2k4|contribs]]) 04:04, 26 June 2014 (UTC)
{{end closed}}

=Requests for permissions=
{{message box|image=Symbol comment vote.svg|message='''Note:''' When adding nominations, please use the format &lt;code&gt;=={{tlx|usercheck|Username}} (Right requested)==&lt;/code&gt; followed by the nomination.
}}
=={{usercheck|rattleCAD}} (reviewer)==
rattleCAD is an opensource project on sourceforge.net &lt;br /&gt; http://sourceforge.net/projects/rattlecad. &lt;br /&gt;I wants to create a maunual for users here on wikibooks. I am the programmer of rattleCAD and wants to become also a reviewer of the wikibook: [[https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/RattleCAD_User_Manual rattleCAD User Manual] {{usercheck|rattleCAD}}
* You don't need the reviewer bit to contribute.  Eventually, once you have breadth of experience contributing to the project, you get automatically promoted to reviewer.  --[[User:Pi zero|Pi zero]] ([[User talk:Pi zero|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Pi zero|contribs]]) 17:41, 15 June 2014 (UTC)

{{/ArchiverBot}}
{{/Jusjih}}

==Request for upload permission==

==Upload Access, Administrator Permission &amp; Check-User Access==
{{closed|1=Not done. Make one request for each permission to allow a proper discussion by permission. [[User:QuiteUnusual|QuiteUnusual]] ([[User talk:QuiteUnusual|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/QuiteUnusual|contribs]]) 07:24, 8 September 2014 (UTC)}}
Hello All.

I am a regular editor and reviewer at both WB and WP. I contribute mostly to the German Book on WB. Apart from the same I also am a counter vandalism personal, and keep a watch on the reviews and edits at both the places.

I am currently requesting the following:

1. Upload access here at WB for uploading images and media files (voice recordings and images for German Language), towards the book contribution. I am at office most of the times, and we have media restrictions on media web pages, which is Wiki Media and Commons. Apart from that many a times I have faced troubles uploading on the Commons, and thus would request if, the Upload access is granted to me out at WB.

2. I am a regular Vandal and Spam rain checker. Not only that I see that we have very few Admin Levels (8 to be precise of whom Xania is on a break for some time, and out of Quite, Pi, Dark and Recent, I see Quite and Pi on a regular basis, making only 2 active ones), who are granted to provide Page Protections, Blocks, Vandal Blocks etc, which in order to get actioned, at times take long If I get the rights, I can take actions on the request as and when I am able to on them. I will also be able to do rain checks on the pages, users and the activities. Currently, or rather today I did 20+ reviews of the edits and also reverted few of them. Glad, if can get the sysops right.

3. I would also like to get the Check-User access, which I see is also with very limited people (3 to be precise, if I am not wrong), and see that I can be of use here too. Hope to get the same as well.

'''Jai Jinendra'''. [[User:Harrybrowne1986|Vishal]][[User Talk:Harrybrowne1986| Bakhai]] - [[Special:Contributions/Harrybrowne1986|Works]][[Image:Flag_of_India.svg|15px]] 17:10, 7 September 2014 (UTC)

:This is quite clearly three separate requests, for which quite separate criteria apply. I would re-enter your requests, following the format as laid out in the top of the page. For the record, I {{support}} uploader, {{oppose}} admin, and '''strongly''' {{oppose}} CU. [[User:Chazz|Chazz]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Chazz|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 01:24, 8 September 2014 (UTC)
{{end closed}}

==Uploader Access==
Firstly I would apologies as I entered the access request for all three into one. I am posting all as individual requests. Also [[User:Chazz|Chazz]], thank you for your support for this.

As stated earlier, I request Upload access here at WB for uploading images and media files (voice recordings and images for German Language), towards the book contribution. I am at office most of the times, and we have media restrictions on media web pages, which is Wiki Media and Commons. Apart from that many a times I have faced troubles uploading on the Commons, and thus would request if, the Upload access is granted to me out at WB. '''Jai Jinendra'''. [[User:Harrybrowne1986|Vishal]][[User Talk:Harrybrowne1986| Bakhai]] - [[Special:Contributions/Harrybrowne1986|Works]][[Image:Flag_of_India.svg|15px]] 08:30, 8 September 2014 (UTC)

{{oppose}} After reading the reasons for the request it simply does not conform to requirements of the function of uploader. As an alternative solution to [[User:Harrybrowne1986]] problems he may request help from someone at Commons to a) find a proxy that works b) serve as a proxy for the uploads.  --[[User:Panic2k4|Panic]] ([[User talk:Panic2k4|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Panic2k4|contribs]]) 00:42, 15 September 2014 (UTC)  

:Hello [[User:Panic2k4|Panic]]. Thank you for the suggestion. However, as I already stated, the main reason I am asking is, I face issues with uploads in Commons, and many a times the Uploads fail. In those cases, my bandwidth goes for a toss, and also my time. '''Jai Jinendra'''. [[User:Harrybrowne1986|Vishal]][[User Talk:Harrybrowne1986| Bakhai]] - [[Special:Contributions/Harrybrowne1986|Works]][[Image:Flag_of_India.svg|15px]] 18:16, 19 September 2014 (UTC)

::Again I don't see in there any reason to grant you the tools to upload what would be by our rules unacceptable files into Wikibooks. Seek a proxy that can do the work for you without requiring us to create an exception and a workload to deal with your issues.  --[[User:Panic2k4|Panic]] ([[User talk:Panic2k4|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Panic2k4|contribs]]) 21:00, 19 September 2014 (UTC) 

:::I do not see where did I state that I wish to upload any unacceptable file? Please read again, as I specifically mentioned the files are dated about 50 years. Also, I request you to let me know, what do you mean by when you said &quot;deal with your issues&quot;. Where and what is the issue here? If I face trouble uploading, and if I say I lose my time and my bandwidth after trying to upload something, is this an issue? I also do not see any reason behind all of these things, like &quot;My English Skills&quot;, &quot;My Issues&quot;! All I know is that I have a &quot;Neutral English&quot;, and that I do not find any proper justification in the way things have been picked on my requests. I might be new compared to some of the others, but I do have to say this, that I am really surprised at the way I am being treated here. '''Jai Jinendra'''. [[User:Harrybrowne1986|Vishal]][[User Talk:Harrybrowne1986| Bakhai]] - [[Special:Contributions/Harrybrowne1986|Works]][[Image:Flag_of_India.svg|15px]] 18:33, 23 September 2014 (UTC)

:::: If a file is acceptable at Commons it is automatically not acceptable here.
:::: Deal with your issues means deal with your problems. Problems that are exclusive to yourself.
:::: I did no comment on you English skills and I find them not relevant if you at least can understand our policies and guidelines and fill up the required upload information.
:::: I do agree that people have gone in a tangent when they should have clearly simply opposed your request on enough valid grounds. If you look at the archives you may notice that you aren't being treated differently that everyone else in the past. You also didn't help your cause by initiating discussions for several flags at the same time. I am opposing you in this one request because no one else was and you certainly (for what I understood) would be uploading files that wouldn't be acceptable here, since the cornerstone of the request is to use our project to upload files that you aren't' capable of uploading to Commons on technical problems, not license issues. At Wikibooks we only accept some Non-free media files as defined in our [[WB:MEDIA|Media policy]]. --[[User:Panic2k4|Panic]] ([[User talk:Panic2k4|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Panic2k4|contribs]]) 21:38, 23 September 2014 (UTC)

===Comments===

* For the record, I {{support}} uploader. [[User:Chazz|Chazz]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Chazz|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 01:24, 8 September 2014 (UTC)
:If I'm reading this correctly, requester seems to be saying that upload to commons is blocked at his workplace and he believes upload to WB may not be. I'm a little concerned that if he starts uploading to WB from his workplace, his workplace may respond by shutting down upload to WB as well... and maybe all access to all Wikimedia sites. Companies have been known to do that sort of thing... but if that's a risk requester wants to take with his entire company, and if he understands fair use and copyright issues, then my support remains in place... though shaken, I have to admit, by QU's comments below. [[User:Chazz|Chazz]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Chazz|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 18:25, 8 September 2014 (UTC)
::Don't get me wrong, once I understand the request properly I'm happy to consider it - I just don't understand it properly and I'm not really comfortable with uploading material here that should be at Commons most particularly as we don't have the volunteers to police the uploads like they do to ensure copyright compliance. I can grant the permission, remove the permission if abused and delete any bad uploads here so I'm not overly concerned about ensuring &quot;perfection in understanding&quot; first - unlike the admin and CU requests. [[User:QuiteUnusual|QuiteUnusual]] ([[User talk:QuiteUnusual|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/QuiteUnusual|contribs]]) 18:34, 8 September 2014 (UTC)
::: Hello [[User:Chazz|Chazz]] &amp; [[User:QuiteUnusual|Quite]].&lt;br&gt;I actually missed reading out this portion earlier. My office blocks only those sites, from which it has open source and data vulnerability issues, like commons, as it has its back-end data source on open library forum. Apart from commons, all other sites are open, till the time, the link do not lead to any porn, or inappropriate sites/topics/forum. Unlike commons, where, I agree and, no doubt had a lot of trouble, due to my own mistakes, I understand my responsibility here, and have always portrayed it. Also, the site Commons is blocked totally, and not just uploads, but none of the other projects are blocked, as are required at times for reference in our work. '''Jai Jinendra'''. [[User:Harrybrowne1986|Vishal]][[User Talk:Harrybrowne1986| Bakhai]] - [[Special:Contributions/Harrybrowne1986|Works]][[Image:Flag_of_India.svg|15px]] 10:28, 14 September 2014 (UTC)
* This request is out of line with the reason the uploader flag is granted. It is only granted to those needing to upload non-free media that is unacceptable on Wikimedia Commons. [[User:QuiteUnusual|QuiteUnusual]] ([[User talk:QuiteUnusual|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/QuiteUnusual|contribs]]) 08:40, 8 September 2014 (UTC)
:Not too sure of the abrupt ending of the sentence [[User:QuiteUnusual|Quite]] and out of line! What I understand, is that I wish to upload a lot of audio files, and other images for the scope of German, and which is way too tedious to be done from Commons, and, since, I cannot access Commons from my work place, (wherein I work on WB/WP, when I get time), I will not be able to get the file codes, and also, the media linkage on the server gets too high. People do get the uploader access here as well, if it pertains out of non free media uploads as well. Please let me know, if this is feasible for the grant? Danke Schôn. '''Jai Jinendra'''. [[User:Harrybrowne1986|Vishal]][[User Talk:Harrybrowne1986| Bakhai]] - [[Special:Contributions/Harrybrowne1986|Works]][[Image:Flag_of_India.svg|15px]] 08:59, 8 September 2014 (UTC)
:*I don't understand why you think the upload would be &quot;tedious&quot; at Commons but okay at Wikibooks? Can you explain why you think uploading at Wikibooks would be easier? [[User:QuiteUnusual|QuiteUnusual]] ([[User talk:QuiteUnusual|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/QuiteUnusual|contribs]]) 09:18, 8 September 2014 (UTC)
:*You also seem to have received a lot of comments on your talk page at Commons ([https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User_talk:Harrybrowne1986 here]) that suggests you don't understand free media and copyright rules. Is that what you mean by having difficulty with Commons? If so, you'll have the same problems here. And I see you have had images deleted as copyright violations from Wikipedia too. None of this suggests we should let you do the same here - [[User:QuiteUnusual|QuiteUnusual]] ([[User talk:QuiteUnusual|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/QuiteUnusual|contribs]]) 11:59, 8 September 2014 (UTC)
:*I know that I have a lot of removals from commons, and I agree to the points (to a certain extend of course), as I believe, that what I did was lack of knowledge at that time. If you would see, post those comments, I have uploaded images of my own, and while I continued my fight against vandalism. I am not sure, if you looked the dates up on WP, for images which got deleted. I believe, anyones can commit a mistake (me, you or anyone else). If that person comes out of it, and still is chased for the same thing again and again for no valid reason, it is just showing less respect for the other good deeds of his. The images and media (audio) files I am speaking about uploading here are for the German book, and are dated more than 50 years. So, they anyways can be uploaded here. The fact I said about the commons trouble, is that my system at times gets stuck due to some error, and the uploads do not get completed. This I have faced lot of times, only in commons. Still, if you do not wish to grant me one, I am fine with it. '''Jai Jinendra''' [[User:Harrybrowne1986|Vishal]][[User Talk:Harrybrowne1986| Bakhai]] - [[Special:Contributions/Harrybrowne1986|Works]][[Image:Flag_of_India.svg|15px]] 13:44, 13 September 2014 (UTC)
:*I would probably support this request if all of the other comments hadn't been here.  I can fully understand the problem and here in Italy websites are routinely blocked without warning.  Commons and Source were both unavailable on many ISPs for most of June and July.  Do we now judge people based on their actions on other Wikimedia sites?  If that's the case why don't we just use global blocks for everything and global permissions rather than local ones?--[[User:Xania|ЗAНИA]] [[Image:Flag_of_the_Isle_of_Mann.svg|15px]][[User talk:Xania|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]] 19:20, 8 October 2014 (UTC)

==Administrator Permission==
{{closed|1=Not done. After 8 days there is clearly no support for the rights at this time. I would suggest you try again in 9 months or so once you have longer tenure here and contributors know better. [[User:QuiteUnusual|QuiteUnusual]] ([[User talk:QuiteUnusual|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/QuiteUnusual|contribs]]) 10:57, 16 September 2014 (UTC)}}
Again, as I mentioned earlier, I am a regular Vandal and Spam rain checker. Not only that I see that we have very few Admin Levels (8 to be precise of whom Xania is on a break for some time, and out of Quite, Pi, Dark and Recent, I see Quite and Pi on a regular basis, making only 2 active ones), who are granted to provide Page Protections, Blocks, Vandal Blocks etc, which in order to get actioned, at times take long If I get the rights, I can take actions on the request as and when I am able to on them. I will also be able to do rain checks on the pages, users and the activities. Currently, or rather today I did 20+ reviews of the edits and also reverted few of them. Glad, if can get the sysops right.

I request [[User:Chazz|Chazz]], to let me know the reason for {{oppose|Opposing}}, as I am not sure why, he is stating this. I might be able to work on the point, for the reason he is opposing.

'''Jai Jinendra'''. [[User:Harrybrowne1986|Vishal]][[User Talk:Harrybrowne1986| Bakhai]] - [[Special:Contributions/Harrybrowne1986|Works]][[Image:Flag_of_India.svg|15px]] 08:30, 8 September 2014 (UTC)

===Questions===

#Can you explain the reasons you issued a &quot;no spam, no vandalism&quot; warning to the IP editors who made [https://en.wikibooks.org/w/index.php?title=General_Chemistry/The_Quantum_Atom&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=2695971 this edit] and [https://en.wikibooks.org/w/index.php?title=Accordion%2FPrint_Version&amp;diff=2696260&amp;oldid=2502384 this edit]? I would judge neither as vandalism - one is poor quality but a good faith edit, the other is a valid correction. You seem to have a fairly high rate of issuing incorrect warnings which coupled with your relatively weak English language skills and lack of experience (less than 1,000 edits across all projects) suggest to me that you are not ready to be trusted with block and delete buttons. However, please feel free to explain your actions.  [[User:QuiteUnusual|QuiteUnusual]] ([[User talk:QuiteUnusual|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/QuiteUnusual|contribs]]) 10:15, 8 September 2014 (UTC)

::Hello [[User:QuiteUnusual|Quite]]. I agree with you that, I misjudged, and, placed incorrect message for the mentioned IP users. I have gone ahead and amended the message for both. I '''know''' that I do not commit ''high rate'' of issuances of incorrect warnings and that I am very good with my language skills. I have been from my school days, and still am. So, I am not being able to understand why you are mentioning ''relatively weak English language skills''?  I am aware too, that I have less than 1,000 edits. I generally do less of editing, and am more of into either fighting vandalism or into my WB German Project. Apart from that I do not get to much time over the weekdays to log-in. The way I have committed some mistakes, the same might have gone for you in your initial days. Everybody is given a chance, and that too, I am not asking it to flaunt, that see, I have these rights, but too do good for WB. I used to do it previously as well, and will continue to do it. I try to learn from my mistakes and thus I work on them. It is to see how I fair and not what mistakes I have committed in the past. It is good to keep in mind, but not good to stop the future, by dwelling in the past. I hope that I am clear in my English! '''Jai Jinendra''' [[User:Harrybrowne1986|Vishal]][[User Talk:Harrybrowne1986| Bakhai]] - [[Special:Contributions/Harrybrowne1986|Works]][[Image:Flag_of_India.svg|15px]] 14:30, 13 September 2014 (UTC)
:::Regarding &quot;relatively weak English skills&quot;: I will not argue with your education, but there is a very great difference between excellent English education and the way a native speaker uses the language. Quite clearly from your writing, while you have a good knowledge of English, you are not a native speaker of the language. In the first few sentences of the above, I note the following infelicities in grammar: &quot;I do not commit ''high rate'' of issuances of incorrect&quot; missing &quot;a&quot; before &quot;high rate&quot; and unnecessary form &quot;issuances&quot; over-complicates the entire clause; &quot;I am not being able to understand why you are mentioning&quot; &quot;not being able&quot; is not proper English grammar in this sentence, &quot;being&quot; does not belong; &quot;I generally do less of editing&quot; superfluous &quot;of&quot;. I cannot comment on the other items you discuss here. [[User:Chazz|Chazz]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Chazz|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 17:55, 13 September 2014 (UTC)
::Thank you Chazz. When I mentioned the first point without an ''a'', I knew that it was not required, in the sentence. I also framed a proper sentence, when I used ''issuances'', in order to make my point clear. In &quot;Not being able&quot;, I agree, being should not have been used, as it really does not belong in the sentence. I should have framed it in a much better way, like, 'I am unable to understand, why you are mentioning/why you mentioned', and that would have been a proper construction. To be frank, when a person literally points a finger at you, and states it in a manner as placed earlier: [You seem to have a fairly high rate of issuing incorrect warnings '''which coupled with your relatively weak English language skills'''], especially, when it was mentioned, ['''weak English'''], it pinched a lot, as I know, that although I am not a native speaker, my skills are no way below par, and I do not need to prove it. No doubt, I have a tendency to use US English more, than the UK one, however, I try to be fair, and use a proper one, as I know many native speakers, using completely incorrect English. '''Jai Jinendra''' [[User:Harrybrowne1986|Vishal]][[User Talk:Harrybrowne1986| Bakhai]] - [[Special:Contributions/Harrybrowne1986|Works]][[Image:Flag_of_India.svg|15px]] 18:19, 13 September 2014 (UTC)

===Comments===

*For the record, I {{oppose}} admin. [[User:Chazz|Chazz]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Chazz|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 01:24, 8 September 2014 (UTC)
:[[User:Chazz|Chazz]], request you to let me know, the reason for opposing. Danke Schôn. '''Jai Jinendra'''. [[User:Harrybrowne1986|Vishal]][[User Talk:Harrybrowne1986| Bakhai]] - [[Special:Contributions/Harrybrowne1986|Works]][[Image:Flag_of_India.svg|15px]] 08:59, 8 September 2014 (UTC)
::Of course, now that there is an appropriate venue. Each project in Wikimedia has its own feel, its own style if you will, and it takes time on a project to understand that local milieu. An administrator must understand that style if he is to work effectively. With possibly five hundred edits on WB, most of them simple reversals of vandalism, I do not believe that you have had the necessary exposure to learn the style of this project, which is quite different from WP. For vandalism reversals, admin permission is not needed, rollback is quite sufficient. [[User:Chazz|Chazz]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Chazz|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 15:22, 8 September 2014 (UTC)
:::Hello [[User:Chazz|Chazz]]. Thanks for the comment. May I know, what do you mean by '''Of course, now that there is an appropriate venue.'''. Just wanted to know, if you thought, my work is all wrong or something like that? Might be I do things differently, which you thought to be wrong!&lt;br&gt;I am trying to do things in a proper manner, and am being just as per the requirements. No one is perfect, and neither am I. '''Jai Jinendra'''. [[User:Harrybrowne1986|Vishal]][[User Talk:Harrybrowne1986| Bakhai]] - [[Special:Contributions/Harrybrowne1986|Works]][[Image:Flag_of_India.svg|15px]] 17:15, 14 September 2014 (UTC)
::::When you were asking for all three permissions at the same time, there was no space to comment on your request for admin separately from the others. That was all that I meant there. But I'm afraid my concern remains: your work on this project has been largely vandalism reversals, which don't require understanding of the &quot;project culture&quot;, something that is different from one project to another. And without seeing more creative work, whether editing or actually writing, I have no way to judge whether you understand the culture of EN:WB. [[User:Chazz|Chazz]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Chazz|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 17:53, 14 September 2014 (UTC)
:{{outdent|::::::::}}
:Hello [[User:Chazz|Chazz]]. Firstly, I would like to apologies, if I sounded rude (which I believe I did). I did not mean to. Secondly, please help me understand what is meant by '''project culture''', as I have done more than just reverts. I have been, and am currently contributing for the German book. Also, few other edits. Apart from that I do reviewing, Welcome newcomers, try and help others, and also learn on the way. :) '''Jai Jinendra'''. [[User:Harrybrowne1986|Vishal]][[User Talk:Harrybrowne1986| Bakhai]] - [[Special:Contributions/Harrybrowne1986|Works]][[Image:Flag_of_India.svg|15px]] 18:23, 14 September 2014 (UTC)
::Well, the fact that you feel that it is a reasonable thing to request admin privileges when you have only a few hundred edits under your belt would be a strong indicator that you have some problems understanding the culture here. EN:WB moves more slowly than many other projects, despite having a lot of articles and contributors. The key point, I guess, is that I don't really feel that anything has appeared in your edit log that would really allow me to know whether or not you fit into this project... and the sudden appearance looking for high office does sort of argue against.
::On the English issue, I don't doubt your abilities when you're really trying... but you don't try all the time, nobody does. And in the paragraph of yours just above this response, I would like to point out &quot;apologies&quot;... [[User:Chazz|Chazz]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Chazz|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 01:32, 15 September 2014 (UTC)
{{oppose}} btw, I feel like you are hat collecting. Idk you very well, and the poor English skills makes you look confusing to communicate with. --[[User:Goldenburg111|goldenburg111]] ([[User talk:Goldenburg111|talk]]) 21:22, 14 September 2014 (UTC)

:Not sure, what people here consider English as! I have very good communication skills, and all I can see is everyone JUDGING as if they are the best. Please, where do I portray anything 'confusing' and 'poor skills'? Also to let you know, I am not '''hat collecting'''. I also do not know you. I would request you to not just jump to &lt;s&gt;Do not just jump to&lt;s&gt; any conclusion, and &lt;s&gt;do&lt;s&gt; not to be judgmental. It shows a bad picture of the people here. Sorry to say this, but it feels like, I gave the opportunity for the people who had to vent out. '''Jai Jinendra'. [[User:Harrybrowne1986|Vishal]][[User Talk:Harrybrowne1986| Bakhai]] - [[Special:Contributions/Harrybrowne1986|Works]][[Image:Flag_of_India.svg|15px]] 22:13, 14 September 2014 (UTC)
{{end closed}}

==CheckUser Access==
{{closed|1=Not done. Wikibooks policy requires a CheckUser to be an administrator, which there is also no support for at this time. In addition, the CU right requires 25 votes - this is not going to be achieved at this time. I suggest you try again for admin in the future and once you have tenure as an admin consider standing for CU again. [[User:QuiteUnusual|QuiteUnusual]] ([[User talk:QuiteUnusual|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/QuiteUnusual|contribs]]) 10:59, 16 September 2014 (UTC)}}
The last but not the least, access request for CU.

I would also like to get the Check-User access, which I see is also with very limited people (3 to be precise, if I am not wrong), and see that I can be of use here too. Hope to get the same as well.

Not repeating myself, but still I am not sure why (and I am rather curious of this) [[User:Chazz|Chazz]] states '''strongly''' {{oppose|Opposing}} for this?

'''Jai Jinendra'''. [[User:Harrybrowne1986|Vishal]][[User Talk:Harrybrowne1986| Bakhai]] - [[Special:Contributions/Harrybrowne1986|Works]][[Image:Flag_of_India.svg|15px]] 08:30, 8 September 2014 (UTC)

===Questions and comments===

*Please explain your understanding of the CheckUser policy, what the tool is used for, and how to interpret its results. [[User:QuiteUnusual|QuiteUnusual]] ([[User talk:QuiteUnusual|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/QuiteUnusual|contribs]]) 08:33, 8 September 2014 (UTC)
:First and foremost, I do not see, how a trust is built, if the tendency is more of neglecting all the positive things one does. Earning the trust is what matters the most, which I agree to. However, if the person is not given the chance to earn it, and just is being opposed to for everything, I believe there is nothing I can do in that case. How would you know if a person is worth it or not, if he is not given the time to prove it. I might be right, might be wrong in saying that &quot;I do not trust you or anyone else&quot;. Then what to do? We all have to go hand in hand, and trust can only be gained in the time that goes by. This is my criteria of understanding the level required to trust a person. What is the understanding of others, I am not aware of.

As for understanding what CU Policy is, all I have to say is, as a layman, that CU assists one to keep check on any disruptions or misleading edits to the project. This also assists one in maintaining the check and providing vital information, in order to stop any disruption caused by an IP or User, for any kind of Sock Puppetry and if required put a block/report for future edits from the requisite address/user. One thing I would say, is that I do require assistance taking into consideration, the time other CU's have given here, and of course looking at the changes that have occurred from the time Wiki started; from the time the CU's have started. So..

I am not saying that I want it so badly, that I would argue too much about it, but all I am saying is that I am sure, I am the last person to misuse any power granted to me(be it any privilege). I also know that this access is a very big deal as [[User:Chazz|Chazz]] stated, and also I appreciate the nature of CU [[User:Pi zero|Pi]], that it cannot be and is not the same as admin privilege. However, I am certain, that I will not, as I stated earlier, misuse any power, and before doing anything, which I am not sure of, will take assistance from others, as I do, in any case, where I am stuck. I further understand that this is a very big responsibility, and should be provided to only those users, who can be trusted, and who understand the right to it. '''Jai Jinendra' [[User:Harrybrowne1986|Vishal]][[User Talk:Harrybrowne1986| Bakhai]] - [[Special:Contributions/Harrybrowne1986|Works]][[Image:Flag_of_India.svg|15px]] 16:06, 13 September 2014 (UTC)
:You have demonstrated my concern clearly. You have explained what you think the CU tool is used for, not the CU policy. Please explain the CU policy as this governs the use of the tool. If you don't understand the policy, you can hardly be trusted to use the tool in line with that policy.[[User:QuiteUnusual|QuiteUnusual]] ([[User talk:QuiteUnusual|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/QuiteUnusual|contribs]]) 20:33, 13 September 2014 (UTC)
::The CU Policy as I understand is as follows:
Any CU is governed by -&gt;
#The CU Policy
#The Privacy Policy
#The Magic-8-Ball fundamental

The CU &amp; Privacy Policy state:&lt;br&gt;
The policy prohibits disclosure of any personal information, unless there is a breach or violation of any policy (e.g., spamming, vandalism, continuous disruption of pages, voiding policies, etc.,). If and only if revealing information about the concerned person/ip is what will help in prevention of the said disruption,  then only should the information be revealed, else, it is considered a breach of trust and privacy policy. It is another name for data protection, and it is very important, as the private information could be misused by anyone for any purpose.&lt;br&gt;One exception in restrictive manner is (though not exactly, but for understanding bit), in case one has revealed their own information in the stated project/post.

The privacy policy is very much clear about the same. The following are the &quot;When is the personal information used&quot;:
#With Your Permission (requested for a Wikimedia scholarship, or if requested for a reason)
#For Legal Reasons (on order from the court, law, company legal requirements, etc,)
#If the Organization is Transferred (Really Unlikely!) (Mergers, Acquisitions, if)
#To Protect You, Ourselves &amp; Others (possible violation, threat, breaches, etc.,)
#To Our Service Providers (third-party service providers or contractors)
#To Understand &amp; Experiment (to protect, develop and contribute)
#Because You Made It Public (information posted by the person him/herself)

Also during the [https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/CheckUser_policy#Release:_Policy_on_Release_of_Data following situations]:
#In response to a valid [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/subpoena subpoena] or other compulsory request from law enforcement,
#With permission of the affected user,
#When necessary for investigation of abuse complaints,
#Where the information pertains to page views generated by a spider or bot and its dissemination is necessary to illustrate or resolve technical issues,
#Where the user has been vandalizing articles or persistently behaving in a disruptive way, data may be released to a service provider, carrier, or other third-party entity to assist in the targeting of IP blocks, or to assist in the formulation of a complaint to relevant Internet Service Providers,
#Where it is reasonably necessary to protect the rights, property or safety of the Wikimedia Foundation, its users or the public.
It is to be remembered specifically that '''Wikimedia policy does not permit public distribution of such information under any circumstances, except as described above.'''

It is much better, if the personal information is not revealed, even if the user is committing abuse, if it is possible, and only reveal information about, which says, 'same network, or not the same service provider', rather than IP. 
It is better not to give any information from one's end if the person is in doubt.

As per the [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magic_8-Ball#Possible_answers Magic-8-Ball fundamental], it is a very good thing to, not reveal anything, in certain situations, and give ''possible'' answers like the specified 20 (10 +-ive, 5 --ive, 5 Neutral):
#It is certain
#It is decidedly so
#Without a doubt
#Yes definitely
#You may rely on it
#As I see it, yes
#Most likely
#Outlook good
#Yes
#Signs point to yes
#Reply hazy try again
#Ask again later
#Better not tell you now
#Cannot predict now
#Concentrate and ask again
#Don't count on it
#My reply is no
#My sources say no
#Outlook not so good
#Very doubtful

Basically, it is the same, and has high responsibilities associated with it. I find the [https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Help:CheckUser Guide], [https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/CheckUser_policy Policy], and the [https://wikimediafoundation.org/wiki/Privacy_policy Wiki Privacy Policy], very helpful for this.

I hope, I have mentioned as requested. However, I am sure, time teaches more, and just theoretical knowledge is not sufficient for anything. Practical knowledge is very much required in order.
'''Jai Jinendra'''. [[User:Harrybrowne1986|Vishal]][[User Talk:Harrybrowne1986| Bakhai]] - [[Special:Contributions/Harrybrowne1986|Works]][[Image:Flag_of_India.svg|15px]] 13:03, 14 September 2014 (UTC)

This discussion seems too extensive and does not focus on what people are objecting to in order to result in a positive outcome. In fact the request was premature as the community has generally only granted the tool to standing administrators that have been supporting the project for a significative time-frame, unless there is an emergency as such this will always result in opposition to requests that do not conform to the norm, making the discussion unnecessary as nothing that the proponent may say will change these facts.&lt;br&gt;
Unless [[User:Harrybrowne1986]] has some rational that would supplant the common practice (that he clearly was not aware of, in itself showing that he does not have the necessary experience) he should just retract the request.  --[[User:Panic2k4|Panic]] ([[User talk:Panic2k4|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Panic2k4|contribs]]) 00:32, 15 September 2014 (UTC)

===Support===

===Oppose===

# For the record, I... '''strongly''' {{oppose}} CU. [[User:Chazz|Chazz]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Chazz|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 01:24, 8 September 2014 (UTC) &lt;br/&gt;As to why, part of that is the reasons I stated above, regarding unfamiliarity with the culture of this project. The user's relative inexperience also leads me to believe this user does not understand what a big deal CU is, with its potential to violate user privacy. CU requires trust from the project's users, and I have seen nothing to suggest that the requestor has yet earned that trust. [[User:Chazz|Chazz]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Chazz|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 15:28, 8 September 2014 (UTC)
# {{oppose}} Checkuser is a very, very big deal. I don't think the requester appreciates what a big deal it is. It's certainly not something to be mentioned in the same breath with requesting admin.  --[[User:Pi zero|Pi zero]] ([[User talk:Pi zero|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Pi zero|contribs]]) 12:33, 8 September 2014 (UTC)
# '''Strong''' {{oppose}} It does not look like you know the tools very well. I have a good feeling you are hat collecting, in which requesting rights in which you do not need. Thanks. --[[User:Goldenburg111|goldenburg111]] ([[User talk:Goldenburg111|talk]]) 21:19, 14 September 2014 (UTC)
:I just believe, that no one knew the tool properly, before using them, and they did get the access to it. To let you know once more, I am not '''hat collecting''', and I do know the tools which I use. If I do not know, I learn them, and excel. '''Jai Jinendra'''. [[User:Harrybrowne1986|Vishal]][[User Talk:Harrybrowne1986| Bakhai]] - [[Special:Contributions/Harrybrowne1986|Works]][[Image:Flag_of_India.svg|15px]] 22:13, 14 September 2014 (UTC)
{{end closed}}</text>
      <sha1>d53lgslm5jm8cyuvzs7jscv2fvsss4r</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Wikibooks talk:Requests for permissions</title>
    <ns>5</ns>
    <id>841</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2260598</id>
      <parentid>2260590</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-02-02T17:33:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* i want to be a admin. */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{talk header}}

== Need some order ==
I think we should make RFA look like Wikipedia's one. Now everything is messed up: support, oppose votes, comments, chat etc. There should be clearly separeted sections of: support, oppose votes, questions, comments.

The same problem appears in other votings like [[WB:NP]], which is completely unreadable. --[[User:Derbeth|Derbeth]] 19:48, 17 October 2005 (UTC)


I don't think it's necessary to do that. I prefer the mix everything in together approach personally. It's a discussion rather than a vote. [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 10:58, 19 October 2005 (UTC)

:Apparently, the adminship rules are less strict here, so I don't think there's a need to have a fancy RfA like Wikipedia. I've been here for a few days, and I've discovered that this place and Wikipedia are two different places. '''[[User:Kayau|&lt;span style=&quot;color:navy&quot;&gt; Kayau &lt;/span&gt;]]''' ''[[User talk:Kayau|David Copperfield]]''  [[Special:Contributions/Kayau|&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;MOBY DICK&lt;/span&gt;]]  &lt;small&gt; [[:w:User:Kayau/guestbook|the great gatsby]] &lt;/small&gt;  07:49, 3 August 2009 (UTC)
:The RfA process at Wikipedia is a disaster in action and designed for.. well Wikipedia. Our system seems to be fairly effective in getting things done. [[User:Geoff Plourde|Geoff Plourde]] ([[User talk:Geoff Plourde|talk]]) 18:03, 3 August 2009 (UTC)
::IMO linear sequencing is fine if we indicatge support/opposition/nuetrality by boldfacing our opinion. 
::'''Keep''' linear ''adhocracy''. [[User:Geofferybard|Geofferybard]] ([[User talk:Geofferybard|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Geofferybard|contribs]]) 20:18, 19 May 2011 (UTC)

== Admin question ==

I have spent quite a bit of time around the RfA process at en.wiki, and know the ins and outs, but am a little puzzled here. Roughly how long does a user have to be active before adminship is a real possibility? About how many edits? I guess I'm gonna get some response about it is a case-by-case basis and that editcountitis is bad, but I ''would'' like a candid answer. Thanks. --[[User:Lord Voldemort|Lord Voldemort]] [[User talk:Lord Voldemort|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;(Dark Mark)&lt;/font&gt;]] 18:31, 11 November 2005 (UTC)

: There are no strict requirements. As for now, you should be &quot;active at Wikibooks for a while&quot; and &quot;known and trusted&quot;. --[[User:Derbeth|Derbeth]] 18:42, 11 November 2005 (UTC)

::I realise there are no strict requirements. I was just looking for some general answer. What does &quot;active at Wikibooks for a while&quot; even mean? 1 week? 1 month? 3 months? 6 months? 1 year? And I know people have their own standards and such, I am looking for a frank, to the point answer. At Wikipedia, you have a hard time becoming Admin if you haven't been there for around 3 months or have less than 1000 edits. There is no rule, but that seems to be about the line most people have in their standards. I want to know what the general community consensus is here. Thanks. --[[User:Lord Voldemort|Lord Voldemort]] [[User talk:Lord Voldemort|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;(Dark Mark)&lt;/font&gt;]] 18:51, 11 November 2005 (UTC)

:::I've been an admin for only a short time now, and I am up to a total of about 1500 edits, and have been a contributer for a relatively short period of time. If you have a good history (even if it is brief), and you ask nicely, you will probably get it if you want it. --[[User:Whiteknight|Whiteknight]] &lt;sub&gt;[[User talk:Whiteknight|T]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Whiteknight|C]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[Special:Emailuser/Whiteknight|E]]&lt;/sup&gt; 19:25, 11 November 2005 (UTC)

:::I from what it looks like here, you have less then 100 edits, and you dont seem to have any history before november. If this is the case you are at a pretty good pace, (about 10 edits per day or more), so if you wait another solid month, and maybe help to clean up a spot of vandalism, you would have my vote. --[[User:Whiteknight|Whiteknight]] &lt;sub&gt;[[User talk:Whiteknight|T]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Whiteknight|C]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[Special:Emailuser/Whiteknight|E]]&lt;/sup&gt; 19:27, 11 November 2005 (UTC)

::::Well, I wasn't thinking about nominating myself any time in the near future, I was just wondering if I ever ''did'' want to run. I do plan to stick around because I see a lot of stuff happening here. Thanks WhiteKnight. --[[User:Lord Voldemort|Lord Voldemort]] [[User talk:Lord Voldemort|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;(Dark Mark)&lt;/font&gt;]] 19:30, 11 November 2005 (UTC)

: You know, edits are not everything. For me, a candidate for admin should be proficient with MediaWiki mechanisms: history, moving, special pages, templates. He should also prove that he knows Wikibooks policies. I don't think an admin should take part in discussion about policies and be active at staff lounge, but I require that he is able to patrol Recentchanges regularly. I would also check if the user does not start arguments and whether his contributions are useful to Wikibooks. --[[User:Derbeth|Derbeth]] 19:43, 11 November 2005 (UTC)

:: I like to see people become admins once you have been able to figure out how to use the major tools for editing, like page moves and marking in a watchlist, as well as going beyond just adding a little bit of text to a page.  Participation in discussion, especially on Staff Lounge and the VfD discussions is useful as well.  One huge plus is if you have been able to help out with a vandalism attack and have been able to on your own revert some vandalism and help restore some of the damage without resorting to the use of admin tools.  All of this, plus knowing some of the general policies of Wikibooks is all I look at.  I believe that the quality of the edits is more important than the number of edits anyway.  If you do an edit and put in 20K more content instead of 2000 edits of one word each, I would say the one edit is far more valuable.  Using this philosophy, you could become an admin with just 50 high quality edits where you spend a lot of time reading policies and getting to know the community.  I think it is important that an admin is going to stick around as well, so an admin candidate that created the account just two weeks ago is IMHO less likely to get the admin status than somebody who has been on here for more than a year.

:: Jimbo has suggested that becoming an admin is &quot;not that big of a deal&quot;, and if you are willing to put in a little bit more effort for Wikibooks and help police what is going on, you are certainly encouraged to try and become an administrator.  --[[User:Robert Horning|Rob Horning]] 02:04, 12 November 2005 (UTC)

:::Well, like I said earlier (and I'm not sure you were directing this totally at me), I am not really interested in &quot;running&quot; for Admin any time soon. And to play Devil's Advocate, I believe he said it is &quot;no big deal&quot;. Cheers. --[[User:Lord Voldemort|&lt;font color=&quot;purple&quot;&gt;LV&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#3D9140&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Lord Voldemort|(Dark Mark)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 15:09, 14 November 2005 (UTC)

== Edit limit ==

I suggest creating edit limit for users who want to vote here. I think we may take [[Wikibooks:Collaboration of the Month]] and [[WB:BOTM]] as example and require at least 20 edits. --[[User:Derbeth|Derbeth]] [[User talk:Derbeth|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]] 20:21, 28 February 2006 (UTC)
:I think a more substantial edit count should be used. 20 edits can happen pretty easily for very new users, and I would think something a bit larger like 50 edits would be better. This ensures a bit more practice around the project. -[[User:Withinfocus|Matt]] 21:28, 28 February 2006 (UTC)

::Yeeeah, I think ''some'' minimum should be set, but think we should allow (and encourage if they have something substantive to say) anons and low-edit accounts to '''comment'''. --[[User:Lord Voldemort|&lt;font color=&quot;purple&quot;&gt;LV&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#3D9140&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Lord Voldemort|(Dark Mark)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 00:59, 1 March 2006 (UTC)

: An edit limit seems a good idea.  I have not seen here the same problems with suspicious (may be sock puppets or friends) votes and other such nonsense seen at [[WB:COTM|COTM]] and [[WB:BOTM|BOTM]] (and occasionally [[WB:VFD|VfD]]), so I don't see a need for a higher limit than for those.  If problems arise, then we can raise it.  Or if we need to raise the edit limit for [[WB:COTM|COTM]] and [[WB:BOTM|BOTM]], then we can raise the edit limit here to match.  --[[User:JMRyan|JMRyan]] 20:25, 3 March 2006 (UTC)

:::I personally don't like the idea, new users are effected just as much by who becomes an adin as the ones who have been around.  Plus I think that enforcing an edit limit may make a new user feel left out in some cases perhaps, but I agree in that something needs to be in place to prevent sockpuppets from getting involved, perhaps someone with checkuser can &quot;certify&quot; the voting results by checking for sockpuppets, although thats not a fool-proof method, I don't think anything is.[[User:RyanB88|RyanB88]] 21:09, 18 February 2007 (UTC)
::::I agree that newer users should be encouraged to exercise full citizenship. Many have background on WMF, or at RealWorld university. The problem with checkuser is that it is intrusive but maybe a non-judgemental individual could be entrusted to screen for sock-voting.(Probably no way that can be done unintrusively.)The only other idea I have is that the number of user edits could be displayed next to the voter's signature through some sort of software device. If any programmers out there feel like looking into that maybe we can do that and to get fancy, create an algorithm that multiplies users edits times votes for a weighted average. But wait - these aren't votes, they are discussions. This is one of those things with no &quot;right&quot; answer. Cf [[epistemology]], [[w:wave particle duality]] and the [[w:Heisenberg uncertainty principle]].[[User:Geofferybard|Geofferybard]] ([[User talk:Geofferybard|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Geofferybard|contribs]]) 20:27, 19 May 2011 (UTC)

==Desysop request==
About the desysop request for my account : It's ok for me to be desysoped here. I don't know if I will contribute here very much in short future. My sysop privilege came essentially from the period when all wikibooks were on the same domain. Now, it's not really useful anymore. What is sure, is that I will not abuse from these privileges, so don't worry, but if you want to remove them, it's ok. [[User:Traroth|Traroth]] 14:13, 17 March 2006 (UTC)

== Sysop Removal Timeline ==

When does everyone think inactive sysops can be re-nominated to be removed of rights? As time goes on many of these admins' inactivity times just lengthen. Perhaps every six months a vote can be held? Also, it might not be a bad idea to define what &quot;inactivity&quot; means here since many of the supposed current votes have been non-consesused due to last-second voting regarding mandatory inactivity rules. -[[User:Withinfocus|Matt]] 02:02, 11 April 2006 (UTC)

:Yes. Though it might be better to reconsider the issues again in abstract first. The initial discussions showed there was unanimity amongst those voting to remove those who had made no edit of any description in the last 12 months (unless there are other wikimedia-related matters than need to be taken into consideration). The discussions on the other nominees seem to have stalled - mostly relating to a nomination that was considered by some to be arguing for de-sysopping on fault rather than no fault. This even led to one user opposing the de-sysopping of a user who has consented to his own de-sysopping, which just seems weird - as is the case where a level of inactivity of well over 12 months was broken by one single edit on a usertalk page to thank him for a vote he made on meta.

:The discussion areas for &quot;no fault&quot; de-sysoppings under a &quot;use it or lose it policy&quot; are:

::Complete inactivity over 12 months (excepting those who need reserve rights for Wikimedia Foundation or MediaWiki development reasons) - ''de facto'' already agreed as being reason for de-sysopping
::User request or with the consent of the user - we'd need to agree this, but personally I can't see why this should be controversial
::Complete inactivity over 6 months (excepting those who need reserve rights for Wikimedia Foundation or MediaWiki development reasons) - there was around 80% support for this looking at the nominations on the project page - maybe we can agree this in the abstract
::Inactivity over 12 months - ie there was some activity (maybe fewer than 10 edits, or no edits to the main namespace) - again, there was some significant support for this looking at the nominations - maybe this is worth discussing again in the abstract
::Intermittent (or continuing) editing activity, but no usage of sysop-only rights for a 12 month period - again, maybe this is worth discussing again in the abstract

:[[User:Jguk|Jguk]] 06:40, 11 April 2006 (UTC)

I oppose establishing any such timeline without the general discussion suggested by [[User:Jguk|Jguk]].  We seemed to have at least more or less agreed to do some housecleaning of inactive Admins at the [[Wikibooks:Reading room/Archives/2006/February#Removing Sysop Status|Staff Lounge discussion]].  But the consensus spoiling &quot;last minute votes&quot; seem to indicate that we had less of a consensus than we had thought.  In the [[Wikibooks:Reading room/Archives/2006/February#Removing Sysop Status|Staff Lounge discussion]], [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] suggested we should have a policy on these issues.  [[User:Derbeth|Derbeth]]'s horror expressed as &quot;Oh dear, not another new policy&quot; reply notwithstanding, I support having a policy or guideline on the matter (possibly new or possibly worked into existing policies).  In the recent vote, there seemed to be some confusion both over what we ''were'' doing and over what we ''should'' have been doing.  Were we desysopping those with no activity for 12 months?  No activity for 6 moths?  Desysopping those with non-admin activity only for 6 or 12 months?  Desysopping those with no non-admin activity outside their own books?  I changed one of my votes over such confusion.  There was even disagreement over whether we should be having no-fault desysopping votes at all.  Having a policy or even a guideline to point to might even have ameliorated a bit the contretemps that occurred over [[Wikibooks:Requests for adminship/Archive#Marshman ( talk .7C email .7C_contribs )| Marshman's vote]] (okay, well, maybe that one's a stretch).

I don't have much of a position on the issues raised by [[User:Jguk|Jguk]].  Here is what little I do have:

* No-fault desysopping due to 12 months inactivity (whether that's complete inactivity, near complete inactivity, non-admin inactivity, etc.) is more likely to garner a consensus than desysoping due to 6 months inactivity.  I base that on the discussions both at [[Wikibooks:Reading room/Archives/2006/February#Removing_Sysop_Status|the Staff Lounge discussion]] and at the desysopping votes themselves.  I like consensus.  Consensus is good.  :-)

* Assuming we have set times for these desysopping votes or time spans between them, we should consider not holding a desysopping vote for the same admin two times in a row.  As long as they are not doing any damage, I don't want to give the impression that we're piling on.  If that adopted, it might argue for holding housecleaning desysop votes twice a year rather than yearly.

* Perhaps we should maintain a strict wall between for-cause desysop votes and no-fault housecleaning desysop votes.  For-cause reasons for desysopping are of a ''very'' different type than no-fault housecleaning desysop votes.  I don't see a little bit of for-cause and a little bit of no-fault reasons supporting each other.  For-cause and no-fault desysoppings need to stand by themselves as sufficient.  On the other hand, the &quot;piling on&quot; problem concerns me here.  Consider [[Wikibooks:Requests for adminship/Archive#Marshman ( talk .7C email .7C_contribs )| Marshman's case]].  How much nastier would that fight have been if we held one type of vote (for-cause or no-fault) first and then the other type a month later.  I don't right now have any brilliant ideas as to how to separate for-cause and no-fault votes without leaving us susceptible to piling on problems.  But I do feel that such a brilliant idea would be highly desirable.

--[[User:JMRyan|JMRyan]] 23:01, 12 April 2006 (UTC)

== Change Requests for deadminship ==

I think the requests for deadminship should be changed to requests for removal of powers, or simular and it could be useed fro de-adminning, de-checkusering, de-boting, ect...[[User:RyanB88|RyanB88]] 17:59, 18 February 2007 (UTC)
:May be worth you looking around and getting used to the place for a bit. Suggestions are always welcome but this seems to work for us - thanks --[[User:Herbythyme|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;Herby&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;b&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#90F&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Herbythyme|talk thyme]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/b&gt; 18:07, 18 February 2007 (UTC)
::I dunno... &quot;Request for removal of special status&quot; has a nice ring to it. --[[User:SBJohnny|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;'''SB_Johnny'''&lt;/font&gt;]] | &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:SBJohnny|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 19:01, 18 February 2007 (UTC)
::As I see it, their is no way to request to have someones bot flag or checkuser status or buearcrat (i probably spelled this worng) status removed.[[User:RyanB88|RyanB88]] 21:02, 18 February 2007 (UTC)

== more ==

now it is my turn to talk here

'''i need admin''' for the following reason
i know how to block and i want to do it in real &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[w:Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Anthony 5432|Anthony 5432]] ([[User talk:Anthony 5432|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Anthony 5432|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
:Then you need to request it on the project page rather than the talk page (go to [[WB:RFP]]). It's fair to say you are unlikely to achieve a consensus to have the admin flag when you've made no contributions here to any books. &lt;font color=&quot;#E66C2C&quot;&gt;[[User:QuiteUnusual|'''Unusual? Quite''']]&lt;/font&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#306754&quot;&gt;[[User talk:QuiteUnusual|TalkQu]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 22:24, 21 November 2009 (UTC)

== How do I know if I have certain permissions? ==

I haven't worked with Wikibooks for a bit, but am the one that created the [[How to use a Motorola DVR]] book. It looks like flagged revisions have been added, but I have no idea how to 'approve' items. There is mention that some submit or other buttons should show up, but I don't see that. Basically, I assume I haven't been granted the correct permissions? I have no idea on how to check if I should have them or not, or if I'm just missing something. [[User:Andyross|andyross]] ([[User talk:Andyross|talk]]) 14:27, 16 February 2010 (UTC)

:That's been corrected. -- [[User:Adrignola|Adrignola]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Adrignola|talk]] [[Special:Contributions/Adrignola|contribs]]&lt;/sup&gt; 15:10, 16 February 2010 (UTC)

== CU ==

I hope this won't lead to a straw poll like WN ArbCom elections... [[User:Kayau|Kayau]] ( [[User talk:Kayau|talk]] &amp;#124; [[Special:Emailuser/Kayau|email]] &amp;#124; [[Special:Contributions/Kayau|contribs]] ) 14:15, 15 August 2010 (UTC)

:CUs have a minimum requirement of support &quot;votes&quot;, take a look in Adrignola's nomination.  It shouldn't be a static number but a percentage based on the active administrators.  --[[User:Panic2k4|Panic]] ([[User talk:Panic2k4|talk]]) 14:31, 15 August 2010 (UTC)

::Actually, the requirement is at least 25 votes.  It's the last bastion of an actual vote.  It should be based on project size, but it's not. &amp;ndash;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Adrignola|Adrignola]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Adrignola|talk]]&lt;/small&gt; 15:16, 15 August 2010 (UTC)

:::After a fixed minimum number of votes, the next simplest arrangement would perhaps be a number simply proportional to active admins, which would seem to make it too easy for tiny projects and prohibitively difficult for huge projects.  One might supplement that with absolute lower and upper bounds on the required minimum, or go for something even more baroque (logarithmic scale, anyone?).  But the more complicated you make it, the harder it is to use and the more of a controversy magnet it becomes.

:::Smaller projects are given some relief in trying to scrape up the requisite numbers by the fact that there is no fixed limit on how long a CU vote can remain open.  Sanity checks are that the whole local community has to have been properly notified of the vote ('''which, since we haven't clearly settled on what we're doing, has not yet happened here'''), and that once you claim to have the requisite level of consensus, you have to request at Meta, which gives the Stewards a chance to look over the proceedings to see if there's anything dicey about them.  Details are at {{nowrap|[[Meta:Checkuser policy#Access to CheckUser]]}}.  --[[User:Pi zero|Pi zero]] ([[User talk:Pi zero|talk]]) 16:03, 15 August 2010 (UTC)
::::It has been my experience that WMF projects do, despite protestations to the contrary, have a certain number of individuals who are eager to acquire administrative power in order to promote or protect POV or for ego-gratification reasons &lt;font color=green&gt; present company excepted&lt;/font&gt;. Thus I would suggest erring on the side of (a) less is more regarding CU's but more importantly (b) quality more important than quantity in that CU's should have a very detailed understanding of rights and responsibilities, be accessible to folks with less technical expertise and have a demonstrated record of wielding power judiciously, NPOV and fairly. My bottom line is that I use properly disclosed multiple accounts for lawful purposes, like protecting my sanity from POV warriors, and I don't doubt that someday a POV Warrior will try to use CU and attempt to characterize my lawful-per-policy multiple accounts as somehow indicative of (evil vampire soundtrack) &quot;socking&quot;. [[User:Geofferybard|Geofferybard]] ([[User talk:Geofferybard|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Geofferybard|contribs]]) 20:35, 19 May 2011 (UTC)

== i want to be a admin. ==

please can i be one &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[w:Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Katherine808082|Katherine808082]] ([[User talk:Katherine808082|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Katherine808082|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;
:Please see [[Wikibooks:Administrator|here]] for an understanding of what is expected from an administrator. If after reading this you want to be considered, you need to place your request at [[WB:RFP]] &lt;font color=&quot;#E66C2C&quot;&gt;[[User:QuiteUnusual|'''QU''']]&lt;/font&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#306754&quot;&gt;[[User talk:QuiteUnusual|TalkQu]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 17:33, 2 February 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>kit4y0n297igiftnhuagbmltjv3y58q</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Spanish/Exercises/Regular Verbs</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>842</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2607653</id>
      <parentid>2607378</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-02-08T23:32:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Recent Runes</username>
        <id>66908</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/Ariebombarie123|Ariebombarie123]] ([[User talk:Ariebombarie123|talk]]) to last version by Recent Runes</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Spanish/Lesson 3| ^Lesson 3^]]
----

=== Rellena los espacios en blanco ===

=== ''Fill in the blank'' ===

Por favor, rellena los espacios en blanco con la forma correcta del verbo:
''Please, fill in the blank with the correct form of the verb:''
&lt;!--Editors please note: the answers should be left hidden to provide an exercise for everybody.--&gt;

1. Nosotros ____&lt;!--aprendemos--&gt;_____ (aprender) español.
''We learn Spanish.''

2. Yo ____&lt;!--compro--&gt;_____ (comprar) un libro.
''I buy a book.''

3. Carmen y Roberto ____&lt;!--viajan--&gt;_____ (viajar) a Mexico.
''Carmen and Roberto travel to Mexico.''

4. Ana ___&lt;!--habla--&gt;_______ (hablar) ingles.
''Ana speaks English.''

5. Tú ______&lt;!--bebes--&gt;__ (beber) una cerveza.
''You drink a beer.''

6. Susana _____&lt;!--escribe--&gt;___ (escribir) una carta.
''Susana writes a letter.''

7. Los niños ______&lt;!--estudian--&gt;___ (estudiar) para el examen.
''The children study for the exam.''

8. Fernando y Lucas ____&lt;!--cantan--&gt;______ (cantar) una cancion.
''Fernando and Lucas sing a song.''

9. Tú ____&lt;!--lees--&gt;____ (leer) un libro.
''You read a book.''

10. Vosotros _______&lt;!--subís--&gt;__ (subir) las escaleras.
''You (plural) climb the stairs.''

----------------------------------------
[[Spanish/Exercises/Regular_Verbs_-_Solutions|Soluciones a los ejercicios]] ''Solution to exercices''

[[Spanish/Lesson 3| ^Lesson 3^]]

[[Category:Spanish]]</text>
      <sha1>s7931ojqo4x1l3eleg2oub0k2s02n25</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Spanish/Solutions to Exercises</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>843</id>
    <revision>
      <id>532456</id>
      <parentid>496622</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-07-22T07:46:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">This page is a list of links to the solutions to the exercises in this Wikibook.  The exercises themselves can be found [[Spanish/Exercises|here]].

==Lesson 1==
*[[Spanish/Exercises/Greetings - Solutions|Greetings]]
*[[Spanish/Exercises/Personal Pronouns - Solutions|Personal Pronouns]]
*[[Spanish/Exercises/Verbs ser And estar - Solutions|Ser and Estar]]
==Lesson 2==
*[[Spanish/Exercises/Articles - Solutions|Articles]]
*[[Spanish/Exercises/Mathematics - Solutions|Mathematics]]
*[[Spanish/Exercises/Telling Time - Solutions|Telling Time]]
==Lesson 3==
*[[Spanish/Exercises/Regular Verbs - Solutions|Regular Verbs]]
==Lesson 4==
*[[Spanish/Exercises/Stem Changing Verbs - Solutions|Stem Changing Verbs]]
==Lesson 5==
*[[Spanish/Exercises/Comparisons - Solutions|Comparisons]]
*[[Spanish/Exercises/Possessive Adjectives - Solutions|Possessive Adjectives]]
*[[Spanish/Exercises/Questions - Solutions|Questions]]
==Lesson 6==
*[[Spanish/Exercises/Object Pronouns - Solutions|Object Pronouns]]
==Lesson 7==
*[[Spanish/Exercises/Preterite - Solutions|Preterite]]
*[[Spanish/Exercises/Preterite vs. Imperfect - Solutions|Preterite vs. Imperfect]]

[[Category:Spanish]]</text>
      <sha1>2qa3mtt7htvs69bftq26g8of1062ts4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Ruby Programming</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>844</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2676188</id>
      <parentid>2584448</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-06-24T06:42:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>170.248.145.58</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Learning Ruby */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[File:Ruby_logo.png|thumb|150px|Ruby was named after [[Wikipedia:Ruby|the precious gem]].]]

'''Ruby''' is an [[w:interpreted|interpreted]], object-oriented [[w:programming|programming]] language. Its creator, [[Wikipedia:Yukihiro Matsumoto|Yukihiro Matsumoto]], a.k.a “Matz,” released it to the public in 1995.  Its history is covered [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruby_Programming_Language here].  Its many features are listed [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruby_Programming_Language#Features here].

The book is currently broken down into several sections and is intended to be read sequentially.  [[#Getting started|Getting started]] will show how to install and get started with Ruby in your environment. [[#Basic Ruby|Basic Ruby]] demonstrates the main features of the language syntax. The [[#Ruby language|Ruby language]] section is organized like a reference to the language.
[[#Available Standard Library Modules|Available modules]] covers some of the standard library.  [[#Intermediate Ruby|Intermediate Ruby]] covers a selection of slightly more advanced topics.  Each section is designed to be self contained. 

== Table of Contents ==
{{print version}}
{{PDF version|Ruby_Programming}}
=== Getting started ===
:[[/Overview/]]
:[[/Installing Ruby/]]
:[[/Ruby editors/]]
:[[/Notation conventions/]]
:[[/Interactive Ruby/]]
:[[/Mailing List FAQ/]]

=== Basic Ruby ===
:[[/Hello world/]]
:[[/Strings/]]
:[[/Alternate quotes/]]
:[[/Here documents/]]
:[[/ASCII/]]
:[[/Encoding/]]
:[[/Introduction to objects/]]
:[[/Ruby basics/]]
:[[/Data types/]] — numbers, strings, hashes and arrays
:[[/Writing methods/]]
:[[/Classes and objects/]]
:[[/Exceptions/]]

=== Ruby Semantic reference===
*[[/Syntax/]]
**[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Lexicology|Lexicology]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Lexicology#Identifiers|Identifiers]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Lexicology#Comments|Comments]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Lexicology#Embedded Documentation|Embedded Documentation]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Lexicology#Reserved Words|Reserved Words]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Lexicology#Expressions|Expressions]]
**[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Variables and Constants|Variables and Constants]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Variables and Constants#Local Variables|Local Variables]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Variables and Constants#Instance Variables|Instance Variables]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Variables and Constants#Class Variables|Class Variables]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Variables and Constants#Global Variables|Global Variables]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Variables and Constants#Constants|Constants]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Variables and Constants#Pseudo Variables|Pseudo Variables]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Variables and Constants#Pre-defined Variables|Pre-defined Variables]]
**[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Literals|Literals]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Literals#Numerics|Numerics]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Literals#Strings|Strings]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Literals#Interpolation|Interpolation]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Literals#Backslash Notation|Backslash Notation]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Literals#Alternate Notation|The % Notation]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Literals#Command Expansion|&lt;s&gt;Command Expansion&lt;/s&gt;]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Literals#Regular Expressions|&lt;s&gt;Regular Expressions&lt;/s&gt;]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Literals#Arrays|Arrays]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Literals#Hashes|Hashes]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Literals#Ranges|Ranges]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Literals#Symbols|Symbols]]
**[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Operators|Operators]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Operators#Assignment|Assignment]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Operators#Self Assignment|Self Assignment]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Operators#Multiple Assignment|Multiple Assignment]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Operators#Conditional Assignment|Conditional Assignment]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Operators#Scope|Scope]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Operators#and|&lt;code&gt;and&lt;/code&gt;]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Operators#or|&lt;code&gt;or&lt;/code&gt;]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Operators#not|&lt;code&gt;not&lt;/code&gt;]]
**[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures|Control Structures]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures#Conditional Branches|Conditional Branches]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures#if|&lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt;]]
*****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures#if modifier|&lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt; modifier]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures#unless|&lt;code&gt;unless&lt;/code&gt;]]
*****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures#unless modifier|&lt;code&gt;unless&lt;/code&gt; modifier]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures#case|&lt;code&gt;case&lt;/code&gt;]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures#Loops|Loops]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures#while|&lt;code&gt;while&lt;/code&gt;]]
*****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures#while modifier|&lt;code&gt;while&lt;/code&gt; modifier]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures#until|&lt;code&gt;until&lt;/code&gt;]]
*****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures#until modifier|&lt;code&gt;until&lt;/code&gt; modifier]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures#for|&lt;code&gt;for&lt;/code&gt;]]
*****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures#for in|&lt;code&gt;for&lt;/code&gt; ... &lt;code&gt;in&lt;/code&gt;]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures#break|&lt;code&gt;break&lt;/code&gt;]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures#redo|&lt;code&gt;redo&lt;/code&gt;]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures#next|&lt;code&gt;next&lt;/code&gt;]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures#retry|&lt;code&gt;retry&lt;/code&gt;]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures#Exception Handling|Exception Handling]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures#raise|&lt;code&gt;raise&lt;/code&gt;]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures#begin|&lt;code&gt;begin&lt;/code&gt;]]
*****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures#rescue modifier|&lt;code&gt;rescue&lt;/code&gt; modifier]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures#Miscellanea|Miscellanea]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures#return|&lt;code&gt;return&lt;/code&gt;]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Control Structures#returning|&lt;code&gt;returning&lt;/code&gt;]]
**[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Method Calls|Methods]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Method Calls#super|&lt;code&gt;super&lt;/code&gt;]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Method Calls#Iterators|Iterators]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Method Calls#yield|&lt;code&gt;yield&lt;/code&gt;]]
**[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Classes|Classes]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Classes#Class Definition|Class Definition]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Classes#Instance Variables|Instance Variables]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Classes#Class Variables|Class Variables]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Classes#Class Methods|Class Methods]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Classes#Instantiation|Instantiation]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Classes#Declaring Visibility|Declaring Visibility]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Classes#Private|Private]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Classes#Public|Public]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Classes#Protected|Protected]]
****[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Classes#Instance Variables|Instance Variables]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Classes#Inheritance|Inheritance]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Classes#Mixing in Modules|Mixing in Modules]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Classes#Ruby Class Meta-Model|Ruby Class Meta-Model]]
***[[Ruby Programming/Syntax/Hooks|Ruby Hooks]] add the ability to know when new methods are defined et al.

See also some [http://ruby-doc.org/docs/keywords/1.9/ rdoc] documentation on the various keywords.

=== Built in Classes ===

This is a list of classes that are available to you by default in Ruby.  They are pre-defined in “core.”

* [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Built-In Functions|Built-in Functions]]
* [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Predefined Variables|Predefined Variables (globals)]] {{stage|25%}}
* [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Predefined Classes|Predefined Classes]]
** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects|&lt;code&gt;Object&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Array|&lt;code&gt;Array&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Class|&lt;code&gt;Class&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Comparable|&lt;code&gt;Comparable&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Encoding|&lt;code&gt;Encoding&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Enumerable|&lt;code&gt;Enumerable&lt;/code&gt;]]
**** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Enumerable|&lt;code&gt;Enumerable::Enumerator&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Enumerable|&lt;code&gt;Enumerator&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Exception|&lt;code&gt;Exception&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/FalseClass|&lt;code&gt;FalseClass&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/IO/Fiber|&lt;code&gt;Fiber&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/IO|&lt;code&gt;IO&lt;/code&gt;]]
**** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/IO/File|&lt;code&gt;File&lt;/code&gt;]]
***** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/IO/File/File::Stat|&lt;code&gt;File::Stat&lt;/code&gt;]]
**** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/IO/GC|&lt;code&gt;GC&lt;/code&gt;]]
***** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/IO/GC/Profiler|&lt;code&gt;GC::Profiler&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Marshal|&lt;code&gt;Marshal&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Method|&lt;code&gt;Method&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Math|&lt;code&gt;Math&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Module|&lt;code&gt;Module&lt;/code&gt;]]
**** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Module/Class|&lt;code&gt;Class&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/NilClass|&lt;code&gt;NilClass&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Numeric|&lt;code&gt;Numeric&lt;/code&gt;]]
**** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Numeric/Integer|&lt;code&gt;Integer&lt;/code&gt;]]
***** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Numeric/Integer/Bignum|&lt;code&gt;Bignum&lt;/code&gt;]]
***** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Numeric/Integer/Fixnum|&lt;code&gt;Fixnum&lt;/code&gt;]]
**** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Numeric/Float|&lt;code&gt;Float&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Range|&lt;code&gt;Range&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Regexp|&lt;code&gt;Regexp&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/RubyVM|&lt;code&gt;RubyVM&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/String|&lt;code&gt;String&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Struct|&lt;code&gt;Struct&lt;/code&gt;]]
**** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Struct/Struct::Tms|&lt;code&gt;Struct::Tms&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Symbol|&lt;code&gt;Symbol&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Time|&lt;code&gt;Time&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/Thread|&lt;code&gt;Thread&lt;/code&gt;]]
*** [[Ruby Programming/Reference/Objects/TrueClass|&lt;code&gt;TrueClass&lt;/code&gt;]]

=== Available Standard Library Modules ===

These are parts of Ruby that you have available (in the standard library, or via installation as a gem).
To use them you typically have to require some filename, for example &lt;code&gt;require 'tracer'&lt;/code&gt; would make accessible to you the Tracer class.

You can see a list of basically all the (std lib ruby) modules available in the [http://github.com/ruby/ruby/tree/trunk/lib/ ruby source] and [http://github.com/ruby/ruby/blob/trunk/lib/README lib readme].  There are a several more modules available in the std lib, which are C based extensions.  You can see their list [http://github.com/ruby/ruby/tree/trunk/ext here].

* [[/Standard Library/BigDecimal|BigDecimal]] gives you a way to have arbitrary precision Decimal style numbers.  Never succumb to rounding errors again!
* [[/Standard Library/Debugger|Debugger]] gives you a way to step through debug your Ruby code.
* [[/Standard Library/DRb|Distributed Ruby]] (DRb) gives you a way to make remote procedure calls against objects in a different VM.
* [[/Standard Library/mkmf|mkmf]] is a utility used to generate makefiles for ruby extensions.
* [[/Standard Library/Mutex|Mutex]] gives you a way to control thread concurrency.
* [[/Standard Library/Net::HTTP|Net::HTTP]] gives you a way to download web pages.
* [[/Standard Library/Open3|Open3]] gives you a way to run a sub-process and have easy access to its I/O.
* [[/Standard Library/OpenSSL|OpenSSL]] is a wrapper to the OpenSSL (C) library, giving you access to secure socket connections.
* [[/Standard Library/Pathname|Pathname]] gives you an easy way to manipulate filenames and create/remove files.
* [[/Standard Library/Profiler|Profiler]] gives you a way to profile what is taking up the most time in your code.
* [[/Standard Library/OpenURI|OpenURI]] gives you a way to download files using ruby.
* [[Ruby Programming/XML Processing/REXML|REXML]] is a way to parse XML in pure Ruby.
* [[/Standard Library/Ripper|Ripper]] gives you a way to parse pure Ruby code into an AST.
* [[/Reference/Objects/Socket|Socket]] gives you access to Network connectivity.
* [[/Standard Library/Tracer|Tracer]] gives you a way to see which lines of your code are being executed and in what order.
* [[/Standard Library/Win32::Registry|Win32::Registry]] gives you a way to query and edit the windows registry.
* [[/Standard Library/Win32API|Win32API]] gives you a way to call into specific windows core methods easily.
* [[/Standard Library/WIN32OLE|WIN32OLE]] gives you a way to use Windows OLE.

=== Other Libraries ===

* [[/Database Interface Modules/]]

==== GUI Libraries ====

* [[/GUI Toolkit Modules/]] gives a run down of various options for ruby GUI programming.

Here is info on some specifically:

* [[Ruby Programming/GUI Toolkit Modules/Tk|Tk]]
* [[Ruby Programming/GUI Toolkit Modules/GTK2|GTK2]] Notes on the GTK/Gnome bindings.
* [[Ruby Programming/GUI Toolkit Modules/Qt4|Qt4]]

== Intermediate Ruby ==

Here are some more in depth tutorials of certain aspects of Ruby.

:[[/Unit testing/]]
:[[/RubyDoc/]]
:[[/Rake/]]
:[[/RubyGems/]]
:[[/Running Multiple Processes/]]
:[[/Reference/Objects/Socket|Using Network Sockets]]
:Building [[/C Extensions/]]
:[[/Rails/]]
:[[/Embedding Ruby/]] within a separate C program

== External links ==

{{wikipedia|Ruby Programming Language}}

* [http://www.ruby-lang.org/ Ruby homepage]
* [http://www.ruby-forum.com/ Access to various Ruby mailing lists]
* [http://wiki.github.com/rdp/ruby_tutorials_core/ruby-talk-faq Ruby Talk FAQ]
* [http://www.rubyforge.org/ RubyForge: The Repository for Open-source Ruby Projects ]
* [http://rubytrends.com] a place where people vote on things they like most per category

=== Documentation ===

==== Core Docs ====

* [http://www.ruby-doc.org/ Ruby Documentation Homepage]

* [http://www.ruby-doc.org ruby-doc.org] various ruby documentations and tutorials, as well as information on how to update ruby's core docs should you so desire.
* [http://webri.tigerops.org webri] ruby core api as a webri

==== gem docs ====

* “rdoc.info”:http://www.rdoc.info yard rdoc’s for gems hosted on github
* “ruby toolbox”:http://ruby-toolbox.com list of gems by popularity

=== Learning Ruby ===

* [http://tryruby.org/ Try Ruby] - learn the basics of the Ruby language in your browser.
* [http://www.learnstreet.com LearnStreet] - Free online Ruby tutorials &amp; practice exercises
* [http://www.meshplex.org/wiki/Ruby/Ruby_on_Rails_programming_tutorials A Ruby Tutorial that Anyone can Edit] (broken)
* [http://www.yoyobrain.com/cardboxes/preview/103 Learning Ruby] A free tool to find and learn Ruby concepts

==== Books ====

===== Print =====
* [http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/9780596516178/ The Ruby Programming Language] by David Flanagan, Yukihiro Matsumoto aka “Matz,” the creator of Ruby. Also covers 1.9
* [http://pragprog.com/titles/ruby3 Programming Ruby 3] (aka “Pickaxe”) — this 2009 version covers Ruby 1.9
* [http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/9781593271480/ Ruby by Example]

===== Online =====

* [http://ruby-doc.org/docs/ProgrammingRuby/  Programming Ruby (a.k.a. “Pickaxe”) 1st edition online version]
* [http://rubylearning.com/download/downloads.html Ruby Study Notes]
* [http://www.scribd.com/doc/2236084/Whys-Poignant-Guide-to-Ruby Why’s (Poignant) Guide To Ruby]
* [http://www.humblelittlerubybook.com/book/ Humble Little Ruby Book]
* [http://hawthorne-press.com/WebPage_RHG.html Ruby Hacker’s Guide ]is a guide to the guts of (mostly 1.8) ruby, translated from its original Japanese.

==== Quick References ====
* [http://www.zenspider.com/Languages/Ruby/QuickRef.html Ruby Quick Reference (some of more obscure expressions are explained)]
* [http://www.rubyinside.com/ruby-cheat-sheet-734.html Ruby Cheat Sheets  (a list of some different Ruby cheat sheets)]

{{subjects|Ruby programming language}}
{{alphabetical|R}}
{{status|50%}}
__NOTOC__

[[de:Ruby-Programmierung]]
[[es:Programación en Ruby]]
[[eo:Lernolibro pri Rubeno]]
[[fr:Programmation Ruby]]
[[nl:Programmeren in Ruby]]
[[ja:Ruby]]
[[pl:Ruby]]
[[ru:Ruby]]
[[zh:Ruby Programming]]</text>
      <sha1>4qq4ctek63kf63omw48gp74l9ub2xjl</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:David Martland</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>845</id>
    <revision>
      <id>152982</id>
      <timestamp>2003-08-26T15:46:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>David Martland</username>
        <id>90</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>test</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Let's see where these all turn up!

[[a:User:David Martland]]
[[b:User:David Martland]]
[[c:User:David Martland]]
[[d:User:David Martland]]
[[e:User:David Martland]]
[[f:User:David Martland]]
[[g:User:David Martland]]
[[h:User:David Martland]]
[[i:User:David Martland]]
[[j:User:David Martland]]
[[k:User:David Martland]]
[[l:User:David Martland]]
[[m:User:David Martland]]
[[n:User:David Martland]]
[[o:User:David Martland]]
[[p:User:David Martland]]
[[q:User:David Martland]]
[[r:User:David Martland]]
[[s:User:David Martland]]
[[t:User:David Martland]]
[[u:User:David Martland]]
[[v:User:David Martland]]
[[w:User:David Martland]]
[[x:User:David Martland]]
[[y:User:David Martland]]
[[z:User:David Martland]]</text>
      <sha1>gur71ey09j5p5t6adcvtd6c5nyta4n5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Spanish/Exercises/Personal Pronouns</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>850</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2403905</id>
      <parentid>616032</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-04T21:36:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>190.233.129.227</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Clarification of vosotros</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Spanish/Lesson 1| ^Lesson 1^]]
----
Pronombres personales.
''(Personal pronouns.)''

Ejercicio 1.
Rellena los espacios en blanco con los pronombres personales correctos en español.

''Exercise 1.''
''Fill the blank spaces with the correct Spanish personal pronouns.''


{|  border=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot;
|-
|  
Inglés:                      
|
Español
|-
|
''English:''
|
''Spanish:''
|-
| -- || --
|-
|
'''I'''     am        
|
'''Yo'''         soy 
|-
|
1. '''You'''   are           
|
______     eres
|-
|
2. '''He'''    is
|  
______     es
|-
|
3. '''She'''   is
|  
______     es
|-
|
4. '''We'''    are
|  
______     somos
|-
|
5. '''You''' (plural)  are
|  
______     sois
|-
|
6. '''They'''  are
|  
______     son
|}


Ejercicio 2.
Rellena los espacios en blanco con los pronombres personales correctos en español.

''Exercise 2.''
''Fill the blank spaces with the correct Spanish personal pronouns.''




{|  border=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot;
|-
|  
Inglés:                      
|
Español
|-
|
''English:''
|
''Spanish:''
|-
| -- || --
|-
|
'''You'''  are                   
|
'''Vosotros'''    estáis
|-
|
1. '''He'''   is                   
|
______      está
|-
|
2. '''You'''  are                   
|  
______      estás
|-
|
3. '''I'''    am 	           
|  
______      estoy
|-
|
4. '''They''' are                   
|  
______      están
|-
|
5. '''We'''   are                   
|  
______      estamos
|-
|
6. '''She'''  is                    
|  
______      está
|}

----------------------------------------
[[Spanish/Exercises/Personal_Pronouns_-_Solutions|Soluciones a los ejercicios]] ''Solution to exercices''

[[Spanish/Lesson 1| ^Lesson 1^]]

[[Category:Spanish]]</text>
      <sha1>a0oxenufcjf276o6eowcqnja75uga8d</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Wikibooks:Language and literature bookshelf</title>
    <ns>4</ns>
    <id>852</id>
    <restrictions>edit=autoconfirmed:move=autoconfirmed</restrictions>
    <revision>
      <id>2169311</id>
      <parentid>1871144</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-09-17T18:24:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Hasenläufer</username>
        <id>441085</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* External links */ typo</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{deprecated bookshelf|[[Subject:Literature]]}}
{{bookshelves}}
{{bookshelf|Language and literature bookshelf}}
{{stages}}

{{info|Looking for the languages themselves? Try the [[Wikibooks:Languages bookshelf|Languages bookshelf]]. This contains a &lt;u&gt;list&lt;/u&gt; of annotated texts. For Wikibooks &lt;u&gt;policy&lt;/u&gt; regarding annotated texts, please see [[Wikibooks:Annotated texts]]. When adding to this list please add the book title with a square bullit with the author's name, if it is a compilation of works, label it with &quot;various authors.&quot;}}

__TOC__

{{Requested books}}

== Linguistics ==

* [[Conlang]]{{stage short|50%}}
* [[Linguistics]]{{stage short|25%}}
* [[Policy Debate|Policy Debate]]{{stage short|25%}}
* [[Extemporaneous Speaking|Extemporaneous Speaking]]{{stage short|25%}}
* [[Student Congress Debate|Student Congress (Legislative) Debate]]{{stage short|25%}}

{{Requested books}}

==Composition and writing==
: ''Please add short guides to specific genres to [[Creative Writing]].''

* [[Basic Writing: Process and Practice]]{{stage short|75%}}
* [[Business writing]]{{stage short|50%}}
* [[Composition]]{{stage short|50%}}
* [[Conworld]]{{stage short|25%}}
* [[Creative Writing]]{{stage short|25%}}
* [[How to write a research paper in History]] {{stage short|50%}}
* [[How to write an essay]] {{stage short|25%}}
* [[How to Keep a Journal]] {{stage short|25%}}
* [[Rhetoric and Composition]] {{stage short|75%}}
* [[Professional and Technical Writing|Professional and Technical Writing: A Rhetorical Guide to Tech Comm]]{{stage short|50%}}
* [[Writing Adolescent Fiction]]{{stage short|25%}}
{{Requested books}}

==Rhetoric==
&lt;div style=&quot;float: right;&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
* [[Basic Writing: Process and Practice]]{{stage short|75%}}
* [[Rhetoric and Composition]] {{stage short|75%}}
* [[Professional and Technical Writing|Professional and Technical Writing: A Rhetorical Guide to Tech Comm]]{{stage short|50%}}
* [[Rhetoric and Writing in the Public Sphere: An Introduction]]{{stage short|25%}}
* [[Visual Rhetoric]]{{stage short|75%}}

{{-}}
{{Requested books}}

==Regional literature==
* English literature:
** [[William Shakespeare's Works|William Shakespeare]] {{stage short|25%}}
** [[Guide to English Literature|Guide to English Literature]]{{stage short|25%}}
* American literature:
**[[American Literature]]{{stage short|25%}}
* [[Japanese Literature]]
* Genre Literature:
** [[Science Fiction Literature]]{{stage short|25%}}

{{Requested books}}

==General topics in literature==
* [[Literary criticism]]{{stage short|25%}}
* [[History of Literature]]{{stage short|25%}}

{{Requested books}}

==Multiple works and author guides==
* [[William Shakespeare's Works|William Shakespeare's Works (with Notes)]] {{stage short|25%}}
* [[Plato]]{{stage short|25%}}
* [[19th Century Literature]]{{stage short|25%}}
* [[The Poetry of Gaius Valerius Catullus]]{{stage short|25%}}
* [[How to Read Young Adult Literature Like a Young Adult Writer]]{{stage short|25%}}
{{Requested books}}

==Mythology and folklore==
* [[Mythology]]{{stage short|25%}}
* [[Greek Mythology]]{{stage short|25%}}
* [[Indian Mythology]]{{stage short|25%}}

{{Requested books}}

==Fiction annotations==

* [[Accelerando Technical Companion|Technical Companion]] of ''[[w:Accelerando|Accelerando]]'' by [[w:Charles Stross|Charles Stross]]{{stage short|25%}}
* ''[[Angels and Demons]]'' by [[w:Dan Brown|Dan Brown]]{{stage short|50%}}
* [[Annotations of The Complete Peanuts|Annotations of ''The Complete Peanuts'']] by [[w:Charles M. Schulz|Charles M. Schulz]]{{stage short|25%}}
* ''[[Atlas Shrugged]]'' by [[w:Ayn Rand|Ayn Rand]]{{stage short|75%}}
* ''[[The Divine Comedy]]'' by [[w:Dante Alighieri|Dante Alighieri]]{{stage short|25%}}
* ''[[Lord of the Flies]]'' by [[w:William Golding|William Golding]]{{stage short|25%}}
* ''[[Of Mice and Men]]'' by  [[w:John Steinbeck|John Steinbeck]]{{stage short|25%}}
* ''[[The Once and Future King]]'' by [[w:T. H. White|T. H. White]]{{stage short|25%}}
* ''[[A Tale of Two Cities]]'' by [[w:Charles Dickens|Charles Dickens]]{{stage short|25%}}
* ''[[The Wealthy Barber]]'' by [[w:David Barr Chilton|David Barr Chilton]]{{stage short|25%}}
* ''[[The Grand Inquisitor]]'' by [[w:Fyodor Dostoevsky|Fyodor Dostoevsky]]{{stage short|25%}}
* ''[[The Poetry of Gaius Valerius Catullus]]'' by [[w:Gaius Valerius Catullus|Gaius Valerius Catullus]]{{stage short|25%}}

{{Requested books}}

==Nonfiction annotations==
* ''[[The Annotated Constitution of the United States|Constitution of the United States]]'' by various authors
* [[Annotated laws relating to Conrail]] by various authors
* ''[[Seven Habits Study Guide|The Seven Habits of Highly Effective People?]]'' by [[w:Stephen Covey|Stephen Covey]]
* ''[[The Voynich Manuscript]]'' by various authors

{{Requested books}}

==Annotations with source text==
[[Madame Bovary]] by Gustave Flaubert

==See also==
* [[Wikibooks:Annotated texts|Annotated texts policy]]
* [[Wikibooks:Languages bookshelf|Languages bookshelf]]
* [[Wikiversity:School of Literature and English Studies|Wikiversity School of Literature and English Studies]]

==External links==
* [[s:|Wikisource]]
* [http://www.gutenberg.org/ Project Gutenberg]

{{Associated Wikimedia|Language
|Commons category    = Language
|Wikinews portal     = 
|Wikinews category   = 
|Wikipedia           = Language
|Wikipedia portal    = Language
|Wikiquote           = 
|Wikiquote category  = 
|Wikisource          = 
|Wikisource category = Language
|Wikiversity         = 
|Wikiversity school  = 
|Wiktionary          = language
|Wiktionary appendix = 
|Wiktionary category = Language
}}

{{Associated Wikimedia|Literature
|Commons category    = Literature
|Wikinews portal     = 
|Wikinews category   = 
|Wikipedia           = Literature
|Wikipedia portal    = Literature
|Wikiquote           = Literature
|Wikiquote category  = 
|Wikisource          = 
|Wikisource category = Literature
|Wikiversity         = 
|Wikiversity school  = Literature and English Studies
|Wiktionary          = literature
|Wiktionary appendix = 
|Wiktionary category = Literature
}}

[[Category:Wikibooks bookshelves|Language and literature bookshelf]]</text>
      <sha1>b3t1542bz8ank6j5cyvndo515wcic14</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Spanish/Exercises/Verbs ser And estar</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>853</id>
    <revision>
      <id>616034</id>
      <parentid>532397</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-10-18T04:12:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Guanabot</username>
        <id>5478</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>User-controlled Bot: table syntax updated</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Spanish/Lesson 1| ^Lesson 1^]]
----
Llena los espacios en blanco con la forma verbal correcta del verbo &quot;ser&quot;.
''Fill the blank spaces with the correct form of the verb &quot;ser&quot; (to be).''




{|  border=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot;
|-
| Inglés: || Español
|-
| ''English:'' || ''Spanish:''
|-
| -- || --
|-
| I '''am''' your brother. || Yo '''soy''' tu hermano.
|-
| I '''am''' your sister. || Yo ____ tu hermana.
|-
| You '''are''' my friend. || Tú ____ mi amigo.
|-
| You '''are''' my boss || Usted ___ mi jefe
|-
| He '''is''' a good man. || Él ____ un buen hombre.
|-
| She '''is''' a traveller. || Ella ____ una viajera.
|-
| We '''are''' students. || Nosotros ____ estudiantes.
|-
| You '''are''' dangerous. || Vosotros ____ peligrosos.
|-
| You '''are''' Spaniards || Vosotras ___ españolas
|-
| You '''are''' Argentinians || Ustedes ___ argentinos
|-
| They '''are''' people. || Ellos ____ personas.
|}
----
Llena los espacios en blanco con la forma verbal correcta del verbo &quot;estar&quot;.
''Fill the blank spaces with the correct form of the verb &quot;estar&quot; (to be).''


{|  border=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot;
|-
| Inglés || Español
|-
| ''English'' || ''Spanish''
|-
| -- || --
|-
| I '''am''' in my home. || Yo _____ en mi casa.
|-
| You '''are''' in the correct place. || Tú _____ en el sitio correcto.
|-
| You '''are''' angry. || Tú _____ enojado.
|-
| You '''are''' happy || Usted ___ contento
|-
| He '''is''' in Europe. || Él _____ en Europa.
|-
| She '''is''' sad. || Ella ___ triste.
|-
| We '''are''' in the Americas. || Nosotros _____ en América.
|-
| You '''are''' in Africa. || Vosotros _____ en África.
|-
| They '''are''' ill. || Ellos _____ enfermos.
|}
----------------------------

Llena los espacios en blanco con la forma verbal correcta del verbo &quot;ser&quot; o &quot;estar&quot;.
''Fill the blank spaces with the correct form of the verb &quot;ser&quot; or &quot;estar&quot; (to be).''


{|  border=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot;
|-
|  
Inglés:                      
|
Español
|-
|
''English:''
|
''Spanish:''
|-
| -- || --
|-
| I '''am''' in China.
| Yo '''estoy''' en China.''(soy/estoy)''
|-
| You '''are''' my friend. || Tú _____ mi amigo.''(eres/estás)''
|-
| You '''are''' there. || Tú _____ allí. ''(eres/estás)''
|-
| She '''is''' my sister.
| Ella _____ mi hermana. ''(es/está)''
|-
| He '''is''' ill. || Él _____ enfermo. ''(es/está)''
|-
| We '''are''' ready.
| Nosotros _____ preparados. ''(somos/estamos)''
|-
| We '''are''' intelligent. ||
Nosotros _____ inteligentes. ''(somos/estamos)''
|-
| You '''are''' in Europe for Christmas.
| Vosotros _____ en Europa para Navidad. ''(sois/estáis)''
|-
| You '''are''' sad. ||
Vosotras _____ tristes. ''(sois/estáis)''
|-
| They '''are''' sympathetic. ||
Ellas ____ comprensivas. ''(son/están)''
|-
| They '''are''' interesting people. ||
Ellos ____ gente interesante. ''(son/están)''
|}
----------------------------------------
[[Spanish/Exercises/Verbs_ser_And_estar_-_Solutions|Soluciones a los ejercicios]] ''Solution to exercices''

[[Spanish/Lesson 1| ^Lesson 1^]]

[[Category:Spanish]]</text>
      <sha1>b465add0tq27lb0tcr9v0tnfq0ef36s</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>CACS/Glossary/CSS</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>871</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1508360</id>
      <parentid>1493434</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-05-25T23:52:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>recat</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Cascading Style Sheet''' '''(CSS)''' &lt;small&gt;''(Web Pages, HTML)''&lt;/small&gt; is an HTML feature using a set of hierarchic input files that specify display characteristics used to interpret various ''HTML'' formatting tags. The '''CSS2''' version also supports the description of display properties that are applied to ''XML'' applications. The CSS is an open specification maintained by the ''W3C'', and detailed online information describing style sheets may be found at the [http://www.w3.org/pub/WWW/Style/css/ W3C's Specification Page].

[[Category:{{FULLBOOKNAME}}|{{FULLCHAPTERNAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>edxlwzb9yfdbb59ggxr24wgypbuvo6p</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>GCSE Science/Electricity</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>873</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2170547</id>
      <parentid>2170545</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-09-21T11:46:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">

Information on the Oxford, Cambridge and RSA examinations is available from the [http://www.ocr.org.uk/qualifications/type/gcse_2011/   OCR Website].

*[[GCSE Science/Static Electricity|Static Electricity]]
**[[GCSE Science/Uses of static electricity]]
**[[GCSE Science/Advanced static electricity topics]]
*[[GCSE Science/Electrolysis|Electrolysis]]
*[[GCSE Science/Circuits]]
**[[GCSE Science/Current, voltage resistance and Ohm's law]]
**[[GCSE Science/Three useful components]]
**[[GCSE Science/Circuits Part2]]
**[[GCSE Science/Parallel and series circuits]]
*[[GCSE Science/Safety in Mains circuits| Safety in Mains Circuits]]
*[[GCSE Science/Electrical Power|Power]]
*[[GCSE Science/Electromagnetism|Electromagnetism]]
**[[GCSE Science/Magnetic effects of a current]]
**[[GCSE Science/Uses of electromagnets]]
**[[GCSE Science/The motor effect]]
**[[GCSE Science/Induction]]
**[[GCSE Science/Generating electricity]]
**[[GCSE Science/Transformers]]

==End of Module tests==
*[[GCSE Science/Electricity multiple choice|Multiple choice]]
*[[GCSE Science/Terminal exam questions|Terminal exam questions]]



----
See also [[Electronics]].

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>mndp3cjlyoaczlb7pemeorf0d7z2s5o</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>GCSE Science/Static Electricity</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>874</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2419390</id>
      <parentid>2419389</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-15T12:08:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rvv</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[GCSE Science/Electricity]]
----
Have you ever noticed a crackle when you pull off a sweater? Have you ever had your hair stick to your face after combing? What about seeing a balloon stick to the wall after it has been rubbed? All these effects are caused by '''static electricity'''. Static electricity is the imbalanced charges of matter.  It was the Greeks who first noticed that when they rubbed a piece of amber, it attracted small pieces of paper. The Greek word for amber is elektron, and it is from this that we get our words electron and electricity.

==What causes static electricity?==
Usually materials are electrically neutral. This means that they are ''not'' electrically charged. However this doesn't mean that materials have no charges ''inside'' them. All materials are made of atoms.  Atoms are made of particles called electrons, protons, and neutrons.  Electrons have a negative charge, protons have a positive charge, and neutrons (as you can probably guess by the name) have no charge.  Materials are partly made of charged particles.  Materials have no overall charge whenever they have the same number of electrons and protons. The negative charge of the electrons exactly cancels out the positive charge of the protons. 

'''Test YourSelf:''' 
Q1) The element lithium  has three protons. How many electrons must a neutral lithium atom have?

Inside an atom the protons and neutrons are held firmly at the very centre in a structure called the nucleus. The electrons however are held much more loosely. Some can be found at the surface, and if the surface is rubbed, they can be rubbed away. This removal of electrons will leave the atom with more protons than electrons. It will have a positive charge because the protons are positively charged. Atoms that are charged are called ions.

When you rub a balloon on your sweater some of the electrons are transferred from the sweater to the balloon. The sweater becomes positively charged. 

'''Test YourSelf:''' 
Q2) What charge will the balloon have?

==How do the two types of charge behave?==

The sweater is positively charged, the balloon negative. The balloon sticks to the sweater. This is because '''unlike charges attract'''. If you were to take two balloons, both of which had been negatively charged and brought them together you would find that they tried to push apart. This is because '''like charges repel'''.

[[Image:Balloons (static electricity).png]]

''' Test Yourself''' 
Q3) Look at the balloons above. The pair on the left are being repelled. The pair on the right are being attracted. Notice that one out of each pair of balloons is negatively charged. What is the sign (positive or negative) of the charges on the other two balloons?

==Sparks can fly!==



When a large enough charge is built up sparks can fly. A spark is just a flow of electrons through the air. This can sometimes be very dangerous. For example, petrol flowing through a pipeline can pick up a charge by friction. If a spark flies it could ignite the petrol. For this reason, pipes are earthed. Earthing means connecting the pipe to the ground by means of a copper wire. Copper, unlike air, is a very good conductor of electricity. The electrons can flow easily and safely to the ground without sparking.

Some devices make use of sparks. A Van de Graaf generator consists of a large metal dome that is in contact with a rubber or plastic looped belt. As the belt moves, friction causes it to become charged; the charge is spread out over the metal dome where it builds up until it is large enough to cause a spark.


&lt;center&gt;[[Image:Girl touch Van de Graaf.png]]&lt;/center&gt;

In the diagram above a girl is standing on a washing up bowl and touching a Van de Graaf machine.

'''Test Yourself'''
Q4) What do you think is the purpose of the washing up bowl?

'''Test Yourself'''
Q5) Explain why the girl's hair is standing on end (no it's not her style, it's to do with the charge)



{| bgcolor=&quot;ffeeaa&quot;
|-
|
'''Summary'''
*Friction can cause electrons to rub off one material onto another
*Two objects with the same type of charge repel
*Two objects with the opposite type of charge attract
*To prevent sparks, discharge the object by connecting it to earth with a metal conductor
*To encourage sparks, insulate the object
|}

[[GCSE Science/Answers-Static Electricity|Answers to questions]] | [[GCSE Science/Electricity|&lt;&lt; Electricity]] | [[GCSE Science/Uses of static electricity|Uses of static electricity &gt;&gt;]]

[[Category:GCSE Science]]</text>
      <sha1>cor0g7r4hj1a656h1inna6b5g99jyti</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Balloons (static electricity).png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>875</id>
    <revision>
      <id>636429</id>
      <parentid>153010</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-11-04T11:02:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Theresa knott</username>
        <id>93</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">
{{GFDL}}
{{Cc-by-sa-2.5}}
balloons being attracted and repelled. Drawn by theresa knott</text>
      <sha1>tj9251aybaeg3u5x2zqrf7f78kzp6u1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Girl touch Van de Graaf.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>876</id>
    <revision>
      <id>636437</id>
      <parentid>153011</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-11-04T11:04:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Theresa knott</username>
        <id>93</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">diagran showing what happens if you stand on a washing up bowl and touch a van de graaf. Drawn by Theresa Knott

{{GFDL}}
{{Cc-by-sa-2.5}}</text>
      <sha1>belczcwtpg58omcoxcs8ffxn2rorqfa</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:GCSE Science</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>877</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2174368</id>
      <parentid>951193</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-10-02T23:54:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>HethrirBot</username>
        <id>475400</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Robot: Cosmetic changes</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Hey Theresa knott, looks like an exciting project. Best of luck and welcome to the textbook project. We're gonna like change the world, an' stuff ! Thanks for the help. (I added a couple of navigation links for you) ... --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

Thanks for the links! We certainly are gonig to change the world, but it's a daunting prospect this early on. Still little by little -- [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 10:29, 29 Aug 2003 (UTC)
----
I've been thinking. I sort of hijacked this page for GCSE science. It occurs to me that someone visiting this page migh want see see things on the scientific method, anyalysing data, Good and not so good science. Examples of downright sloppy science and even fraud. That sort of thing.If anyone want's reclaim this page for general science rather than GCSE science, feel free, but please link GCSE science to the main page or somewhere it is likely to be seen [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 21:36, 18 Sep 2003 (UTC)

:Very chivalrous of you. I imagine that as this site grows there will be all kinds of overlaps on name usage, with multiple books and stuty guides on any topic. Hopefully there will be so much activity that people will be fighting over namespaces. Well, not that I am hoping for fighting. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

== Tweaks ==
Theresa, love the design of the page. I tweaked it up a bit for you. Question: Just what does &quot;GCSE&quot; stand for, anyways ? If I knew I forgot and don't know where to check. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

Thanks for the tweaks. GCSE stands for General certificate of secondary education. 

:&lt;headmistress giving a &quot;you should know better&quot; look&gt; 
The best place to check for information is wikipedia ;-) see this article for more details http://www.wikipedia.org/wiki/GCSE 
:&lt;/headmistress giving a &quot;you should know better&quot; look&gt; [[User:Theresa knott]]

::Headmistress ? OK, this must definitely be a non-US thing. Seriously, I have never heard of General certificate of secondary education before. I thought the S would stand for science ..

== Funny science songs ==
You may like the songs found on this page. Sort of more designed for kids but it was funny to me as an adult too. Maybe it could fit into your book somewhere although I wouldn't know where.

http://www.acme.com/jef/science_songs/

- Thank you

== Subpages ==
Wouldn't it be better to use subpages? For example, right now you have &quot;GCSE_science&quot; and &quot;Introduction_(GCSE_science)&quot; and so on. With subpages, they would be &quot;GCSE_science&quot; and &quot;GCSE_science/Introduction&quot; and so on. It seems tider to me because all the GCSE science pages are then contained under 'GCSE_science'. Just a thought. :) --[[User:Avxxv|Avxxv]] 20:10, 15 October 2005 (UTC)

:Subpages is a feature that was added long after this book was created. Sure, having subpages will be much tidier, but things will have to be moved in a way to not ruin internal links. --[[User:Krackpipe|Krackpipe]] 18:58, 7 December 2005 (UTC)

== Proposed rename ==

I'd like to change these pages so that they all start with &quot;GCSE Science/&quot;. This would bring these pages into link with other wikibooks. Any move would be done in such a way as to preserve all links. I trust this will prove to be non-controversial, but note the proposal here first to allow for comments, [[User:Jguk|Jguk]] 12:50, 24 February 2006 (UTC)

== Image format ==

A lot of images in this textbook are in GIF format. They should be converted to PNG, or a PNG alternative should be found. [[User:Ksd5|Emanla Eraton]] 15:26, 26 August 2007 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>h5qioplvxe1jrf3huu7m8unnotr02tr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Simple atom (lithium).png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>878</id>
    <revision>
      <id>636438</id>
      <parentid>153013</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-11-04T11:05:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Theresa knott</username>
        <id>93</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Diagram drawn by Theresa Knott

{{GFDL}}
{{Cc-by-sa-2.5}}</text>
      <sha1>qg0d939lbr321zlfqap3x7hv8bwuy17</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>GCSE Science/Answers-Static Electricity</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>880</id>
    <revision>
      <id>491234</id>
      <parentid>381396</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-06-18T07:31:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Back to [[GCSE Science/Static Electricity]]

----
'''Q1)''' 3 --- all atoms have the same number of protons as electrons


'''Q2)''' Negative ---	electrons have been added to the balloon.


'''Q3 left hand pair)'''  Negative--- The balloons are  repelled

'''Q3 right hand pair)'''Positive --- The balloons are attracted. Remember '&quot;like charges repel, unlike charges attract'''   


'''Q4)''' The purpose of the washing up bowl is to insulate the girl from the ground. People are reasonable conductors of electricity. If the girl just stood on the floor electricity would run through her body and leak away. She would act as an earth wire for the Van de Graaf.

'''Q5)''' The girl's hairs all pick up static electricity from the Van de Graaf machine.  Remember '''like charges repel''', so each hair tries to get as far away from the other hairs as possible. That is why her hair stands on end.

[[Category:GCSE Science]]</text>
      <sha1>bwk5qacgpysgxbo0121izx2tgm70xk0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:Theresa knott</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>882</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1184942</id>
      <parentid>1182289</parentid>
      <timestamp>2008-05-14T16:56:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>86.29.128.62</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* bsrboy */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">I LOVE your drawings ... you are going to make me get off my duff and do some of my own because I see how much they immediately add to the work. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

Theresa, what program are you using to make those drawings ? Just wondering .. Hey never mind, I just checked your user page on the main WP and saw that you have links and info about it .. you use MS Word ?? Interesting ... I hope you keep up the passion. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

Thanks, Theresa. You've really restored my confidence in the whole Wikibooks thing. I've encountered a lot of unwritten, poorly-written or excessively incomprehensible stuff, and what I see with GCSE Science is a breath of fresh air! Keep up the good work, it's of sufficient quality to actually see it competing with other major textbooks. Well done! --[[User:81.157.26.41|81.157.26.41]] 21:31, 6 Jan 2005 (UTC)

----
Theresa, sub-pages are any page that contains a '/' in the page name. Normally, a slash in the URL indicates a file structure or directory entry on the server. They were used a lot in Wikipedia, but have mostly been removed there.
We've discussed them here as a possible way to solve the need for duplicate modules. Thus ''GCSE/Atomic Structure'' would be different than ''Physics/Atomic Structure''. The Wikipedia approach would be to name these modules ''Atomic Structure in General Science'', but this seems combersome.
Another approach involvers the use of Namespaces. This would get things like ''GCSE:Atomic Structure''.

There are a couple of us experimenting with things like automated table of contents and pop-up windows for footnotes or a glossary. When we get a good technique that works, we'll update or create a guideline page. In the meantime, most of us are just continuing whatever method a book started with. We know we'll have some cleanup when a good technique is settled on. Hope this explains some of whats going on. Keep up the good work, and I second Karl's praise for your illustrations.  [[User:LouI|LouI]] 19:57, 1 Sep 2003 (UTC)

==Covalent bonding==
Hey Theresa, thanks for your edits on the organic subpages. This statement from [[Organic Chemistry/Foundational concepts of organic chemistry/Covalent bonding|Covalent bonding]] does not seem to be true tho: &quot;Covalent bonds always occur in molecules that only have one type of atom&quot;. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
----
I was just looking at your science book. It sure is a large volume to cover. Do you plan on writing the whole thing ? I see your edits all of the time for quite some time now and yet the volume left to go is much larger than that which is done. I guess my book is the same tho, and when I finish ochem its on to other subjects .. Oh yeah, I hope you approve of the edit I did on the main science book page. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
:It certainly is a large amount of work. If I do it all by myself on and off as the mood takes me it'll take maybe two or three years to complete. Still nothing worth doing is easy. What I hope will happen, when I get the electricity module really well done, a proper useable resource, then people might start actually using it. If that happens {well I should say when that happens) someone else may be inspired to write another module, Still if I have to do the whole thing myself I will. Oh and yes the edit on general science is good.[[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 21:21, 18 Sep 2003 (UTC)
==Evangelizing==
By the way, I was talking up your page to a guy I ran into at work who is an eighth-grade teacher, saying how it is coming along and everything. He was pretty excited about it. As we get along farther on these things I think growth will accelarate. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
==Admin==
Theresa I want to nominate you to be an admin. I cant find the page tho.. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

==Ochem==
Looks nice ! --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

==We miss you==
Hi Theresa, what's new. I haven't seen you around lately .. I hope you are not mad about my not understanding the meaning of GCSE or anything related. Are you taking a break ? Not giving up I hope. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

==Welcome back Theresa ! ==

I did miss you but am glad you were able to take a refreshing breather, and look forward to seeing you around these pages once again. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

==Quiz maker tool==
Teresa, are you familiar with this site ? http://javascript.about.com/library/tools/blquizmaker.htm

It writes quiz code for you so you can make dynamic Q&amp;A's. Maybe we (you) could use it. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

----

Theresa - The main page was perfectly fine before (Statement not true about whatever size screen you have ~ I never had to scroll right left. Not sure what the proper sizing is, but the central contents area looks a bit squeezed now - [[User:Marshman|Marsh]] 21:18, 4 Nov 2003 (UTC) I think the problem arises from that little box added at top right. -- [[User:Marshman|Marsh]]

Theresa - I'm using IE.  The html width % tags should adjust things for both individual browser and screen resolutioon settings (all things functioning perfectly).  By adjusting the contents table to 80% it did get smaller on my screen, but everything else around (above and below) stayed the same (the tables are nested), so there was no right-left adjustment in text outside the colored contents box.  Is it (on your browser) actually filling more than full screen width?  Usually, that is caused by something forcing the width out of specified bounds (e.g., a line or graphic that is too large for screen setting, or something similar in essence overriding the percent width commands) - [[User:Marshman|Marsh]] 22:55, 4 Nov 2003 (UTC)

I too am using IE. I think the problem that have is to do with the navigation frame on the L.H.S. of the page. (the one with the wikibooks logo) This takes up about 20% of the page width, so if the tables set at 100% the page will always be wider than the browser window. I don't see why we need to set a width at all really, so I've removed the width attributes entirely, letting the viewers browser decide how wide to make the table. Does this look ok to you ? [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 09:17, 5 Nov 2003 (UTC)

Did removing the Width=100% make any difference on your browserr? - [[User:Marshman|Marsh]] 17:37, 5 Nov 2003 (UTC)
:Yes it's cured the problem for me. Does it still look OK to you? [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 23:03, 5 Nov 2003 (UTC)
::After I brought the three columns a bit closerr to same size, it looks fine on my screen, but only fills about 80% of the available space.  If it was off screen with 100% setting on your monitor, then something must be forcing the layout wide (and the colored box table complies by filling 100% of &quot;too big&quot;); but I cannot see what that is.  Most suspicious is the longer titles in the book listings. That is all I can see that could overide settings as there are no wide graphics anywhere.  What does the French Wikibooks main page look like on your system?  It is fine on mine. - [[User:Marshman|Marsh]] 00:49, 6 Nov 2003 (UTC)     

----
About the picture of Paris, I took it on the french Wikipedia, in the article about Paris. Traroth 10:26, 5 Nov 2003 (UTC) 
:I see. I'll do the necessary editing then. [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 11:12, 5 Nov 2003 (UTC)
----
A belated thankyou for the image on [[Discrete mathematics:Functions and relations]] :) [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 10:27, 12 Nov 2003 (UTC)
:You're very welcome :-) [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 11:35, 12 Nov 2003 (UTC)

== Foundation or Higher? ==

As far as I know, there is no Foundation or Higher. It is law that schools (except public schools...) have to have balanced sciences.

There is Single Science, 6 modules, Double Science, 12 modules, or Seperate Sciences, 18 modules.

Single Science makes you do 6 modules in the 2 GCSE years and you recieve one grade (from * down to F/U/similar).

Double Science makes you do 12 modules in the 2 GCSE years and you recieve two identical grades (from ** down to FF/UU/similar). They can never be different so excelling in Chemistry will not get you very far.

Seperate Sciences (that's me!) is like taking a Biology, Physics and Chemistry GCSE. Each have 6 modules and you get three seperate grades.

What's Foundation and Higher? [[User:R3m0t|R3m0t]] 16:52, 5 Dec 2003 (UTC)

It's the paper you sit in many exam boards Foundation is balanced, you still get 12 modules for doulble science, but the papers omit the most difficult questions. You can get grades C downwards. The higher paper is gives grades A -D any lower than that you get a U. The paper sat is not specified on the final certificate though, A grade C For example can be got by sitting either paper and nobody but the candidate need know which paper was sat.  [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 08:31, 7 Dec 2003 (UTC)

== Algebra:Functions images ==

Thanks for those.  The apple picture is great!  I'm going to move the second illustration down from the relation section to the function part; any chance you could make another similar picture demonstrating a relation that's not a function (ie., at least one right-hand element points to more than one left-hand element)?  That would really make the distinction clear.  --[[User:Spikey|Spikey]] 01:35, 18 Dec 2003 (UTC)

Hi T :) If you do intend on resizing the image yourself, you may want to simplify it just a little, it may be a bit complicated on sight to spot that it isn't a function - perhaps have the mapping 1-&gt;{2,3}, 2-&gt;3, 3-&gt;4, 4-&gt;4? Just a suggestion, really, no big deal if you don't wanna change it! :) [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 10:45, 20 Dec 2003 (UTC)

== r3m0t and Science ==

&lt;nowiki&gt;*bows*&lt;/nowiki&gt; Well thank you! Merely 14 years 4 months. [[User:R3m0t|r3m0t]] 07:19, 15 Jan 2004 (UTC)

I'm in year 10, doing Triple Science, AS Mathematics and I'm doing a Chemistry coursework this term. I already did Chemical Patterns, Chemistry in Action and Energy and Electricity and got three A*s (woohoo!). Also finishing Human Body unit and starting Waves, Atoms and Space. I'll try come along to the [[GCSE Science]] and help out when I can :) [[User:R3m0t|r3m0t]] 10:41, 16 Jan 2004 (UTC)

: Well, so far I've done... um... let's see. I've done ''Chemical Patterns'', ''Chemistry in Action'', ''The Human Body'', ''Inheritance and Survival'', ''Energy and Electricity'', ''Waves, Atoms and Space'' - that's all of Single Science. Also finished ''Health and Exercise'' and ''Chemicals of the Earth'' (I think that's it) in Double Science. Also currently doing ''Movement and Change'', in Double, which I started on the 24th. I recieve my Chemistry coursework next week.
: Well, this is going to sound really stupid, but... what do you need help with? :) I would much prefer ''Movement and Change'' because that's what I'm doing right now. PS We use Edexcel in this school. [[User:R3m0t|r3m0t]] [[Special:Contributions/r3m0t|(cont)]] [[User talk:r3m0t|(talk)]] 11:48, 26 Mar 2004 (UTC)
: Well, I prefer Chemistry to Physics, so what the hell - I'll do ''Chemical Patterns'', I think. Need to go find the syllabus thing. [[User:R3m0t|r3m0t]] [[Special:Contributions/r3m0t|(cont)]] [[User talk:r3m0t|(talk)]] 11:48, 26 Mar 2004 (UTC)

== languages ==
Theresa, maybe its no big thing but I am so frustrated I want to rend my clothes. Let me cry on your shoulder ... sniff .. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

== venn diagrams==
Sure thing, Diagram Queen :) Just need some ideas for what to be shown  in them, haven't had much time to think about the DM book for a while... [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 10:31, 3 Feb 2004 (UTC)

==editing feature==
Theresa, have you seen the feature where little boxes show up at the top of the editing box that let you do some formatting in one click ? I was on a friend's computer and these icons showed up that I had never seen, to make text bold or italic, among other things. Maybe it does not work on my Mac or something. Do you know what I am talking about ? It was an XP home edition machine that I saw it on, but the XP pro version work does not seem to support it. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

== thanks ==

Thank you for your kind words. Your support means a lot to me. I will take your advice and will curtail my wikipedia time to make more time for wikibooks. [[User:Perl|Perl]] 13:09, 25 Mar 2004 (UTC)

BTW, Ill be in NEw york for a few days so I won't be able to contribute until Monday. [[User:Perl|Perl]] 13:13, 25 Mar 2004 (UTC)

== thanks ==

Thanks for your work on the physics wikibook. 

-- [[DavidCary]]

p.s.: are you looking for the book
&quot;The Magic Army&quot; by Leslie Thomas http://www.fetchbook.info/The_Magic_Army.html
?

----
Yeah, that's a possibility. If he revert's again I'll use the babelfish or something :) [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 02:12, 4 Jul 2004 (UTC)

== how to ==

forgive my ignorance but for the life of me i can't get the venus image to post from the wikipedia article over to the module. why is this? i was also thinking of bringing the tables from the articles explaining the planet stats. can you help me out maybe post a tutorial type of thing on my talk page here. sorry to bother you. oh and p.s. i look forward to working on this project with everyone, i beleive it will be a great success! --[[User:Larsie|Larsie]] 16:50, 8 Nov 2004 (UTC)

:It can't be done! (Which explains why you can't do it) However a new project called wikicommons has just been launched. This is a central repository for wikimedia pictures. I ''think'' you can get images from commons to display on any wiki, but I don't know for sure as I've never tried it. Take a look [http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Main_Page here] and see if you can figure it out.

== nasa ==

hey there would you be able to tell me where i can find info on how to bring the nasa image from the site to the module? --[[User:Larsie|Larsie]] 18:16, 8 Nov 2004 (UTC)

:Go to the NASA site and download the image onto your harddrive. (Clicking on the image and selecting &quot;save as&quot; should do it. Make sure you save it where you can find it again. Change the name if necessary; it should be descriptive. then click the upload button and navigate yo where the file is on your computer. Put the public domain tag in the summary and also add that it's from NASA then hit the upload button. Let me know if you have any problems. [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 20:10, 8 Nov 2004 (UTC)

i actually know how to format now it's just that i can't download images as i use my work pc for all my contributions so i don't have the ability to gather images and upload them, sorry. --[[User:Larsie|Larsie]] 20:57, 8 Nov 2004 (UTC)

check out what i did for the venus category (the image showing venus in blue) is that ok or should i not do it like that. --[[User:Larsie|Larsie]] 21:07, 8 Nov 2004 (UTC)
:No you can't do that. What you are doing is retreiving the image live from their website everytime you look at the page. This has two consiquences
:#If their website is down for any reason, or if they decide to move the image location or name, we'll see a &quot;missing image&quot; note instead.
:#Because the viewers browser fetches the image from thier website rather than ours, ''they'' have to pay for the bandwith rather than us. bandwith theft is considered extremely poor etiquette.

You best bet is to just put the url on the talk page and let someone else sort adding it to the page. [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 06:48, 9 Nov 2004 (UTC)

thanks for the heads up there theresa, appreciate it. --[[User:Larsie|Larsie]] 17:14, 9 Nov 2004 (UTC)

== Image:Inside_the_sun.PNG ==
[[Image:Inside_the_sun.PNG|left|200px|thumb|Easy to Understand]]
[[Image:Sunlayers.gif|right|200px|thumb|Hard to Understand]]
I like this diagram.  Could I have a go at it?  I'd be happy to correct the typo.
Also, I'd like to create a new version, under a different name.  It would have the photosphere, chromosphere, and corona labelled.  I see a comment here from Karl Wick that you create your images in MS Word.  If that's true, I should be able to edit in MS Word, right?  Could you upload the &quot;original&quot; picture file or a Word document with the picture file in it.
I could download, work on them, and report back to you on what I've done with your baby.  --[[User:SV Resolution|SV Resolution]] 16:23, 23 August 2005 (UTC)

Thanks for responding to my message.  I appreciate your invitation to re-use your image. I thought the original version -- in the format you had when you were editing it, before you saved it as a PNG -- would be better than the png, because it might have more bits.  If I start working from a copy, I could just degrade the image.  Thanks if you can enlighten me. --[[User:SV Resolution|SV Resolution]] 00:52, 29 August 2005 (UTC)

== Commons ==
If possible, add your those of your images that have no english-spesific labels to wikimedia commons. I've already added anode image there, and used it in finnish-language wikipedia article. [http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Image:Electrolysis_anode.png]

== image copyright ==


== Copyright problem with [[:Image:Electrolysis anode.png]] ==
{{mbox|type=warning|msg=
Thanks for uploading [[:Image:Electrolysis anode.png]]. The [[w:Wikimedia Foundation|Wikimedia Foundation]] is very careful about what Wikibooks includes because of [[w:United States copyright law|copyright law]], and requires that we maintain a strict [[Wikibooks:Copyright|copyright policy]]. [[:Image:Electrolysis anode.png]] and other files you uploaded may soon be deleted unless we can determine the copyright holder and status. The copyright holder is usually the creator, the creator's employer, or the last person who was transferred ownership rights. Please take the time to read [[Wikibooks:Media]] to learn more about what copyright information is required to satisfy our requirements and remember to include this important information for every file that you upload in the future as well. If you have any questions, feel free to contact me, or ask another Wikibookian at the [[Wikibooks:Study help desk|help desk]].

See {{UserImages}} for a complete list of your uploads which may get deleted soon.&lt;br/&gt;Thank you. {{{2|}}}}}
 --[[User:Derbeth|Derbeth]] 09:26, 6 October 2005 (UTC)

== Duplicate account ==

What do you this should be done with your second account? I think it's ok to block it infinitely to avoid possibility that someone could break its password and uses as sockpuppet. --[[User:Derbeth|Derbeth]] [[User talk:Derbeth|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]] 19:25, 25 April 2006 (UTC)
A block on that account will trip the autoblocker when I log in with this one. I'm not sure blocking it is really necessary at all. If somone could break its password then they could probably break the paaword on this account too, and this one has admin privaledges! [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 20:09, 25 April 2006 (UTC)

== Question ==

Hi THeresa! I just registered today, and I have a question about articles on Wikibooks. Are there cases here where blank pages are accepted? I saw [[European History/Chapter 14]] was created today and saw that [[European History/Chapter 13]] is in a similar vein. Just wondered because Chapter 13 seems to be several years old. [[User:Sjakkalle|Sjakkalle]] 11:30, 26 April 2006 (UTC)
:I can't for the life of me see why someone needs to create a totally blank page. Books are different from encylopedias because they need to be structured. So obviosly chapter 13 should come before chapter 14 in the contents page, but once there is a link there I can't see a reason to actually create the page blank. I'll leave it a little while as the book is clearly being worked on (if not that chapter) and see what happens. [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 11:36, 26 April 2006 (UTC)

== Process Control Wikibook ==

You left a note on the &quot;Ellastic Collisions&quot; page of the Process Control Wikibook. I am currently merging that old book into the new [[Control Systems]] book. I am copying the text verbatim from this page into the [[Talk:Control Systems|Discussion page]]. You mentioned that you had some issues with the text of the page, so let me know if this material is worth salvaging and moving to a better location, or if we should just delete it and start fresh. --[[User:Whiteknight|Whiteknight]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Whiteknight|talk]]) ([[Control Systems|current]])&lt;/small&gt; 20:21, 26 April 2006 (UTC)

:Can you provide a link because I can't find the original page or my comments.  [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 20:38, 26 April 2006 (UTC)

::The current contents of the page are listed on the talk page of the control systems book [[Talk:Control Systems|here.]] The contents of the talk page are still available at [[Talk:Elastic_Collisions|Their original location]], but I will soon move the talk information over, and delete the old talk page as well. --[[User:Whiteknight|Whiteknight]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Whiteknight|talk]]) ([[Control Systems|current]])&lt;/small&gt; 21:22, 27 April 2006 (UTC)

== School Project ==

I'm probably going to be a TA next semester, and I was toying with the idea of offering my students extra credit for making (class-related) contributions to wikibooks. I saw your school project, and would very much like to know how well it is working out for your students, how easy it is to teach wikiformatting to people who may be completely unfamiliar with text markup etc. I think it's very admirable for you to be getting young people involved, not only in the learning process, but also in the teaching process as well. Kudos to you! --[[User:Whiteknight|Whiteknight]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Whiteknight|talk]]) ([[Control Systems|current]])&lt;/small&gt; 19:14, 4 May 2006 (UTC)

:Well they seem to be enjoying it! I haven't actually taught much formatting at all; some of the brighter ones are picking it up for themselves. It's very easy after all, and the nice thing about a wiki is that someone else can always fix the formatting later.

:You need to think carefully about safety. My pupils are all quite young, so I gave them a very stern talking to about how they are allowed to behave online, and i vetted their usernames etc. You also need to think about staff pupil relationships. If the pupils are teenagers I recommend that you create a seperate account for yourself for use in the project and keep you main account secret from them. 

:Thanks for your kind words, but children love to show off what they know. When the term ends I'm going to print up the pages and bind them together into a little booklet and give them a copy each to take home. [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 05:17, 5 May 2006 (UTC)

::Good suggestions, all. Thanks, and good luck with your project. --[[User:Whiteknight|Whiteknight]]&lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Whiteknight|talk]])([[User:Whiteknight/Proposed Books|projects]])&lt;/small&gt; 16:01, 5 May 2006 (UTC)

== Naming convention ==

Please inform your students to obey our naming conventions. They mess up a little creating pages like &quot;simple switch&quot; (I have just deleted one thinking it is a vandalism). It's very simple, you just need to write &lt;tt&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[/pagename/]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; or &lt;tt&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[/Pagename|pagename]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; instead of &lt;tt&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[pagename]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;. --[[User:Derbeth|Derbeth]] [[User talk:Derbeth|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]] 08:57, 11 May 2006 (UTC)


Yep I will, but they are young :-( What is easy for us is hopelessly complicated for a kid. [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 12:07, 11 May 2006 (UTC)

== Great! ==

So happy to have a contributor! The standards you suggest are right on the money. &quot;key stage three&quot; as you call it is exactly the same age group I was aiming for. As for science currently learned, It vairies from school to school but generally they will have had basic environmental science, weather, some geology, basic electricity, etc... In the USA, public school texts do not focus enough on laboratory experimentation as a form of learning. Because of this, i would like the book to have a large basis in experimentation, lab work and procedure, and careful observation as methods of learning material covered in the book, but also as preparation for high school science (ages 14-18) where this sort of analysis is required.  I look forward to working with you! please feel free to edit any part of the book that you find a way to improve! Thanks for the offer! For more info about my ideas for the book, you can see the [[Introduction_to_Physical_Science/Editing_Guide|guide]]. [[User:Basejumper123|Basejumper123]] 20:42, 12 May 2006 (UTC)

==Standards==
I found this guide to Massachussetts Science education standards at the state department website [[Image:Mass_Science_standards_06.pdf|here]]

== Newbie friend ==

I have retired from my work at wikipedia. I have been told that wikibooks has a more pleasant atmosphere than en.wikipedia so I thought I would give it a chance. I know that you are a long-term wikibookian so I thought I would tell you I set up an account so you can watch out for newbie screw-ups, and maybe time permitting over any guidance or advice. Thanks. -[[User:JCarriker|JCarriker]] 08:30, 6 June 2006 (UTC)

== Your images ==

Here's [http://tools.wikimedia.de/~daniel/WikiSense/UntaggedImages.php?wikifam=.wikibooks.org&amp;wikilang=en&amp;order=img_user_text&amp;max=500&amp;img_user_text=Theresa+knott&amp;grouped= the list] of images you uploaded that are untagged. --[[User:SBJohnny|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;'''SB_Johnny'''&lt;/font&gt;]] | &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:SBJohnny|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 09:09, 4 November 2006 (UTC)

:Sorry for my delay in responding to you. You seem to have properly tagged all your images now, but I gladly would have done it for you if you had asked. We didn't mean to alarm you! See you around. --[[User:Whiteknight|Whiteknight]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Whiteknight|talk]]) ([[User:Whiteknight/Proposed Books|projects]])&lt;/small&gt; 13:57, 6 November 2006 (UTC)

== Acetone peroxide synthesis ==

I have proposed the acetone peroxide synthesis for deletion. What do you think? [[User:Ewen|Ewen]] 14:18, 13 November 2006 (UTC)

==Image copyright problem with [[:Image:Magnetic field of a current carrying wire.png]]==
 
Thanks for uploading [[:Image:Magnetic field of a current carrying wire.png]]. However, the image may soon be deleted unless we can determine the copyright holder and copyright status. The [[w:Wikimedia Foundation|Wikimedia Foundation]] is very careful about the images included in Wikibooks because of [[w:Copyright|copyright law]] (see Wikibooks' [[Wikibooks:Copyright|Copyright policy]]).

The copyright holder is usually the creator, the creator's employer, or the last person who was transferred ownership rights. Copyright information on images is signified using copyright templates. The three basic license types on Wikibooks are [[w:open content|open content]], [[w:public domain|public domain]], and [[w:fair use|fair use]]. Find the appropriate template in [[Wikibooks:Image copyright tags]] and place it on the image page like this: &lt;code&gt;{&amp;#123;TemplateName}}&lt;/code&gt;.

Please signify the copyright information on any other images you have uploaded or will upload. Remember that images without this important information or giving false information can be deleted by an administrator. If you have any questions, feel free to contact me, or ask them at the [[Wikibooks:Study help desk|Study help desk]]. Thank you. [[User:Az1568|Az1568]]&lt;sup&gt; ([[User talk:Az1568|Talk]])&lt;/sup&gt; 07:41, 6 January 2007 (UTC)

== Your De-Adminship ==

Hello. I would like to inform you that you will have your sysop rights removed here on '''7 Feb 2008''' due to inactivity. If you would like to discuss the matter, please see [[WB:RFA]]. You can re-apply for adminship at a later date if you wish. Thanks. -[[User:Withinfocus|&lt;font color=&quot;#000000&quot;&gt;'''within'''&lt;/font&gt;]][[User talk:Withinfocus|&lt;font color=&quot;#7A7A7A&quot;&gt;'''focus'''&lt;/font&gt;]] 23:10, 7 January 2008 (UTC)


== [[:Image:Electric bell.png]] is missing [[WB:ICT|license]] or source information==
{{mbox|type=warning|msg=
'''Thanks for uploading [[:Image:Electric bell.png]].''' The [[w:Wikimedia Foundation|Wikimedia Foundation]] is very careful about what Wikibooks includes because of [[w:United States copyright law|copyright law]], and requires that we maintain a strict [[Wikibooks:Copyright|copyright policy]]. [[:Image:Electric bell.png]] and other files you uploaded may soon be deleted because there is missing license or source information.

The copyright holder is usually the creator, the creator's employer, or the last person who was transferred ownership rights. Please take the time to read [[Wikibooks:Media]] to learn more about what copyright information is required to satisfy our requirements and remember to include this important information for every file that you upload in the future as well. Please edit image descriptions pages directly to add a [[WB:ICT|license template]] and source; there's no need to upload the image again. If you have any questions, feel free to contact me, or [[WB:HELP|ask another Wikibookian]].

See {{UserImages}} for a complete list of your uploads which may get deleted soon.&lt;br/&gt;Thank you. &amp;nbsp;'''&amp;ndash;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Mike.lifeguard|&lt;font color=&quot;Indigo&quot;&gt;Mike.lifeguard&lt;/font&gt;]]'''&amp;nbsp;&amp;#124;&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Mike.lifeguard|&lt;font color=&quot;Indigo&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 20:35, 10 May 2008 (UTC)}}

== bsrboy ==

I didn't &quot;add&quot; the Swastika the next day. It was always there. It's been The Vandal Warrior's page for ages and no one mentioned it to me. When that user removed he didn't put a good enough reason for removing it, so I put it back and explained me reason, then he put it back still without any discussion, so I reverted it, then he blocked my user page and still didn't discuss it. Then I asked him why he did via email... No email reply and guess what? I got my email blocked! Great... I really was going to do as you said, but none of this would have happened, if he talked about it with me or maybe if you did... or if anyone did, rather than just getting blocked. It seems unfair to be blocked from email someone when all I did was ask him why he reverted it?! And still no reply! What's going on with Wikipedia. What happened to the politeness and respect I had for administrators? [[Special:Contributions/86.29.128.62|86.29.128.62]] ([[User talk:86.29.128.62|talk]]) 16:56, 14 May 2008 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>naq5fcurvz9k8oubh3xpv3ca1xtv1ef</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>GCSE Science/Uses of static electricity</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>886</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2700481</id>
      <parentid>2700475</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-09-15T14:33:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/46.60.252.83|46.60.252.83]] ([[User talk:46.60.252.83|talk]]) to last version by Jianhui67</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[GCSE Science/Electricity]]
----
There are several practical uses of   static electricity. We will look at two of them on this page. There are many more, but these are probably the easiest to understand.

==The Photocopier==
One example of the practical use of static electricity is a photocopier. A photocopier is a complicated piece of equipment, but the basic principle of how it works is fairly simple. The best way to understand what is going on is to consider it as a stage by stage process.

{|
|-
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; | [[Image:Stages of how a photocopier works.png]]
|-
| Stage 1 || Stage 2 || Stage 3 || Stage 4
|}

===Stage one===
Positive charge is sprayed onto a plate from a high voltage power supply which is called charging by friction. The plate is connected to the earth but the charge does not have quite enough energy to flow away from it. (The plate is not a good conductor of electricity.)

===Stage two ===
Paper is placed over the plate and a light is shone onto the paper. Where the paper is white the light is reflected onto the plate. Where the paper is dark a shadow falls onto the plate. The light falling on the plate gives it just the extra energy needed to allow the  charge to escape to earth. The plate becomes neutral where the paper is white but keeps its charge where the paper is black. The plate is now a copy of the paper with charges taking the place of ink. You could call this a template.

===Stage three ===
Toner particles are sprayed through a negatively charged nozzle onto the plate. As the toner passes through the nozzle it picks up the charge so that each particle of toner becomes negatively charged. The now charged toner is attracted to the areas of positive charge because '''unlike charges attract'''. More light then allows the positive charge to escape (However the negative charge on the toner remains.)

===Stage four ===
A piece of paper is given a very strong positive charge, and then placed in contact with the plate. The paper attracts the toner. The paper is then removed from the plate and passed through a heating unit. The heat melts the toner and bonds it to the paper. 

In a real photocopier, there is no plate, just a large drum. As the drum rotates its surface goes through stages one through four.  At the end of the sequence a scraper removes any toner left on the drum and the whole process is repeated with a new image. A good photocopier is capable of producing 20 duplicate pages per minute (20ppm), which is approximately one page every three seconds.

===Questions on Photocopiers ===
'''Q1)''' If the black areas of the image leave a positive charge on the plate what charge do the white areas of the image leave? (''Be very careful, the answer may not be what you think!'')

'''Q2)''' How does the light shining onto the charged plate allow it to lose its charge?

'''Q3)''' Why is the toner given a negative charge?

'''Q4)''' Why does the paper attract the toner?

{| bgcolor=&quot;ffeeaa&quot;
|-
|
'''Summary'''
*A photocopier uses a static electricity image to attract ink
*Unlike charges attract, the image and the ink are oppositely charged
*Unlike charges attracting is also used when spray painting cars
|}

==Other uses of static electricity==

===Spray painting  car parts===
When paint is sprayed from a paint gun, the painter normally needs to use a fair amount of skill to ensure the paint goes on evenly. By connecting the spray nozzle to a negative electrode, it is possible to charge each droplet of paint. If the car part is then given the opposite charge, the paint droplets will be attracted to the car body part. This has several advantages:
*Less mess - The paint goes to the charged body part and not to the electrically neutral floor.
*Less wastage - All the paint ends up on the body part, very little is wasted.
*Less skill needed - Because the charge is over the entire car part, the paint will stick to it.
*Neater job - The paint is distributed evenly across the surface

===Questions===
'''Q1)''' If the paint droplets are given a positive charge, what charge should the car part be given?

'''A1)''' A negative charge as the positive will always be looking for a negative to balance it out. 

'''Q2)''' Why does less paint fall on the floor? Give reasons for your answer

'''Q3)''' In the application of painting cars, wouldn't negatively charging the spray source and positively charging the object being sprayed also attract dust, dirt and, trash too?

===Pollution Control===
Static electricity is used in pollution control by applying a static charge to dirt particles in the air and then collecting those charged particles on a plate or collector of the opposite electrical charge. Such devices are often called electrostatic precipitators.


Factories use static electricity to reduce pollution coming from their smokestacks. They give the smoke an electric charge. When it passes by electrodes of the opposite charge, most of the smoke particles cling to the electrodes. This keeps the pollution from going out into the atmosphere.

----
[[GCSE Science/Uses of Static electricity answers|Answers]] | [[GCSE Science/Static Electricity|&lt;&lt;Static Electricity]] | [[GCSE Science/Advanced static electricity topics| Advanced topics&gt;&gt;]]

[[Category:GCSE Science]]</text>
      <sha1>f30wh82jbe5k8xjhf4wrbmpemf7cycp</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Stages of how a photocopier works.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>887</id>
    <revision>
      <id>636418</id>
      <parentid>153022</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-11-04T10:59:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Theresa knott</username>
        <id>93</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">A step by step drawing by Theresa Knott

{{GFDL}}
{{Cc-by-sa-2.5}}</text>
      <sha1>3nyq7c1hgfios1jbit1yyrw5impc2hs</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Discrete Mathematics/Graph theory</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>889</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2715781</id>
      <parentid>2711479</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-21T01:13:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>130.156.1.78</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Special Graphs */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">A ''graph'' is a mathematical way of representing the concept of a &quot;network&quot;.

== Introduction ==
A network has points, connected by lines. In a graph, we have special names for these. We call these points ''vertices'' (sometimes also called nodes), and the lines, ''edges''.

Here is an example graph. The edges are red, the vertices, black.

[[File:Discrete Mathematics Example Graph.png]]

In the graph, &lt;math&gt;v_1, v_2, v_3, v_4&lt;/math&gt; are vertices, and &lt;math&gt;e_1, e_2, e_3, e_4, e_5&lt;/math&gt; are edges.

== Definitions of graph==
There are several roughly equivalent definitions of a '''graph'''.  Most commonly, a graph &lt;math&gt;G&lt;/math&gt; is defined as an ordered pair &lt;math&gt;G=(V,E)&lt;/math&gt;, where &lt;math&gt;V=\{v_1,\ldots,v_n\}&lt;/math&gt; is called the graph's '''vertex-set''' and &lt;math&gt;E=\{e_1,\ldots,e_m\}\subset\{\{x,y\}|x,y\in V\}&lt;/math&gt; is called the graph's '''edge-set'''.  Given a graph &lt;math&gt;G&lt;/math&gt;, we often denote the vertex—set by &lt;math&gt;V(G)&lt;/math&gt; and the edge—set by &lt;math&gt;E(G)&lt;/math&gt;.  To visualize a graph as described above, we draw &lt;math&gt;n&lt;/math&gt; dots corresponding to vertices &lt;math&gt;v_1,\ldots, v_n&lt;/math&gt;.  Then, for all &lt;math&gt;i,j\in\{1,\ldots,n\}&lt;/math&gt; we draw a line between the dots corresponding to vertices &lt;math&gt;v_i, v_j&lt;/math&gt; if and only if there exists an edge &lt;math&gt;\{v_i,v_j\}\in E&lt;/math&gt;.  Note that the placement of the dots is generally unimportant; many different pictures can represent the same graph.

Alternately, using the graph above as a guide, we can define a graph as an ordered triple &lt;math&gt;G=(V,E,f)&lt;/math&gt;:
* a set of vertices, commonly called V
* a set of edges, commonly called E
* a relation &lt;math&gt;f: E \rightarrow \{\{x,y\}|x,y\in V\}&lt;/math&gt; that maps to each edge a set of ''endpoints'', known as the ''edge-endpoint relation''.  We say an edge &lt;math&gt;e\in E&lt;/math&gt; is '''incident''' to a vertex &lt;math&gt;v\in V&lt;/math&gt; iff &lt;math&gt;v\in f(e)&lt;/math&gt;.

In the above example, 
* V={v&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;, v&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, v&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;, v&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;}
* E={e&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;, e&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, e&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;, e&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;, e&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;}
* f such that e&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; maps to {v&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;, v&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;}, e&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; maps to {v&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;, v&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;}, e&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; maps to {v&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;, v&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;}, e&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; maps to {v&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, v&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;}, and e&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt; maps to {v&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;, v&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;}.

If &lt;math&gt;f&lt;/math&gt; is not injective — that is, if &lt;math&gt;\exists e,e'\in E&lt;/math&gt; such that &lt;math&gt;e\neq e', f(e) = f(e')&lt;/math&gt; — then we say that &lt;math&gt;G&lt;/math&gt; is a '''multigraph''' and we call any such edges &lt;math&gt;e,e'\in E&lt;/math&gt; ''multiple edges''.  Further, we call edges &lt;math&gt;e \in E&lt;/math&gt; such that &lt;math&gt;|f(e)|=1&lt;/math&gt; '''loops'''.  Graphs without multiple edges or loops are known as '''simple graphs'''.

Graphs can, conceivably, be infinite as well, and thus we place no bounds on the sets V and E. We will not look at infinite graphs here.

=== Directions, Weights, and Flows ===

We define a '''directed graph''' as a graph such that &lt;math&gt;f&lt;/math&gt; maps into the set of ordered pairs &lt;math&gt;\{(x,y)|x,y\in V\}&lt;/math&gt; rather than into the family of two-element sets &lt;math&gt;\{\{x,y\}|x,y\in V\}&lt;/math&gt;.  We can think of an edge &lt;math&gt;e\in E&lt;/math&gt; such that &lt;math&gt;f(e)=(x,y)&lt;/math&gt; as 'pointing' from &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt; to &lt;math&gt;y&lt;/math&gt;.  As such we would say that &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt; is the ''tail'' of edge &lt;math&gt;e&lt;/math&gt; and that &lt;math&gt;y&lt;/math&gt; is the ''head''.  This is one of the vagaries of graph theory notation, though.  We could just as easily think of &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt; as the head and &lt;math&gt;y&lt;/math&gt; as the tail.  To represent a directed graph, we can draw a picture as described and shown above, but place arrows on every edge corresponding to its direction.

In general, a '''weight''' on a graph &lt;math&gt;G&lt;/math&gt; is some function &lt;math&gt;c: E(G)\rightarrow \mathbb R&lt;/math&gt;.

A '''flow''' &lt;math&gt;(G,c)&lt;/math&gt; is a directed graph &lt;math&gt;G=(V,E,f)&lt;/math&gt; paired with a weight function such that the weight &quot;going into&quot; any vertex is the same amount as the weight &quot;going out&quot; of that vertex.  To make this more formal, define sets
*&lt;math&gt;f^+(v)=\{e\in E(G)|f(e)=(v,x), x\in V(G)\},\; \forall v\in V(G)&lt;/math&gt;
*&lt;math&gt;f^-(v)=\{e\in E(G)|f(e)=(x,v), x\in V(G)\},\; \forall v\in V(G)&lt;/math&gt;
Then, formally stated, our requirement on the weight function is
&lt;math&gt;\sum_{e\in f^+(v)} c(e)=\sum_{e\in f^-(v)} c(e),\; \forall v\in V(G).&lt;/math&gt;

=== Special Graphs ===
[[Image:Completegraphon6vertices.png|thumb|The complete graph on 6 vertices]] 
Some graphs occur frequently enough in graph theory that they deserve special mention.  One such graphs is the ''complete graph'' on n vertices, often denoted by K&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;.  This graph consists of n vertices, with each vertex connected to every other vertex, and every pair of vertices joined by exactly one edge.  Another such graph is the ''cycle graph'' on ''n'' vertices, for ''n'' at least 3.  This graph is denoted C&lt;sub&gt;''n''&lt;/sub&gt; and defined by V := {1,2,..,n} and E := {{1,2},{2,3}, ..., {n-1,n},{n,1}}.  Even easier is the ''null graph'' on ''n'' vertices, denoted N&lt;sub&gt;''n''&lt;/sub&gt;; it has ''n'' vertices and no edges!  Note that N&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; = K&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; and C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; = K&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;.

=== Some Terms ===
Two vertices are said to be ''adjacent'' if there is an edge joining them. The word ''incident'' has two meanings:

* An edge ''e'' is said to be incident to a vertex ''v'' if ''v'' is an endpoint of ''e''.
* Two edges are also incident to each other if both are incident to the same vertex.

Two graphs ''G'' and ''H'' are said to be ''isomorphic'' if there is a one-to-one  function from (or, if you prefer, one-to-one correspondence between) the vertex set of ''G'' to the vertex set of ''H'' such that two vertices in ''G'' are adjacent if and only if their images in ''H'' are adjacent. (Technically, the multiplicity of the edges must also be preserved, but our definition suffices for simple graphs.) 

=== Subgraphs ===
[[File:Subgraph.svg|thumb|Generated Subgraphs]]
A ''subgraph'' is a concept akin to the subset. A subgraph has a subset of the vertex set V, a subset of the edge set E, and each edge's endpoints in the larger graph has the same edges in the subgraph. A 

A subgraph &lt;math&gt;H&lt;/math&gt; of &lt;math&gt;G&lt;/math&gt; is ''generated'' by the vertices {&lt;math&gt;a, b, c,...&lt;/math&gt;}&lt;math&gt;\in H&lt;/math&gt; if the edge set of &lt;math&gt;H&lt;/math&gt; consists of all edges in the edge set of &lt;math&gt;G&lt;/math&gt; that joins the vertices in &lt;math&gt;H=&lt;/math&gt;{&lt;math&gt;a, b, c, ...&lt;/math&gt;}.

A ''path'' is a sequence of edges &lt;math&gt;&lt;e_1,...,e_N&gt;&lt;/math&gt; such that e&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; is adjacent to e&lt;sub&gt;i+1&lt;/sub&gt; for all i from 1 to N-1. Two vertices are said to be connected if there is a path connecting them. 

&lt;!-- clean this up A connected component of a graph is a maximal subgraph generated by vertices which are all mutually connected. A cycle is a path with the same initial and final vertex. A connected cycleless graph is called a tree. A maximal subgraph of a connected graph which is a tree is called a spanning tree. A planar graph is a graph representable by points on a plane as vertices and nonintersecting continuous curves as edges. --&gt;

== Trees and Bipartite Graphs ==

A ''tree'' is a graph that is (i) connected, and (ii) has no cycles.
Equivalently, a tree is a connected graph with
exactly &lt;math&gt;n-1&lt;/math&gt; edges, where there are &lt;math&gt;n&lt;/math&gt; nodes in the tree.

A ''Bipartite graph'' is a graph whose nodes can be partitioned into two disjoint
sets U and W such that every edge in the graph is incident to one node in U and one
node in W. A tree is a bipartite graph.

A ''complete bipartite graph'' is a bipartite graph in which each node in U is connected to every node in W;
a complete bipartite graph in which U has &lt;math&gt;n&lt;/math&gt; vertices and V has &lt;math&gt;m&lt;/math&gt; vertices
is denoted &lt;math&gt;K_{n,m}&lt;/math&gt;.

Adjacent,Incident,End Vertices

Self loops,Parallel edges,Degree of Vertex

Pendant Vertex : Vertex Degree one &quot;Pendant Vertex&quot;
Isolated Vertex : Vertex Degree zero &quot;Isolated Vertex&quot;

== Hamiltonian and Eulerian Paths ==
Hamiltonian Cycles:
A Hamiltonian Cycle received its name from Sir William Hamilton who first studied the travelling salesman problem. A Hamiltonian cycle is a path that visits every vertex once and only once i.e. it is a walk, in which no edge is repeated (a trail) and therefore a trail in which no vertex is repeated (a path). Note also it is a cycle, the last vertex is joined to the first.

A graph is said to be Eulerian if it is possible to traverse each edge once and only once, i.e. it has no odd vertices or it has an even number of odd vertices (semi-Eulerian). This has implications for the Königsberg problem. It may be easier to imagine this as if it is possible to trace the edges of a graph with a pencil without lifting the pencil off the paper or going over any lines.

== Planar Graphs ==

A ''planar graph'' is an undirected graph that can be 
drawn on the plane or on a sphere in such
a way that no two edges cross, 
where an edge &lt;math&gt;e = (u,v)&lt;/math&gt; is drawn as a continuous curve 
(it need not be a straight line) from u to v.

Kuratowski proved a remarkable fact about planar graphs:  A graph is
planar if and only if it does not contain a subgraph homeomorphic to 
&lt;math&gt;K_5&lt;/math&gt; or to &lt;math&gt;K_{3,3}&lt;/math&gt;.
(Two graphs are said to be homeomorphic if we can shrink some components of each
into single nodes and end up with identical graphs.  Informally, this means that
non-planar-ness is caused by only two things—namely, having the structure of
&lt;math&gt;K_5&lt;/math&gt; or &lt;math&gt;K_{3,3}&lt;/math&gt; within the graph).

=== Coloring Graphs ===
A graph is said to be planner if it can be drawn on a plane in such way that no edges cross one anather except of course of vertices

Each term, the Schedules Office in some university must assign a time slot for each final exam. This is not easy, because some students are taking several classes with finals, and a student can take only one test during a particular time slot. The Schedules Office wants to avoid all conflicts, but to make the exam period as short as possible.

We can recast this scheduling problem as a question about coloring the vertices of a graph. Create a vertex for each course with a final exam. Put an edge between two vertices if some student is taking both courses. For example, the scheduling graph might look like this:
Next, identify each time slot with a color. For example, Monday morning is red, Monday
afternoon is blue, Tuesday morning is green, etc.

Assigning an exam to a time slot is now equivalent to coloring the corresponding vertex.
The main constraint is that adjacent vertices must get different colors; otherwise, some student has two exams at the same time. Furthermore, in order to keep the exam period short, we should try to color all the vertices using as few different colors as possible.
For our example graph, three colors suffice:
red, green, blue.

The coloring corresponds to giving one final on Monday morning (red), two Monday afternoon (blue), and two Tuesday morning (green)...

=== K Coloring ===

Many other resource allocation problems boil down to coloring some graph. In general, a graph G is kcolorable if each vertex can be assigned one of k colors so that adjacent vertices
get different colors. The smallest sufficient number of colors is called the chromatic number of G. The chromatic number of a graph is generally difficult to compute, but the following theorem provides an upper bound:

Theorem 1. A graph with maximum degree at most k is (k + 1)colorable.
----

Proof. We use induction on the number of vertices in the graph, which we denote by n. Let P(n) be the proposition that an nvertex
graph with maximum degree at most k is (k + 1)colorable.
A 1 vertex graph has maximum degree 0 and is 1colorable,
so P(1) is true.

Now assume that P(n) is true, and let G be an (n + 1)vertex
graph with maximum degree at most k. Remove a vertex v, leaving an nvertex
graph G . The maximum degree of G is at most k, and so G is (k + 1)colorable
by our assumption P(n). Now add back vertex v. We can assign v a color different from all adjacent vertices, since v has degree at most k and k + 1 colors are available. Therefore, G is (k + 1)colorable.
The theorem follows by induction.

== Weighted Graphs ==
A '''weighted graph'''  associates a  label (weight) with every edge in the graph. Weights are usually real numbers, and often represent a &quot;cost&quot; associated with the edge, either in terms of the entity that is being modeled, or an optimization problem that is being solved. 

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>d5j52x0j3s464an37hqu2q803dqzfho</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Boatconformation.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>891</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748856</id>
      <parentid>746293</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-02-09T19:55:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>lftdbfdb9bftwmpa42ewbdhqaw7jksr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Computer Programming/Linux Programming</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>898</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2681114</id>
      <parentid>1798025</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-07-14T11:03:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==About the platform==

The '''GNU''' operating system was started by Richard Stallman as a free replacement for the UNIX operating system. At the same time Linus Torvalds was working on a kernel, which he adapted to fit the GNU operating system. As time progressed, many applications from UNIX and DOS were ported to GNU/Linux as well as the thousands of new applications written for it.  GNU/Linux has become a completely self-sufficient operating system with applications ranging from the many console applications to the numerous highly advanced GUI applications (many of which are based on lower level console applications) and everything else in between.

The most popular languages for use on the GNU/Linux platform include [[C Programming|C]]/[[C++ Programming|C++]] and [[Programming:Java|Java]], however the range of programming languages supported by the GNU/Linux platform cover the entire spectrum of the software development world. Other popular languages are [[Perl|Perl]], [[Python Programming|Python]] and [[Ruby Programming|Ruby]]. Shell scripting is often used for administrative tasks but cannot be called a complete high level language.

==Basic information==

Most UNIX code is instantly portable to GNU/Linux systems - it can be compiled as on a UNIX system.  GNU/Linux programming tools are mostly from the GNU project at http://www.gnu.org, including gcc (free C/C++ compiler), and equivalents of make, ld, as, etc.  Numerous others are available for various languages, including java. 


== Further reading ==


* [http://www.dwheeler.com/secure-programs/ &quot;Secure Programming for Linux and Unix HOWTO -- Creating Secure Software&quot;] by David A. Wheeler 2003

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>f458xhbgl0h80qsrc5tlacak9pfkz3a</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Spanish/Exercises/Stem Changing Verbs</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>899</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2702624</id>
      <parentid>2702622</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-09-22T17:41:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>69.196.73.194</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Fill in the blank */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Spanish/Lesson 4| ^Lesson 4^]]
----
&lt;!---Do not fill in the blanks!  This is supposed to be an exercise for the reader.  It should be printed out and filled in, or pasted into a text editor. --&gt;
=== Fill in the blank ===
&lt;!---Do not fill in the blanks!  This is supposed to be an exercise for the reader.  It should be printed out and filled in, or pasted into a text editor. --&gt;
Don't fill in the blank with the wrong form of the verb: 

&lt;!---Do not fill in the blanks!  This is supposed to be an exercise for the reader.  It should be printed out and filled in, or pasted into a text editor. --&gt;
1. Yo _____cierro_______________ (cerrar) la puerta. ''I close the door.''

&lt;!---Do not fill in the blanks!  This is supposed to be an exercise for the reader.  It should be printed out and filled in, or pasted into a text editor. --&gt;
2. Tú ___________pierdas____________ (perder) tus llaves. ''You lost your keys.''

&lt;!---Do not fill in the blanks!  This is supposed to be an exercise for the reader.  It should be printed out and filled in, or pasted into a text editor. --&gt;
3. ¿____________prefieres_____________(preferir) usted la langosta? ''Do you prefer lobster?''

4. Nosotros __________entiendemos_____________ (entender) los ejercicios. ''We understand the exercises.''

5. Felipe y Juan ___________empiezan___________(empezar) las prácticas de gramática. ''Felipe and Juan begin the grammar practices.''

6. Ellos _________quieran___________ (querer) almorzar. ''They want to eat us.''

7. La chica _________pierde____________ (perder) su pañuelo. ''The girl loses her ______.''

8. ¿Qué _____________piensa_________ (pensar)? ''What do you -singular- think?''

9. Sofía ___________entienda____________ (entender) a Julio. ''Sofía understands Julio.'' 

10. Yo no ___________quiero___________ (querer) la ensalada. ''I don't want the salad''
----
'''Bonus:''' Argentinian voseo

2. Vos ___________pierdan__________ (perder) tus llaves. ''You lose your keys.''

8. ¿Qué ___________piensas___________ (pensar)? ''What do you -singular- think?''
----
[[Spanish/Exercises/Stem Changing Verbs - Solutions|Soluciones a los ejercicios]] ''Solutions to the exercises''

[[Spanish/Lesson 4| ^Lesson 4^]]

[[Category:Spanish]]</text>
      <sha1>4o9qixg3vrkv6jtddchmczpb1f5g8h0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Mic</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>900</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1748985</id>
      <parentid>196124</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-04-01T20:19:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>can't redirect between wikis</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[w:en:User:Mic]]</text>
      <sha1>sav5c50ud8tkhqgt871i78ivnrbhzmn</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Biochemistry metabolism 1.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>901</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2366334</id>
      <parentid>882030</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-19T22:17:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Replacing links, replaced: {{CC-self}} → {{self|cc-by-sa-2.5}} using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Metabolism overview (PNG format)

This image is based on [[media:Biochemistry_metabolism_1.svg|this SVG file]]

{{self|cc-by-sa-2.5}}
{{GFDL-self}}</text>
      <sha1>1vnrdy81znv6nbtzcke2azf1ygz52wo</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Biochemistry/Metabolism and energy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>902</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2704580</id>
      <parentid>2444535</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-09-27T14:24:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>202.67.41.51</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Hydrogen bonds */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Biochemistry]] 

[[Biochemistry/Catalysis|&lt;&lt; Catalysis]] | [[Biochemistry/pKa values|pKa values &gt;&gt;]]
----
== Metabolism ==
=== Anabolism and catabolism ===
Metabolism (Fig. 1) is, broadly speaking, the conversion of food into energy, cell components, and waste products.

[[image:biochemistry_metabolism_1.png]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 1''': Overview of metabolism

The above diagram shows the different parts of metabolism:
* ''energy source'', which is, after all, the sun, whose energy is harvested through photosynthesis
* ''catabolism'', the breakdown of food into chemical energy, which is needed in
* ''anabolism'', the construction of complex cell molecules from small environmental molecules, utilizing chemical energy
Catabolic reactions release energy and are therefore &lt;tt&gt;exergonic&lt;/tt&gt;, while anabolic reactions use up energy and are therefore &lt;tt&gt;endergonic&lt;/tt&gt;.

=== High-energy phosphates ===
Due to the large variety of food compounds, and the large number of biochemical reactions which need energy in anabolism, it would be quite inefficient to couple a specific anabolic reaction to a specific energy source in catabolism. Instead, the cell uses an intermediate compound, a kind of universal energy currency. This intermediate is called ''high-energy phosphate''.

But when is a phosphate group called &quot;high-energy&quot;, and how does it differ from a &quot;low-energy&quot; phosphate? A giveaway is the &amp;Delta;G&lt;sup&gt;0'&lt;/sup&gt; of hydrolysis. Hydrolysis separates a phosphate from a compound by adding water:
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; O &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; O
 R-OP-OH + H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O &amp;#8652; R-OH + HO-P-OH
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; O &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; O

The &amp;Delta;G&lt;sup&gt;0'&lt;/sup&gt; of a low-energy (or &quot;inorganic&quot;) phosphate group (called P&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;) is 9-20 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, while the &amp;Delta;G&lt;sup&gt;0'&lt;/sup&gt; of a high-energy phosphate (denoted &amp;#9413;) is ~30 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;.

=== pKa value ===
Now what makes this &amp;#9413; so special? To explain this, we must take a little excourse into pH and pKa values. A phosphate group has between zero and three &lt;tt&gt;OH&lt;/tt&gt; groups. This allows &amp;#9413; to exist in up to four different forms (0, 1, 2, and 3 &lt;tt&gt;OH&lt;/tt&gt; groups, Fig. 2), depending on the pH value of the surrounding solution. A pKa value gives us the pH value at which 50% of the molecules are in one form (e.g., 1 &lt;tt&gt;OH&lt;/tt&gt; group) and another (e.g., 2 &lt;tt&gt;OH&lt;/tt&gt; groups). This is expressed by the ''Henderson-Hasselbalch equation'' :

:&lt;math&gt;{pH} = {pK}_{a} + log{[base] \over [acid]}&lt;/math&gt;

[[image:biochemistry_metabolism_2.png]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 2''': The four possible forms of a phosphate group. pK&lt;sub&gt;a2&lt;/sub&gt; represents the conditions in the cell.

Now to the promised difference between &amp;#9413; and PP&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;. The breaking of the ester bond of an RO&amp;#9413; releases more energy than the breaking of a PP&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; bond (Fig. 3), because of
# ''electrostatic repulsion'' between the two phosphate groups in PP&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;
# ''resonance stabilization'' of two P&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; groups, compared to PP&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; (Fig. 4)

[[image:biochemistry_metabolism_3.png]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 3''': Hydrolysis of &amp;#9413; and PP&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;.

[[image:biochemistry_metabolism_4.png]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 4''': Resonance stabilization of P&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;.

Resonance stabilization means that both &lt;tt&gt;OH&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt&gt;=O&lt;/tt&gt; can &quot;travel&quot; around the phosphate. Of course, this is a crude analogy; they do not really move, the electrons are just &quot;smeared&quot; around the phosphate atom. This is also indicated by the use of the &amp;#8596; arrow, instead of &amp;#8652;; the three forms &lt;u&gt;do not exist&lt;/u&gt;, they are just a way of writing down the chemical reality.

As you can see in Fig. 3, the &amp;Delta;G&lt;sup&gt;0'&lt;/sup&gt; value for PP&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;#8652;2P&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; is &amp;#8810;0, shifting the reaction strongly in favor of the 2P&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;.

== Molecules using high-energy phosphates ==

=== Anhydride between phosphoric acid and carboxyl group ===
Hydrolysis : &amp;Delta;G&lt;sup&gt;0'&lt;/sup&gt; = -49.3 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br&gt;
[[image:biochemistry_metabolism_5a.png]]

=== Guanidine phosphate ===
Hydrolysis : &amp;Delta;G&lt;sup&gt;0'&lt;/sup&gt; = -43.0 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br&gt;
[[image:biochemistry_metabolism_5b.png]]

=== Enol phosphate ===
For example, this picture is wrong, the carbon has 5 bonds to it after it tautomerizes, which is impossible and a rookie organic chemistry error. please fix phosphoenolpyruvate&lt;br&gt;
Hydrolysis : &amp;Delta;G&lt;sup&gt;0'&lt;/sup&gt; = -61.9 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br&gt;
[[image:biochemistry_metabolism_5c.png]]

=== ATP ===
Adenosine triphosphate contains one low-energy and two high-energy phosphate bonds:&lt;br&gt;
[[image:biochemistry_metabolism_5d.png]]&lt;br&gt;
Low energy : &amp;Delta;G&lt;sup&gt;0'&lt;/sup&gt; = -14,2 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br&gt;
High energy : &amp;Delta;G&lt;sup&gt;0'&lt;/sup&gt; = -30.5 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br&gt;

*ATP is regenerated from ADP (adenosine diphosphate), P&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; and energy (from food); H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O is released in the process.
*ATP is the short-term energy &quot;currency&quot; of the cell.
*ATP concentration in the cell is low (ATP: 2-8mM; ADP:0,2-0,8mM). ATP is generated in high &quot;turn over&quot;.
*ATP performs its chemical work through ''coupled reactions''.
*Coupled reactions are always &amp;#9413; ''transfers'', never direct hydrolysis

Basically, any ATP-driven reaction is reversible, building ATP from ADP and P&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; in the process. However, some ATP-driven reactions should never be reversed; these include nucleotide and protein synthesis. If these were reversed, the organism would disassemble its own DNA and proteins for energy, a rather unfortunate strategy. For reactions that should never be reversed, ATP can be broken down into AMP (adenosine monophosphate) and PP&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;, which in turn becomes 2&amp;times;P&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;. This reaction has a &amp;Delta;G&lt;sup&gt;0'&lt;/sup&gt; of -65,7 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, which is totally irreversible under ''in vivo'' conditions.

It should be noted that AMP can not directly be converted to ATP again. Instead, the enzyme ''AMP kinase'' forms two ADP molecules from one ATP and one AMP. The resulting ADPs are then treated as described above.

== Non-covalent bonds ==
The destruction of covalent bonds takes up huge amounts of energy. The breakdown of an O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; molecule into two oxygen atoms needs ~460 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. Thus, nowhere in &quot;living&quot; biochemistry are covalent bonds actually destroyed; if one is broken, another one is created. This is where non-covalent bonds come in, they are weak enough to be broken down easily, and to form &quot;bonds&quot; again.  For this reason, many biochemical functions are using so-called weak/secondary/non-covalent bonds.

Weak bonds are created and destroyed much more easily than covalent ones. The typical range of energy needed to destroy such a weak bond is 4-30 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. Thus, the formation of weak bonds is energetically favorable, but these bonds are also easily broken by kinetic (thermal) energy (the normal movement of molecules). Biochemical interactions are often temporary (e.g., a substrate has to leave an enzyme quickly after being processed), for which the weakness of these bonds is essential. Also, biochemical specificity (e.g., enzyme-substrate-recognition) is achieved through weak bonds, utilizing two of their major properties:
* Since individual weak bonds are, well, weak, several of them have to occur in a specific pattern at the same time in roughly the same place.
* The short range of weak bonds.

The link that follows demonstrates the type of non-covalent forces: [http://www.pearsonhighered.com/mathews/ch02/fi2p2.htm]
There are three basic types of weak bonds, and a fourth &quot;pseudo-bond&quot;:


=== Ionic bonds ===
Ionic bonds are electrostatic attractions between permanently charged groups. Ionic bonds are not directed. Example:
:X-CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup&gt;.....&lt;/sup&gt; H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;N-Y
::~ 20 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;

=== Hydrogen bonds ===
Hydrogen bonds are also established by electrostatic attraction. These attractions do not occur between permanently charged groups, but rather between atoms temporarily charged by a ''dipole moment'', resulting from the different [[electronegativity]] of atoms within a group. Hydrogen bonds are even weaker than ionic bonds, and they are highly directional, usually along a straight line. Besides being weaker than ionic bonds, hydrogen bonds are also weaker, and longer than similar covalent bonds.
Hydrogen bonds are unique because they only exist when the Hydrogen is bonded to an oxygen (O), Nitrogen (N), or Fluorine (F), but the most common hydrogen bonds in biochemistry are:
:X-OH &lt;sup&gt;.....&lt;/sup&gt; O-Y
:X-OH &lt;sup&gt;.....&lt;/sup&gt; N-Y
:X-NH &lt;sup&gt;.....&lt;/sup&gt; O-Y
:X-NH &lt;sup&gt;.....&lt;/sup&gt; N-Y
Hydrogen bonds equal an energy between 12-29 kJ mol, whereas covalent bonds are much higher. For example, the covalent bond between oxygen and hydrogen is about 492 KJ mol-1&lt;/sup&gt;.

==''Hydrogen Bonds and Water''==
Water has unique properties, after all, it is chosen to be the universal solvent. The unique properties of water are due to hydrogen bonding between all the oxygens and hydrogens of the content. The hydrogen bonds occurring in water are about 2 angstroms apart from each other. Although hydrogen bonding is only about 5% as strong as covalent bond, they still cause water to have a high boiling point, and a high surface tension. The following link will take you to the structure of water and its Hydrogen Bonding: [[http://users.rcn.com/jkimball.ma.ultranet/BiologyPages/H/Hbonds_water.gif]]

=== Van der Waals attractions ===
{{subject|{{subject|Biochemistry/Metabolism_and_energy}}{{subject|#REDIRECT [[Biochemistry/Metabolism_and_energy]]#REDIRECT [[#REDIRECT [[Insert text]]#REDIRECT [[--[[Special:Contributions/218.19.141.18|218.19.141.18]] ([[User talk:218.19.141.18|talk]]) 07:14, 19 April 2009 (UTC)Insert text&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;math&gt;Insert non-formatted text here&lt;/math&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;]]]]}}}}
Van der Waals attractions are established between electron density-induced dipoles. They form when the outer electron shells of two atoms ''almost'' (but not quite) touch. The distance of the atoms is very important for these weak interactions. If the atoms are too far apart, the interactions are too weak to establish; if the atoms are too close to each other, their electron shells will repel each other. Van der Waals attractions are highly unspecific; they can occur between virtually any two atoms. Their energy is between 4-8 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;.
[[File:&lt;nowiki&gt;Example.jpg&lt;/nowiki&gt;{{subject|&lt;s&gt;Biochemistry/Metabolism_and_energy&lt;/s&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;Subscript text&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;}}]]

=== Hydrophobic forces ===
Hydrophobic forces are not actually bonds, so this list has four items, but still just three bond types. In a way hydrophobic forces are the negation of the hydrogen bonds of a polar solute, usually water, enclosing a nonpolar molecule. For a polar solute like water, it is energetically unfavorable to &quot;waste&quot; a possible hydrogen bond by exposing it towards a nonpolar molecule. Thus, water will arrange itself around any nonpolar molecule in such a way that no hydrogen bonds point towards that molecule. This results in a higher order, compared to &quot;freely&quot; moving water, which leads to a lower entropy level and is thus energetically unfavorable. If there is more than one nonpolar molecule in the solute, it is favorable for the nonpolar molecules to aggregate in one place, reducing their surrounding, ordered &quot;shell&quot; of water to a minimal surface. Also, in large molecules, such as proteins, the hydrophobic (nonpolar) parts of the molecule will tend to turn towards the inside, while the polar parts will tend to turn towards the surface of the molecule.

=== References===
Cooke, Rosa-lee. ''Properties of Water''. Lecture 10. Mountain Empire Community College. n.d. Web. http://water.me.vccs.edu/courses/env211/lesson10_print.htm

Kimball, John W.. ''Hydrogen Bonds''. Kimball’s Biology Pages. Feb. 12, 2011. Web. http://users.rcn.com/jkimball.ma.ultranet/BiologyPages/H/Hbonds_water.gif

Lower, Stephen. ''States of matter: Water and hydrogen bonding''. General Chemistry Virtual Textbooks. 2009. Aug. 26, 2010. Web. 
http://www.chem1.com/acad/webtext/states/water.html

n.p. ''Covalent vs. Non-Covalent Bonds''. n.d. http://www.pearsonhighered.com/mathews/ch02/c02cv.htm

W. W. Norton &amp; Company. ''Hydrogen Bonding in Water''. Web. 2012.  http://www.wwnorton.com/college/chemistry/gilbert2/tutorials/chapter_10/water_h_bond/

WyzAnt Tutoring. ''WyzAnt Tutoring''. Bonds. 2012. Web. http://www.wyzant.com/Help/Science/Chemistry/Bonds/
----
[[Biochemistry/Catalysis|&lt;&lt; Catalysis]] | [[Biochemistry/pKa values|pKa values &gt;&gt;]]

[[Biochemistry]]
[[Category:Biochemistry]]</text>
      <sha1>ry3ukrf625lodqtyy8iq0gz4mb6entj</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Biochemistry metabolism 2.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>904</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2366335</id>
      <parentid>882031</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-19T22:17:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Replacing links, replaced: {{CC-self}} → {{self|cc-by-sa-2.5}} using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Figure 2: The four possible forms of a phosphate group

This image is based on [[media:Biochemistry_metabolism_2.svg|this SVG file]]

{{self|cc-by-sa-2.5}}
{{GFDL-self}}</text>
      <sha1>pdtqi4g44ofn1xz6qllenjz253izjbm</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Biochemistry metabolism 3.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>905</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2366336</id>
      <parentid>882033</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-19T22:17:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Replacing links, replaced: {{CC-self}} → {{self|cc-by-sa-2.5}} using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Figure 3: Hydrolysis of Ⓟ and PP&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;

This image is based on [[media:Biochemistry_metabolism_2.svg|this SVG file]]

{{self|cc-by-sa-2.5}}
{{GFDL-self}}</text>
      <sha1>tjg7xeebbrmf9niembhqesk8ozkoc17</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Biochemistry metabolism 4.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>906</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2366337</id>
      <parentid>882034</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-19T22:17:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Replacing links, replaced: {{CC-self}} → {{self|cc-by-sa-2.5}} using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Figure 4: Resonance stabilization of P&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;

This image is based on [[media:Biochemistry_metabolism_2.svg|this SVG file]]

{{self|cc-by-sa-2.5}}
{{GFDL-self}}</text>
      <sha1>pwirpg8midviojm9ct32key39px3glz</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:81.249.66.2</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>908</id>
    <revision>
      <id>153043</id>
      <timestamp>2003-08-30T23:10:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Maveric149</username>
        <id>7</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[FrWikipedia:mathématiques]] is pretty neat. Is that new? It would make more sense if fr: could be reserved for magic intra-project links instead of always pointing to different Wikipedia versions. This would solve some very important technical problems for non-Wikipedia projects. A shorthand would be nice though; FrWP: would work. --[[User:Maveric149|mav]]</text>
      <sha1>5w9ggbwdn2rdychgzmtjscbo5c0cxr7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Calculus/Limits/An Introduction to Limits</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>909</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2070206</id>
      <parentid>1875739</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-03-16T13:15:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Greenbreen</username>
        <id>436161</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Answered question</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Requests==
While it's asked how | lim [x -&gt; 0]{sin(x)/x} = 1 | can be proven, this isn't demonstrated - there also isn't an actual demonstration elsewhere online, nearly as I can determine. Shouldn't one be put in? --[[User:68.212.77.222|68.212.77.222]] 23:05, 26 Apr 2005 (UTC)

Is there anyone interested in writing [[en:How to evaluate the limit of a real-valued funtion ]]?  --wshun

I think we should put the formal definition of the limit right at the end of page. As it is the most difficult concept to full grasp. And we need some excercises.

The last example seems to imply that f(x) = (x^2 - 9)/(x - 3) is not the same as g(x) = x + 3.  Why is this true?

Because you can't divide by zero; g(3) = 3 + 3 = 6, whereas f(3) = (3^2-9)/(3-3) = (0/0) = undefined.  The functions will, however, be equal at all other points.  (yes I edited your question to make my answer easier to articulate.  :) ) 

BTW, I would consider completely deleting the introduction.  It makes some questionable statements, and I can't see it as being anything but confusion for someone who doesn't know anything about limits already.  --Xhad


Am I the only one that thinks that this whole thing is worthless without the Cauchy definition of a limit? You cannot proove any of the statements unless you define limits properly. The best way to define them is the Cauchy definition!!

==arbitrary break==
(x^2-9)/(x-3) has the problem of a loss of information as x approaches 3.  The solution to this is rearranging the problem so that you are no longer dealing with having a small number on the denominator.  This is the realm of computational mathematics, though, and I'm not sure if it's useful to put in a Calculus textbook.  --Ronald Raygun

To me that sounds like something that would be appropriate for a Calc primer for physicists, but it seems beyond the scope of a typical Calculus course. --Xhad

It would be neat if someone would implement a parser that would feed this latex math notation to a graphing program... easy visualisation on the click of a function. -- [[User:Kowey|Kowey]] 09:03, 4 Oct 2004 (UTC)


Can any-one tell me that if we are taking x-&gt;0  and f(x)-&gt;L//then why are puting there an = in the answer when it should be ~(approximate value) --221.135.232.166 10:19, 27 June 2007

To answer the above question, it is because of the definition of a limit.  Although we think of &lt;math&gt; \lim_{x \to c} f(x)&lt;/math&gt; intuitively by the process of taking values of &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt; closer and closer to &lt;math&gt;a&lt;/math&gt;, the limit is not formally related to the value of &lt;math&gt;f(x)&lt;/math&gt; at &lt;math&gt;x=a&lt;/math&gt;, which may not even be defined.  For instance, consider the function defined as follows:

&lt;math&gt;
f(x) =\left\{\begin{matrix} 0 &amp; \mbox{if }  x\neq 1 \\
\mbox{27} &amp; \mbox{if } x=1\end{matrix}\right.
&lt;/math&gt;

By the definition of limit, &lt;math&gt; \lim_{x \to 1} f(x)=0&lt;/math&gt;, which is a really bad approximation of &lt;math&gt;f(x)&lt;/math&gt; at &lt;math&gt;x=1&lt;/math&gt;. [[User:Greenbreen|Greenbreen]] ([[User talk:Greenbreen|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Greenbreen|contribs]]) 13:15, 16 March 2011 (UTC)

==Possible inclusions for this page==
- limits at infinity (horizontal asymptotes) - Infinite limits (e.g. vertical asymptotes) -  Left/right handed limits - thinking of limits of indeterminant forms  (those that can be evaluated without Lhopitals rule)  - proofs of limit rules/one side limit theorem

Maybe this page needs to be broken up.  Continuity is a whole topic, and the formal definition/proofs of limit rules could also be pulled to its own page.  -- julius

==dutch==

Hey there, I'm making a dutch version of this book/chapter. I think I may have solved some presentational problems so if you like check out http://nl.wikibooks.org/wiki/Analyse:Limieten. Robert Zboray

==LEDE==
The section named [http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Calculus/Limits#Finding_limits Finding Limits] starts as follows: ''Now we will concentrate on finding limits, rather than proving them. In the proofs above, we started off with the value of the limit. How did we find it to even begin our proofs?'' I find this confusing. There are no '''proofs''' ''above'' that I can see, only examples. And in those examples we did actually find the value of the limit. (I realize that this error is probably a rest from a previous re-dispositional edit..) Or am I missing something? In that case I apologize. /Hugo --[[User:83.181.53.162|83.181.53.162]] 20:31, 5 November 2006 (UTC)

== &lt;s&gt;You CAN divide by zero&lt;/s&gt; ==

EVERYONE LISTEN TO THIS. I'M TIRED THAT EVERYONE KEEPS TELLING THAT YOU CAN'T DIVIDE BY ZERO.
Of course you can; it's a limit.

lim x/y = a. When y approaches zero, a = infinity.

:Technically, you can divide by ''y'' in the limit as ''y'' approaches zero. You cannot divide by zero without the use of such a limit. Remember that:
::&lt;math&gt;\lim_{y \to 0} y \ne 0&lt;/math&gt;
:The limit never allows ''y'' to actually take the value of zero, only to approach that value by infinitessimal amounts. As such, ''y'' never equals zero, but instead equals a value infinitessimally close to zero. The two quantities, while close, are not strictly the same. --[[User:Whiteknight|Whiteknight]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Whiteknight|talk]]) ([[User:Whiteknight/Proposed Books|projects]])&lt;/small&gt; 20:33, 9 January 2007 (UTC)

Whoa! I'm going to have to set this straight.  You can't divide by zero, neither algebraically nor analytically.  In algebra, the defining quality of the additive identity, zero, is that it has no multiplicative inverse (unless the set is trivially {0}).

PROOF:
:Assume that zero has an multiplicative inverse, and let 0 * a = 1.
:b*a + 1 = b*a + 0*a = (b + 0)*a = b*a   (assumption, distributive prop., def. of additive identity)    
:which means that 1 = 0, which is a contradiction whenever the set is not {0}.
Let's look at it analytically now.  Remember, a limit has to be well-defined to exist.  If it takes on different values depending on the way you approach the limit, then the limit doesn't exist.
Back to your example:
:lim(y-&gt;0) x/y.  Without loss of generality, let x &gt; 0 (if x = 0, then the limit is 0, and if x &lt; 0, we can multiply it by -1)
:lim(y-&gt;0 from the left-negative side) x/y &lt; 0 and lim(y-&gt;0 from the right-positive side) x/y &gt; 0
:Therefore the limit is not well-defined.  It doesn't exist.
Now, you could try to patch it by definition, but no matter what you'll be left with some &quot;infinity&quot; which isn't accounted for.  Also, negative infinity is not equal to positive infinity... that's easy enough to see.

Lastly, to the point: &lt;math&gt;\lim_{y \to 0} y = 0&lt;/math&gt;.  If one uses the formal definition this is obvious.  There is no actual &quot;approaching&quot; - that's just a simple way to think about it.  &quot;The two quantities, while close, are not strictly the same&quot; - They are only different in that they have different names.  (Sketch: Let the infinitesimal x (&gt;0) be a number different from 0, so that x/2 is not 0.  Then |y - 0| &lt; x/2. Obviously y cannot be x, for x &lt;= |x| = |x - 0| &lt; x/2 is a contradiction.) The infinitesimal is a nice tool for investigating functions of limits, but technically it's not a number in the sense you're trying to use it.
[[User:Mo Anabre|Mo Anabre]] 06:43, 1 May 2007 (UTC)

:I did simplify too much in my explanation, i should have taken the time to explain it properly. --[[User:Whiteknight|Whiteknight]] ([[User talk:Whiteknight|talk]]) 17:37, 1 May 2007 (UTC)

Hello! Intuitively, zero is a special symbol (like &lt;math&gt;\infty&lt;/math&gt;), that denotes empty expression. But if there is abscence of anything, what are you trying to compare with divident? Of course, division by zero can be defined artificialy, but AFAIK all such definitions lead to contradictions with other axioms.
[[User:Exanode|Exanode]] 15:16, 7 November 2007 (UTC)

There are two limit of each function (though sometimes both give the same result), one from the positive side and one from the negative side, so actually you can take the limit of x/y as y approaches 0. This is also a mistake in the text, which says that the limit of 1/(x-2) as x approaches 2 is undefined. The limit of this function from the negative side is negative infinity and the limit from the positive side is positive infinity.

==TO: authors.==

Please put some visualizations in the text. It's best to describe things like limits with graphics and give viewers an intuitive visual analogy.

I've seen some very interesting eLearning math courses with lots of graphical analogies. It made the concept of functions limit (among other things) easily understandable. Unfortunately the said courses are copyrighted and closed source.

:That's a great suggestion! If you have images or visualizations that you would like to donate, or if you know where we can find free or open-source images that we can use, that would be great. Unfortunately, creating lots of images takes time, and we are all just volunteers here. If you would like to join our project and help out, it would be appreciated. --[[User:Whiteknight|Whiteknight]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Whiteknight|talk]]) ([[User:Whiteknight/Proposed Books|projects]])&lt;/small&gt; 21:24, 10 January 2007 (UTC)

:: Do you mean adding images to (for example) the Sqrtx216.gif function? There's a link to an image link there - I can't decide whether it is a old link that's been deleted or a request for a new link. [[User:DavidMcKenzie|DavidMcKenzie]] 15:40, 6 February 2007 (UTC)

Shouldn't we start with the values approaching a particular value? That makes it a lot easier to understand.

==Conversation==
For what it matters, after learning a little more about formal continuity, density isn't even required.  For instance, every function on the integers is continuous (since as a subspace of R, they have the discrete topology). Also, something interesting for anyone reading the person down there below Eric119: the integers are complete.  [[User:Mo Anabre|Mo Anabre]] 20:59, 1 November 2007 (UTC)

I changed it back.  The density of the rationals in the reals is quite enough to justify a concept of continuity of f.
[[User:Mo Anabre|Mo Anabre]] 17:48, 1 May 2007 (UTC)

I don't understand why this is wrong. If the domain of f is only the rationals, then, according to our definition of limits (which seems to have vanished from the article), no matter what delta we have there will exist irrational x such that 0 &lt; |x - c| &lt; delta and thus f(x) is not defined and therefore the condition |f(x) - L| &lt; epsilon cannot be true. (And then there is no limit and therefore a discontinuity.) If there is a problem in all this, please let me know. [[User:Eric119|Eric119]] 01:28, 6 Sep 2004 (UTC)

this is just wrong! The real number line is complete, meaning there are no holes. However, if we say ''f''&amp;nbsp;(''x'')&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;2 and restrict the domain of ''f'' to rational numbers, there will be holes at the places corresponding to irrational numbers. There are irrational numbers between any two rational numbers, so all the rational numbers on which ''f'' is defined are isolated from each other. But, there are rational numbers between any two irrational numbers, so each hole must be at a single point. There are infinite irrational numbers over any interval, so there are an infinite number of infinitely small holes between any two points on the graph. The places where ''f'' is defined are also infinite and infinitely small. The function ''f'' has no limits defined anywhere, despite that any graph would look like a simple line.

== application to calculus out of context ==

The &quot;application to calculus&quot; section references an example and several figures that don't exist. I presume that the section was copied over from some other source, and either the context and figures were neglected, or they were deemed a copyright violation and deleted (but the &quot;application to calculus&quot; section remained). Please rewrite this section so that it no longer references material that doesn't exist on wikibooks! Thanks! [[User:Luvcraft|Luvcraft]] 17:26, 2 July 2007 (UTC)

----
== application to calculus out of context another note== 
I think - that limit itself has no too much &quot;independent&quot; uses... Actually - it is instrument for establishment of strict differentiation theory... So - I would just abandon this item... Good illustration of use of limit concept could be concept of tangent line , or &quot;moment velocity&quot; vector... But - they are once more - from field of physics and geometry, and not - pure calculus...
--[[User:Psimonovsk|Simonovsky Pavel]] 18:29, 10 October 2007 (UTC)

== As x -&gt;0  sin (1/x) -&gt;0 ==

Sin (1/x) has no limit as x approaches 0.  I have sources.  The chapter must be changed. [[User:Zginder|Zginder]] 13:43, 12 September 2007 (UTC)

Zginder, did you even read the section?  I'm putting it back and fixing the _one_ error you didn't like. In the future please try to fix typos before deleting whole sections because of them. [[User:Mo Anabre|Mo Anabre]] 20:53, 1 November 2007 (UTC)

== Problem with 'Limit rules' ==
Why are all the limit rules listed with no proofs? Shouldn't the be proven before they are given? [[User:142.151.186.71|142.151.186.71]] 04:38, 9 October 2007 (UTC)
: Agreed. Maybe the proofs can be put in an appendix with a working link from the 'Limit Rules' section or at the very end of the module. --[[User:Hamsterpoop|Hamsterpoop]] 05:21, 29 October 2007 (UTC)
:: If it get some time here I'll try to come up with some of them, shouldn't bee too hard. [[User:142.151.186.71|142.151.186.71]] 20:41, 3 November 2007 (UTC)

== Began Edit ==
I started editing the beginning of the page, trying to start the discussion of a limit in a way that I (modestly) felt was more engaging, and tried to integrate it with the rest of the text.  I hope to come back and try to do more work.

Thanks.

[[Special:Contributions/128.208.76.146|128.208.76.146]] ([[User talk:128.208.76.146|talk]])
== Formal Definition of a Limit ==
Was the formal definition of a limit completely removed, or moved somewhere else? If the former, why? [[User:RSiferd|RSiferd]] ([[User talk:RSiferd|talk]]) 05:11, 21 May 2008 (UTC)
:It appears later in this &quot;chapter&quot; [[Calculus/Formal Definition of the Limit]]. And again, almost identically, at [[Calculus/Formal limits]]. --[[User:Mrwojo|Mrwojo]] ([[User talk:Mrwojo|talk]]) 19:22, 28 December 2008 (UTC)
:I've merged them at [[Calculus/Formal Definition of the Limit]]. --[[User:Mrwojo|Mrwojo]] ([[User talk:Mrwojo|talk]]) 05:54, 13 January 2009 (UTC)

== Video? ==
Does wikibooks have embedvideo extension installed?  {{#ev:googlevideo|-2777717103359291179}}

It does not appear to.  Should it?  Or some other video extension?  Can we request this?

[http://video.google.com/videoplay?docid=-2777717103359291179 Introduction to Limits Lecture]

~[[User:serundeputy|serundeputy]]

== Infinite oscillation is redundant ==

The section on infinite oscillation is very redundant.  Maybe it could be shortened?
[[Special:Contributions/173.74.178.117|173.74.178.117]] ([[User talk:173.74.178.117|talk]]) 01:29, 7 July 2010 (UTC)

:Thanks for the comment.  There are not many people working on the book right now, so it could be a few years before someone acts on this comment.  But you can feel free to be bold and remove any parts that you don't like.  Don't worry, people quickly look over things that change because of the whole &quot;watchlist&quot; setup, so even if your just learning calculus yourself or an old pro you can still be an equally valid contributor.  You can do so with or without an account, but I usually recommend having one, so you can configure your preferences. [[User:Thenub314|Thenub314]] ([[User talk:Thenub314|talk]]) 16:00, 7 July 2010 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>ayq1t82tt8w6s9yurn9vxlj29tsqyrg</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:RoseParks</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>910</id>
    <revision>
      <id>153045</id>
      <parentid>2335</parentid>
      <timestamp>2003-09-03T02:39:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>RoseParks</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">Hi! It seems we meet again, after the Nupedia experience (though I remember seeing you on wikipedia occasionally?). Thanks for the fixes in thermodynamics. Most of these were typos and not my bad English, rest assured :-)

Do not fear to run out of work, I plan to write lots more on the biochemistry front! --[[User:Magnus Manske|Magnus Manske]]

Good to be in contact, again. You are either in a big hurry or your English is slipping...and I am sure I know which ;-) --[[User:RoseParks|RoseParks]]</text>
      <sha1>siltj8vna7wwbaael0xyzrlyqvroydq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Wikibooks talk:Neutral point of view</title>
    <ns>5</ns>
    <id>911</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1945622</id>
      <parentid>1945378</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-10-10T13:08:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Darklama</username>
        <id>7662</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* POV in textbooks */ 2 cents</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">I think the NOV policy needs some discussion for wikibooks project.  

We may agree that wikibooks should not a place to produce a book that asserts some specific position or view, though I am not completely sure.

Should we say, for example, there should not be a book about environmental conservation (or gun control or birth control) that asserts that conservation is important? (The more NPOV way of referring to that is &quot;many (including, A, B) think that conservation is important because of ..., though there are some criticisms, most notably by C that ....&quot; 

In case of encyclopedia, there is a solution - we can sometimes split an article into many articles, and explain different points of views in length. 

If we were to implement this kind of solution, we might want to develop multiple &quot;modules&quot; or components of books along with multiple table of contents (each of which take different sets of modules to create a book from one particular POV). 

Feel free to copy this to mailing list or elsewhere. [[User:Tomos|Tomos]] 22:54, 31 Aug 2003 (UTC)
:I agree that NPOV will have to apply differently here than Wikipedia.  Since the project is still nascent, the best bet is to just go with it and, hopefully, a consensus will develop over time -- since most of our regulars are likely also Wikipedians, I think this will be a relatively easy process.  The conservation textbook you mentioned is a good example; it would be silly to interrupt every point with an explanation of why not everyone believes it.  The same would apply to descriptions of evolution, the Big Bang, etc.  We can assume a particular POV on the part of the reader in these cases, and should probably include an introduction or preface that explains why we are ignoring the fact that not everyone believes the same way on these issues. [[User:TUF-KAT|TUF-KAT]] 18:00, 12 Oct 2004 (UTC)

My opinion is that NPOV is not really at home here. Textbooks and other learning materials at times are written, and NEED to be written, from a &quot;non-neutral&quot; point of view. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]] 21:51, 12 Oct 2004 (UTC)

:I'm pretty new here, but I strongly belive that NPOV is not appropriate for Wikibooks. I think that there is, perhaps, some questionable sort of &quot;objectivity&quot; that something like an Encyclopedia can strive for, but I do not think this the case with a book. Limiting ourselves to books that meet an-NPOV standard would limit ourselves to books that sound an aweful lot like encyclopedias. Wikibooks seems to be about something beyond that.

:''Furthermore'', since Wikibooks is trying to create textbooks or books that could be used for learning, in a project like Wikiversity, etc., I think it is important to recognize that &quot;objective&quot; truth is a POV that tends to privilege the status-quo. Like the above example, if you are writing a book on environmental conservation, I believe it would not only be &quot;silly&quot; to strive for NPOV, I believe it would be counter-productive. As a history student, I believe that every narrative has an implicit subjectivity, (or POV). Any narrative that is constructed, for instance history, anthropology, sociology, etc., comes from a point of view and has political implications. The notion of &quot;objectivity&quot; and &quot;objective truth&quot; for instance in Anthroplogy, has been used to blind people from the significance of privileged white male anthropologists observing other cultures. (And Anthropology, with its claim to &quot;objective truth,&quot; has played a vital role in the construction of scientific racism.)

:I'm sorry if I'm trailing off here... I just feel strongly that recognizing subjectivity as opposed to hiding from it is a more fruitful approach to something such as Wikibooks. [[User:Fokion|Fokion]] 23:36, 11 September 2006 (UTC)

----

If there is a '''need''' to have something written from an non-NPOV, then that need should (will?) be clearly noted in the text itself.  The real question of NPOV is what does 'neutral' really mean?  That should be clearly defined in the policy.  My initial idea is that if something exists to be talked about factually, there is something in empirical reality that can be cited, and ought to be cited.  Conclusions and opinions based on that empirical concepts should be built logically.  ''If'' there are any countering opinions (or ''significant'' counter theories) they should be explained as if they were subject to the same rules.  --[[User:Delfeld|Neal Delfeld]] 18:24, 11 November 2005 (UTC)

:I think a problem here is that the idea of talking &quot;factually&quot; and &quot;empirical reality&quot; may work well with something like computer science or mathematics, but not so well with history or social theory. History, for instance, is not made of concrete facts, one stacking upon another. NPOV may work better with the &quot;hard&quot; sciences, but in the humanities or social sciences there is no such thing.[[User:Fokion|Fokion]] 00:16, 12 September 2006 (UTC)

== POV in textbooks ==

I think our history, geography and Chinese history textbooks are almost certainly biased. Especially history. You know, the 'the ancient Egyptians were great architects' or 'Alexander the Great was a great ruler'. For the ancient Egyptians they even gave the wrong fact because they followed Herodotus' version. But to the smaller ones. Like 'the Spartans are a warlike people'. Most people agree that, don't we? By modern standards they are pretty warlike. But is that still an opinion, an opinion to the eyes of us modern people? And one more thing: Athenians built many open-air theatres. What defines many? There could be theatres on every corner of Planet Drama. :)

By the way, I think the emoticon should be removed. It makes our policy here look much more casual. Policies and guidelines can joke, sure, WP does that all the time, but not include non-standard ways of expressing. [[User:Kayau|Kayau]] ( [[User talk:Kayau|talk]] &amp;#124; [[Special:Emailuser/Kayau|email]] &amp;#124; [[Special:Contributions/Kayau|contribs]] ) 23:56, 18 June 2010 (UTC)

:They say that history is written by the victorious.  Of particular note to your thoughts is [[m:Can history be truly NPOV?]]. &amp;ndash;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Adrignola|Adrignola]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Adrignola|talk]]&lt;/small&gt; 03:22, 10 October 2010 (UTC)

::Ha. I have to agree. Chinese history, for example, is written from a Confucian point of view. [[User:Kayau|Kayau]] ([[User talk:Kayau|talk]] &amp;#124; [[Special:Emailuser/Kayau|email]] &amp;#124; [[Special:Contributions/Kayau|contribs]]) 03:32, 10 October 2010 (UTC)
: Compared with Wikipedia our NPOV policy is much more casual. I think Wikipedia expects their articles to be written neutral from the beginning while Wikibooks accepts that neutrality is a process that takes time. Wikipedia's expectations are reflected in that its policy defines what it means for articles to be neutral and how to achieve neutrality while Wikibooks relies on the scope of each book to affect what it means to be neutral and how neutrality is achieved which is reflected by the more general and less specific approach used in Wikibooks' policy.
: If you believe the statements above that you quoted are a problem, be bold and fix them. &quot;Anthropologists like Blah and Blah considered the ancient Egyptians to be great architects&quot; or &quot;During his time people considered Alexander the Great to be a great ruler, hence the name&quot; to give two possible fixes. For the smaller ones you could even do &quot;Compared with modern standards the Spartans are a warlike people&quot; or &quot;Today the Spartans are considered warlike people.&quot; --&lt;span style=&quot;font: bold 10pt 'courier new', comic, sans, ms;&quot;&gt;[[User:Darklama|&lt;font color=&quot;midnightblue&quot;&gt;dark&lt;/font&gt;]][[User_talk:Darklama|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;lama&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 13:08, 10 October 2010 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>29h1xn5c6bhcvhi55l8cv3gz5bc997w</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Sp3.jpg</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>913</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748855</id>
      <parentid>153048</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-02-09T19:54:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>bqzg6alf693qn5egkcy4lip7de3tqdd</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:History of Food and Cooking</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>914</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2686737</id>
      <parentid>2675102</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-07-31T19:58:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Koavf</username>
        <id>16549</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Koavf moved page [[Cookbook:History of food and cooking]] to [[Cookbook:History of Food and Cooking]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Cookbook help page}}

== Historic texts ==
The origin of many modern dishes can be traced back to ancient times, but there are very few surviving texts written before 1000 AD that deal with cooking. In many cases where texts exist, the recipes and directions they provide are little more than guidelines and assume much knowledge on the part of the cook.

For example the following is a recipe taken from the Forme of Cury, a roll of cookery written around 1390 by the master cooks of King Richard II of England.

:'''Compost.'''

:Take rote of persel, of pasternak, of rafens, scrape hem and waische hem clene. Take rapes &amp; caboches, ypared and icorue. Take an erthen panne with clene water &amp; set it on the fire; cast alle þise þerinne. Whan þey buth boiled cast þerto peeres, &amp; parboile hem wel. Take alle þise thynges vp &amp; lat it kele on a faire cloth. Do þerto salt; whan it is colde, do hit in a vessel; take vyneger &amp; powdour &amp; safroun &amp; do þerto, &amp; lat alle þise thynges lye þerin al nyyt, oþer al day. Take wyne greke &amp; hony, clarified togider; take lumbarde mustard &amp; raisons coraunce, al hoole, &amp; grynde powdour of canel, powdour douce &amp; aneys hole, &amp; fenell seed. Take alle þise thynges &amp; cast togyder in a pot of erthe, &amp; take þerof whan þou wilt &amp; serue forth.

&lt;!-- Take ???, scrape them and wash them clean. Take ???. Take an earthenware pan with clean water and set it on the fire; toss in the aforementioned ingredients. When ???, throw in ??? and parboil thoroughly. Let cool on a ??? cloth. Could someone please finish this translation? --&gt;

This recipe, which is written in late Middle English, is open to interpretation as it gives no specific quantities and assumes that the reader will know how long certain things need to be cooked, soaked, etc.

You shouldn't let this deter you from reading old texts concerning cookery; indeed there is a certain degree of fun in taking an old recipe and determining how it might have been prepared.

Some books dealing with ancient cookery are:
* The Forme of Cury, 1390 - http://www.ibiblio.org/pub/docs/books/gutenberg/etext05/8cury10.txt
* More links at http://cunnan.sca.org.au/wiki/Recipe

== Origins ==

=== Americas ===
'''North America'''
* Turkey
* Cranberries, blueberries, huckleberries, strawberries
* Pumpkins, zucchini
* Black Walnuts
* Chilli Peppers, bell peppers

'''Central America'''
* Amaranth, tobacco
* Corn
* Peanuts
* Squash
* Tomatoes

'''South America'''
* Sweet Potatoes
* Chocolate, from cacao bean
* Strawberries
* Potatoes

===Europe===
* Horse
* Atanasovsko Salt
* Wieliczka Salt
* Baskunchak Salt
* Pork
* Herring
* Vinegar
* Rye
* Raspberry
* Blackcurrant
* Parsnips
'''Mediterranean'''
* Beets
* Broccoli
* Cauliflower
* Cabbage
* Kale
* Kohlrabi
* Brussels sprouts

'''Balkans'''
* Walnuts
* Olives

===Africa ===
* Yams
* Watermelon
* Coffee, originated in Ethiopia

===Middle East===
* Mustard
* Cannabis
* Oats
* Barley
* Lettuce
* Radishes
* Onions
* Leeks
* Wheat
* Carrots
* Parsley
* Cucumbers
* Vinegar
* Spinach

=== Asia ===
* Chicken
* Shiitake Mushrooms 
* Yams
* Eggplant
* [[Chinese Herbs]]
* Rice 
* Banana 
* Baelfruit
* Bilimbi 
* Breadfruit
* Chempedak 
* Coconut 
* Durian 
* Jackfruit
* Langsat 
* Lime
* Longan 
* Lychee 
* Mango
* Mangosteen
* Persimmon 
* Pomelo 
* Rambuttan 
* Rose Apple
* Sea Apple
* Starfruit
* Snakefruit

'''Siam / Thailand'''
* Galanga, Galangal, Greater Galangal 
* Thai Ginger (Krachai)
* Hot Basil, Sweet Basil, Lemony Basil 

'''Tibet'''
* Barley
* Blackcurrant, north asia

'''Korean Peninsula'''
* Barley
* Millet
* Wheat
* Legumes

=== Polynesia ===
'''Australia'''

Macadamia nuts



[[Category:Cookbook|History of food and cooking]]</text>
      <sha1>rfn6xxoii17ywq8ki7gwhvgrykpokt9</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Computer Programming/Variables</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>915</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1361557</id>
      <parentid>190208</parentid>
      <timestamp>2008-12-18T01:42:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Darklama</username>
        <id>7662</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[Talk:Computer programming/Variables]] moved to [[Talk:Computer Programming/Variables]]:&amp;#32;naming convention consistency</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">The introduction to variables may make sense for a course to &quot;Programming C&quot;
and a like. But in a more broader context it does not satisfy me. Some thoughts:

Variables may ''reference'' values rather than ''stand in for''. You can
make the variables to reference to another value later on in the program,
you can have to variables to reference the same value and you can then
manipulate these value through either variable.

The later is explained in the text, but we may abstract from &quot;memory addresses&quot; here. 

Moreover, there are programming languages where you have to declare
a variable before you can use but don't need to give it a type. I'm thinking
of Oz here. In some dynamically typed languages like ruby, procedures/functions/methods declare proc./func./method need arguments (which are
variables) declared but without a type.

: Your points make sense...why don't you edit the page?
: This 'book's in a bit of a larval state still and still needs some work [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 09:16, 1 Sep 2003 (UTC)

::textbook.wikipedia.org was just mentioned in a couple of slashdot comments (not articles! don't panic!). I doubt that there'll be lots of people arriving but there might be a few gawkers moving through.

:I tried to edit the introduction but could not figure how to get to it.
:What I was trying to add
:Dates and times can be in various formats such as USA (mm/dd/yyyy); European (dd.mm.yyyy); Japanese (yyyy.mm.dd); based on Chinese Year (not Biblical); and others.
[[User:AlMac|AlMac]] 09:25, 16 July 2005 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>3c8jhopkzcwg4jb62tosynsv3ujwyey</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cell Biology/Lysosomes</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>916</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1896791</id>
      <parentid>1442883</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-07-21T16:20:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>fixed links/category</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Cell Biology]] | [[../Parts of the cell|Parts of the cell]] |  [[../Organelles|Organelles]]

[[../Golgi apparatus|&lt;&lt; Golgi apparatus]] | Lysosomes | [[../Peroxisomes|Peroxisomes &gt;&gt;]]

----


== Lysosomes == 
Membrane-bound sacs called lysosomes contain digestive enzymes that can break down such macromolecules as proteins, nucleic acids, and polysaccharides (Figure 6-23). Lysosomes have several functions. They fuse with incoming food vacuoles and expose the nutrients to enzymes that digest them, thereby nourishing the cell. Lysosomes also function like safety officers when they help destroy harmful bacteria. In certain cells—for example, your white blood cells—lysosomes release enzymes into vacuoles that contain trapped bacteria and break down the bacterial cell walls. Similarly, lysosomes serve as recycling centers for damaged organelles. Without harming the cell, a lysosome can engulf and digest another organelle. This makes molecules available for the construction of new organelles.The structures vary in size from 0.2 to 2 micrometers in diameter. The staining reveals a crystal like matrix in spherical vesicles. The crystalloid matrix is urate oxidase. These are small organelles containing around 40 enzymes for intercellular digestion. The lysosome membrane helps to protect the enzymes as much as it helps protect the cell. This is because the optimal pH for these enzymes is around a pH of 5. The membrane of the lysosome is again a lipid bilayer and is thought to have a ATP hydrolysis to pump H+ into the lysosome to maintain the pH. This also has another affect, that is free protons. Other small molecules can pass through the lysosome membrane, but will then become charged by picking up a free proton, then they are less likely to be able to leave the lysososome. A good reference on Lysosomes is at
:http://cellbio.utmb.edu/cellbio/lysosome.htm 

----
[[../Golgi apparatus|&lt;&lt; Golgi apparatus]] | Lysosomes | [[../Peroxisomes|Peroxisomes &gt;&gt;]]

[[Cell Biology]] | [[../Parts of the cell|Parts of the cell]] [[../Organelles|Organelles]]

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>6v7e9i0dlqt87rq5hrde4h5h46ikg45</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cell Biology/Peroxisomes</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>917</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1896792</id>
      <parentid>495866</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-07-21T16:21:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>fixed links</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Cell Biology]] | [[../Parts of the cell/]] | [[../Organelles/]]

[[../Lysosomes|&lt;&lt; Lysosomes]] | Peroxisomes | [[../Cytosol|Cytosol &gt;&gt;]]

----
It used to be thought that peroxisomes are formed by the budding of smooth Endoplasmic Reticulum (ER). However, now it is thought that they form through self-assembly. (I will get more information references as I do some more thorough literature searches). The peroxisome is another major source of Oxygen utilization (along with the mitochondrion). There are specific proteins associated with the peroxisomes membrane, also there are 3 oxidation enzymes associated with peroxisomes:

# D-amino acid oxidase 
# Urate Oxidase 
# Catalase 

The enzyme contents vary with various types of cells. One of the main functions of peroxisomes in liver cells is detoxification. This is done by the oxidation of substances like:

# Alcohol - About 1/2 of the ethanol one drinks is converted to acetaldehyde by oxidation. 
# Phenols 
# Formic acid 
# Formaldehyde 

=== Why peroxisomes are not like lysosomes ===

Peroxisomes are organelles that contain oxidative enzymes, such as D-amino acid oxidase, urate oxidase, and catalase. They may resemble a lysosome, however, they are not formed in the Golgi complex. Peroxisomes are distinguished by a crystalline structure inside a sac which also contains amorphous gray material. They are self replicating, like the mitochondria. Components accumulate at a given site and they can be assembled into a peroxisome. They may look like storage granules, however, they are not formed in the same way as storage granules.

Peroxisomes function to rid the body of toxic substances like hydrogen peroxide, or other metabolites. They are a major site of oxygen utilization and are numerous in the liver where toxic byproducts are going to accumulate. 

The peroxisome is made as a phospholipid bilayer, encapsulating oxidative materials. They would be 'sphere-ish' in shape, not necessarily a perfect sphere, and sometimes, they may take other shapes. But most electron micrographs I have seen (2 dimensions) show them as circles. (As you may be aware, the Cell membrane is also a phospholipid bilayer.) Peroxisomes have membrane proteins that are critical for peroxisomal function, to import proteins into their interiors, proliferate or segregate to daughter cells (This update, thanks to Babich Temps). The main differences would be:

# Types of phospholipids used. 
#Size of the membrane (i.e. peroxisomes are MUCH smaller than the cell).

----
[[../Lysosomes|&lt;&lt; Lysosomes]] | Peroxisomes | [[../Cytosol|Cytosol &gt;&gt;]]

[[Cell Biology]] | [[../Parts of the cell/]] [[../Organelles/]]

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>rinhl521t1inpa7nxlzbsik9ncalk5z</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cell Biology/Cytosol</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>918</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1896793</id>
      <parentid>495803</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-07-21T16:22:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>fixed links/category</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Cell Biology]] | [[../Parts of the cell/]] | [[../Organelles/]]

[[../Peroxisomes|&lt;&lt; Peroxisomes]] | Cytosol | [[../Cytoskeleton and Microtubules|Cytoskeleton and Microtubules &gt;&gt;]]

----
The cytosol (as opposed to cytoplasm, which also includes the organelles) is the internal fluid of the cell, and a large part of cell metabolism occurs here. Proteins within the cytosol play an important role in signal transduction pathways, glycolysis, and act as intracellular receptors and ribosomes. In prokaryotes, all chemical reactions take place in the cytosol. In eukaryotes, the cytosol contains the cell organelles. In plants, the amount of cytosol can be reduced due to the large tonoplast (central vacuole) that takes up most of the room of the cell.

The cytosol is not a &quot;soup&quot; with free-floating particles, but highly organized on the molecular level. The cytosol also contains the cytoskeleton. It is made of fibrous proteins and (in many organisms) maintains the shape of the cell, anchors organelles, and controls internal movement of structures, e.g., transport vesicles.

As the concentration of soluble molecules increases within the cytosol, an osmotic gradient builds up toward the outside of the cell. Water is flowing into the cell, making it larger. To prevent the cell from bursting apart, molecular pumps in the plasma membrane, the cytoskeleton, the tonoplast or a cell wall (if present) are used to counteract the osmotic pressure. 

----
[[../Peroxisomes|&lt;&lt; Peroxisomes]] | Cytosol | [[../Cytoskeleton and Microtubules|Cytoskeleton and Microtubules &gt;&gt;]]

[[Cell Biology]] | [[../Parts of the cell/]] | [[../Organelles/]]

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>q2mpkefxvkpmh4ffizsr84268o5qoz1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>GCSE Science/Advanced static electricity topics</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>921</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2525352</id>
      <parentid>2525303</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-05-12T16:24:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/115.64.50.203|115.64.50.203]] ([[User talk:115.64.50.203|talk]]) to last version by 94.171.156.247</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[GCSE Science/Electricity]]
----
Before reading this module check to see if you need to. If you intend to take the foundation paper, you may find that you do not need to do the work on this page. If in doubt check with your teacher.

==Where charge concentrates==

{| align=&quot;right&quot; cellpadding=&quot;10&quot;
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | [[Image:Charged asymetric conductor.png]]
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;ccddff&quot; |  The charge spreads out on  this &lt;br/&gt;uneven conductor unevenly. The &lt;br/&gt;two electrons that are circled &lt;br/&gt;in red cannot see each other.&lt;br/&gt; The body of the conductor gets&lt;br/&gt; in the way and shields them. This&lt;br/&gt; is why the charges congregate&lt;br/&gt; around the highly curved areas.
|}
When an object is charged up with electrons, the electrons try to spread out over the object to be as far apart as possible. This means they go to the surface rather than spread throughout. On a metal object the material of which the object is made shields the electrons from one another. They do not ‘’see’’ the electrons round the back. This means that highly curved objects can hold more electrons than flat objects. For a complicated shape, the electrons tend to congregate on the more highly curved areas, and to desert the flatter areas.

==Inducing charge separation on neutral objects==

Consider a crystal of gold for example. {This argument works for all materials}. Normally the atoms are perfectly spherical, and completely neutral. 

'''Q1)''' Why are the atoms neutral?

Remember that neutral atoms contain positive charges in the nucleus and negative electrons orbiting in their shell. Normally the center of the positive charges and the center of the negative electrons is in the same place: the exact center of the atom. If we bring up a charged object to them however, something important happens. Look at the diagram on the right.


{| align=&quot;right&quot;
|-
| [[Image:Charge separation on a crystal.png]]
|}A charged rod is brought near the surface of the crystal. {Note: the rod is not shown, just the charges on it}. The electrons in the atoms try to get away from the negative charge because they are repelled. The positive charges in the nucleus try to get nearer to the negative rod because they are attracted to it. The result is the atom slightly changes shape. The center of the negative charges goes to the right of the center of the atom and the center of the positive charges goes to the left. We say there is a '''separation of charges'''

'''Q2)''' What would happen if we brought up a positively charged rod?

'''There is always an attractive force between the rod and the crystal no matter what the charge on the rod'''.

To see why this is so, we need to know one more thing about electrostatics. '''The force of repulsion or attraction falls off with distance'''. In fact, rather like gravity it falls off as the ''square'' of the distance. This means if you go to twice the distance the force becomes only a quarter as much. If you go three times the distance it becomes only one ninth as great and so on. Now look at the diagram again. The negative charges in the atoms are repelled by the rod, the positive ones are attracted, but '''the positive charges are closer''', so overall there is a force of attraction.

'''Q3)''' Repeat the above argument with a positively charged rod to convince yourself that there is still an attractive force.

==Lightning==


{| align=&quot;center&quot;
|-
| [[File:Multiple Lightning Strikes.jpg]]
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;ccddff&quot; | Time-lapse photography captures multiple cloud-to-ground&lt;br/&gt; lightning strikes during a night-time thunderstorm.
|}

Lightning is basically a great big spark. In a thunderstorm, separation of charge occurs in big rain clouds. No one is really sure of ''how'' this occurs, although it appears to be caused by ice crystals rubbing together and becoming charged. but what ''is'' known is that storm clouds have a negative bottom and a positive top. The bottom of the cloud is nearer to the ground so it induces a positive charge on the ground. When the voltage becomes high enough a spark flies between the cloud and the earth; this is lightning. The spark is so hot, it causes the air to rapidly expand then collapse; this causes thunder.

'''Q4)''' Why does the voltage need to be very high before lightning can occur?
===Lightning rods===
Lightning rods are used to protect buildings from lightning strikes. They are usually made from a length of copper rod with a pointed end. They are attached to tall buildings and the lightning strikes them rather than the building itself.

'''Q5)''' Why do you think the rods are made of copper rather than iron which is cheaper?

'''Q6)''' Why do the rods have a pointed end?

'''Q7)''' It is standard advice that if caught out in a storm you should ''never'' stand under a lone tree. Why is this advice good?                                                                       


{| bgcolor=&quot;#ffeeaa&quot;
|-
|
'''Summary'''
*Charge congregates around highly curved surfaces
*A charged object induces charge separation in nearby neutral objects. This ''always'' produces an attractive force
*Lightning is just a big spark from a cloud to the ground, thunder is the sound of the spark
*Lightning rods protect buildings by attracting the lightning strike and conducting the charge safely to ground
|}



----
[[GCSE Science/Advanced Static electricity topics answers|Answers]] | [[GCSE Science/Uses of static electricity| &lt;&lt;Uses of static electricity]] | [[GCSE Science/Electrolysis|Electrolysis&gt;&gt;]]

[[Category:GCSE Science]]</text>
      <sha1>dybojvd0zydwy81256s2qb6qknlno2c</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>