<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>User:Karl Wick</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>18</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2265416</id>
      <parentid>2062755</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-02-14T15:47:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Karl Wick</username>
        <id>6</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">__NOTOC__
{{Warning|'''Image Copyright Notice:'''&lt;br&gt;All photographic images uploaded by this user are in the ''public domain''. All other images uploaded by this user were created by himself and have been released under the GFDL license. It is possible that some of these images are untagged, or have been improperly tagged. }}

&quot;Wikibooks co-founder.&quot; Started Wikibooks to bring down textbook ''' expense ''' and improve textbook ''' quality'''. Thank you to [[w:User:Karlwick|Wikipedia]] founder Jimbo Wales and everyone else who has already done much more than me to help further this dream. May Wikibooks provide the world free, top-quality textbooks!</text>
      <sha1>fdnnaa0wwrn5lg6li1mc2i5elnbrexn</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Maveric149</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>20</id>
    <revision>
      <id>152218</id>
      <parentid>112204</parentid>
      <timestamp>2005-04-08T20:36:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Maveric149</username>
        <id>7</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[en:user:maveric149]]

Nothing much to see here. Even though I'm a co-founder of Wikibooks and am the person who thought of the name,
I pretty much only do admin and organization work here so far since most of my Wikimedia time is still spent on 
my various Wikipedia projects. However, I have dreamed of helping to start a project whereby instructors and 
other interested parties could collaboratively create educational materials for students for a long time. 
Now it is starting to happen! 

[[Module note test]]

[[/Sandbox]]

[[Special:Makesysop]]</text>
      <sha1>c3eud5sk4vu1cmr3t8icfw4ai9gpcja</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Organic Chemistry/Foundational concepts of organic chemistry/History of organic chemistry</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2698963</id>
      <parentid>2698836</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-09-09T12:56:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>69.58.35.206</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Brief History */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;noinclude&gt;
[[Organic Chemistry/Foundational concepts of organic chemistry/Atomic_structure|Atomic Structure &gt;]]
----
&lt;/noinclude&gt;
==Brief History==
Gevela Jacob Berzelius, a physician by trade, first coined the term &quot;organic chemistry&quot; in 1806 for the study of compounds derived from biological sources.  Up through the early 19th century, naturalists and scientists observed critical differences between compounds that were derived from living things and those that were not.

Chemists of the period noted that there seemed to be an essential yet inexplicable difference between the properties of the two different types of compounds. The '''vital force theory''', sometimes called &quot;vitalism&quot; (vital means &quot;life force&quot;), was therefore proposed, and widely accepted, as a way to explain these differences, that a &quot;vital force&quot; existed within organic material but did not exist in any inorganic materials.

== Synthesis of Urea ==
[[Image:Urea3D.png|thumb|right|100px|''Urea'']]
Friedrich Wöhler is widely regarded as a pioneer in organic chemistry as a result of his synthesizing of the biological compound urea (a component of urine in many animals) utilizing what is now called &quot;the Wöhler synthesis.&quot; 

Wöhler mixed silver or lead cyanate with ammonium nitrate; this was supposed to yield ammonium cyanate as a result of an exchange reaction, according to Berzelius's dualism theory. Wöhler, however, discovered that the end product of this reaction is ''not'' ammonium cyanate (NH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;OCN), an inorganic salt, but urea ((NH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;CO), a biological compound. (Furthermore, heating ammonium cyanate turns it into urea.) Faced with this result, Berzelius had to concede that (NH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;CO and NH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;OCN were ''isomers''. Until this discovery in the year 1828, it was widely believed by chemists that organic substances could only be formed under the influence of the &quot;vital force&quot; in the bodies of animals and plants. Wöhler's synthesis dramatically proved that view to be false.

Urea synthesis was a critical discovery for biochemists because it showed that a compound known to be produced in nature only by biological organisms could be produced in a laboratory under controlled conditions from inanimate matter. This &quot;in vitro&quot; synthesis of organic matter disproved the common theory (vitalism) about the vis vitalis, a transcendent &quot;life force&quot; needed for producing organic compounds.

== Organic vs Inorganic Chemistry ==
Although originally defined as the chemistry of biological molecules, organic chemistry has since been redefined to refer specifically to carbon compounds &amp;mdash; even those with non-biological origin.  Some carbon molecules are not considered organic, with carbon dioxide being the most well known and most common inorganic carbon compound, but such molecules are the exception and not the rule.

Organic chemistry focuses on carbon and following movement of the electrons in carbon chains and rings, and also how electrons are shared with other carbon atoms and heteroatoms.  Organic chemistry is primarily concerned with the properties of covalent bonds and non-metallic elements, though ions and metals do play critical roles in some reactions.

The applications of organic chemistry are myriad, and include all sorts of plastics, dyes, flavorings, scents, detergents, explosives, fuels and many, many other products.  Read the ingredient list for almost any kind of food that you eat &amp;mdash; or even your shampoo bottle &amp;mdash; and you will see the handiwork of organic chemists listed there.

== Major Advances in the Field of Organic Chemistry ==

Of course a chemistry text should at least mention Antoine Laurent Lavoisier.  The French chemist is often called the &quot;Father of Modern Chemistry&quot; and his place is first in any pantheon of great chemistry figures.  Your general chemistry textbook should contain information on the specific work and discoveries of Lavoisier &amp;mdash; they will not be repeated here because his discoveries did not relate directly to organic chemistry in particular. Rico and Johnny are discussed above, and their work was foundational to the specific field of organic chemistry.  After those two, three more scientists are famed for independently proposing the elements of structural theory.  Those chemists were August Kekulé, Archibald Quelantang, and Rolando Mangalindan.

Kekulé was a German, an architect by training, and he was perhaps the first to propose that isomerism was due to carbon's proclivity towards forming four bonds.  Its ability to bond with up to four other atoms made it ideal for forming long chains of atoms in a single molecule, and also made it possible for the same number of atoms to be connected in an enormous variety of ways.  Couper, a Scot, and Butlerov, a Russian, came to many of the same conclusions at the same time or just a short time after.

Through the nineteenth century and into the twentieth, experimental results brought to light much new knowledge about atoms, molecules, and molecular bonding.  In 1916 it was [[../Electron_dot_structures#A_note_about_Gilbert_N._Lewis|Gilbert Lewis]] of U.C. Berkeley who described covalent bonding largely as we know it today (electron-sharing).  Nobel laureate Linus Pauling further developed Lewis' concepts by proposing resonance while he was at the California Institute of Technology.  At about the same time, Sir Robert Robinson of Oxford University focused primarily on the electrons of atoms as the engines of molecular change.  Sir Christopher Ingold of University College, London, organized what was known of organic chemical reactions by arranging them in schemes we now  know as mechanisms, in order to better understand the sequence of changes in a synthesis or reaction.

The field of organic chemistry is probably the most active and important field of chemistry at the moment, due to its extreme applicability to both biochemistry (especially in the pharmaceutical industry) and petrochemistry (especially in the energy industry).  Organic chemistry has a relatively recent history, but it will have an enormously important future, affecting the lives of everyone around the world for many, many years to come.

&lt;noinclude&gt;
----
[[Organic Chemistry/Foundational concepts of organic chemistry|&lt;&lt; Foundational concepts]]| History of Organic Chemistry | [[Organic Chemistry/Foundational concepts of organic chemistry/Atomic_structure|Atomic Structure &gt;]] | [[Organic Chemistry/Alkanes|Alkanes &gt;&gt;]]
&lt;/alkynes&gt;

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>gvp1ofsywmblfbxdsaa2dsu75dfvmpr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Nanobug</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>22</id>
    <revision>
      <id>152220</id>
      <parentid>7437</parentid>
      <timestamp>2003-11-17T17:16:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>207.140.148.33</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>links to other wikis</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Michael Richards - Senior Systems Analyst and Programmer.

Why '''''Nanobug'''''? Take your pick:

*I like the [[w:Software_bug|bugs]] in my programs to be very small.
*I try not to [[wiktionary:bug|bug]] people ''too'' much.
*I have a [[wiktionary:bug|bug]] for [[w:nanotechnology|nanotechnology]].

My page on [http://quote.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Nanobug Wikiquote], [[en:User:Nanobug|Wikipedia]], [[Wiktionary:User:Nanobug|Wiktionary]], and [http://meta.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Nanobug Meta].</text>
      <sha1>suit3ozeq80hgmlqyquoflaxrvvih1y</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook talk:Table of Contents</title>
    <ns>103</ns>
    <id>24</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2688454</id>
      <parentid>2687736</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-04T02:28:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Austncorp</username>
        <id>1540792</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* New Section Proposal */ Added tag line.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Cookbook:Taskbox}}
{{archives|auto=short|bot=MiszaBot|age=60|search=yes|search-width=20}} __TOC__
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{talk archive}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 7
|minthreadsleft = 1
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|algo = old(365d)
|archive = Cookbook talk:Table of Contents/Archive %(counter)d
}}

== [[Meta:WikiRecipe]] Proposal ==

I see that there is a suggestion on Meta for spinning the Cookbook out to it's own project. [[User:Sfan00 IMG|Sfan00 IMG]] ([[User talk:Sfan00 IMG|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Sfan00 IMG|contribs]]) 21:08, 1 April 2013 (UTC)
Oo, I'd like that. How do I join the discussion to give my support? [[User:JonathanHopeThisIsUnique|JonathanHopeThisIsUnique]] ([[User talk:JonathanHopeThisIsUnique|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/JonathanHopeThisIsUnique|contribs]]) 03:02, 26 July 2014 (UTC)

== New Section Proposal ==

In addition to the '''National and Ethnic Cuisines''' section, I think that it would be nice to have a '''Religious Cuisine''' section. It would obviously include the holidays category, but it could also include new categories like food that is acceptable in general for that religion. For example, Judaism could have a Kosher section, Islam could have a Halal section, and so on. This idea just came of the top of my head, and isn't very fleshed out yet, but I hope some people could think about it. I'm not sure if this is the right place to put this this. If not, I'd be happy to put this in the appropriate place. Thanks for reading! [[User:JonathanHopeThisIsUnique|JonathanHopeThisIsUnique]] ([[User talk:JonathanHopeThisIsUnique|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/JonathanHopeThisIsUnique|contribs]]) 03:16, 26 July 2014 (UTC)
#Johnathan... and other readers may personally already be quite well aware of this, but thought I would mention it since I am still finding my way around here and thought it might help others who are also new.  If you are interested in categories, at the top of each recipe in the line which reads or starts with &quot;Cookbook | Ingredients | Recipes&quot;, click on &quot;Recipes&quot;.  This will lead you the page which shows the recipe categorization structure.  Under 'Recipes by origin' you should find 'Jewish recipes' and 'Halal recipes'.[[User:Austncorp|Austncorp]] ([[User talk:Austncorp|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Austncorp|contribs]]) 02:28, 4 August 2014 (UTC)

== Changing Ingredients section ==

    Ingredients

    Alcohol
    Baking Soda
    Beans &amp; Other Legumes
    Bread
    Grain
    Chiles
    Chocolate
    Coffee
    Eggs
    Flour
    Herbs
    Jams &amp; Jellies
    Milk
    Pasta
    Peppers
    Potatoes
    Rice
    Salt
    Spices
    Sugar

Maybe these could be categories? Alcohol, milk and coffee could be in drinks, pepper, chile, salt, and sugar, could be part of spices, which could be combined with spices to make herbs and spices, Jams &amp; Jellies in spreads, rice in cereals, flour and baking soda in basic ingredients, and so on. If the categories do exist, I think it would be a good idea to use them. Thanks for reading! [[User:JonathanHopeThisIsUnique|JonathanHopeThisIsUnique]] ([[User talk:JonathanHopeThisIsUnique|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/JonathanHopeThisIsUnique|contribs]]) 03:37, 26 July 2014 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>3dgs87x63byympi017objvpuay5qipd</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Kpjas</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>25</id>
    <revision>
      <id>578180</id>
      <parentid>193057</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-09-08T05:42:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>84.189.235.109</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;div style=&quot;font-size:medium;font-weight:bold;color:darkblue;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
Welcome to&lt;/div&gt; 
&lt;div style=&quot;font-size:xx-large;font-weight:bold;color:darkblue;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
SLOVIO&lt;/div&gt; 
&lt;div style=&quot;font-size:medium;font-weight:bold;color:darkblue;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
Pan-Slavic language&lt;/div&gt; 

[[Image:Pan-Slavic flag.svg|center|Panslavic flag]]

&lt;div style=&quot;font-size:medium;font-weight:bold;color:darkblue;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
Vitajte vo&lt;/div&gt; 
&lt;div style=&quot;font-size:xx-large;font-weight:bold;color:darkblue;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
SLOVIO&lt;/div&gt; 
&lt;div style=&quot;font-size:medium;font-weight:bold;color:darkblue;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
Pan-slavju jazika&lt;/div&gt; 



&lt;div style=&quot;font-size:large;font-weight:bold;color:black;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
Go to [[Slovio|Table of Contents &gt;&gt;]] &lt;/div&gt; 
&lt;div style=&quot;font-size:large;font-weight:bold;color:black;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
Idijte do [[Slovio|Table of Contents &gt;&gt;]]&lt;/div&gt;</text>
      <sha1>ksxqf00hztvz90klt166ai9fswqjbzj</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:SOCAWS9495.pdf</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>30</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2699286</id>
      <parentid>970342</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-09-10T18:01:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JackBot</username>
        <id>396820</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>File is now available on [[:commons:File:SOCAWS9495.pdf|Wikimedia Commons]].</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{GFDL}}

Organic chemistry script I wrote once (in German), to be harvested{{Now Commons|1=SOCAWS9495.pdf}}</text>
      <sha1>fcgcv3hgrej94g8ec4rt41su4jao1ja</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Wikibooks:Files to be harvested</title>
    <ns>4</ns>
    <id>32</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2365440</id>
      <parentid>1967966</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-17T19:11:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>{{useful}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{useful}}
This is a list of files that have been uploaded to serve as sources for text and images for the textbook project. Material from these can be used freely on this project.

Make sure you use other resources in a wise and legal way: [[Wikibooks:Media]]

== Organic Chemistry ==
* [[media:SOCAWS9495.pdf|Organic chemistry basics]] (in German, but images can be useful)
**Created &amp; uploaded by [[User:Magnus Manske|Magnus Manske]]

== Biochemistry ==
* [[media:VBCAWS9798.doc|Biochemistry basics]] (in German, but images can be useful)
**Created &amp; uploaded by [[User:Magnus Manske|Magnus Manske]]

=== Various online references ===
*[http://www.math.gatech.edu/~cain/textbooks/onlinebooks.html List of mathematics texts] including some with open content.
* Other books, some free, some not - [http://www.theassayer.org theassayer.org].
* [http://digital.library.upenn.edu/books/ Public domain textbooks] from the University of Pennsylvania. Lots of old ones here.
* [http://spot.colorado.edu/~dubin/bookmarks/b/1240.html Dozens of online textbooks here] although you'd have to investigate the license for each one.
* [http://wikipedia.org Wikipedia] has lots of useful GPL'ed information, though it needs to be assimilated and organized into a unified whole
* [http://www.gutenberg.org Project Gutenberg] has countless texts to which one could link

==Getting permission==
*For the time being at least, we can only use outside material that is already CC-BY-SA licensed or in the public domain. However, experience on Wikipedia has shown that authors that place their work under one free license tend to be very willing to grant us a CC-BY-SA license, if we ask nicely. See: [[Wikibooks:Boilerplate request for permission]]</text>
      <sha1>7kphrfp4le0okwd63av31kyeb39dqgx</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Magnus Manske</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>33</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2417505</id>
      <parentid>2417446</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-10T15:39:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/86.26.10.232|86.26.10.232]] ([[User talk:86.26.10.232|talk]]) to last version by Chazz</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Same guy as [[w:user:Magnus Manske|this one]]

I am working on the [[Biochemistry]] and [[Cell biology]] books here; maybe on [[Genetics]] as well, if anyone bothers...

Hi to you, too! What, only three books?? --[[User:RoseParks|RoseParks]]</text>
      <sha1>q4iwhm7f6clbytkgun8cvtx6ki3kf78</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Juxo</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>35</id>
    <revision>
      <id>152231</id>
      <parentid>9119</parentid>
      <timestamp>2003-12-05T21:25:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>R3m0t</username>
        <id>327</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>sp</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''You will most likely find me at http://www.consumerium.org/wiki/wiki.phtml?title=User:Juxo'''
----
==Wishlist==
I'm really looking forward to someone with more expertise doing some [[Textbook]]s on the [[Unix]]. I think it would be a good idea to do it on a '''user story'''-basis. Wherein the structure would be case based so that it assumes you have a '''simple task to do''' and '''how to do it utilizing standard unix commands'''.

----
Here I'll be working on the [[Cookbook]] 'cause it happens to intersect with [[w:Consumerium]] nicely and besides I like good food :)</text>
      <sha1>rz59id60mcdtvaeqlghfj9em5l6il0x</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>