<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>File:Apple slicing function.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>3351</id>
    <revision>
      <id>268483</id>
      <parentid>155282</parentid>
      <timestamp>2005-10-30T08:50:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>H Padleckas</username>
        <id>1153</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>original image modified as stated</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Illustration drawn by Theresa Knott

In October 2005, [[User:H Padleckas|H Padleckas]] uploaded a version of this image originally from Wikibooks and drawn by Theresa Knott and modified by [[User:H Padleckas|H Padleckas]] in about October 2004 by adding in and out arrows and the label &quot;function '''h'''&quot; on the function box.  It will be used in the chapter(s) as before.  [[User:H Padleckas|H Padleckas]] 08:50, 30 October 2005 (UTC)

Since it is based on Theresa Knott's work, I will assume at this time she may want to use a GFDL license.  If she agrees to release it to the public domain, then I would change the status to PD or PD-self.  [[User:H Padleckas|H Padleckas]] 08:50, 30 October 2005 (UTC)

{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>et5i81phki07kqq7okph2l9wb4g3l5s</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Russian/Contents</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3358</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2549549</id>
      <parentid>2158865</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-08-14T06:09:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Capablanca</username>
        <id>1010243</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>false number, unsubstantiated, real number by all sources indicates an approx 260-270 million speakers worldwide, not 350+, ironic given the russian language wiki article is listed at the beginning of this very language intro page...</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">__NOTOC__
&lt;!-- Comment out: This should be made more tasteful, looks like a Hardhat warning sign now
{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;4&quot; style=&quot;background:#f7f8ff; width:800px; border: #FF0000; border-collapse: collapse;&quot;
| align=&quot;center&quot; | &lt;div style=&quot;float: left; padding:5px;&quot;&gt;
[[Image:Preferences-desktop-font.svg|80px]]&lt;/div&gt;
'''Note''': To use this book, your web browser must first be configured to display Cyrillic characters. If the characters in the grey box below appear as blank boxes or garbage, it is not properly configured.&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/small&gt;
{| border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; cellpadding=&quot;6&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;border: #eeeeff; border-collapse: collapse;&quot;
| style=&quot;background-color:#eeeeee;&quot; |На дворе трава, на траве дрова, не руби дрова на траве двора.&lt;/font&gt;
|}
The text in the above box should've looked like this:&lt;br /&gt;
[[Image:RussianShouldLookLike.png]]
|}
--&gt;
[[File:Moscow-city2007.JPG|thumb|&lt;span class=&quot;IPA unicode audiolink&quot;&gt;[[Media:Ru-Moskva.ogg|Москва]]&lt;/span&gt;
----
[[w:Moscow|Moscow]], the capital of Russia 
 ]]
The '''Russian Wikibook''' is a collaborative effort to create a comprehensive textbook for learners of the Russian language. Russian is an East Slavic language, related to [[Ukrainian]] and [[Belarusian]], and is spoken by over 270 million people worldwide. This book includes four sections: a main text curriculum, a grammar supplement, an appendix, and a vocabulary. The main text guides the student through the lessons and provides everything to understand the texts that are to be understood. The grammar supplement provides a greater detail into the concepts presented in the lessons. The appendix is there to refer to for usage and other miscellaneous concepts. The vocabulary groups words into concept-based sections for studying.

==Содержа́ние (Contents)==
* [[Russian/Introduction|Предисло́вие]] (Foreword) {{stage short|25%}}
* [[Russian/Alphabet|Áзбука]] (Alphabet)

===Гла́вы (Chapters)===
# [[Russian/Lesson 1|Как тебя́ зову́т?]] (What is  your name?) {{stage short|75%}}
# [[Russian/Lesson 2|Lesson 2]] {{stage short|25%}} - Introducing yourself.
# [[Russian/Lesson 3|Lesson 3]] {{stage short|25%}} - Basic Grammar.
# [[Russian/Lesson 4|Lesson 4]] {{stage short|25%}} - Vocabulary.
# [[Russian/Lesson 5|Lesson 5]] {{stage short|25%}} - Text.

===[[Russian/Grammar|Грамма́тика (Grammar)]]===	
* [[Russian/Grammar/Introduction|Introduction]]	{{stage short|00%}}
* [[Russian/Grammar/Articles|Articles]] {{stage short|50%}}
* [[Russian/Grammar/Gender|Gender]] {{stage short|50%}}
* [[Russian/Grammar/Cases|Cases]] {{stage short|50%}}
** [[Russian/Grammar/Nominative|Nominative]] {{stage short|50%}}
** [[Russian/Grammar/Genitive case|Genitive]] {{stage short|50%}}
** [[Russian/Grammar/Dative case|Dative]] {{stage short|50%}}
** [[Russian/Grammar/Accusative case|Accusative]] {{stage short|50%}}
** [[Russian/Grammar/Instrumental case|Instrumental]] {{stage short|50%}}
** [[Russian/Grammar/Prepositional case|Prepositional]] {{stage short|50%}}
* [[Russian/Grammar/Adjectives|Adjectives]] {{stage short|50%}}
* [[Russian/Grammar/Pronouns|Pronouns]] {{stage short|00%}}
** [[Russian/Interrogative Pronouns|Interrogative Pronouns]] {{stage short|00%}}
** [[Russian/Personal Pronouns|Personal Pronouns]] {{stage short|00%}}
** [[Russian/Possessive Pronouns|Possessive Pronouns]] {{stage short|00%}}
* [[Russian/Grammar/Verbs|Verbs]]  {{stage short|50%}}
** [[Russian/Verbal Aspect|Verbal Aspect]]  {{stage short|50%}}
** [[Russian/Grammar/Past tense|Past tense]] {{stage short|50%}}
** [[Russian/Grammar/Future tense| Future tense]] {{stage short|50%}}
* [[Russian/Grammar/What and Which|What and Which]] {{stage short|00%}}

===Приложе́ние (Аppendix)===
*[[Russian/Names|Russian Names]] {{stage short|00%}}
*[[Russian/Alphabet|Alphabet]] {{stage short|00%}}
** [[Russian/False Friends|False Friends]] {{stage short|00%}}
* [[Russian/Cursive|Cursive]] {{stage short|00%}}
* [[Russian/Loanwords|Loanwords]] {{stage short|00%}}
* [[Russian/Prepositions|Prepositions]] {{stage short|00%}}

===Слова́рь (Vocabulary)===
*[[Russian/Vocabulary|Vocabulary]] {{stage short|00%}}
* [[Russian/Numbers|Numbers]] {{stage short|25%}}
*[[Russian/Geographical Names|Geographical names]] {{stage short|00%}}
*[[Russian/Useful Words and Expressions|Useful Words and Expressions]] {{stage short|00%}}
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
----
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
[[Russian/Various Stuff|Miscellaneous resources]] {{stage short|00%}}

[[Russian/Internet Resources|Internet Resources]] {{stage short|00%}}

[[Russian/Contributors|Contributors]] {{stage short|00%}}

{{Russian}}

[[de:Russisch]]
[[el:Ρωσικά]]
[[nl:Russisch]]
[[pl:Rosyjski]]
[[fr:Enseignement du russe]]
[[he:רוסית]]
[[zh:俄语]]

{{Subject|Russian}}</text>
      <sha1>ne8id32pelvjn39ss5d6f7t2rzu7798</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Mxn/Vietnamese</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>3361</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2537642</id>
      <parentid>926651</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-06-20T06:23:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mxn</username>
        <id>167</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Updated link</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:{{NAMESPACE}}:{{lcfirst:{{PAGENAME}}}}}}
=Draft 1=
Following is a draft outline of the planned Vietnamese Wikibook. These planned articles are pitifully out of order &amp;ndash; I'd like them to be ordered by difficulty, and have one lead into the other, like an academic course would.

'''Note:''' ''This list has been modified and placed in a [[Vietnamese: Contents|Table of Contents]].''

I plan to use some of the content on [http://www.1ec5.org/mingerweb/viet/index.html Học với Tôi], one of my websites, in this textbook.

----

=Draft 2=

This time, I'm going to aim at a more structured plan. The current Vietnamese book will be split into three levels, according to difficulty and amount of usage. Each book will have a goal (preliminary goals are stated below).

Each book &amp;ndash; often more than once within the book &amp;ndash; the same topic is repeated. Each time it is repeated, it is either a review, or a deeper look at the topic.

In the end, I'd like each chapter to have a title in Vietnamese, at least three exercises (or should the goal be two exercises until the next draft?), and 

This plan '''won't take effect until the current book gets a decent amount of lessons started''' (half of them?). It'll probably also require that someone else helps me out.

I'm basing this plan on the experience I've had for three years so far, learning Spanish. If you have any questions, reservations, doubts, clarifications needed, comments, compliments, or flames &amp;ndash; just kidding &amp;ndash; feel free to respond on this page's Talk Page.

==Level 1: Chào!==
This book will get you started. It will focus on basic phrases, vocabulary, and structure. By the end, you should know enough to visit a Vietnamese community (not necessary in Vietnam) for a day and be able to minimally communicate with the people there.

===Introduction===
*About the authors
*History: do we really need this at the intro level, or can we have this as a cultural note later on?
*Pros &amp;amp; cons

===The Basics===
The essential stuff that you need to know before you begin with vocabulary and grammar. Lessons:

*Alphabet
**Consonants
**Vowels
*Tones: just an introduction to tones and tone marks; we'll build on this lesson extensively later on
*Numbers (single-digit)
*Colors

===Chào!===
Starting a conversation by introducing yourself. Lessons:

*Greetings
*Introducing yourself
*Saying goodbye

Cultural note:
:The handshake: taking a look at shaking hands with others, as opposed to the tradition of bowing

===Tôi Là... (?)===
Describing yourself.

*Age
**Numbers (double-digit)
*Physical characteristics (height, build, hair, facial characteristics)
*Clothes: just enough to describe someone (red shirt, blue jeans, white cap)
*Nationality

...

===Cái Gì?===
Asking questions. Lessons:

*Interrogative pronouns (question words)

...

==Level 2: Hàng Ngày==
This intermediate-level book will expand on the vocabulary and structures introduced in Level 1. It will focus on everyday situations and tasks. By the end, you should be able to spend a few weeks (is that too much?) in Vietnam, communicating with the people around you.

===Phòng Ngủ===
The bedroom.

===Phòng Tắm===
(Or should we call it Phòng Cầu Tiêu?) The bathroom, its fixtures, toiletries, and so on.

*Fixtures
*Toiletries &amp;amp; associated actions

===Phòng Bếp===
The kitchen.

*Appliances &amp;amp; associated actions

===Ngon Lắm!===
Learning about Vietnamese food. This is basically a cultural chapter (but it, of course, has tons of vocabulary), and an extension of possible cultural notes that could appear well before here.

*Rice dishes
*Soup
*Sandwiches
*Snacks
*Beverages

This section should be so good that everyone who takes a course using this book should look forward to this section in particular. This would be a good opportunity for an instructor using this course to take the students on a field trip to a Vietnamese restaurant

Cultural note: We'll take a look at how the Vietnamese typically do not assign specific dishes to certain meals during the day (for example, eating ''phở'' or ''cháo'' (porridge) for breakfast, lunch, and/or dinner).

===Nhà Hàng===
Eating at the restaurant. (Or could we call it ''Tiệm ăn''?)

*Ordering food
*Payment: we'll likely introduce the money topic earlier on

==Level 3==
This is the advanced academic-level book. By the end, you should be able to study various subjects in Vietnamese, such as mathematics and science.

==Level 4==
This is the highly-advanced book. By the end of this book, you should be able to read modern Vietnamese literature and study in Vietnamese.</text>
      <sha1>kexeihcim7c46by2nxi0s6gjjv8gl8f</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:One-Hour Thanksgiving Dinner</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>3362</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1751405</id>
      <parentid>852282</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-04-05T19:48:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>remove average prices - meaningless, there are two many variables</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{recipe}}

This recipe is for an entire '''Thanksgiving Dinner''' that takes one hour to cook.  The recipe uses various pre-cooked ingredients and instant foods, and is designed for those cooking Thanksgiving dinner for the first time, such as college students.

== Ingredients ==

*1 5&amp;ndash;6 lb fully pre-cooked smoked [[Cookbook:Turkey|turkey]] breast.   Certain brands are readily available in almost every U.S. supermarket, however they must be fully-cooked frozen turkey breast, as they only require 1 hour of heating.   Avoid processed turkey breast loaf. 
*2 cans of desired vegetables. 
*1&amp;ndash;2 box package(s) of instant potatoes or stuffing.
*1 package of 12 instant frozen [[Cookbook:Biscuit|biscuit]]s.  The frozen home-baked butter variety works best.  It is important that the biscuits in a can are not used.
*1 package of turkey gravy mix. 
*1 small disposable aluminum turkey pan with built-in rack. 
*1 can of spray oil (can be substituted with regular vegetable oil). 

=== Optional ===

*1 pre-made [[Cookbook:Pumpkin Pie|pumpkin pie]].  
*1&amp;ndash;2 cans [[Cookbook:Cranberry Sauce|cranberry sauce]]. 
==Procedure==
#Make sure you have thawed the turkey breast. A frozen 5&amp;ndash;6 pound breast thaws within one day in the refrigerator. It is also very important that you have purchased a frozen fully pre-cooked breast. The words &quot;heat and serve&quot; may be on the package.
#Preheat your oven to 350°F.
#Remove turkey from bag and place in aluminum roasting pan.
#Spray the turkey with cooking oil. If using regular vegetable oil, rub the breast with it.
#Place turkey breast in the oven on the middle rack.
#Cook for 15 minutes.
#Begin the gravy mix according to package directions.
#Place the vegetables on the range set to low heat.
#Prepare the instant potatoes or stuffing according to the package directions.
#On a small pan lay out your frozen biscuits allowing them to touch one another. At this point the turkey breast should have been cooking for 30 minutes.
#Place your biscuits on the lower rack. The biscuits will cook just fine with the turkey in the oven and will be ready in 25&amp;ndash;30 minutes. Check them at 20 minutes to be sure they do not burn.   
#Finish preparing your instant potatoes or stuffing, instant gravy, and vegetables. Place them in serving dishes if desired. Place the cranberry sauce in a serving dish. If you are serving pie along with the dinner you will also need to place the pie on a serving dish. If a frozen pie has been purchased, follow the microwave directions.
#At the end of the hour, remove the turkey. It is recommended that you use a food thermometer to make sure it has achieved a temperature of 160°F &amp;mdash; the minimum temperature necessary to kill any bacteria which have survived the freezing process. Remove the turkey and serve.

This dinner serves 6&amp;ndash;8 people comfortably.

== Leftovers ==

There are many uses for the leftover turkey.  Sliced turkey leftovers can be used to make sandwiches or [[Cookbook:Turkey Biscuit|turkey biscuits]].

The portion along the bone can be used to prepare turkey soup by placing it in a soup pot along with 4 cups of water, 1 chopped onion, 2 tablespoons salt, and pepper to taste.  Bring to a boil, then lower the heat and allow to simmer for 2 hours.  Add another cup of water, spices to taste, desired vegetables such as carrots or potatoes, and noodles. Simmer for an additional hour and a half.

[[Category:Turkey recipes|One-Hour Thanksgiving Dinner]]
[[Category:Thanksgiving recipes|One-Hour Thanksgiving Dinner]]
[[Category:Holiday recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>h3etwu9bt4lgsyed6ieb492g4zzhxim</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Indonesian/Important Phrases</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3367</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2611132</id>
      <parentid>2611131</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-02-22T17:48:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Aldnonymous</username>
        <id>414537</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Common phrases */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">These are some of the most commonly used words and phrases.

==Common phrases==

{| border=0 cellpadding=3 cellspacing=0
|- bgcolor=#eeeeee
! align=left | Translation
! align=left | Phrase
! align=left | IPA
! align=left | Pronunciation
|-
|Indonesian||''bahasa Indonesia''||{{IPA|/bahasa indoˈnesia/}}||Ba-Ha-Sa In-Do-Ne-Sia
|-
|hello||''halo'' (both in casual speech and on the telephone)||{{IPA|/ˈhalo/}}||Ha-Lo
|-
|welcome||''selamat datang''||{{IPA|/səˈlamat ˈdatang/}}||Se-La-Mat Da-Tang
|-
|good morning||''selamat pagi''||{{IPA|/səˈlamat ˈpagi/}}||Se-La-Mat Pa-Gi
|-
|good afternoon||''selamat siang'' (from 12 o'clock in the afternoon)||{{IPA|/səˈlamat ˈsiaŋ/}}||Se-La-Mat Si-Al
|-
|good evening||''selamat sore'' (from 3 p.m.)||{{IPA|/səˈlamat ˈsore/}}||Se-La-Mat So-Re
|-
|good night||''selamat malam'' (from 6 p.m.)||{{IPA|/səˈlamat ˈmalam/}}||Se-La-Mat Ma-Lam
|-
|good-bye||''dadah'' (commonly-used, informal)||{{IPA|/ˈdadah/}}||DAH-dahh
|-
|good-bye||''selamat tinggal'' (said by the person leaving)||{{IPA|/səˈlamat ˈtiŋgal/}}||Se-La-Mat TING-gahl
|-
|good-bye||''selamat jalan''  (said by the person staying)||{{IPA|/səˈlamat ˈʥalan/}}||Se-La-Mat JAH-lahn
|-
|please||''tolong''||{{IPA|/ˈtoloŋ/}}||To-Long
|-
|thank you||''terima kasih''||{{IPA|/təˈrima ˈkasih/}}||Te-Ri-Ma Ka-sih
|-
|you're welcome||''terima kasih kembali''||{{IPA|/təˈrima ˈkasih kəmˈbali/}}||Te-Ri-ma Ka-sih Kem-ba-li
|-
|this||''ini''||{{IPA|/ˈini/}}||ini
|-
|that||''itu''||{{IPA|/ˈitu/}}||itu
|-
|How much?||''Berapa?''||{{IPA|/bəˈrapa/}}||Be-Ra-Pa ?
|-
|yes||''ya''||{{IPA|/ja/}}||Ya
|-
|no||''tidak''||{{IPA|/ˈtidaʔ/}}||Ti-Dak 
|-
|generic toast (when drinking)||''selamat minum''||{{IPA|/səˈlamat ˈminum/}}||Se-La-Mat Mi-Num
|-
|Sorry||''maaf''||{{IPA|/maˈʔaf/}}||Ma-Af
|-
||I don't understand.||''Saya tidak mengerti.''||{{IPA|/ˈsaja ˈtidaʔ məŋərˈti/}}||Sa-Ye Ti-dak Me-nger-ti
|-
|I don't know.||''Saya tidak tahu.''||{{IPA|/ˈsaja ˈtidaʔ ˈtahu/}}||Sa-Ya Ti-Dak Ta-hu
|-
|the English language||''bahasa Inggris''||{{IPA|/baˈhasa ˈiŋgris/}}||Ba-Ha-Ha-Ha-Sa Ing-rris
|-
|Do you speak English?||Bisa bahasa Inggris?''||{{IPA|/ˈbisa baˈhasa ˈiŋgris/}}||Bi-Sa Ber-Baha-sa Ing-rris?
|-
|I cannot speak Indonesian.||''Saya tidak bisa berbicara bahasa Indonesia.''||{{IPA|/ˈsaja ˈtidaʔ ˈbisa bərbiˈʨara baˈhasa indoˈnesia/}}||Sa-Ya Ti-Dak Bi-Sa Ber-Baha-Sa In-Do-Ne-Sia
|-
|I want to go to...||''Saya mau pergi ke...''||{{IPA|/ˈsaja mau̯ pərˈgi kə/}}||Sa-Ya Mau Per-gi Ke...
|-
|Where is the restroom?||''Di mana toilet?''||{{IPA|/di ˈmana ˈtoilet/}}||Di-Ma-Ne Ru-mah Sa-kit?
|-
|Happy birthday!||''Selamat ulang tahun!''||{{IPA|/səˈlamat ˈulaŋ ˈtahun/}}||Se-La-Mat Ulang Ta-hun
|}

==Helpful vocabulary for asking about words==
When you're trying to find the right word, these can help you ask for suggestions:
* same &amp;rarr; sama
* almost the same &amp;rarr; hampir sama / mirip
* antonym &amp;rarr; lawan kata

If you forget these, you can fall back on: 
* sinonim &amp;rarr; synonym
* antonim &amp;rarr; antonym
''Sinonim'' and ''antonim'' are not common words, but they are easy to remember, many Indonesian speakers understand them, and they can be helpful in your early stages of trying to communicate.

== Kata-kata Penting (''Important Phrases'') ==

Lost traveller's guide for important phrases.

* Thank you &amp;rarr; Terima kasih
* Yes &amp;rarr; Ya
* No, not &amp;rarr; Tidak (used to negate anything but nouns)
* No, Not a X &amp;rarr; Bukan X (where X is a noun)
* Sorry &amp;rarr; Maaf
* Excuse me &amp;rarr; Permisi
* Never mind / It's okay &amp;rarr; Tidak apa-apa
* Okay &amp;rarr; Baik
* Please (to let other people pass) &amp;rarr; Silahkan
* Please (to order something) &amp;rarr; Tolong
* Please give me X &amp;rarr; Tolong berikan saya X

* My name is X &amp;rarr; Nama saya X
* I am from Y &amp;rarr; Saya dari Y
* Where is Z? &amp;rarr; Di mana Z?
* Where is X embassy? &amp;rarr; Di mana kedutaan X?
* I lost my passport &amp;rarr; Paspor saya hilang (Literally, my passport is lost)
* Taxi &amp;rarr; Taksi (almost the same pronunciation)
* Where are you going? &amp;rarr; Ke mana? (Literally = to where?)
* To X? &amp;rarr; Ke X
* Turn left &amp;rarr; Belok kiri
* Turn right &amp;rarr; Belok kanan
* Go straight ahead &amp;rarr; Lurus (Terus)
* There / Over there &amp;rarr; Di situ

* What's this/that? &amp;rarr; Apa ini/itu? (pointing to something)
* I want to see it. &amp;rarr; Saya mau lihat itu
* How much? &amp;rarr; Berapa?
* How much is this/that? &amp;rarr; Berapa ini/itu?
* Too expensive &amp;rarr; Kemahalan
* Give me a lower price &amp;rarr; Kurang sedikit harganya
* Cannot &amp;rarr; Tidak bisa

==Time==
* sudah (already)
* belum (not yet)
These are the words used to deal with almost any situation involving past or future. If neither word is used, it likely means that the action is happening around now. 

[[Category:Indonesian]]</text>
      <sha1>aoabumskgy399m9jlq2x42qvxrko0ae</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Japanese/Contents</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3369</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2313966</id>
      <parentid>2274535</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-04-28T03:23:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Panic2k4</username>
        <id>2865</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Not Japanese language */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">= Categorization =

* '''[[Japanese Phrasebook]]''' was broken out of this book.

== Introductions ==
* '''[[Japanese/Cover]]
* '''[[Japanese/Introduction]]'''
* '''[[Japanese/Introduction/About]]'''
* '''[[Japanese/Study methods]]'''
* '''[[Japanese/Contributor's Guide]]'''

== Linguistics ==
* '''[[Japanese/Pronunciation]]'''
* '''[[Japanese/Pitch accent]]'''
* '''[[Japanese/Dialects]]'''
** ''[[Special:PrefixIndex/Japanese/Dialects]]''
* '''[[Japanese/Grammar]]'''

== Reading and writing ==
[[File:KanjiPractice.jpg|thumb]]
* '''[[Japanese/Japanese writing system]]'''
* '''[[Japanese/Kana Chart]]'''
* '''[[Japanese/Kana]]'''
* '''[[Japanese/Kanji]]'''
** ''[[Special:PrefixIndex/Japanese/Kanji]]''

=== Reading practice ===
* '''[[Japanese/Reader]]'''

== Vocabulary ==
[[File:言-red.png|thumb|right]]
: ''[[Special:PrefixIndex/Japanese/Vocabulary]]''
* '''[[Japanese/Vocabulary]]'''
* '''[[:Category:Japanese vocabulary]]'''
* [[Japanese/Vocabulary/Everyday Phrases]]

== Grammar ==
=== Nouns ===
* '''[[Japanese/Grammar/Nouns]]'''

=== Verbs ===
* '''[[Japanese/Grammar/Verbs]]''' — An overview of classes and forms.
* '''[[Japanese/Verb conjugation table]]'''.
* [[Japanese/Grammar/Verbs/te form]]
** [[Japanese/Grammar/Verbs/te form/iru]]
*** [[Japanese/Lesson Progressive/Answers]] - should probably be deleted. Quiz is trivial. 
* '''[[Japanese/Grammar/Transitivity]]'''
* [[Japanese/Lesson Conditional]]
* '''[[Japanese/Lesson/Simultaneous action]]'''
* [[Japanese/Grammar/~あげく（に）]]

=== Adjectives ===
* '''* [[Japanese/Grammar/Adjectives]]''' Still a bit rough, but good enough to put on the front page.

=== Pronouns ===
* [[Japanese/Lessons/Personal pronouns]]

=== Particles ===
* '''[[Japanese/Grammar/Basic Particles]]''' は, が, を, に, へ, か, の, と や, も, で, から, まで, より
* '''[[Japanese/Grammar/Sentence ending particles]]''' か, の, ね, よ, ぞ, な, な, かな &amp; かしら, ぜ, わ, さ
* [[Japanese/Lessons/Other uses of particles]] Combining particles, simple clauses and various other little bits.

=== Counters ===
* '''[[Japanese/Grammar/Counters]]'''

=== Pro-forms ===
* '''[[Japanese/Grammar/Pro-forms]]'''

=== Others, Sentence Patterns ===
* [[Japanese/Lesson Relative Clauses]]
* [[Japanese/Lesson/Where is it?]]
* [[Japanese/Grammar/Grammar Assorted]]
* [[Japanese/Grammar/~ほど]]
* [[Japanese/Lessons/Assembling simple sentences]] (lists a few setence structures in an introductory fashion)

==== Giving and receiving ====
* '''[[Japanese/Lesson Giving and Receiving]]'''

=== Time and day ===
* [[Japanese/Lessons/Days]] Maybe rename as &quot;Days of the month&quot; or &quot;Dates&quot;
* '''[[Japanese/Lesson/Telling time]]'''

==== Formality and honorifics ====
* [[Japanese/Grammar/Honorifics]] — includes formal/informal verb forms.
* [[Japanese/Grammar/Honorific prefixes]] — includes prefixes attached to nouns to show respect.
* [[Japanese/Grammar/Politeness]] — word choices in different levels of formality.
* [[Japanese/Grammar/Writing]]
* [[Japanese/Lessons/Personal suffixes and name usage]]

==== Comparisons ====
* '''[[Japanese/Grammar/Comparisons]]'''

= Lessons =

* [[Japanese/Lessons/Introduction/Ogenki desu ka/Yes and no]]
* [[Japanese/Lessons/Introduction/Ogenki desu ka/Questions using ka]] — Very short. Only discusses the question marker &quot;か&quot;.

=== Copula, existence and predicates ===
* [[Japanese/Elementary Japanese/Lesson 2]] (undeveloped) ''AはBです''
* [[Japanese/Lesson/What is that?]]
** [[Japanese/Basic Japanese/Answers/Lesson 2]]
* [[Japanese/Lessons/Introduction/Konnichiwa/Noun predicates]]
* [[Japanese/Existence and Copula]]
* [[Japanese/Lesson/Existence]]

=== Introductions and greetings ===
* [[Japanese/Lessons/Introduction/Konnichiwa/Formal salutations]] [[Japanese/Lessons/Introduction/Lesson 1/Unit 1-1/Answers|answers]] [[Japanese/Basic Japanese/Answers/Lesson 1|answers]]

=== Adjectives ===
* [[Japanese/Lessons/I-adjectives]] — Needs more examples to match the な-adjectives.
* [[Japanese/Lessons/Na-adjectives]]
* [[Japanese/Lessons/Introduction/Ii tenki desu ne/Talking about the weather]] — Undeveloped; discusses describing the weather ((&lt;time&gt; は) &lt;adjective&gt;天気 ですね。) and &quot;ね&quot;.

=== Numbers ===
* [[Japanese/Numbers]]
* [[Japanese/Lessons/Lesson 3]] Inquiring about phone numbers and age.

=== Miscellaneous ===
* [[Japanese/Lesson/Asking for something]]
* [[Japanese/Lesson/Giving directions]]
* [[Japanese/Lessons/Introduction/Konnichiwa/Formality]] — Informal greetings and discussion on when these are acceptable.
** [[Japanese/Lessons/Introduction/Lesson 1/Unit 1-4/Answers]]
* [[Japanese/Lessons/Introduction/Amerika-jin desu ka/Foreign loan words]]
* [[Japanese/Lessons/Word list 1]] &quot;''This is the list of words you should have learned during the first five weeks of this course.''&quot;
* [[Japanese/Mini-tutorial lesson]] — Phrases and conversation at a restaurant.

= Structure/Lesson Plans/Syllabus =
* [[Japanese/Practical Lessons]]
* [[Japanese/Practical Lessons/Syllabus]]
* [[Japanese/Lessons/Basic]] (content for about ten lessons)
* [[Sugu ni Hajimemashō]]
== Users ==
* [[User:Balloonguy/Japanese]] — A discussion about the rearrangement of contents. (precedes this overhaul and is somewhat outdated by it)
* [[User:Telamon/Japanese]] — A single page with greetings.
* [[User:Helpfulstuffnz/Japanese]] — A restructuring of the old main page.
* [[User:Mkn/Japanese]] — A new book, never got past an introduction and a page on Japanese scripts.
* [[User:Retropunk/Japanese_Curriculum]] (in active development &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller&quot;&gt;01:20, 14 November 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;)
* [[User talk:Nesnad/sandbox]] Nesnad's Quick Start Japanese.

= Other =
* [[Transwiki:Transcribing_English_to_Japanese]]
== Links and resources ==
These should be found place on pages where are relevant.
* [[w:Category:Japanese language tests]])
* [[Japanese/Internet Links]]
* [[Japanese/Software]]

=== Commons ===
* [[commons:Category:Japanese pronunciation]]
* [[commons:Commons:CJK stroke order project]]

== Meta ==
* [[Japanese/Discussion]]
* [[Japanese/Discussion/Archives:December, 2005]]
* [[Japanese/Discussion/Archives:September, 2005]]
* [[Japanese/Q&amp;A]]
* [[Japanese/Q&amp;A/Archive 1]]

=== Templates ===
: ''[[:Category: Japanese templates]]''

* [[Template:Furi]]
* [[Template:Japanese example]]
* [[Template:Japanese vocabulary entry]]
* [[Template:Japanese related]]
* [[Template:Japanese kana]]
* [[Template:Japanese kanji readings]]

==== Just an idea... ====
... tell me what you think.
* [[Template:Japanese verb style]]

==== Navigation ====
* [[Template:Janav]] (There is nothing on this, so far, but the look is nice and we might as well base a book-wide navigation on this ... if we choose to use a book-wide navigation template at all.)
* [[Template:Japanese kana navigation]]
* [[Template:第三夜Nav]]

==== Meta ====
* [[Template:Japanese obsolete]]
* [[Template:Japanese todo]]

==== JLPT specific ====
: ''rename these to remove the superfluous &quot;Japanese/&quot;?''
* [[Template:Japanese/JLPT 3 Vocabulary]]
* [[Template:Japanese/JLPT 4 Vocabulary]]
* [[Template:JLPT 4 kanji navigation]]
* [[Template:Japanese/Parts of speech]]

==== Ruby ====
These are out-dated and should be replaced with {{tl|furi}} when used in Japanese text, but kept for general use elsewhere on Wikibooks.

* [[Template:Ruby]] (should be kept)
* [[Template:Ruby-2]] (not really that useful. Delete)

Not sure what to do about these:
* [[Template:Rubywikt]]
* [[Template:Rubywikt-2]]

== Not Japanese language ==
* [[Japanese/Background Japan]] (should be a separate book or merged introduction)

[[Category:{{BOOKNAME}}|{{SUBPAGENAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>rqhbj5zalt329m4thzj65mttevubjt1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Elements of Art</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3374</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1915519</id>
      <parentid>1856093</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-08-19T20:57:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>formatting; status=0%</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{book title|Elements of Art| }}


{{:Elements of Art/Navline}}

{{Subjects|Visual arts}}
{{Alphabetical|E}}
{{status|0%}}</text>
      <sha1>ie63b999276hf8q8gewzls5lzit2w5m</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Household Cyclopedia Sauces</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>3375</id>
    <revision>
      <id>636570</id>
      <parentid>438104</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-11-04T13:48:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Herbythyme</username>
        <id>40889</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>a cats</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{cookwork}}
{{recipe}}

''Articles &quot;rescued&quot; from VfD at Wikipedia, to be sorted at a later time if found useful''

== SAUCES ==

===Common Sauce===

From the 1881 Household Cyclopedia 

Soak slices of veal, ham, onions, parsnips, 2 cloves of garlic, 2 heads of cloves, then add broth, a glass of white wine, and 2 slices of lemon; simmer it over a slow fire, skim it well, and sift it.

===Parson's sauce===

From the 1881 ''Household Cyclopedia''

Chop lemon-peel very fine, with 2 or 3 pickled cucumbers, a bit of butter, salt, and coarse pepper, a little flour, with 2 spoonful of catsup, and stew it on the fire without boiling. 

===Nonpareil sauce===

From the 1881 ''Household Cyclopedia''

Take a slice of boiled ham, as much breast of roasted fowl, a pickled cucumber, a hard yolk of an egg, one anchovy, a little parsley, and a bend of shallot, chopped very fine; boil it a moment in good catsup, and use it for meat or fish. 

===Gravy cakes===

From the 1881 ''Household Cyclopedia''

Chop 2 legs of beef in pieces, put them into a pot of water, stew it over a slow fire a day and a night; then add onions, herbs, and spices as for gravy; continue stewing it till the meat is off the bones, and the gravy quite out; then strain the liquor into a milk-pan, to which quantity it should be reduced; when cold, take off the fat, put it into a saucepan, and add whatever is required to flavor it; simmer it on a slow fire till reduced to about 12 saucers twothirds full, put them in an airy place till as dry as leather, put them in paper bags, and keep in a dry place. 

===Sailor's sauce===

From the 1881 ''Household Cyclopedia''

Chop a fowl's liver with a or 3 shallots, and a couple of truffles or mushrooms; simmer these in a spoonful of oil, 2 or 3 spoonful of gravy, a glass of wine, a little salt and coarse pepper, simmer it about half an hour, and skim it very well before using. 

===Queen's sauce===

From the 1881 ''Household Cyclopedia''

Simmer crumbs of bread in good gravy, until it is quite thick, take it off the fire, and add a few sweet almonds pounded, 2 hard yolks of eggs, and a breast of fowl roasted, all pounded very fine; boil a sufficient quantity of cream to your sauce, and sift all together, then add pepper and salt, and warm it without boiling.

===Catsup for sea-stores===

From the 1881 ''Household Cyclopedia''

Take a gallon of strong stale beer, a pound of anchovies washed from the pickle, the same of shallots peeled, 1/2 an ounce of mace, 1/2 an ounce of cloves, 1/4 of an ounce of whole pepper 3 or 4 large races of ginger, and 2 quarts of large mushroom flaps, rubbed to pieces. Cover these close, and let it simmer till half wasted. Then strain it through a flannel bag; let it stand till quite cold, and then bottle it. This may be carried to any part of the world; and a spoonful of it to a pound of fresh butter melted, will make a fine fish sauce, or will supply the place of gravy sauce. The stronger and staler the beer the better will be the catsup. 

''Another'' -- Chop 24 anchovies, having first boned them; put to them 10 shallots cut small, and a handful of scraped horse-radish, 1/4 of an ounce of mace, a quart of white wine, a pint of water, and the same quantity of red wine, a lemon cut into slices, 1/2 a pint of anchovy liquor, 12 cloves, and the same number of peppercorns. Boil them together till it comes to a quart, then strain it off cover it close, and keep it in a cold dry place. Two spoonful of it will be sufficient for a pound of better. It is a good sauce for boiled fowls, or, in the room of gravy lowering it with hot water, and thickening it with a piece of butter rolled in flour. 

===Cream sauce for a hare===

From the 1881 ''Household Cyclopedia''

Run the cream over the hare or venison just before frothing it, and catch it in a dish; boil it up with the yolks of two eggs, some onion, and a piece of butter rolled in flour and salt. Half a pint of cream is the proportion for two eggs. 

===Sweet sauce===

From the 1881 ''Household Cyclopedia''

Mix 2 glasses of red wine, one of vinegar, 3 teaspoonful of cullis, a bit of sugar, 1 sliced onion, a little cinnamon, and a laurel-leaf; boil them a quarter of an hour. 

===Brown sauce===

From the 1881 ''Household Cyclopedia''

Mix together one tablespoonful of moist sugar, two of French vinegar, three of salad oil, a teaspoonful of mixed mustard, some pepper and salt, end serve.

[[Category:Sauce recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>m0ptgeozrilh87apzsfe41cpdvhkpfj</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Elements of Art/Introduction</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3376</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1910906</id>
      <parentid>1910802</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-08-14T11:56:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Recent Runes</username>
        <id>66908</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/121.96.146.222|121.96.146.222]] ([[User talk:121.96.146.222|talk]]) to last revision by [[User:Jomegat|Jomegat]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{:Elements of Art/Navline}}
==ELEMENTS OF ART-INTRODUCTION==

===Audience (who the book is for)===

Students, producers and consumers of diverse forms of art, including but not limited to painting, drawing and sculpture, who would like to know more about the elements and theory of their specific art and art in general. This book is also for those who have an interest in the history of art. It will be richly illustrated, so that the facts and concepts it contains will be comprehended by children and adults, and be within their interest levels.

===Purpose (why it might be used)===

Elements of Art is designed to be used as a reference book. It is also a teaching book, to be consulted with other and more advanced/specialised resources on the subject, including textbooks that people may already be using. It can be a 'cram book' for examinations and tests, or a 'coffee table' book to take to the museum, library or keep at home.

===Form (the shape of the book)===

Chapters explaining (describing, analysing) the form, content and structure of particular elements of art, as well as general concepts reinforced throughout the book, and at the end of a section. Generally they are designed to build upon one another.

Thus, there are chapters about line, colour, dimensionality (2-D forms of art like drawing and painting, and 3-D like sculpture) and shape.

==General Questions about Art (five Ws and a H-hopefully will be answered throughout the book, by clicking on specific links)==

WHO
WHAT
WHERE
WHEN
WHY
and HOW

What are the elements of art?
How many elements?
What are the forms of art?
What is the difference between two-dimensional art?
What is line?
What is colour?
How is line used?
How is colour used?
What is a dimension?
What are the components of two dimensions? Of three?
How can I show emotion?
What have artists used to show emotion?
What have artists used to show senses?

Who is an artist?
Who created the first art?

Where was the first art created?
Where were major art developments?
Where can I go and see (hear/touch/taste/smell) art?
Where can I go and learn more about art?
Where do I start?

When was the first art created?
When were the major art developments?
When is an artwork complete?

Why do we create art?
Why do we need art?
Why do we respond to elements?
Why use line/colour/whatever there and not here?

http://SeaCloud9.org This web site is dedicated to the latest technological advancements, open source code, and cutting edge multimedia art.

[[Category:Elements of Art|Introduction]]</text>
      <sha1>9qmt79xm09moqqws6rx27l2o3s9xtlu</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Elements of Art/Line</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3377</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2691452</id>
      <parentid>2691451</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-15T02:25:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>203.25.67.3</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Vertical */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{:Elements of Art/Navline}}
==LINE==

===What is line?===

In art, line is the continuous movement of a mark from dot to dot.

==Different lines==
===Lines of direction===
====Horizontal====

Horizontal lines travel from left to right and are relative to the horizon.

====Vertical====

Vertical lines travel up and down.

Often used in paintings with trees.

====Diagonal====

Diagonal lines go in two directions.

One kind of diagonal line goes down from left to right.
Starting from the right, it can also go up to the left.

===Lines of length===

====Short lines====

====Long lines====

===Lines of thickness===

The thickness or thinness of a line can be affected by using different materials. A ballpoint pen will create a thinner line than a big marker.

====Thick lines====

====Thin lines====

==Putting lines together==

There are many ways to put lines together.

One of the simplest is to join a horizontal and a vertical line. A square is two horizontal lines and two vertical lines.

Many lines can be put together to make a shading effect. An example of this is cross-hatching, where many small horizontal lines are put over many small vertical lines. This gives a realistic effect.

==Effect of lines==

===Lines of movement===

===Lines of emotion===

Horizontal lines can represent calmness and tranquility whereas vertical lines tend to have more of a grandeur effect. Curved lines tend to represent nature as well as confusion and busyness. 

Diagonal lines represent movement.

Thick lines can represent anger whereas thin lines can represent shyness, or invisibility.

==Chapter summary==

[[Category:Elements of Art|Line]]</text>
      <sha1>mrk57mne160zgm758x0zmyzk6j3eddc</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Botany/Magnoliophyta</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3378</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2352383</id>
      <parentid>2352366</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-05-23T15:01:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>173.8.113.1</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Flower evolution */  following informational/conversational tone</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;small&gt;&lt;&lt; [[Botany#Contents|Contents Page]] |  [[Botany/Pinophyta|Chapter 14]] | &lt;/small&gt;Chapter 15&lt;small&gt; | [[Botany/Liliopsida|Chapter 16]] &gt;&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
----
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;big&gt;&lt;big&gt;Chapter 15. Magnoliophyta (I)&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/big&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
----

The '''Division Magnoliophyta''' in the Kingdom Plantae comprises those species of plants that were formerly classified as '''angiosperms''' and are known widely as the ''flowering plants''. You have already studied flowers ([[Botany/Plant_reproduction|Chapter 4]]), so now understand that the Division Magnoliophyta comprises all those species of plants that have flowers. For perspective: all of the plants we have read about in '''Section II''' of the ''Botany Study Guide'' up to this point do not have flowers, but certainly do have reproductive structures. We also know that flowers are the reproductive structures of the plants that bear them, and that reproductive structures are not limited to flowering plants. Thus, &quot;flowers&quot; are  structures that distinguish plants in the Division Magnoliophyta from plants in the other divisions of the Kingdom Plantae. Observe a flower, and you know you are examining an angiosperm. However, not all angiosperms have obvious, showy flowers. You will need to consider that the structure of a flower is quite variable across all the many species of angiosperms (about a quarter million have been identified) and a few flowering plants actually seldom flower.  However, angiosperm botanists put great stock in the structure of flowers as a way of classifying plants&amp;mdash;more than any other part of a plant, the flower provides the basis for placement of a species in subtaxa (classes, orders, and families) of the Division Magnoliophyta.   

The Division Magnoliophyta is split into two large classes: the '''Magnoliopsida''' and the '''Liliopsida'''.

* Read [[w:en:Flowering plant|Flowering plants]] (&lt;small&gt;The following links are included&lt;/small&gt;)
** Reread [[w:en:Cotyledon|cotyledon article]]
** Read [[w:en:Dicotyledon|dicotyledons]] (Magnoliopsida)
** Read [[w:en:Monocotyledon|monocotyledons]] (Liliopsida)
** Read [[w:en:How to distinguish a monocot from a dicot|How to distinguish monocots and dicots]] &lt;small&gt;and follow any links that you are uncertain about&lt;/small&gt;

There are over 300 families and 250,000 species of flowering plants.  The remainder of this chapter will be concerned with the dicotyledonous angiosperms ('''Class Magnoliopsida'''), leaving the monocotyledonous angiosperms to be covered in the [[Botany/Liliopsida|next chapter]].  

==Flower evolution==
Conifers are pollinated by wind, meaning they must produce a large amount of pollen grains for only a few to arrive at the female megaspore, resulting in fertilization. An advancement that allowed for higher rates of fertilization per energy expended in making pollen would surely result in that new plant type being prolific and even dominant. However, a single mutation would never result in a flower adequately adapted to spread pollen using animals. Flowers are the result of a special kind of evolution called [[w:en: co-evolution| co-evolution]].

If plants reproduced and thrived with wind pollination, why did flowers evolve? 

Suppose one wind pollinated plant began to have its' pollen eaten by an animal, for example a beetle. Then suppose the beetle spreads the pollen from the male cones to the female cones while looking for pollen because it can't tell the difference between the male and female cones; it searches both, spreading pollen from the male to the female in doing so. This plant has an advantage over all wind pollinated plants, because of a higher rate of fertilization. Any mutation that leads to pollen being spread by an animal soon becomes prevalent within a species, because the plant pollinated by an animal is more efficient. The plant and the animal rely on each other, one for food, the other for reproduction. Any mutation in the animal that helps pollinate the plant will become prolific through natural selection, just as mutations that favor feeding the insect or making the insect come to the flower will be dominant. This back and forth evolution results in such seemingly improbable structures as flowers that look like female moths that are pollinated by amorous male moths, or flowers and bird beaks that complement the feeding of the bird and the pollination of the flowers.

== Class Magnoliopsida (dicots) ==
Members of the Class Magnoliopsida are defined partly on the basis of the seed or seedling having two cotyledons, most obvious at germination. But the differences between dicots and monocots are many, and we will be able to recognize most flowering plants that we encounter as belonging to one or the other class without having to dissect the seed or observe the seedling.    

----

&lt;center&gt;
{{BotanyTOC2}}
&lt;/center&gt;

[[Category:Botany]]</text>
      <sha1>c3luiuoxwyahkruyt3rzsk6e3k87nce</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Elements of Art/Shape</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3379</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2562868</id>
      <parentid>2561061</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-10-02T23:47:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Recent Runes</username>
        <id>66908</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rejected the last 2 text changes (by [[Special:Contributions/112.198.241.39|112.198.241.39]] and [[Special:Contributions/66.76.156.104|66.76.156.104]]) and restored revision 1937741 by 99.227.56.43</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{:Elements of Art/Navline}}
==SHAPE==

Shapes are created with lines in a given space, either real or imaginary. Shapes can be endlessly rotated. There can be organic shapes or geometric shapes.

==Different shapes==

===Circle===

A circle is a shape with only one side created from a single, continuously curved line which encompasses the whole of the shape.

===Triangle===

A triangle is a shape comprised of three straight lines which meet at three endpoints - the bottom side is horizontal, and the other two sides are diagonal, meeting each other at a point.

===Square===

A square is a shape which is made of four straight lines which intersect at four points at 90 degree angles: the top and bottom lines are parallel to one another, as are the two lines comprising the sides of the square. In a square, each of the sides is the exact length of the other sides (a rectangle is a different shape where the opposing sides are equal in length; thus, all squares are rectangles but not all rectangles are squares.)

===Pentagon===

A shape with 5 sides. The bottom side is horizontal, there are two vertical sides that are parallel and the two top sides are diagonal.

A common use of the pentagon is to draw a house.

===Hexagon===

A shape with six sides. 4 sides are diagonal and 2 are horizontal.

===Star===

==Three-dimensional shapes==

===Cone===

===Cube=== 
A cube has 8 endpoints, 12 edges and 6 faces.  At every endpoint 3 lines intersect, and at an intersection any two edges are perpendicular to each other.  Finally every edge has the same length.

==Putting shapes together==

Most shapes in art are combinations of the shapes described above. They may be expressed (that is, they have a clear outline) or implied (the viewer has to seem them for his/herself).

Also, different shapes can be put together for interesting results.

===Rotating shapes===

==Effects of shapes==

===Movement===

===Emotion===

===Weight===

===Height===

==Chapter summary==

[[Category:Elements of Art|Shape]]</text>
      <sha1>5bhmaw7oniu3qruo37szv2lt6guv9gl</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Elements of Art/Two and Three Dimensions</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3380</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2629771</id>
      <parentid>2567735</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-04-13T07:47:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Fishpi</username>
        <id>366400</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rejected the last text change (by [[Special:Contributions/223.230.64.113|223.230.64.113]]) and restored revision 2564442 by 112.198.219.132</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{:Elements of Art/Navline}}
==Two and Three Dimensions==


Dimensions, in art, can create some really interesting effects.

They are connected with perspective, which is often used in graphic design, especially one-point perspective and two-point perspective.

====Two dimensions====

The two dimensions are height and width.

====Three dimensions====

The three dimensions are height and width and depth. Depth is often applied by projecting a shadow. Three-dimensional shapes can often be created by extra lines, or by doing a net.

===Art forms that use two dimensions===

Drawing
Painting

===Art forms that use three dimensions===

Sculpture Origami

===Art forms that use two and three dimensions===
Provide examples
Mixed-media.

===Putting dimensions together===

===Effects of dimensions===

[[Category:Elements of Art|Two and Three Dimensions]]</text>
      <sha1>ivzyfbahu9bt8p32fqve6hil8ef7oer</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>General Chemistry/Properties of matter</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3381</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1909362</id>
      <parentid>1909074</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-08-10T18:20:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Recent Runes</username>
        <id>66908</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/111.125.77.36|111.125.77.36]] ([[User talk:111.125.77.36|talk]]) to last revision by [[User:Nlhowell|Nlhowell]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{GeneralChemTOC}}

The fundamental properties that we use to measure matter in are; Inertia, Mass, Weight, Volume, Density and Specific Gravity. The [[Periodic Table|periodic table]] is a visual method of interpreting the chemical properties of elements which effect the measurements below.

These measurements can be classified into two categories, intrinsic and extrinsic.  

==Extrinsic Properties==

Extrinsic properties (also called extensive), such as volume and weight, are directly related to the amount of material being measured.

* [[wikipedia:Inertia|Inertia]] - the resistance of an object to changes in motion ([[Wikipedia:Sir_Isaac_Newton|Newton's]] first law).
** Measured as mass because it is intimately related to mass.  Mass has inertia by virtue of its nature.
** Common units: kilograms (kg), grams (g), pounds (lb).
** Fundamental property of matter.

* [[wikipedia:Mass|Mass]] - a) the amount of matter in an object; b) a measure of resistance to acceleration that an object has.
** Common units; [[wikipedia:kilograms|kilograms]] (kg), grams(g), pounds (lb), ounces (oz).
** Sometimes equated with weight, but only valid when the acceleration due to [[wikipedia:Gravity|gravity]] is understood to be 9.81 m/s&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; (i.e., earthly conditions), or when a different definition of the word &quot;weight&quot; is used, as is normal in commerce and the medical sciences.

* Weight:
# Mass times the acceleration of gravity.
# Note that Weight is very different from Mass, a common misconception for students. However, weight and mass are related. An easy way to remember the difference is that no matter what planet you are on, you will always be the same mass. However, if you enter a different planet or go on the moon, your '''weight''' will change.
# The measure of the attraction between two objects, one of which is generally much larger than the other.
# Common units: newtons (N), pounds-force (lbf), ounces-force (ozf).

* Force:
** Common units: pounds-force (lbf) or newtons (N).
** Relevant equation(s):
**# '''''F''''' = ''m'' '''''a''''' ( Force = Mass * acceleration )
**# '''''W''''' = ''m'' '''''g''''' ( Weight = Mass * Gravity )
**# '''N''' = 1 kg &lt;b&gt;m/s&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/b&gt; ( newtons = kilograms * meters per second squared )
** Notes: The acceleration of gravity near the surface of the earth is 9.81 meters per second squared or 9.81 m/s&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;.

* [[wikipedia:Volume|Volume]] - the amount of space that an object occupies.
** Common units: liters (l), cubic meters (m&amp;sup3;), cubic feet (ft&amp;sup3;), fluid ounces, pints, quarts, gallons.

==Intrinsic Properties==

Intrinsic properties (also called intensive) are those which are independent of the quantity of matter present. For example, the density of gold is the same no matter how much gold you have to measure.  Common intrinsic properties are density and specific gravity.

* [[wikipedia:Density|Density]] - units of mass per unit of volume.
** Common units: g/cm&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; and kg/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;
** Relevant equation(s):
**# ''D'' = ''m''/''v ( Density = mass/volume )
** These measurements are relative to temperature. The density of water (at 4 degrees Celsius) is 1.00 g/cm&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;.  Above and below that temperature, the density will be slightly different.

* [[wikipedia:Specific_Gravity|Specific Gravity]] - ratio of a substance's density relative to the density of water.  Usually table values use a water temperature of 25 degrees Celsius. See current reference books for examples. 
** Since specific gravity is a ratio with the same numerator as denominator, it has no units.
** Specific gravity is usually measured with a hydrometer.
** Specific gravity can be an ambiguous measurement if the temperatures of the two substances are different.

* [[wikipedia:Specific_Heat|Specific Heat]] - the amount of energy required to raise the temperature of one gram of a pure substance by one degree Kelvin. 
** Common units J/(g*K) (Joules per gram-Kelvin).</text>
      <sha1>o274dzhjqtv5bwcp24lb356g1aw2j3p</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:4.8.64.47</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>3382</id>
    <revision>
      <id>155309</id>
      <timestamp>2003-12-19T08:18:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dbroadwell</username>
        <id>383</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">User 4.8.64.47 is dbroadwell before he created an account.

---

Go WikiWiki!</text>
      <sha1>3unfn11z4e0rmjuesku6bvfqfpvl1fm</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Dbroadwell</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>3383</id>
    <revision>
      <id>155310</id>
      <parentid>10461</parentid>
      <timestamp>2003-12-22T01:25:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dbroadwell</username>
        <id>383</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Grapeseed paper removed ... now for something different.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;center&gt;This page Blank ... on purpose.
--
[[User:Dbroadwell|Dbroadwell]] 01:25, 22 Dec 2003 (UTC)&lt;/center&gt;</text>
      <sha1>3do165id0rcf67dpjrhdteqdzzs1nv4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:Dbroadwell</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>3384</id>
    <revision>
      <id>155311</id>
      <parentid>10414</parentid>
      <timestamp>2003-12-20T08:36:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dysprosia</username>
        <id>32</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>tip</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Hi Dbroadwell, welcome to Wikibooks. Just a tip: Please try and keep a relative [[Wikibooks:Neutral point of view|Neutral point of view]] when you add content (for example you can't really &quot;plug&quot; Python without considering alternatives or criticisms of Python, for example).

Thanks, and keep contributing! :) [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 09:00, 19 Dec 2003 (UTC)

I've replied at my [[User talk:Dysprosia|talk page, here]]. [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 23:28, 19 Dec 2003 (UTC)

You may be interested to know that you can make subpages of your user page, for example, you may want to make a sandbox, so you might create [[User:Dbroadwell/Sandbox]], or [[User:Dbroadwell/Grape seed oil]], and when you're done with them you can request an admin to delete them :) [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 08:36, 20 Dec 2003 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>b63sy45eplauxhpwddq4xxlpqk8sst4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Japanese/Vocabulary/Phrases and Idioms</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3385</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2174784</id>
      <parentid>1657407</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-10-03T16:52:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>HethrirBot</username>
        <id>475400</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Robot: Cosmetic changes</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">== ... が好きです ==
'''''... ga suki desu'''''

Expresses that a thing or person is liked.
The subject, marked by が, is liked by the person marked with the topic marker は (if mentioned).

=== Examples ===
:彼はリンゴとバナナが好きです
:''kare wa ringo to banana ga suki desu.''
:He likes apples and bananas.

:英語を勉強するのがとても好きだよ！
:''eigo o benkyo suru no ga totemo suki da yo!''
:I really like studying English!

== ... なければならない ==
'''''... nakereba naranai'''''

The construction &quot;(verb stem)なければならない&quot;, ''-nakereba naranai'' is used to express an obligation: something that has to be done.

(Literally, the -なければ ''-nakereba'' conjunction is the negative conditional form, &quot;if not (this action)&quot;; ならない ''naranai'' is &quot;to not become&quot;, the plain negative of なる ''naru''. The literal implication is that if the action is not done, nothing else can proceed.)

=== Examples ===
:今日は銀行にいかなければならない。
:''kyô wa ginko ni ikanakereba naranai.''
:I have to go to the bank today.

:おじいさんがすぐに帰らなければ、私はマクドナルドに行きます。
:''Ojii-san ga suguni kaeranakereba watashi wa makudonarudo ni ikimasu.''
:If Grandpa doesn't return soon, I'm going to McDonald's.

Since ならない ''naranai'' is the plain-form negative of the verb なる ''naru'' (to become), in a more formal or polite situation one would use the polite negative form なりません ''narimasen'' instead.

== 下手の横好き（へたのよこずき） ==
'''''heta no yoko-zuki'''''

An idiom meaning that you are &quot;unskilled but enthusiastic&quot; or &quot;crazy about it, but not very good at it&quot;. Used about a hobby or skilled activity.

=== Example ===
:山田： 田中さんは英語がお上手ですね。
:''Yamada：Tanaka-san wa eigo ga ojouzu desune.''
:Yamada: Mr Tanaka, you speak English well.

:田中： いいえ、下手の横好きなんですよ。
:''Tanaka: iie, heta no yoko-zuki nandesuyo.''
:Tanaka: Oh no, I like it, but I'm not very good at it

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>jajk5f0y8he1489h57enmmd1a5hot4h</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Spanish/First Conjugation Verb</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3386</id>
    <revision>
      <id>616162</id>
      <parentid>532401</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-10-18T04:26:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Guanabot</username>
        <id>5478</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>User-controlled Bot: table syntax updated</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Verb '''amar''' (to love)

This is the typical example of a regular first conjugation verb in Spanish.

==Formas simples==


{| border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
| &amp;nbsp; || colspan=&quot;5&quot; | Indicativo || colspan=&quot;3&quot; | Subjuntivo
| Imperativo
|-
| &amp;nbsp; || Presente || Pretérito&lt;br&gt;
imperfecto
| Pretérito&lt;br&gt;perfecto&lt;br&gt;
simple
| Futuro || Condicional || Presente || Pretérito&lt;br&gt;
imperfecto
| Futuro || Presente
|-
| yo || amo || amaba || amé || amaré || amaría || ame || amara / amase
| amare || ---
|-
| tú || amas || amabas || amaste || amarás
| amarías || ames || amaras / amases || amares || ama
|-
| él || ama || amaba || amó || amará || amaría || ame || amara / amase
| amare || ame
|-
| nosotros || amamos || amábamos || amamos || amaremos
| amaríamos || amemos || amáramos / amásemos
| amáremos || amemos
|-
| vosotros || amáis || amabais || amasteis || amaréis
| amaríais || améis || amarais / amaseis
| amareis || amad
|-
| ellos || aman || amaban || amaron || amarán
| amarían || amen || amaran / amasen || amaren || amen
|}

==Formas no personales==
*'''Infinitivo''': amar
*'''Gerundio''': amando
*'''Participio''': amado

[[Category:Spanish]]</text>
      <sha1>641evyt70z5pohqyoi6rj9p7bec5u43</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Spanish/Second Conjugation Verb</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3387</id>
    <revision>
      <id>616163</id>
      <parentid>532453</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-10-18T04:26:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Guanabot</username>
        <id>5478</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>User-controlled Bot: table syntax updated</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Verb '''temer''' (to fear)

This is the typical example of a regular second conjugation verb in Spanish.

==Formas simples==


{| border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
| &amp;nbsp; || colspan=&quot;5&quot; | Indicativo || colspan=&quot;3&quot; | Subjuntivo
| Imperativo
|-
| &amp;nbsp; || Presente || Pretérito&lt;br&gt;
imperfecto
| Pretérito&lt;br&gt;perfecto&lt;br&gt;
simple
| Futuro || Condicional || Presente || Pretérito&lt;br&gt;
imperfecto
| Futuro || Presente
|-
| yo || temo || temía || temí || temeré
| temería || tema || temiera / temiese
| temiere || ---
|-
| tú || temes || temías || temiste || temerás
| temerías || temas || temieras / temieses
| temieres || teme
|-
| él || teme || temía || temió || temerá
| temería || tema || temiera / temiese
| temiere || tema
|-
| nosotros || tememos || temíamos || temimos || temeremos
| temeríamos || temamos || temiéramos / temiésemos
| temiéremos || temamos
|-
| vosotros || teméis || temíais || temisteis || temeréis
| temeríais || temáis || temierais / temieseis
| temiereis || temed
|-
| ellos || temen || temían || temieron || temerán
| temerían || teman || temieran / temiesen
| temieren || teman
|}

==Formas no personales==
*'''Infinitivo''': temer
*'''Gerundio''': temiendo
*'''Participio''': temido

[[Category:Spanish]]</text>
      <sha1>rmfxr6qj4th5q7ibcg6arxh8ehq57t8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>