<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Jamaican Jerk Spice</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4023</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1736938</id>
      <parentid>851446</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-03-15T21:36:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{ingredient}} | [[Cookbook:Spices and herbs|Spice]] | [[Cookbook:Cuisine of Jamaica|Jamaican cuisine]]

'''Jamaican jerk spice''' is a pungent, hot mixture of [[Cookbook:Spices and herbs|spices]] used to flavor [[Cookbook:Meat|meats]] before grilling or roasting.

==Recipes==
*2 [[Cookbook:Tablespoon|tablespoons]] [[Cookbook:Cayenne pepper|cayenne pepper]] 
*1 [[Cookbook:Teaspoon|teaspoon]] [[Cookbook:Cinnamon|cinnamon]], ground 
*1 teaspoon [[Cookbook:Nutmeg|nutmeg]], ground 
*1 teaspoon [[Cookbook:Allspice|allspice]], ground 
*1 teaspoon dried onion powder
*2 teaspoons dried [[Cookbook:Thyme|thyme]] 
*1 tablespoon [[Cookbook:Sugar|sugar]] 
*1 tablespoon dried minced [[Cookbook:Onion|onion]] 
*1 tablespoon [[Cookbook:Salt|salt]] 

''or''

*4 tablespoon ground [[Cookbook:Allspice|allspice]] 
*1 tablespoon ground dried [[Cookbook:Thyme|thyme]] 
*1 tablespoon [[Cookbook:Paprika|paprika]] 
*1 teaspoon ground [[Cookbook:Red Pepper|red pepper]] 
*1 teaspoon [[Cookbook:Garlic|garlic]] powder 
*1 teaspoon [[Cookbook:Onion|onion]] powder 
*1 teaspoon [[Cookbook:Salt|salt]]  
*½ teaspoon [[Cookbook:Pepper|black pepper]]

[[Category:Recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Jamaican recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Spice Mix recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>napwzckmv3fwsztpk27pwd7kze2ycp6</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Jamaican Jerk Chicken</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4024</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2685167</id>
      <parentid>2605628</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-07-27T18:19:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Austncorp</username>
        <id>1540792</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Adjusted cats.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{recipe}} | [[Cookbook:Cuisine of Jamaica|Jamaican cuisine]]
__NOTOC__
==Ingredients==
* 1/2 tsp ground allspice
* 1 tsp salt
* 1 tsp black pepper
* 2 tbsp cayenne pepper
* 1/2 tsp ground ginger
* 1 tsp ground cinnamon
* 1/4 tsp freshly grated nutmeg
* 1/2 tbsp dried thyme
* 2 tbsp dehydrated lemon peel
* 3 tbsp dark rum
* 4 boneless skinless chicken breasts
* 1/4 cup brown mustard

== Procedure ==
#Combine rum and mustard and rub all over chicken.
#Combine remaining ingredients and rub all over chicken. Refrigerate for at least 1 hour.(Better if marinated over night
#Place on a greased preheated charcoal grill and cook, turning constantly until internal temperature reaches 165°F. Remove and let rest for 10 minutes. Serves 4.

==Tips, tricks and variations==
The spices always included allspice because the berries of the pimento tree are the source of allspice.
When cooking the meat, barbecue is by far the best technique, failing that oven bake. Basting with beer is worth trying. Serve with rice and peas.

==Warnings==
See the [[Cookbook:Chili Pepper#Precautions|chili pepper]] warnings.


[[Category:Jamaican recipes]]
[[Category:Chicken recipes]]
[[Category:Grilled recipes]]
[[Category:Rum recipes]]</text>
      <sha1>awfta47ds3higoevvoqjcq5ag3zhi3y</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Goulash</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4025</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2683677</id>
      <parentid>2506963</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-07-22T13:09:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Austncorp</username>
        <id>1540792</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Added potato, stew, and boiled cats.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{recipesummary|Hungarian recipes|||2}}
__NOTOC__
{{recipe}}

'''Goulash''' ('''Gulyás''' in [[w:Hungarian language|Hungarian]], meaning cattle stockmen) is a dish from the [[Cookbook:Cuisine of Hungary|Hungarian cuisine]]. 
Here is one very simple Goulash stew recipe, being pretty close to the idealised version.
It is important not to use hot paprika, use the red powder sold simply as &quot;paprika&quot; in most supermarkets instead, hot peppers (chilli) would make the soup too spicy and of the wrong consistency when used exclusively. They can be used for flavouring in various degrees instead.
Sweet paprika can be obtained from [[Cookbook:Cuisine of Poland|Polish]] or central [[Cookbook:European cuisines|European]] delicatessens and specialist supermarkets. It is normally sold in 250 [[Cookbook:g|g]] sachets.

==Ingredients== 
* 3 [[Cookbook:Onion|onions]]
* 1 and a half pound (750 g) [[Cookbook:Beef|beef]]
* 4 [[Cookbook:Potato|potatoes]]
* 2 [[Cookbook:Bell Pepper| bell pepper]]s
* 1 [[Cookbook:Tomato|tomato]]
* 2 tbsp [[Cookbook:Paprika| ground sweet paprika]]
* 5 [[Cookbook:Black Pepper| black peppercorn]] 
* 1 [[Cookbook:Bay Leaf|bay leaf]] 
* a half [[Cookbook:Garlic|garlic]] (6 whole cloves)
*[[Cookbook:Olive Oil|olive oil]]
* salt to taste

==Procedure==
# Chop the onions and the vegetables. Fry half of the onions in the pot. Take some beef (leg or stringy meat) and cut it into small cubes. 
#Put a layer of meat on the bottom of a pot over the fried onions, then a layer of onions, vegetables, the whole garlic cloves, spices and salt. (Wait with the potato). Add another meat layer; continue until you have used all the ingredients, except the potato.  
#Cover the meat with water. Put on a lid, simmer on low heat. Add water only if there is not enough while cooking. It requires almost no stirring. 
#When the meat is cooked, add large pieces of potatoes, add water to cover it if needed, and cook for further 15 minutes.

==Notes, tips and variations==
*Its colour could be even nicer if you add more paprika in the last 10 minutes.
* Add half pound lean cubed pork meat (if you wish) after 20 minutes.
* If you're not afraid of [[Cookbook:Fat|fat]]s add some bacon to the dish.
* A pinch of caraway (seeds or grounded) is often used (''caraway'' not cumin)

==External links==
* [http://www.hungarianbookstore.com/goulash.htm Short essay about Hungarian goulash]
* Origin: http://dezso.klebercz.hu/konyha_gulyas_recept.htm (Hungarian)

[[Category:Hungarian recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Beef recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Potato recipes]]
[[Category:Stew recipes]]
[[Category:Boiled recipes]]
[[Category:Recipes with metric units|{{PAGENAME}}]]

[[nl:Kookboek/Goulash]]</text>
      <sha1>g2yvrxwgwl45b1ndz6eucb9zjqfh0lt</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Cuisine of Hungary</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4026</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2693771</id>
      <parentid>1874997</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-23T00:21:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Austncorp</username>
        <id>1540792</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Corrected Rakott Krumpli link.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{cuisine|Hungary}} | [[Cookbook:European cuisines|European cuisines]]

'''Hungarian cooking'''
Traditional Hungarian cuisine relies on a wide variety of high quality ingredients produced in the country including meats, seasonal vegetables, fruits and honey.

Here are some recipes:
*[[Cookbook:Goulash|Goulash Stew]] (''pörkölt'')
*[[Cookbook:Goulash Soup|Goulash Soup]] (''gulyás leves'')
*[[Cookbook:Paprika Chicken|Paprika Chicken]] (''paprikás csirke'')
*[[Cookbook:Potato Casserole (Rakott Krumpli)|Rackott Krumpli]] (''rakott krumpli''), potato casserole
*[[Cookbook:Silvash Gombotz|Silvash Gombotz]] (''szilvás gombóc''), plum dumplings
*[[Cookbook:Kifli|Vanilla Kifli]], crescent shaped sweet pastry

'''Starters'''

Soup is the quintessential Hungarian starter, and there are literally hundreds of types including cold fruit soups in summer. Another Hungarian speciality is various types of entrails, tripe or particularly pork, duck and goose liver. (foie gras - goose liver).
 
'''Main Dishes'''

Various types of meats are key to many main dishes, particularly pork, beef and chicken. Two breeds unique to Hungary are the Mangalica pig and the Grey long-horned cattle. Game meats such as venison, vild goose,  pheasant and wild boar are also common.  Fresh water fish such as trout, pike, perch and carp are used in the Hungarian cuisine. Potatoes are the usual accompaniment to many dishes, but rice, egg barley, dumplings and pasta are also used. Onions, garlic caravay, parsley and fresh or ground [[Cookbook:Paprika|paprika]] add flavour to many dishes.

'''Desserts and Cakes'''

Hungarians are passionate about their desserts and cakes. A typical dessert is pancakes stuffed with jam, sweet curd cheese or the Gundel pankake, hazelnut puree and served with chocolate sauce. Hungarian cakes tend to be very sweet and are often laced with cream. Famous examples include Dobos and Esterhazy Cakes. Strudel is as much a Hungarian as an Austrian dish, and is typically filled with apple, sour cherries, curd cheese or poppy seeds.

[[Category:Hungarian recipes| ]]</text>
      <sha1>2a6dzmstuk0l1uyrhxvy1v4s5rlkw8y</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Cuisine of Jamaica</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4027</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1868344</id>
      <parentid>1380734</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-06-29T12:33:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Zollerriia</username>
        <id>117986</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>2</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{cuisine|Jamaica}} | [[Cookbook:North American cuisines|North American cuisines]] | [[Cookbook:Caribbean cuisines|Caribbean cuisines]]

*[[Cookbook:Jamaican Chicken Fingers with Honey-Mustard Sauce|Jamaican Chicken Fingers with Honey-Mustard Sauce]]
*[[Cookbook:Jamaican Jerk Spice|Jamaican Jerk Spice]]
*[[Cookbook:Jamaican Jerk Chicken|Jamaican Jerk Chicken]]
*[[Cookbook:Hot Pepper Sauce|West Indian Hot Pepper Sauce]]
*[[Cookbook:Jamaican_patty|Jamaican Patty]]

[[Category:Jamaican recipes| ]]</text>
      <sha1>s5aoa5ffqgjgb835t9x2z08gby1kaft</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:24.43.150.107</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>4028</id>
    <revision>
      <id>155845</id>
      <timestamp>2004-01-23T02:14:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Karl Wick</username>
        <id>6</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Your destructive edits have been undone, please contribute only in a constructive way. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]</text>
      <sha1>e84s1rtez0mt9s66jrtb2awgqbl8dgt</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Guacamole</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4029</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2679750</id>
      <parentid>2653200</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-07-08T21:22:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Austncorp</username>
        <id>1540792</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Changed 'dips' to 'Dip recipes' cat per the renaming of that cat. Suppressed TOC since the various recipes are just numbered.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{recipe}} | [[Cookbook:Cuisine of Mexico|Mexican]] | [[Cookbook:Tex-Mex cuisine|Tex-Mex cuisine]] | [[Cookbook:Appetizers|Appetizers]]
__NOTOC__
[[Image:Guacamole.jpg|right|thumb|300px|Guacamole is a Mexican dish made from crushed avocado]]

'''Guacamole''' is a spicy [[Cookbook:Cuisine of Mexico|Mexican]] paste made from crushed avocado and various [[Cookbook:Herbs and Spices|seasonings]], usually including [[Cookbook:Onion|onions]], [[Cookbook:Chili Pepper|peppers]], [[Cookbook:Garlic|garlic]] and [[Cookbook:Tomato|tomatoes]].  Guacamole is used as a condiment, an ingredient, and as an [[Cookbook:Appetizers|appetizer]] when served with [[Cookbook:Tortilla Chip|tortilla chips]].

==Recipe I==
===Ingredients===
*4 [[Cookbook:Avocado|avocado]]s
*2 [[Cookbook:Tablespoon|tablespoons]] [[Cookbook:Pico de Gallo|pico de gallo]]
*Juice of 1/2 [[Cookbook:Lime|lime]]
*2 chopped [[Cookbook:Jalapeño|Jalapeño]] OR 2 tablespoons crushed [[Cookbook:Red Pepper|red pepper]] OR 1 tablespoon [[Cookbook:Cayenne Pepper|cayenne pepper]]
*1 [[Cookbook:Teaspoon|teaspoon]] [[Cookbook:Salt|salt]]
*4 teaspoon [[Cookbook:Olive Oil|olive oil]]
*1 1/2 teaspoon chopped [[Cookbook:Garlic|garlic]]
*1/2 teaspoon ground [[Cookbook:Black Pepper|black pepper]]
*1 minced jalapeño OR 2 minced [[Cookbook:Chile Pepper|serrano chiles]] OR 2 tablespoon minced any chile pepper like (adjust for spiciness)

===Procedure===
Pit the avocados. Score avocado  without cutting through the skin. Scoop out one avocado with a large spoon and place in mixing bowl. Add the lime juice and stir to evenly coat the avocados. Stir in the Pico de Gallo, garlic, oil, jalapeño, salt,  red pepper, and black pepper, mashing and tossing the avocado pieces until thoroughly mixed. Then scoop out the other avocados and gently mix and toss in the larger pieces. The guacamole is the right consistency when more large pieces than mashed parts remain. Garnish with a sprig of cilantro.

==Recipe II==
''The ingredients and quantities of this recipe are tuned to the tastes of one contributor; you should experiment with it. (Especially note that it has got rather a lot of lime, and you might want to add peppers, chilis or tabasco.)''

===Ingredients===
*2 very ripe [[Cookbook:Avocado|avocados]]
*1 clove [[Cookbook:Garlic|garlic]], chopped
*[[Cookbook:Juice|juice]] of 1 1/2 [[Cookbook:Lime|limes]]
*1 small [[Cookbook:Onion|Red onion]], [[Cookbook:Dice|diced]] very small
*1 small [[Cookbook:Tomato|tomato]], diced very small
*2 [[Cookbook:Tablespoon|tbsp]] chopped [[Cookbook:Cilantro|cilantro]] (coriander leaves)
*[[Cookbook:Salt|salt]] to taste

===Procedure===
Put everything except the avocados into a medium-sized mixing bowl. Halve the avocados and scoop the flesh into the bowl. Using a large fork (or a [[Cookbook:Blender|blender]]), mash the avocados and combine with all the other ingredients. Taste the mixture and add anything you think necessary (be aware that the flavors, especially the lime, will soften a little by the time it is served). Cover and refrigerate for at least an hour to allow the flavors to blend. When it is removed from the refrigerator, there may be some brown on the top, to avoid brown, add guacamole pit to preserve. - scrape it off.

==Recipe III==

This alternative recipe is somewhat simpler, but gives an extremely tasty Guacamole which is great with [[Cookbook:Tortilla Chip|tortilla chips]] or [[Cookbook:Vegetable|vegetables]], or can be used in [[Cookbook:Enchilada|enchiladas]], etc. It also avoids messing about with messy [[Cookbook:Tomato|tomatoes]], or coriander, which some people do not like the taste of. I have tried many guacamole recipes over the years, this is both the simplest, and in my opinion, the tastiest I know.

===Ingredients===
*3 whole [[Cookbook:Avocado|avocados]], ripe but not over-ripe
*1 [[Cookbook:Lime|lime]]
*3 cloves [[Cookbook:Garlic|garlic]]
*2 or 3 whole red [[Cookbook:Chili Pepper|chilli peppers]]
*[[Cookbook:Salt|salt]]

===Procedure===
Prepare avocados by halving and removing the stone (the simplest way to do this is to hold the avocado in the palm of your hand and strike the stone squarely and firmly with a chef's knife - the knife will then pull the stone out easily. If it doesn't come out easily, the avocado isn't ripe enough). Keep one half avocado back, skin and blend the rest using a hand-held food processor, add the juice of the lime, finely chop chillies and garlic, add and blend a bit longer. Add generous salt to taste. Finally roughly chop avocado half kept back and add to paste to give chunky texture. Resulting dip will keep for several days in a fridge, shouldn't brown too much if covered (the lime juice will act as an antioxidant as well as giving a nice flavour), but in general will be found to disappear very rapidly by enthusiastic consumers!

==Recipe IV (quick)==
This recipe is great if you have the ripe avocados because you can make it in about five minutes.

===Ingredients===
* 3-4 ripe avocados
* juice of 1/2 lime
* mild store-bought salsa

===Procedure===
# Peel, seed, and mash the avocados.
# Add the juice of 1/2 lime.
# Stir in store bought (but fresh) mild or medium salsa to taste.
# Serve immediately.

===Variant===
# For fancier version, make your own [[Cookbook:Pico de Gallo|Pico de Gallo]] for use instead of store-bought salsa

==Recipe V (simple)==
This is a rather simple recipe, needing only avocado, lime, dried chili and salt.

===Ingredients===
*1 ripe [[Cookbook:Avocado|avocado]]
*1/2 a [[Cookbook:Lime|lime]]
*[[Cookbook:Chili Pepper|red pepper]] flakes - to taste 
*[[Cookbook:Salt|salt]] - to taste
Note: fresh hot peppers also work well, instead of the red pepper flakes, if available - if used, slice them finely.

===Procedure===
Peel the avocado and pit it, then slice the avocado into small chunks, around a [[Cookbook:cm|centimeter]] or half-[[Cookbook:Inch|inch]] per side.  Juice half the lime.  Add the lime, some salt, and a moderate amount of red pepper to the avocado chunks.  Err on the side of adding too little spice; it's easy to add more, but too much makes the guacamole really scorch.  Mash the ingredients together.

==Recipe VI (simplest)==
This recipe is the simplest of the group. It is very simple and more attuned to use as an additive. This recipe is a more traditional Mexican guacamole and does not include many of the features commonly associated with the dish be Americans used to the Tex-Mex Version.

===Ingredients===
*2 ripe [[Cookbook:Avocado|avocados]]
*juice of 1/2 lime
*2 tablespoons (app.) chopped [[Cookbook:Cilantro|cilantro]]
*salt to taste

===Procedure===
Pit avocado by, carefully, lodging base end of chef's knife in pit, twisting to remove, and then pinching the pit off of the knife. Remove flesh with large spoon, being careful to maintain the integrity of the flesh. Dice in large chunks and transfer to mixing bowl. Mash to desired consistency. Add lime, stire to combine. Add other ingredients, stir to combine.

==Recipe VII==
Similar to the first and second recipes, this variant acts very well on its own as a side dish or appetizer, also very good in [[Cookbook:Fajita|fajitas]]. This recipe can easily be multiplied beyond the two avocado serving.

===Ingredients===
*2 ripe [[Cookbook:Avocado|avocado]]
*2-3 tablespoons chopped [[Cookbook:Cilantro|cilantro]] 
*1/4 cup (app.) of [[Cookbook:Tomato|cherry, grape, or pear tomatoes]] halved or quartered, with 1/8 cup (app.) seeded
*juice of 1 [[Cookbook:Lime|lime]], thoroughly juiced
*4 tablespoons (app.) chopped [[Cookbook:Cilantro|cilantro]]
*1/2 red onion, diced
*2 jalapeño peppers, 1 seeded and 1 not, diced finely
*Kosher salt and extra virgin olive oil to taste

===Procedure===
Pit avocado by, carefully, lodging base end of chef's knife in pit, twisting to remove, and then pinching the pit off of the knife. Remove flesh with large spoon, being careful to maintain the integrity of the flesh. Dice in large chunks and transfer to mixing bowl. Mash to desired consistency. Add lime, stir to combine. Add other ingredients, stir to combine.

===Recommended Uses===
Works well on [[Cookbook:Bean|beans]], in [[Cookbook:Taco|tacos]] and other Mexican food, or even as a topping for [[Cookbook:Bread|bread]].  It also can add flavor and moisture to overly dry food. However, perhaps the best use is as a dip for tortilla chips.

===Variant===
Avocado salad can be made by not mashing the avocado chunks.  Optionally, add a grated [[Cookbook:Carrot|carrot]].  This makes a good side dish or small meal.

----
'''Note''':  True guacamole is only mashed avocado with cilantro, and onion, optionally (yet desirable) hot peppers can be mashed along with the avocado. Oil is never used, olives aren't Mexican, so olive oil should be avoided. It should also be noted that guacamole is a dip sauce originally made so it will be consumed almost instantly, meaning there is no intention to store it at all, so you can omit the use of any kind of oils for these recipes, or even lime juice. Both oil and lime juice are added so guacamole lasts a bit longer than normal.
----

'''Tip''': An old [[Cookbook:Cuisine of Mexico|Mexican]] trick to avoid or reduce the brown oxidized layer on the top is to put the whole avocado pit back into the guacamole once it's prepared. ''Never'' cut the pit in pieces; that will make the guacamole bitter. This trick doesn't really work though. The only way to prevent the oxidation is to eliminate the exposure to air. Covering the surface with plastic wrap so no air is in contact with the sauce works well. Be sure to include some lime in your recipe, this will prevent such oxidation. 

----
'''Tip 2''': 

One of the most vexing problems with guacamole is that it spoils so rapidly. Traditional strategies, such as the use of a well-placed avocado pit or the use of prodigious amounts the lime and/or lemon juice, are used to prevent premature browning of guacamole. A young chef from El Paso, Texas, has developed a much more effective approach to keep guacamole fresh for up to three times longer than traditional methods. Through trial and error, Alfred M. Gladstein found that the use of a various vegetable oils blended in to the concoction would keep it fresh longer and significantly increase the amount of time before the guacamole browns and spoils. In his studies Gladstein found that mixing olive oil in guacamole worked best when serving the dish independently or with warm foods, while vegetable oil (corn or canola) worked best when the guacamole is served with cold foods and salads. When these techniques are employed, Gladstein, who is also known as Chef Jamir, found that the refrigerated guacamole would stay fresh and green for three days or more. He also notes that when serving the guacamole at room temperature, the oil-treated dish will last up to six to eight hours before starting to brown.


[[Category:Mexican recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Tex-Mex recipes]]
[[Category:Appetizer recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Dip recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Vegan recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Sauce recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Avocado recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Featured recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Recipes with metric units|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Recipes with images]]</text>
      <sha1>77ruh77djoxavdack7s4jq8dqlrmwe9</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Preserved Lemon</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4030</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1783170</id>
      <parentid>969503</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-04-28T21:01:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{recipe}} | [[Cookbook:Cuisine of Morocco|Moroccan Cuisine]]

'''Preserved Lemons''' are a common flavoring agent in Moroccan cuisine, particularly in very slow braises known as tagines.  They are also found as an unusual cocktail garnish.

== Ingredients ==
*[[Cookbook:Lemon|Lemons]]
*[[Cookbook:Salt|Salt]]

== Procedure ==
Poke holes in the lemons with a sharp knife.  Pack them in an airtight jar, separating them from one another with salt.  Cover the jar, store in a dark place for a day.  If the lemons have not released enough liquid to cover, add salt and reseal.

Store in a cool dark place for approximately two weeks.  Refrigerate afterwards.

See also: [[Cookbook:Pickling]]

[[Category:Lemon recipes|Preserved Lemon]]
[[Category:Vegan recipes|Preserved Lemon]]
[[Category:Moroccan recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>5325y305aozqthqtuo3me683eq9bu7j</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Cuisine of Mexico</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4031</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2657894</id>
      <parentid>2657682</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-05-19T16:53:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mercurywoodrose</username>
        <id>477878</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{cuisine|Mexico}} | [[Cookbook:North American cuisines|North American cuisines]]

Mexican cuisine is primarily a fusion of indigenous Mesoamerican cooking with European, especially Spanish, elements added after the Spanish conquest of the Aztec Empire in the 16th century. The basic staples remain native foods such as corn, beans and chili peppers, but the Europeans introduced a large number of other foods, the most important of which were meat from domesticated animals.

==Regional Cuisines of Mexico==
*[[Cookbook:Cuisine of Jalisco|Cuisine of Jalisco]]
*[[Cookbook:Cuisine of Yucatan|Cuisine of Yucatan]]

==Recipes==
This is a list of recipes identified as part of Mexican cuisine. It does not include recipes based in part on Mexican ingredients, but which are not indigenous to Mexico itself.

* [[Cookbook:Adobo sauce|Adobo sauce]]
* [[Cookbook:Atropellado de coco|Atropellado de coco]]
* [[Cookbook:Bizcochito|Bizcochito]]
* [[Cookbook:Buñuelos|Buñuelos]]
* [[Cookbook:Burrito|Burrito]]
* [[Cookbook:Camotes enmielados|Camotes enmielados]]
* [[Cookbook:Chilaquiles|Chilaquiles]]
* [[Cookbook:Chiles en nogada|Chiles en nogada]]
* [[Cookbook:Churros|Churros]]
* [[Cookbook:Cochinita pibil|Cochinita pibil]]
* [[Cookbook:Enchilada|Enchilada]]
* [[Cookbook:Flour Tortilla|Flour Tortilla]]
* [[Cookbook:Guacamole|Guacamole]]
* [[Cookbook:Huevos divorciados|Huevos divorciados]]
* [[Cookbook:Huevos Rancheros|Huevos Rancheros]]
* [[Cookbook:Horchata|Horchata]]
* [[Cookbook:Machacado con huevo|Machacado con huevo]]
* [[Cookbook:Menudo|Menudo]]
* [[Cookbook:Mexican Seasoning|Mexican Seasoning]]
* [[Cookbook:Mexican Tomato Soup|Mexican Tomato Soup]]
* [[Cookbook:Pico de Gallo|Pico de Gallo]]
* [[Cookbook:Quesadilla|Quesadilla]]
* [[Cookbook:Refried Beans|Refried Beans]]
* [[Cookbook:Salsa Fresca|Salsa Fresca]]
* [[Cookbook:Taco|Taco]]
* [[Cookbook:Taco Meat|Taco Meat]]
* [[Cookbook:Tacos de bistec|Tacos de bistec]]
* [[Cookbook:Tortilla|Tortilla]]
* [[Cookbook:Tortilla Chip|Tortilla Chip]]
* [[Cookbook:Tres leches cake|Tres leches cake]]

==See also==
*The following cuisines have strong influences from Mexican cuisine:
* [[Cookbook:California cuisine|California cuisine]]
* [[Cookbook:Tex-Mex cuisine|Tex-Mex cuisine]]
* [[Cookbook:Southwestern cuisine|Southwestern cuisine]]

[[Category:Mexican recipes|Mexican recipes]]

[[fr:Livre de cuisine/Recettes de cuisine mexicaine]]</text>
      <sha1>3pq49pacv8jsmx388yrvtl7yb9oxi4t</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Quesadilla</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4032</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2689088</id>
      <parentid>2645887</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-06T02:01:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Austncorp</username>
        <id>1540792</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Added appropriate cats. Minor text adjustments.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{recipe}} | [[Cookbook:Appetizers|Appetizers]] | [[Cookbook:Cuisine of Mexico|Mexico]] | [[Cookbook:Southwestern cuisine|Southwestern U.S. cuisine]] | [[Cookbook:Tex-Mex cuisine|Tex-Mex cuisine]]

Similar to a sandwich, the amount of ingredients for a quesadilla depends on how many you are serving and how big you want to make a particular quesadilla.  Here are ingredients for one serving using the typical size of tortillas most commonly available in stores in the southwestern U.S. (and in many other areas and countries).  Other locally available thin flat breads may work instead of work of tortillas, but, please know, the tortillas are intended to be similar to a 'wrap' to allow the eating of the filling.

==Ingredients==
*2 flour [[Cookbook:Tortilla|tortilla]], 6&quot; (15cm), corn tortillas can be used in a pinch at home, but may not hold together or work as well as flour.
*1/3 cup meltable [[Cookbook:cheese|cheese]]
*1/4 cup Filling (see below)
*[[Cookbook:Cooking Spray|Cooking Spray]]

==Procedure==
#Warm both tortillas in the microwave to the point of flexibility, at least, keeping one warm.
#Preheat a frying pan or griddle (medium-low heat), seasoned with oil or cooking spray. Drop in the first tortilla.
#Drop on it shredded cheese (typically [[Cookbook:Monterey Jack Cheese|Monterey Jack cheese]]).
#Quickly add, and spread out, almost to the edges, any combination of the fillings listed below (or whatever additional ingredients you would like), ideally warmed and very well drained.
# Allow the cheese to melt. The tortilla may brown in spots but it should not be cooked to the point of changing color substantially.
#Press the other tortilla over the top of the tortilla in the pan, making sure it sticks a bit.
#Flip the quesadilla and allow to warm until it joins as a unit.  
#Remove from pan, cut in 1/8ths.
#Eat immediately, or, if you need to serve a bigger group, remove to a fairly low temperature 'keep warm' area, below the melting temperature of the 
cheese.

Quesadillas are not usually not very good re-heated.

==Filings==
*[[Cookbook:Salsa|salsa]]
* [[Cookbook:Sarza Criolla|sarza criolla]]
* [[Cookbook:Chili Pepper|chili pepper]]s
* Chopped [[Cookbook:Tomato|tomatoes]] and [[Cookbook:Cilantro|cilantro]]
* Cooked [[Cookbook:Meat and Poultry|meat or seafood]]
* Fresh spinach--washed and torn into small pieces
* Black beans--canned, rinsed and well drained
* A fairly traditional filling would be grilled chicken, beef or pork, finely minced, sprinkled with a teaspoon of finely minced onion and half of teaspoon of cilantro, with a small amount of some lime squeezed on top.

Usage Note: Some regions of Mexico the quesadilla is a simple corn tortilla with cheese,non-fried.

==Notes, tips, and variations==
#[[Cookbook:Crab Quesadillas with Mango Salsa|Crab Quesadillas with Mango Salsa]]

[[Category:Tortilla recipes]]
[[Category:Cheese recipes]]
[[Category:Cilantro recipes]]
[[Category:Mexican recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Southwestern recipes]]
[[Category:Tex-Mex recipes]]
[[Category:Appetizer recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>b1g1klmldhhm6mxn3f65ti23jrlpez8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Cuisine of Morocco</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4033</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2225617</id>
      <parentid>2225606</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-12-01T13:03:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Frigotoni</username>
        <id>393200</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/212.30.31.29|212.30.31.29]] ([[User talk:212.30.31.29|talk]]) to last version by Zollerriia</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{cuisine|Morocco}} | [[Category:African cuisines|African cuisines]]

Moroccan cuisine has long been considered as one of the most diversified cuisines in the world. The reason is because of the interaction of Morocco with the outside world for centuries. The cuisine of Morocco is a mix of Arab, Berber, Moorish, Middle Eastern, Mediterranean African, Iberian, and Jewish influences. The cooks in the royal kitchens of Fez, Meknes, Marrakech, Rabat and Tetouan refined Moroccan cuisine over the centuries and created the basis for what is known as Moroccan cuisine today.

Morocco produces a large range of Mediterranean fruits and vegetables and even some tropical ones. The country produces large quantities of sheep, cattle, poultry, and seafood which serve as a base for the cuisine.

==Recipes==

*[[Cookbook:Preserved Lemon|Preserved Lemon]]
*[[Cookbook:Moroccan Salad|Moroccan Salad]]
*[[Cookbook:Liver Kebabs|Liver Kebabs]]

[[Category:Moroccan recipes]]

[[fr:Livre de cuisine/Recettes de cuisine marocaine]]</text>
      <sha1>7w7oi3iv9lx8fbparvmdzmnmvfq36cb</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Tomato Pasta</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4034</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2691745</id>
      <parentid>2621204</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-16T01:22:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Austncorp</username>
        <id>1540792</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Added appropriate cats.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{recipesummary|Pasta recipes|3|20-25 minutes|2||700 Cal/2900 kJ}}

{{recipe}}

== Ingredients ==
* 300 g (10 oz) large [[Cookbook:Pasta|pasta]] spirals (dry)
* 2 Tablespoons of extra virgin [[Cookbook:Olive Oil|olive oil]], more if you like it
* 2 large [[Cookbook:Garlic|garlic]] cloves, crushed and finely chopped, more if you like it
* 4 large ripe [[Cookbook:Tomato|tomatoes]], well chopped, seeds and skin included. Remove the seeds and skin if you like, but it isn't mandatory.
* handful of well ripped [[Cookbook:Basil|basil]] leaves
* [[Cookbook:Salt|salt]] and [[Cookbook:Pepper|pepper]], to taste
* 4 Tablespoons of freshly, finely grated [[Cookbook:Parmesan Cheese|Parmesan]]-style [[Cookbook:Cheese|cheese]] ([[Cookbook:Parmigiano Reggiano|Parmigiano Reggiano]] recommended!)

== Procedure ==
# Cook dry pasta in plenty of salted boiling water for 10-12 minutes. By the way, the proper cooking time should be indicated on the pasta box itself. If it's not, you better taste one pasta piece from time to time, and stop the cooking when it's still crispy but not tough though (it should be ''[[Cookbook:Al dente|al dente]]''). Prepare the sauce while the pasta is cooking:
# '''Sauce:''' Heat the olive oil gently in a large [[Cookbook:Frying Pan|frying pan]] or [[Cookbook:Wok|wok]]. When moderately hot add the garlic and gently [[Cookbook:Pan fry|fry]] until lightly coloured only. Avoid overcooking. Add the tomatoes and cook for several minutes, stirring and folding the ingredients. If there is a lot of liquid from the tomatoes, turn up the heat a little and reduce it a bit. Stir in the basil and turn the heat down.
# By this time the pasta should be cooked. Turn off the heat to the pasta and use a slotted spoon to transfer the pasta to the sauce in the other pan. Don't worry if a little of the cooking water is transferred - this is a good thing as long as you don't swamp the sauce with it(you could also use a colander to drain the pasta alternatively). Season to taste, stir and pour into a large pasta bowl for serving. Scatter the cheese over the whole dish, reserving some for the table.

[[Category:Pasta recipes|Tomato Pasta]]
[[Category:Pasta sauce recipes]]
[[Category:Boiled recipes]]
[[Category:Side dish recipes]]
[[Category:Vegetarian recipes|Tomato Pasta]]
[[Category:Tomato recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Recipes with metric units|{{PAGENAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>ieb5ff0ff07plaznntsler3v2gi6kjb</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Mace</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4035</id>
    <redirect title="Cookbook:Nutmeg" />
    <revision>
      <id>155852</id>
      <timestamp>2004-01-23T06:53:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Gentgeen</username>
        <id>279</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>For right now, it's better that it go somewhere</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">#REDIRECT [[Cookbook:Nutmeg]]</text>
      <sha1>k8rsuufg5jqjyt4qocot2kecogwnbxk</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook talk:Recipes</title>
    <ns>103</ns>
    <id>4040</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1254492</id>
      <parentid>789334</parentid>
      <timestamp>2008-08-19T03:02:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mike Hayes</username>
        <id>65007</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* kinds of sugar */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[en:User:Angela]] and I are [[m:Transwiki|Transwiki]]ng wikipedia recipes into the [[Transwiki]] psudonamespace.  If someone wants to go through the transwiki log and work on those articles and bring them to Wikibooks standards, feel free.  It'll add more content to the cookbook faster, as right now I'm going to concentrate on moving the pages out of wikipedia.  Thanks, [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] 09:49, 23 Jan 2004 (UTC)

----
OK, we need to come to a naming convention for recipes.  I've been using Cookbook:&lt;Recipe Name&gt;, others are using Cookbook:Recipes/&lt;Recipe Name&gt; or Cookbook:Recipes/&lt;Recipe name&gt;.  It'll be easier to pick a standard now and just name things as we move them from wikipedia than it will be to decide later.  Anyone else want to weigh in? [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] 09:11, 29 Jan 2004 (UTC)

:OK, I'm going to give this a week and if no one replies, I'll assume I'm the only one here and just pick my standard and start moving recipes to &lt;nowiki&gt;[[Cookbook:Recipe Name]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;.  Time starts .... NOW [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] 08:44, 3 Feb 2004 (UTC)

::Personally I like your system. It's simpler. Also I can see a situation where we need subpages for recipes [[cookbook:recipe Name /european verion]] that soer of thing. [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 09:03, 3 Feb 2004 (UTC)

::Yes, I started the Cookbook:recipies/* standard just to be descriptive and it the Cookbook:* standard does seem like a better idea. [[User:The Grimm Ripper|Grimm]]

==Questionable Ingredients==

==== kinds of sugar ====

Query: Does anyone know what &quot;Castor sugar&quot; is? Is it a brand name or a type of sugar? As long as I'm at it I may as well make a list on this page of questionable ingrediants. [[User:The Grimm Ripper|Grimm]]
: I guess it's a British thing?  Castor sugar is a very fine sugar.  You can make it by putting regular granulated sugar in a blender for a few seconds to make the grains finer. [[User:Solitaire|Solitaire]]
:: That is somewhat correct. Probaly you'll wear out your blender if you abuse it for this purpose! Castor sugar is called superfine sugar in the USA. Unfortunately, castor sugar is the ''default'' sugar in the UK. Many recipes specify it needlessly. As each such recipe is examined, &quot;castor sugar&quot; should be replaced with either &quot;superfine suger&quot; (to indicate a true need for superfine sugar) or just &quot;sugar&quot; (to indicate that any old normal sugar will do). [[User:AlbertCahalan|AlbertCahalan]] 19:38, 5 Apr 2005 (UTC)

::: Castor sugar is not the default sugar in the U.K. but it is used more frequently than in the United States because it is much more commonplace there. It is called &quot;castor sugar&quot; because it is fine enough to be used in a &quot;caster&quot; which is a &quot;shaker&quot;. [[User:Mike Hayes|Mike Hayes]] ([[User talk:Mike Hayes|talk]]) 03:02, 19 August 2008 (UTC)

*'golden syrup' - '''Cane Syrup''' 

:I'm sorry - I have to jump up and down and scream loudly at this comparison. Golden syrup is NOT corn syrup or anything remotely like it. It's a product used mainly in Australia (I don't know if it's available anywhere else...) It is a bit like molasses or treacle only lighter in flavour and consistency. Corn syrup is NOT a suitable substitute for it.[[User:Karen Johnson|KJ]] 06:46, 19 Mar 2004 (UTC)

::''we have stuff here in the US called ''Cane Syrup'', made from sugar cane, kinda like a light molasses.  Would that be a better compairason to golden syrup? [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]]''

:::Oh lord this is going to be a nightmare. I asked an american once what corn syrup was and was told it was golden syrup, I didn't check to see it was correct. On wikipedia there is an article on flapjacks, which redirects to pancakes. In the UK flapjacks are oatcakes made with rolled oats, butter amd golden syrup :-( why can't we all speak the same laguage :-( Anyway, I digress. In the UK golden syrup is made by Tate and Lyle. Since this company also label their granulated sugar as cane sugar I assume cane syrup is correct. Sorry about not checking my facts properly. [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 11:18, 19 Mar 2004 (UTC)

:::: &quot;Tate and Lyle's Golden Syrup&quot; has a pronounced flavour unlike anything generally available in the United States but maple syrup or imitation maple syrup would work well as a substitute. However, it tends to be thinner than golden syrup so one would have to reduce it by boiling to get a similar viscosity. [[User:Mike Hayes|Mike Hayes]] ([[User talk:Mike Hayes|talk]]) 03:02, 19 August 2008 (UTC)

*'Castor sugar' - '''Like granulated sugar only smaller crystals so it dissolves better''' - ''so it's like the US baking sugar or bar sugar? gent''
:Castor Sugar is a very finely ground sugar. You can use plain ordinary sugar in a recipe without a problem except the texture will be coarser.[[User:Karen Johnson|KJ]] 06:46, 19 Mar 2004 (UTC)
::I'm in the US, and sometimes I use &quot;powdered sugar&quot; -- like granulated sugar, but ground into a fine powder. http://sugarindia.com/ has some descriptions of various kinds of sugars. --[[User:DavidCary|DavidCary]] 18:05, 29 Oct 2004 (UTC)
Tate &amp; Lyle's Golden Syrup is, I quote from the tin, &quot;partially inverted refiners syrup&quot;, (that is, some of the sucrose is laevo-rotated, for the chemists out there) &amp; is commonly called treacle in the UK.
Black treacle is the dark stuff like mollasses.
Granulated sugar is your bog-standard sugar, castor sugar is finer, (for using in a caster?) &amp; icing sugar is (very fine, floury), I think, powderd sugar in US. We use it to make icing, (frosting) by mixing with water (&amp; eggwhite for Royal Icing). Hope this is useful, &amp; please correct me where im wrong--[[User:Archolman|Archolman]] 02:46, 6 March 2007 (UTC)

==== other ingredients ====

*&quot;375g of packet fresh ready rolled Puff pastry&quot; (see [[Cookbook:Mille_Cr%C3%AApe]]) - Any ideas on a universal equivilant? '''why not just link to a recipe for [[puff pastry]]?''' - ''whenever I use puff pastry, I go to the store and buy a box.  Actually, I normally have a box or two in the freezer.  Making puff pastry is hard, time consuming, work, and I'd rather pay Pillsbury to do it. gent''
:Frozen puff pastry is available just about everywhere... I don't see that direction as unreasonable wherever you are. But for perfectionists, link it to 'puff pastry' too so they can see how difficult it is to make from scratch! lol [[User:Karen Johnson|KJ]] 06:46, 19 Mar 2004 (UTC)

* &quot;2 small cans dry Mustard&quot; (see [[Cookbook:Senf]]) ''well, what's a small can?  1 oz, 4 oz?'' ( I've seen some cookbooks list *both* Imperial *and* SI units on each and every recipe. Should we encourage this ? Something like  &quot;50 g (1.7 oz.) dry ground Mustard&quot;. At least in one cookbook, the primary units were the ones used by the cook who submitted it. Usually ounces for U.S. chefs, grams for French chefs. The secondary units (in parenthesis) were converted. --[[User:DavidCary|DavidCary]] 18:05, 29 Oct 2004 (UTC) )  

:I'd say we should definitely encourage the use of both imperical and SI units. I've even gone through a few recipies that only have one set of units listed and done the conversions myself when I have too much free time. [[User:The Grimm Ripper|Grimm]]
:: Be very careful! Tablespoons can be 15 mL (Queen Anne), 18 mL (Imperial), or 20 mL (Australian). If you are unsure, let someone else do the conversion. [[User:AlbertCahalan|AlbertCahalan]] 19:38, 5 Apr 2005 (UTC)

Looks like some redirects are in order, once we've got the basic foodstuff articles written.  For the life of me I couldn't figure out what golden syrup or Castor sugar were, thanks Theresa. [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] 00:46, 19 Mar 2004 (UTC)

I did suggest that we need a 'glossary' page giving comparisons and equivelants like this. It's easy to get confused, because cooking is universal but ingredients are NOT... [[User:Karen Johnson|KJ]] 06:46, 19 Mar 2004 (UTC)

:I started a list of [[Cookbook:International food terms|International food terms]].  I listed US/UK terms, as that is what I'm familiar with.  I'm not sure if the UK terms are pretty much always the same as the Australian terms, and I could lump them together, or if there should be a separate column for Australian terms.

:I added it to the Ingredients section on the [[Cookbook]], along with the [[Cookbook:Substitutions|Substitutions]] list I started, although perhaps there's a better place for them. -- [[User:Loum|loum]] 04:19, 24 May 2004 (UTC)

The UK standard spoons are; Tspoon=5ml, Tablespoon=15ml. i think cup sizes are a bit different to US &amp; Aus.  as well:)--[[User:Archolman|Dick]] 23:13, 16 March 2007 (UTC)

==Featured recipes==
So far, I've just picked a recipe from this list about once a week to be our featured recipe on the [[cookbook]] page.  Anyone else want to get in on choosing the recipe? (and ingredient, but that discussion should go somewhere else) [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] 00:46, 19 Mar 2004 (UTC)

==Recipe cleanup?==
A few of the recipes need some work.  For example, look at [[Cookbook:Goulash|Goulash]], [[Cookbook:Jamaican Jerk Chicken|Jamaican Jerk Chicken]], and [[Cookbook:How to cook oysters|How to cook oysters]].  Should we have a central page for these types of cleanup items for the entire wikibooks project, one just for the cookbook, or just use, for example, this talk page to hold this list. [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] 08:57, 4 May 2004 (UTC)
:I would say create a link on the cookbook main page that refers to the &quot;Needs Work&quot; recipes. [[User:Liblamb|liblamb]] 16:48, 12 Jul 2004 (UTC)

== links to GFDL and public domain recipes ==

Should I copy-and-paste these recipes to wiki, even though I've never cooked them before ?

* http://www.faqs.org/docs/consumer/recipes/ (public domain)
* ''The Open Source Cookbook: Fuel For Geeks'' by Matthew Balmer (GFDL) http://www.faqs.org/docs/cookbook/
** this cookbook is GFDL 1.1, and contains front cover, back cover, and invariant texts.  All these things make importing sections from this book difficult under our use of this license.  I think discussion of this cookbook was brought up earlier at [[Talk:Cookbook]]. [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] 21:13, 29 Oct 2004 (UTC)

&quot;Copyright and Recipes&quot;
http://www.recipezaar.com/help/copyright.zsp

:I have no objections to you doing this.  If you do place them in Wikibooks, please make them conform to the template.  You might also want to be selective.  I have entered a number of recipes, one of which is [[Cookbook:Hominy_recipe|Hominy]], that I considered of interest but have not cooked. [[User:Liblamb|liblamb]] 20:00, 29 Oct 2004 (UTC)

----

== Some recipes aren't linked here ==

I've been searching for curry chiekn, but I just found when i find it, that its not listed here, in the recipe index!!  Can someone merge these &quot;lost recipes&quot; please?

Here's some:

[http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Cookbook:Meat_Recipes Cookbook:Meat_Recipes]
:Done [[User:Liblamb|liblamb]] 17:39, 3 Dec 2004 (UTC)

Yeah, I've been finding lots of &quot;lost&quot; recipes the past few days. [[User:The Grimm Ripper|Grimm]]

== Recipe Overviews ==

My wikisyntax is limited, but would it be easy to make a template out of the Overviews?
Also, if I think someone should link to a recipe with what may be considered the ideal format so people adding them have a good template to start with.
{| width=200px border=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;2&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot;  bgcolor=&quot;#f0f8ff&quot; align=&quot;right&quot;
!align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;|Overview
|-align-&quot;center&quot;
|----- 
||Category:
||[[Cookbook:Salad Recipes|Salads]]
|----- 
||Servings:
||2-4 People
|----- 
||Time:
||20 minutes
|----- 
||Difficulty:
|align=&quot;center&quot;|[[Image:1o5dots.svg|Fairly easy]]
|}

Cheers, --[[User:Bleh fu|bleh fu]] [[User talk:Bleh fu|&lt;small&gt;talk fu&lt;/small&gt;]] 15:49, 25 Jun 2005 (UTC)

== Conversation from #wikibooks IRC Channel ==

I have bought this conversation and idea here, from #wikibooks, and also from [[Talk:Cookbook|Cookbook Talk]], in the hope that I may be able to help.  I am on multiple restricted diets, being intolerant of Gluten and Lactose, so I am on a Wheat/Gluten Free and Milk Free diet.  One of WB's admins, Uncle G, has informed me that your recipes are marked for which diets they are suitable.  However, I have noticed looking through the index of recipes that there is no immediate identification of suitability for particular diets there.  I also feel that for meals which cross diets, ie, one which is both Gluten Free and Milk Free, having to match recipes from one category and see that they are in another is time consuming. 

What I have proposed is that we look at a simple identification tag to attach to recipes '''in''' the index, to show immediately to the searcher that the meal is gonna be suitable for them to cook.  

Something along these lines:

'''GF''' indicates Gluten Free recipe

'''MF''' = Milk Free

'''LF''' = Lactose Free

'''RS''' = Reduced Sodium (Salt)

which could be combined to show the suitability immediately, like:

Liver &amp; Bacon Casserole (GF : MF)

or for meals which are suitable for diabetics, DS.

Your thoughts on this are welcome, and I have tagged some pages already pointing people here to discuss this proposal.  I can be contacted here, or thru my Wikipedia talk page, [[Wikipedia:User_talk:Tmalmjursson|Talk to Thor]]. Regards, [[User:Tmalmjursson|Tmalmjursson]] 01:42, 1 February 2006 (UTC)

== is this still maintained? ==

wouldn't the category system be a better option? Especially for indicating whether recipes have images or not... [[User:203.214.115.130|203.214.115.130]] 14:32, 24 April 2006 (UTC)

: Yes the category system is better. [[:Category:Recipes]] will probably be better even at this stage of categorization. It will also be more maintainable over the long run. [[User:Kellen|Kellen]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:Kellen|T]]&lt;/sup&gt; 00:24, 1 May 2006 (UTC)

== Sindhi cuisine ==

There were some recipes on the Wikipedia page [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sindhi_food Sindhi food]. The article's [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Articles_for_deletion/Sindhi_food AfD] determined that the recipes should be transwikied here. I've put them on a subpage [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Fang_Aili/sindi_food_temp here], and anyone interested can copy them from there and place them appropriately at Wikibooks Cookbook. I'd appreciate help from someone who knows what they're doing here. Thanks! (I also posted this message at [[Cookbook talk:Cuisine of India]].) --[[User:Fang Aili|Fang Aili]] 23:29, 24 April 2006 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>q8kogxxgqu6pzj9zu22sy9kwbhglkr4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Tompagenet</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>4042</id>
    <revision>
      <id>155858</id>
      <parentid>12918</parentid>
      <timestamp>2004-01-23T16:22:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tompagenet</username>
        <id>354</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>bullet points</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">This is Tom Page's section on the great project that is WikiBooks. A couple of (hopefully) useful links:

* [[en:User:Tompagenet|My wikipedia page]]
* [http://www.tompagenet.co.uk My personal web page]</text>
      <sha1>a6gcpimcudkk3lrpdj64c0zufesr12r</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cryptography</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4043</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2689702</id>
      <parentid>2666574</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-08T03:19:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DavidCary</username>
        <id>973</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>mention nomenclator?</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">__NOTOC__ 
{{DISPLAYTITLE:&lt;span style=&quot;display:block;text-align:center;font-size:350%;font-style:italic;line-height:1em;&quot;&gt;Cryptography&lt;/span&gt;}}
&lt;center&gt;[[File:Jefferson's disk cipher.jpg|600x320px|Jefferson's disk cipher.]]&lt;/center&gt;{{clear}}
&lt;center&gt;Welcome to '''Cryptography''', the study of transforming information in order to make it secure from unintended recipients or use.&lt;/center&gt;
{{clear}}
{{Book Search|prefix=Cryptography}}
'''Part I: Introducing Cryptography'''
#[[Cryptography/Introduction|Introduction to Cryptography]]
#[[Cryptography/History|History of Cryptography]]
##[[Cryptography/Classical Cryptography|Classical Cryptography]]
##[[Cryptography/Contemporary Cryptography|Contemporary Cryptography]]
##[[Cryptography/Cryptography in Popular Culture|Cryptography in Popular Culture]]
##[[Cryptography/Timeline of Notable Events|Timeline of Notable Events]]
#Fundamental Concepts
##[[Cryptography/Goals of Cryptography|Goals of Cryptography]]
##[[Cryptography/Goals of Cryptanalysis|Goals of Cryptanalysis]]
##[[Cryptography/Cryptography in Computer Security|Role of Cryptography in Computer Security]]
##[[Cryptography/Symmetric Ciphers|Symmetric Key Ciphers]]
##[[Cryptography/Asymmetric Ciphers|Asymmetric Key Ciphers]]
##[[Cryptography/Random number generation|Random Number Generation]]
##[[Cryptography/Hashes|Hashes]]
##[[Cryptography/Key Distribution and Authentication|Key Distribution and Authentication]] (key management and the web of trust)
##[[Cryptography/Common flaws and weaknesses|Common flaws and weaknesses]]
##[[Cryptography/Secure Passwords|Secure Passwords]]
##[[/S-box/]]

'''Part II: Designing Cryptosystems'''
#[[Cryptography/Basic Design Principles|The Basic Principles]]
#[[Cryptography/Little Secrets Hide Bigger Secrets|Little Secrets Hide Bigger Secrets]]
#[[Cryptography/Open Algorithms|Open Algorithms and the Value of Peer-Review]]
#[[Cryptography/Think Like a Cryptanalyst|Think Like a Cryptanalyst]]
#[[Cryptography/Error Correction Systems]]
#[[Cryptography/Mathematical Background|Mathematical Background]]
#[[Cryptography/Computer Security is More Than Encryption|Computer Security is More Than Encryption]]
#[[Cryptography/Unbroken is Not Necessarily Unbreakable|Unbroken is Not Necessarily Unbreakable]]

'''Part III: Cryptanalysis'''
#[[Cryptography/Basic Code-Breaking Principles|The Basic Principles]]
#Weaknesses
##[[Cryptography/Proportionality of Secrecy|Proportionality of Secrecy]]
###[[Cryptography/Key Lengths|Length of the key]]
###[[Cryptography/Random Quality|Quality of Random Source]]
###[[Cryptography/Plaintext Effects|Plaintext effect on Ciphertext]]
##[[Cryptography/Statistical Weaknesses|Statistical Leaking]]
##[[Cryptography/Faults|Faulty Implementation]]
##[[Cryptography/No Peer Reviews|Inadequate Peer-Review]]
##[[Cryptography/Social Engineering and Coercion|Social Engineering and Coercion]]
##[[Cryptography/Side Channels|Side Channels]]
#Attacks
##[[Cryptography/Brute force attack|Brute-Force Attack]]
###[[Cryptography/Dictionary attack|Dictionary Attack]]
##[[Cryptography/Frequency analysis|Frequency Analysis]]
##[[Cryptography/Index of coincidence|Index of Coincidence]]
##[[/Linear cryptanalysis|Linear Cryptanalysis]]
##[[/Differential cryptanalysis|Differential Cryptanalysis]]
##[[Cryptography/Meet In The Middle Attack|Meet in the Middle Attack]]
##[[/Man-in-the-middle attack/]]
#[[/Breaking Hash Algorithms/]]
##[[Cryptography/Collisions|Collisions]]
###[[Cryptography/Generating Collisions|Generating]]
###[[Cryptography/Exploiting Collisions|Exploiting]]
##[[Cryptography/Birthday Attack|Birthday Attack]]
##[[Cryptography/Joux Attack|Joux Attack]]
##[[Cryptography/Time Memory Trade Off|Time Memory Trade Off]] (rainbow tables)
#[[Cryptography/How Historical Systems Were Broken|How Historical Systems Were Broken]]
##[[Cryptography/Breaking transposition ciphers|Transposition Ciphers]]
##[[Cryptography/Breaking Caesar cipher|Caesar Cipher]]
##[[Cryptography/Breaking the Enigma machine|Enigma Machine]]
##[[Cryptography/Breaking Permutation cipher|Permutation Cipher]]
##[[Cryptography/Breaking Vigenère cipher|Vigenère Cipher]] 

'''Part IV: Using Cryptosystems'''
#Applying Cryptography
##Digital Signatures
###[[Cryptography/Digital signatures|Introduction to Digital Signatures]]
###[[Cryptography/DSA|DSA]]
##[[Cryptography/Database protection|Database protection]]
##[[Cryptography/E-cash|E-Cash]]
##[[Cryptography/E-voting|E-Voting]]
##[[Cryptography/DRM|DRM]]
##[[Cryptography/Biometrics|Biometrics]]
##[[Cryptography/Anonymity|Anonymity]]
#Classical Ciphers
##[[Cryptography/Beale cipher|Beale Cipher]]
##[[Cryptography/Transposition ciphers|Transposition Ciphers]]
##[[/Caesar cipher/]]
##[[Cryptography/Atbash cipher|Atbash Cipher]]
##[[/Autokey cipher/]]
##[[Cryptography/Playfair cipher|Playfair Cipher]]
##[[/Polyalphabetic substitution/]]
##[[Cryptography/Scytale|Scytale]]
##[[/Substitution cipher/]]
##[[/nomenclator/]]
##[[Cryptography/Permutation cipher|Permutation Cipher]]
##[[/Affine cipher/]]
##[[/Vigenère cipher/]]
##[[/Polybius square/]]
##[[/ADFGVX cipher/]]
##[[/Fractionation/]] (Polybius square, straddling checkerboard, CT-37c conversion table, etc.)
#Contemporary Ciphers
##Symmetric Ciphers
###[[Cryptography/Enigma machine|Enigma Machine]]
###[[/Solitaire cipher/]]
###[[Cryptography/One time pads|One-Time Pads]]
###[[/Ciphersaber/]]
###[[Cryptography/DES|Data Encryption Standard (DES)]]
###[[Cryptography/AES|Advanced Encryption Standard]]
##Asymmetric Ciphers
###[[Cryptography/Public Key Overview|Overview]]
###[[Cryptography/RSA|RSA]]
###[[Cryptography/ElGamal|ElGamal]]
###[[Cryptography/Elliptic curve|Elliptic Curve]]
###[[/Blum-Goldwasser/]]
##[[Cryptography/Hash function|Hashes]]
###[[/MD5/]]
###[[/SHA-1/]]
###[[/SHA-2/]] 
###[[/SHA-3/]]
###[[Cryptography/RIPEMD-160|RIPEMD-160]]
###[[/Tiger/]]
### [[/message authentication/]] code (often MAC); A MAC algorithm is sometimes called a keyed (cryptographic) hash function.
#[[/Protocols/]]
##Authentication protocols
###e.g. Kerberos
##Key exchange protocols
###[[Cryptography/Diffie-Hellman|Diffie-Hellman]]
##Secure Communications
###e.g. SSL, SSH
###[[/Generate a keypair using OpenSSL/]]

'''Part V: Cryptography and Society'''
#[[Cryptography/Changing usage|The Changing Nature of Cryptographic Use]]
#[[Cryptography/Laws|Cryptography, Governments and Laws]]
#[[Cryptography/Expectations of Normal Users|Expectations of Normal Users]]

'''Part VI: Miscellaneous'''
#Future Possibilities
##[[Cryptography/Quantum Cryptography|Quantum Cryptography]]
##[[Cryptography/Better Linear Computing|Faster, More Parallel Linear Computers]]
#[[Cryptography/Glossary|Glossary of Terms]]
#[[Cryptography/Further reading|Further Reading]]
#Appendix A: Mathematical background
##[[Cryptography/Number Theory|Number Theory]]
##[[Cryptography/Group Theory|Group Theory]]
##[[Cryptography/Computational Complexity|Computational Complexity]]
##[[Cryptography/Prime numbers|Prime numbers]]

#Currently ungrouped content
##[[Cryptography/Tabula recta|Tabula Recta]]
##[[Cryptography/Commitment schemes|Commitment schemes]]
##[[Cryptography/Zero-knowledge proofs|Zero-knowledge proofs]]
##[[Cryptography/Open Source Cryptography|Open source implementation of cryptographic algorithms]]
##[[/initialization vector/]]
##[[/Linear Cryptanalysis/]]
##[[/Differential Cryptanalysis/]]

{| width=&quot;100%&quot; cellspacing=&quot;3&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#fff3f3;border:1px solid #ffc9c9;margin-top:10px;&quot;
|-
| Almost all of these topics have articles about them in Wikipedia (there are about 50-100 crypto related articles) so many sections could be imported.

:Perhaps this needs a little [[Talk:Cryptography|Discussion]].--[[User:RobKohr|RobKohr]] 17:14, 22 Nov 2004 (UTC)
*[[Cryptography/Scratch pad]] - a mid-way ground for importing articles from Wikipedia.
|}

Pages to be merged into the text.

[[Cryptography/Prime Curve/Affine Coordinates]]

[[Cryptography/Prime Curve/Chudnovsky Coordinates]]

[[Cryptography/Prime Curve/Jacobian Coordinates]]

[[Cryptography/Prime Curve/Standard Projective Coordinates]]

[[Cryptography/Notes]]


{| width=&quot;100%&quot; cellspacing=&quot;3&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#f0f0ff;border:1px solid #c6c9ff;margin-top:3px;&quot;
|-
| Sources: [[:Wikipedia:cryptography]], [[:Wikipedia:Transposition cipher]], [[:Wikipedia:Caesar cipher]], [[:Wikipedia:Frequency analysis]], [[:Wikipedia:Brute-force search]].
|}

{{Subjects|Computer science|Applied mathematics}}
{{alphabetical|C}}
{{status|25%}}

[[es:Introducción a la Criptografía]]
[[it:Crittografia]]</text>
      <sha1>invvi4mw1bq19zzqyvh0n1phdwq6t0z</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Literature</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4044</id>
    <redirect title="Subject:Literature" />
    <revision>
      <id>1439391</id>
      <parentid>1439390</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-03-09T22:19:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>NipplesMeCool</username>
        <id>165905</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Redirected page to [[Subject:Literature]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">#REDIRECT [[Subject:Literature]]</text>
      <sha1>i5o82lhdysgv59pxc0a109olhiasdgs</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Canadian History/Confederation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4046</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1960777</id>
      <parentid>1960745</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-10-28T13:25:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jomegat</username>
        <id>12605</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/38.116.202.244|38.116.202.244]] ([[User talk:38.116.202.244|talk]]) to last revision by [[User:Aidanandisabella|Aidanandisabella]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Canada's Obligation==

By the 1860s, Great Britain became really concerned that Canada was more of a shining star than an asset to the Empire.  British politicians did not like the expense of providing for the defence of the North American colonies from real or perceived threats from the Americans.  The American Civil War only heightened fears in Canada of a potential invasion.

Americans, on the other hand, always seemed to have a group of people willing to go to war with Britain and invade British North America, often in high places (for example, Lincoln's Secretary of State, Seward).  Britain's trade with the United States at this time had simply become too valuable to jeopardize by maintaining a colonial system in British North America, so prominent British politicians began the process of pushing Canada &quot;out of the nest,&quot; so to speak.

However, the process was not simple.  British North America consisted of no less than seven colonies, and the vast territory of Rupert's Land owned and run by Hudson's Bay Company.  Uniting this area would prove to be difficult.

--- The following passage is inaccurate --
Confederation was achieved for many reasons.  Canada West and Canada East felt that uniting the colonies would help make all of the colonies stronger, more economically stable, and would make the government system more fair.
The maritimes, who were having a boom period, were disinclined to join confederation. They wanted to join together the maritime colonies and have a separate country for only them, however, the Americans had just finished the Civil War, and had about as many soldiers as all the colonies that were thinking about confederation did combined, and posed a real threat to the colonies. The maritimes thought about it, and with the help of a conference with John A. Macdonald decided to join confederation. The only maritime colonies that didn't join were Newfoundland and Prince Edward Island, which would join later on. 
At the Quebec conference, representatives from all the participating colonies came together and constructed the 72 Resolutions which outlined all of the laws that the new country Canada would have.



{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>lighg1q5qyeil05evckm0ih23vavgik</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Lucid Dreaming/Using</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4071</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2490022</id>
      <parentid>2490018</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-02-20T22:12:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Fax Fagor</username>
        <id>897801</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Hard */ Added: &quot;Rewind time&quot; (personal experience)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{LDTOC}}

==Dream stabilization==
Once you are able to dream lucidly, you may find that it is difficult to stay in the dream; for example, you may wake instantly or the dream may start “fading” which is characterized by loss or degradation of any of the senses, especially vision. Alternatively, a new lucid dreamer could easily forget that they are in a dream, as a result of the shock of the sensation.

Don't worry if you wake immediately after becoming lucid. As you gain more experience of becoming lucid, it will come as less of a shock and you’ll be less likely to wake up. Make sure you do a reality check to be sure you’re not still dreaming. As you gain more experience, you will have an easier time identifying when and remembering that you are dreaming.

You can avoid more gradual fadings by '''stimulating your senses'''. This means listening for sounds, feeling around with your hands, and paying attention to what you see and smell. The idea here is to load your senses with stimulation from the dream so that your senses cannot shift to the real world. If you close your eyes, you are removing a great deal of sensory information and might wake up. Staring at a single point can cause effectively the same problem if you stop seeing everything else in your peripheral vision, or don't see enough movement. If you hear something loud in real life and are hearing nothing in the dream, your senses may shift to the real world, causing you to wake up.

Ideally you should be able to use the techniques below to stabilize your dream ''before'' it starts to fade (or “black out”). As always, prevention is better than treatment - and the more stable and vivid your dreams are, the more enjoyable they will be.  However, if that doesn't work you may be able to use stabilization techniques to stop the fading; the spinning technique is probably the most effective in this case.

If you still can’t stabilize your dream, you may decide to try and wake up with the aim of remembering your dream as accurately as possible while its still fresh in your mind.

===Hand Touching===
Rub your hands together and concentrate on the rubbing. You should feel the friction and the heat of your hands. If you can concentrate on the feelings that this action generates, your dream is likely to stabilize and become more vivid and detailed. You can also keep one hand on your arm while exploring the dream for a constant sense of stimulation.  This technique is most effective when used in conjunction with the “Slowing it down” technique, by staring at your hands while rubbing them together.

===Spinning===
You spin around in your dream much as you would if you suddenly want to feel dizzy in real life. The sensation of movement is the key here to stabilizing the dream. Many people report success with this technique, but it also tends to cause a complete change of your dream scene (see [[#Changing the dream environment|Changing the dream environment]] below). If the dream scene disappears  completely (e.g., becomes black), it is necessary to visualize the dreamscape to return to the dream.

===Slowing it down===
Some people like to stabilize the dream by “stopping to smell the roses” and slowly staring at a dream object until it becomes clear. The dreamer would then look around elsewhere, noticing how detailed everything is, thereby stimulating the visual portion of the dream. ''However, others find this can cause their lucid dream to end.'' If you focus on one object for too long to the exclusion of everything else, you will likely wake up or lose the dream. It works best to pay attention to everything in your vision, including your peripheral vision, not just the center of the object you're staring at. If staring at a single object doesn't work for you, try to let your eyes wander around instead.

===Touching your dream===
If you feel that your dream is too abstract and fear that it might be fading, you can prevent this by grabbing hold of a solid object in your dream and focus on how real the sensation is. A good tip is to find something you know is stuck, for instance a table nailed to the ground, and pull it with all your muscular power (no ''supernatural'' powers!), and you should feel how solid it is. The idea is that you convince yourself that the dream is solid and real — through tactile stimulation — and nothing abstract.

===Regaining waking memory or skills===
This is also likely to enhance your degree of lucidity. Try to remember facts from your waking life, such as your phone number, address, etc., or do some simple math. Or, start reciting the lyrics to your favorite song. Or perhaps try some sports practice you know well — this all depends on which senses / methods of thought process you tend to rely on most in your waking life.

===False awakening===
A couple of the users on the ld4all.com forums have had success with creating a false awakening to stabilize a dream. If the above techniques are failing and you find your dream still fading, ''and you really want to continue your lucid dream'', do the following:

# Expect to have a false awakening.
# When you think you wake up, perform a reality check.

You will either have a false awakening, reality check, and then end up with an even more vivid lucid dream, or will really wake up, perform a reality check, and realize that you just woke up (bad luck!).

The most important part of this is the reality check. This is what will continue your lucid dream. You should be performing reality checks when you wake up. If you plan to induce false awakenings in order to stabilize a dream, the reality check that you perform as you wake up is as important as the one that got you lucid, if not more.

Perform every check in the book until you are '''positively, absolutely, and completely sure''' that you aren’t dreaming. A series of 10 reality checks is more likely to produce dream results in a dream, especially if you are expecting dream results. This technique is for those who are desperate!

''If you have had a good experience with this technique, please go to the talk page and post your experiences, as there have not been many anecdotes of it working yet.''

If you didn’t do any of these, your best option is probably to try to wake up. That way, you will remember more of the dream.

The general rule of dream-stabilization is to '''stimulate the senses'''. If you listen for sounds, feel around with your hands, and pay attention to what you see and smell, you will stimulate your senses. The idea here is to load your senses with stimulation from the dream so that your senses cannot shift to the real world. If you close your eyes, you are removing a great deal of sensory information and might wake up. Staring at a single point can cause effectively the same problem if you stop seeing everything else in your peripheral vision, or don't see enough movement. If you hear something loud in real life and are hearing nothing in the dream, your senses may shift to the real world, causing you to wake up.

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: right; font-size: small&quot;&gt;[[#top|top]]&lt;/div&gt;

==Recovering from lost visuals==
There are a few things you can try to do if you lose your vision. Most of these are less likely to help prolong your dream than the above techniques.

You can also try these if you have just woken up and are lying in your bed. You may be able to return to your dream.

===Autosuggestion===
You can repeat over and over a phrase similar to “I can see my dream,” or otherwise enforce in your mind that you can see a dreamscape. (See [[w:Autosuggestion|Autosuggestion]])

===Visualising===
You can visualise the scene as it would be if you could see it. You could take this as an opportunity to change the dreamscape by visualising a different environment from the previous one in the dream. This can be made easier by spinning as you visualize. (See [[#Changing the dream environment|Changing the dream environment]] below)

==Altering the dream==
===Changing the dream environment===
You can change the dreamscape by simply visualizing a different environment. Stephen LaBerge, author of ''Exploring the World of Lucid Dreaming'', suggests closing your eyes, spinning around, and visualizing a new location. Alan Worsley, a famous lucid dreamer, describes another technique of summoning a television and remote to switched dreamscapes. By simply “changing the channel” on the remote, imagine your surroundings switching to your desired location, as though you were switching through various television programs. 

In both of these methods, details are key. The more details you provide for your next dreamscape, the easier it will be to get there. For example, if you wanted go to the Superbowl in your dreams, you might simply state:

:'''“I want to be at the Superbowl.”'''

But this statement could be improved by adding details:

:'''&quot;I want be in the endzone seats, drinking a Coke, and wearing my favorite player's jersey at the Super Bowl.&quot;'''

===Summoning objects into your dream===
At some point in your lucid dreaming experience, you'll probably want to handle various objects, or talk with certain people. Both of these needs can be fulfilled by using your mind, and the power of suggestion. There is no set way to &quot;make&quot; things in the dream world; in fact, many lucid dreamers devise their own methods through experimentation. However, here are some of the more common &quot;summoning&quot; techniques:

* Try reaching for objects that are not within your field of vision. For example, think to yourself: “When I reach into my pocket, there will be a green box of mints.” Then, attempt to actually take a green box of mints out of your pocket. Other variations of this include reaching behind you for an object, or reaching through a mirror in hopes of getting a hold of what you want.
* To summon a person, you might say to yourself: “When I turn around, [person's name] will be standing in front of me,” or “When I walk through this mirror, I will see [person's name],” or “In a few moments, [person's name] will walk through that door (or around that corner).”
* More experienced lucid dreamers can try making the object materialize right before their eyes. This will require a fair amount of concentration. Here is an example of this process:&lt;br /&gt;

: “I am lucid dreaming in my backyard, and it's currently night. Now, I don't like the dark in my lucid dreams because I'm more likely to wake up, and I fear there are monsters lurking around every corner. So, I want to '''make the sun appear''' so that it'll be daytime. Focusing on the horizon, I visualize the sun rising above it.&lt;br /&gt;
:At first nothing happens, but I continue focusing and...yes! There's some light filtering over the horizon! And now the sun is rising to the sky and it settles there; so far, so good. But wait...the sky is still black. Peering at bit closer at the sun, I can just make out a faint ring of blue sky encircling it. Lifting my hand towards it I shout, &quot;Blue!&quot;. The blue ring quickly spreads across the sky, creating the full daytime effect.”&lt;br /&gt;

* Some dreamers may have success by closing their eyes and imagining the desired object in front of them once when they open their eyes . 
* Try using mechanical devices within the dream, such as a nearby lightswitch or button, to summon objects or people. (i.e. &quot;When I flip this switch/press this button, X will appear.&quot;)

Remember, in the dream world, your expectations shape your surroundings. If you think a big, scary monster is going to step out of the shadows and attack you...well, a big, scary monster probably ''is'' going to step out of the shadows and attack you. So, don't be a victim; take control of your thoughts and use them to your advantage.
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: right; font-size: small&quot;&gt;[[#top|top]]&lt;/div&gt;

==What you can do==
This final section should see you off with a few ideas of what to do in a dream.

It is advised to have a ''clear purpose'' for your lucid dreams whenever you go to sleep. In other words, every night you consider what you want to do when you have a lucid dream, and select one thing, or perhaps two or three if you are skilled. Avoid this:

: &quot;What am I gonna do what am I gonna do? I wanna fly, walk through walls, eat until my stomach explodes, spy on my neighbours, drive in a car real fast, woooeeey I'm gonna . . .&quot; &lt;!--- thanks to BuLLeT-PrOOf at the ld4all.com forums, this is a perfect example of what not to do! ---&gt;

You will either end up doing none of these things in your dream or getting overexcited and waking up.

Now that that’s clear, here’s a list of possible things you could do, ordered in difficulty. Remember that you might find some things unusually hard (or easy) compared to most lucid dreamers, this is perfectly normal! This is a very rough guide — if you’ve managed something in the Easy section, don't be scared to try for something from the Medium section.
===Easy===
* Fly
*: Most people enjoy flying around in dreams. There are different styles of flight that people use, each with a varied level of success for each individual. Methods such as “swimming through the air”, “Superman style” (one arm outstretched), “Neo style” (both arms at your side), and “Airplane style” (both arms out) ,&quot;eagle style&quot; (gliding through the air currents, using your fingered wings to navigate altitudes) are often used. There are a few methods of getting up into the air, such as simply jumping (you can jump really high in dreams if you believe it) or imagining a great force pushing you from your feet or walking up on air as though it is a staircase. Some people summon jetpacks and slip them on to fly. Be creative and dream up your own methods.
* Explore your dream world
*: Be warned, you are quite likely to forget you are dreaming when exploring! Doing reality checks often and muttering to yourself about how real everything seems can help to avoid this. You can also ask a dream character to tag along with you and remind you when you forget that you’re dreaming.
* Walk through a mirror or wall
*: You can pass through dream objects such as walls, glass, trees, and everything else. Confidence is really the key here. Some variations on going through stuff can be going in slowly, wiggling your finger in first, or running quickly into the object and telling yourself you would go through it. Some people particularly like to go through mirrors because of the unpredictable effects this action produces. However, if you tell yourself you will end up at a certain location before passing through a mirror, you can change the dream scene quickly. Be warned, some people experience nothing and wake up after passing through. You may want to hold your arm to keep yourself in the dream.
* Look at the sky
*: People often report amazing skies in lucid dreams. You can also shout colors at it and paint some sunrises.
* Show off to your friends (“Hey guys; I can go through this wall!”)
* Do plenty of sports (trampolining, skiing, swimming, dancing, etc.)
* Use various power such as Telekinesis and magic (a shortcut if you are having problems would be to summon a magic wand/staff or other device)
* Try to read a book that you have never read and remember the content
* Try to browse the Internet and visit sites that you've never visited
* Use things that you have never used
* Last but not least: Edit Wikipedia/Wikibooks articles (see question 90 of the [[w:Wikipedia:Are You a Wikipediholic Test|Wikipediholic Test]]) and see if the changes remain when you awake!

===Medium===
* Eat until you’re near bursting!
* Teleport
* Create some dream characters (possibly from a book or film)
* Try to find your spirit guide
* Experiments (in fact, researchers will often want people of various skills)
* Body swapping/possession (where you enter a different body)
* Morph
* Take some drugs (this is more realistic if you’ve done so in real life)
*: Many people have also experienced realistic effects when trying drugs in dreams that they have never taken in real life.
* Drive a vehicle (This is especially fun if you haven't ever driven in real life)
* Fight
*: Nobody can tell you what you should and should not do in your dreams; the choice remains up to you.
** Use weapons
**: It is usually more interesting to use melee weapons (knives, swords, brass knuckles) than projectile weapons. Machine guns and pistols often run out of ammo and summoning it can be difficult. Misfires and jamming is also common. ''(Your subconscious expectations will shape your dreamscape in all manner of ways, If you believe it is hard to accomplish, if you believe it will jam or misfire, it will. I have had no issues with weaponry such as firearms in my dreams what-so-ever, take this &quot;advice&quot; lightly.)'' However this can be overcome by using Directed Energy Weapons (Lasers, Plasma/pulse rifles), or weapons that can't jam (bows, simple firearms like muskets and so on).

** &quot;Beat up&quot; your enemies

===Hard===
* Have sex
*: The excitement, or closing your eyes, can cause you to wake up. An additional reason for waking up may be fixing your eyes on your partner, as holding a gaze for long is also known to cause waking up. Also your dream partner has a strange way of transforming in the midst of ecstasy. Finding a sex partner isn't very hard, it's keeping them that is difficult. That is why it is best to not panic when they are transforming and accept them for what your subconscious brings you. 
* More morphing like 360 degree vision, [[w:sonar|sonar vision]], etc.
* Create false memories, etc. False memories can be made by having a lucid dream, but scripting it so you will think it is real, e.g. you think what happened in your dream happened in real life. This is hard because you will have to forget it is a dream while staying lucid (knowing it is a dream).
* Compose music or poems (or request them from your subconscious)
* Build a fantasy dream world! (some people build a dream world naturally)
** [http://lucidcrossroads.co.uk Lucid Crossroads]
** [http://www.astralpulse.com/astralpulseisland.html Astral Pulse Island]
** H.P. Lovecraft's [[w:Dreamlands|Dreamlands]]
* Have precognition (your subconscious can be very good at predicting the future with relationships and career)
* Experience death. This could be a very harsh experience, and depending on your religious or philosophical beliefs may summon you into a different world or nothingness.
* Ask the dream to show you your worst fears/deepest traumas/etc. (be prepared for some bad stuff to surface)
* Build/use impossible objects, such as [[w:Hypercube|hypercubes]], [[w:Klein bottle|Klein bottles]], etc.
* Rewind time

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: right; font-size: small&quot;&gt;[[#top|top]]&lt;/div&gt;

==Conclusion==
With all the techniques in this book, you may feel overwhelmed and uncertain of what to do next. Don't worry — just choose a few techniques to “map your way to lucidity”, decide on a few things you will want to do from this page, and start!

If you are still unsure of what to do, don’t worry — you might happen to have a lucid dream tonight!

If you are beginning to feel a compulsive thirst for ''more'' information about dreams, head over to the [[Lucid Dreaming/Further Reading|Further Reading]] section for the sites to satisfy your cravings. Remember to come back occasionally and help make the wikibook grow!

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: right; font-size: small&quot;&gt;[[#top|top]]&lt;/div&gt;
{{LDTOC}}
[[Category:Lucid Dreaming]]

[[es:Sueño lúcido/Uso]]
[[it:Sogno lucido/Uso]]</text>
      <sha1>01cjd54mnbgeohvkbqc2zgdi1znc1vn</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:67.30.103.89</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>4072</id>
    <revision>
      <id>155880</id>
      <parentid>13023</parentid>
      <timestamp>2004-01-24T20:08:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>R3m0t</username>
        <id>327</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">If you are considering being a serious contributor to the wikibook :) it would be appreciated if you were to sign up. You don't even need to enter your email, completely anonymous, but it shows exactly who is who. To reply, click on the (talk) link and click on Edit this page. [[User:R3m0t|r3m0t]] [http://wikibooks.org/w/wiki.phtml?title=Special:Contributions&amp;target=R3m0t (cont)] [[User talk:r3m0t|(talk)]] 12:05, 24 Jan 2004 (PST)</text>
      <sha1>5re71t52vk0qkhnmpdtkb379p0ccajw</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>