<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Pound Cake</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4164</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2689042</id>
      <parentid>2020689</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-05T23:41:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Austncorp</username>
        <id>1540792</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Added baking, lemon and dessert cats.  Added to text slightly.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{recipe}} | [[Cookbook:Dessert|Dessert]] | [[Cookbook:Cake|Cake]]
__NOTOC__
A traditional '''Pound Cake''' recipe would specify one pound each of the following ingredients.  These quantities are too great for most modern families, but an excellent cake can be made with half quantities.  It is usual to weigh the eggs first and then use the same weights of the other ingredients; with a traditional pair of kitchen scales, the eggs are simply used instead of weights.

==Ingredients==
*&amp;frac12; pound [[Cookbook:Flour|flour]] 
*&amp;frac12; pound [[Cookbook:Butter|butter]] 
*&amp;frac12; pound [[Cookbook:Egg|eggs]] (4 eggs)
*&amp;frac12; pound [[Cookbook:Sugar|sugar]] 
*&amp;frac12; pound assorted dried fruit ([[Cookbook:Currant|currants]], [[Cookbook:Sultana|sultanas]], and [[Cookbook:Raisin|raisins]], with perhaps a lesser quantity of [[Cookbook:Glacé cherry|glacé]] [maraschino] cherries).
&amp;frac12; pound is equal to 227 grams. Needless to say, in this recipe, 250 grams of each ingredient could be used.

==Procedure==
#Cream the butter and sugar together until fluffy. 
#Beat in the eggs. 
#Gradually sift in the dry ingredients. 
#Transfer to a greased and floured baking pan. 
#Bake at 175 °C (350 °F), until a skewer inserted shows no moist crumbs when removed.

For an alternative recipe: http://www.videojug.com/film/how-to-make-basic-pound-cake

==Variations==

===Lemon Pound Cake===

====Ingredients====
Cake:
*16 tablespoons unsalted butter, plus 1 tablespoon, softened, for greasing pan
*1.5 cups cake flour, plus 1 tablespoon for dusting pan
*1 teaspoon baking powder
*0.5 teaspoon salt
*1.25 cups sugar
*2 tablespoons grated zest from 2 medium lemons
*2 teaspoons juice from same 2 lemons
*4 large eggs
*1.5 teaspoons vanilla extract

Lemon glaze (optional:)
*0.5 cup sugar
*0.25 cup juice from 1 or 2 medium lemons

====Procedure====
Cake:
#Adjust oven rack to middle position and heat oven to 350 degrees Fahrenheit.  Grease 1 9 by 5 inch Pyrex™ loaf pan with 1 tablespoon softened butter; dust with 1 tablespoon cake flour, tapping out excess.  In medium bowl, whisk together flour, baking powder, and salt; set aside.
#In glass measuring cup or microwave-safe bowl, microwave butter, covered with plastic wrap, 1 to 2 minutes or until melted.  Whisk melted butter thoroughly.
#In food processor, pulse sugar and lemon zest until combined.  Add lemon juice, eggs, and vanilla; process until combined.  With processor running, drizzle melted butter through feed tube.  Transfer mixture to large bowl.  Sift flour mixture over eggs in three steps, gently whisking after each addition.
#Pour batter into prepared pan and bake 15 minutes.  Reduce oven temperature to 325 degrees Fahrenheit and continue to bake until deep golden brown and skewer inserted in center comes out clean (about 35 minutes,) rotating pan halfway through baking time.  Cool in pan for 10 minutes, then turn cake onto wire rack, poke on top and sides with a toothpick or skewer, and brush on lemon glaze (see below.)  Cool to room temperature (at least 1 hour.)  Once cooled, cake can be wrapped tightly in plastic wrap and stored at room temperature for up to 5 days.

Lemon glaze:

While cake is cooling, bring sugar and lemon juice to boil in small nonreactive saucepan, stirring occasionally to dissolve sugar.  Reduce heat to low and simmer until thickened slightly, about 2 minutes.  Brush glaze onto cake.

===Lemon-Poppy seed Pound Cake===
Follow recipe for Lemon Pound Cake through step 1.  Toss 1 tablespoon flour mixture with 0.66 cup poppy seeds in small bowl; set aside.  Continue with recipe from step 2, folding poppy seed mixture into batter after flour is incorporated.

==References==
{{refbegin}}
*Pelzel, Raquel.  January-February 2004.  &quot;Simplifying Lemon Pound Cake.&quot;  ''Cook's Illustrated'', p. 24-25.
{{refend}}

[[Category:Cake recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Lemon recipes]]
[[Category:Baking recipes]]
[[Category:Dessert recipes]]</text>
      <sha1>fy8wrvg7710omyld69izzabjhrube4d</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook talk:Pound Cake</title>
    <ns>103</ns>
    <id>4165</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2018609</id>
      <parentid>2010112</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-01-17T16:26:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whoop whoop pull up</username>
        <id>398123</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Better recipe */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Page history from [[w:en:Pound cake|wikipedia]]==

Legend: (cur) = difference with current version, (last) = difference with preceding version, M = minor edit 

*	(cur) (last) . . 02:51, 29 Jan 2004 . . Gentgeen (Transwikied recipes to wikibooks)
*	(cur) (last) . . 18:12, 22 Dec 2003 . . Noldoaran
*	(cur) (last) . . M 17:08, 6 Dec 2003 . . Seglea (link to recipe)
*	(cur) (last) . . M 17:07, 6 Dec 2003 . . Seglea (linkfix)
*	(cur) (last) . . 17:06, 6 Dec 2003 . . Seglea (added authentic equal-quantities recipe)
*	(cur) (last) . . M 13:20, 6 Dec 2003 . . Jengod (wikify)
*	(cur) (last) . . 09:00, 6 Dec 2003 . . 69.37.18.204 (Sorry if the recipe is a little non-specific, but it is a old handed down recipie, so is likely public domain)

----

== Better recipe ==

I have found a new and supposedly better recipe for lemon pound cake in an old issue of ''Cook's'' magazine, along with a lemon glaze and a lemon-poppyseed variation.  The same magazine claims that the classic recipe (shown here) was recieved poorly by tasters, saying that &quot;the texture was described as 'leaden' and the taste resembled 'an underbaked sugar cookie.'&quot;  Should it replace the current recipe and be cited? --[[User:Whoop whoop pull up|Whoop whoop pull up]] ([[User talk:Whoop whoop pull up|talk]]) 16:55, 30 December 2010 (UTC)

:I'll take your silence as a &quot;yes.&quot; --[[User:Whoop whoop pull up|Whoop whoop pull up]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Whoop whoop pull up|Bitching Betty]] | [[Special:Contributions/Whoop whoop pull up|Averted crashes]]&lt;/sup&gt; 16:26, 17 January 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>rdyxbr0l0y1z9yb0o8csyz3rj8vlmli</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Purée Mongole</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4166</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1695022</id>
      <parentid>626938</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-01-10T20:59:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{recipe}}

'''Purée Mongole'''

==Ingredients==
*One pound dry split [[Cookbook:Pea|peas]]
*Water
*[[Cookbook:Chicken Broth|Chicken broth]]
*[[Cookbook:Carrot|Carrot]], grated
*[[Cookbook:Onion|Onion]], chopped
*One white [[Cookbook:Turnip|turnip]]
*Three stalks [[Cookbook:Celery|celery]], chopped
*[[Cookbook:Salt|Salt]], [[Cookbook:Pepper|pepper]], ground [[Cookbook:Clove|cloves]], [[Cookbook:Tumeric|tumeric]], [[Cookbook:Nutmeg|nutmeg]], [[Cookbook:Cumin|cumin]], [[Cookbook:Curry Powder|curry powder]].
*[[Cookbook:Cornstarch|Cornstarch]]
*[[Cookbook:Sour Cream|Sour cream]], as a garnish

==Procedure==

# One pound dry split peas, in water to cover, plus a can of chicken broth, brought to the boil momentarily and left covered, to soak.
# Meanwhile, assemble the same amounts of grated carrot, chopped onion, one white turnip, three stalks of celery, chopped.
# Add the spices.
# Simmer slowly about an hour, or until veggies are well softened. Correct salt to taste.
# Make a liaison of cornstarch, separately mixed in water first to a thin cream. Bring back to the simmer briefly.
# Blend. Thin with stock (or milk) to the right consistency. It should be thick.

Optional garnish: a floating dab of sour cream with a light sprinkling of nutmeg.

[[Category:Pea recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Soup recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>ff72r7lykpug9ehu8sdhjcvebgpr3pm</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Roasted Brined Turkey</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4167</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2689847</id>
      <parentid>2505623</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-08T13:04:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Austncorp</username>
        <id>1540792</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Added vegetable, roasted and main course cats.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{recipe}} | [[Cookbook:Cuisine of the United States|Cuisine of the United States]]
{{recipesummary|turkey recipes|6-12|4 hours|4|Image=[[Image:Oven roasted brine-soaked turkey.jpg|350px]]}}

This recipe is for a 16-18 pound turkey. Roughly 2 days are required to prepare the turkey. The first day is for preparations and for brining, and the second day is for cooking the turkey.

==Ingredients==
* 8.5-14 pound [[Cookbook:Turkey|turkey]]
* 2 Tbs. (1/2 stick) unsalted butter to coat skin of turkey
* 1/2 gallon of water
** 2 cups salt
** 1/2 cup firmly packed light brown sugar
** 2 Tbs. peppercorns 
* 2 gallons of ice water (50% ice)

==Brining==
#In 1/2 gallon of water, combine the salt and brown sugar for the brine and bring to a boil for about 3 minutes.  Remove from heat and add to 5 gallon bucket.
#Add the remaining ice water.
#Remove neck and giblets from turkey and put in 5 gallon bucket. If brine won't cover turkey add a little more water. 
#Put bucket in a cold area for 6 to 24 hours.

==Roasting Procedure==
The tricky thing about cooking poultry is that the dark meat needs to be about 15 degrees hotter than the white meat. White meat is safe to eat at 165°F (73.9°C), which is the temperature at which salmonella instantly dies. (Though 12 minutes at 140°F (60°C) will kill it as well, so odds are fairly good that, for a roast, you'll kill it all on the way to 165°F (73.9°C)) The problem is that dark meat isn't very good at 165°F (73.9°C). Further complicating this is that if the breast meat gets to the 180°F (82.2°C) that the dark meat wants to be cooked to, it's going to be dry, flavorless, and generally unpleasant.

The white meat parts of the turkey are the breasts and wings. The dark meat are the thighs and drumsticks. Now, the wings and drumsticks are going to cook a bit faster than the bits of meat that are better attached to the bird. That said, you want the drumsticks cooked more, so don't worry so much about them. The wings, however, are probably worth attaching more firmly to the bird. You can do this by imagining you were twisting someone's arm behind their back.  Do this with both wings.  Once you figure out the right twist, you'll find that the tips of the wings will stay firmly in place near the center of the back of the turkey (near its backbone).


Next:
#Preheat the oven to 500°F (260°C). (You'll drop the temperature later, but start it hot to get a crispier, more flavorful skin. The effect will be to keep the fat from melting and rolling down the side of the turkey, which is only going to dry it out.) Roast at lowest level of the oven.
#Place the turkey drumstick side down on a roasting tray (with slots to allow drippings through into a pan), or on a rack sitting in a pan.  You will need a basting tool to get the drippings from this pan throughout the roasting process.
#Place the turkey in the oven.
#After about 30 minutes, drop the heat to 350 °F (176.7°C), remove from oven and put a tent of aluminum foil loosely over the breast of the turkey. This is going to keep the breast meat from overcooking and drying out.
#For optimum safety and uniform doneness, it is recommended to cook stuffing outside the bird. #The internal temperature should be checked with a food thermometer and the breast must reach a minimum of 161 °F (71.67°C) before removing it from the oven. The thigh, ideally, will be around 180°F (82.2°C) at this point.  It should take about 2 3/4 to 3 hours to reach this temperature, a 14-16 pound bird should require a total of 2 to 2 1/2hours of roasting. 
#Let the bird stand 15-20 minutes before carving.

==Alternate Recipe==
America's Test Kitchen also had a similar recipe on their show called &quot;The Perfect Roast Turkey&quot;.

===Ingredients===
*4 cups salt or 2 cups table salt
*1 turkey (12 to 14 pounds gross weight), rinsed thoroughly; giblets, neck, and tailpiece removed and reserved to make gravy
*3 medium onions, chopped coarse
*1 1/2 medium carrots, chopped coarse
*1 1/2 celery stalks, chopped coarse
*6 thyme sprigs
*3 tablespoons unsalted butter, melted

===Instructions===
# Dissolve salt in 2 gallons of cold water in large stockpot or clean bucket. Add turkey and refrigerate or set in very cool (40 degrees or less (4.4°C)) spot for 4 to 6 hours.
# Remove turkey from salt water and rinse both cavities and skin under cool running water for several minutes until all traces of salt are gone. Pat dry inside and out with paper towels. Place turkey on meat rack set over rimmed sheet pan. Place turkey in refrigerator, uncovered, and air-dry for at least 8 hours or overnight.
# Adjust oven rack to lowest position, and heat oven to 400 degrees (204.4°C). Toss one-third of onion, carrot, celery, and thyme with 1 tablespoon of melted butter and place this mixture in body cavity. Bring turkey legs together and perform a simple truss.
# Scatter remaining vegetables and thyme over a shallow roasting pan. Pour 1 cup water over vegetables. Set V-rack in pan. Brush entire breast side of turkey with half of remaining butter, then place turkey, breast side down, on V-rack. Brush entire backside of turkey with remaining butter.
# Roast for 45 minutes. Remove pan from oven (close oven door); baste with juices from pan. With wad of paper toweling in each hand, turn turkey, leg/thigh side up. If liquid in pan has totally evaporated, add another 1/2 cup water. Return turkey to oven and roast for 15 minutes. Remove turkey from oven again, baste, and again use paper toweling to turn other leg/thigh side up; roast for another 15 minutes. Remove turkey from oven for final time, baste, and turn it breast side up; roast until breast registers about 165 degrees (73.9°C) and thigh registers 170 to 175 degrees (76.7°C to 79.4°C) on an instant-read thermometer, 30 to 45 minutes. Remove turkey from pan and let rest until ready to carve. Serve with gravy.


[[Category:American recipes|Roasted Brined Turkey]]
[[Category:Thanksgiving recipes|Roasted Brined Turkey]]
[[Category:Turkey recipes|Roasted Brined Turkey]]
[[Category:Vegetable recipes]]
[[Category:Roasted recipes]]
[[Category:Main course recipes]]
[[Category:Featured recipes|Roasted Brined Turkey]]</text>
      <sha1>jmsbk6y8s4y7qv4ehity4lwngcj7k7f</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Simple Nachos</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4168</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2692343</id>
      <parentid>2679776</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-17T03:41:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Austncorp</username>
        <id>1540792</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Beef to Ground Beef cat, per the recipe.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{recipe}} | [[Cookbook:Cuisine of Mexico|Mexican Cuisine]]

Serves 4 as a meal, or 12 as a snack

==Ingredients==
*1 [[Cookbook:Pound|pound]] (450 g) lean ground [[Cookbook:Beef|beef]] (92% lean or better)
*1 can diced tomatoes with [[Cookbook:Green Pepper|green chiles]]
*2 [[Cookbook:Teaspoon|teaspoons]] or less taco seasoning mix (mostly [[Cookbook:Cumin|cumin]])
*2 [[Cookbook:Tablespoon|tablespoons]] [[Cookbook:Sour Cream|sour cream]]
*1 dash [[Cookbook:Mexican Seasoning|Mexican seasoning]]
*corn [[Cookbook:Tortilla Chip|tortilla chips]]

==Procedure==
#In a [[Cookbook:Skillet|skillet]], [[Cookbook:Browning|brown]] ground beef with Mexican seasoning and Taco Mix. 
#When beef is browned add the can of diced tomatoes with green chiles, cover and allow to [[Cookbook:Simmer|simmer]] an additional 5 minutes.
#Put tortilla chips on a large plate. Place 2 tablespoons of sour cream on plate. Sprinkle beef and diced tomato mixture over top of the chips.
#Serve and enjoy.

[[Category:Ground beef recipes]]
[[Category:Mexican recipes]]
[[Category:Appetizer recipes]]
[[Category:Main course recipes]]
[[Category:Sour cream recipes]]
[[Category:Fried recipes]]
[[Category:Recipes with metric units]]</text>
      <sha1>6sk8sr3ouujrzbl1auby6hasgqwfulk</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:S'more</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4169</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2588372</id>
      <parentid>2588371</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-12-06T15:42:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>분당선M</username>
        <id>536782</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/66.195.91.180|66.195.91.180]] ([[User talk:66.195.91.180|talk]]) identified as [[m:w:WP:VAND|vandalism]] to last revision by Sumone10154. ([[m:w:WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{recipesummary|Dessert recipes|4|5 minutes|1|[[File:Smores 1.jpg|300px]]}}

{{recipe}} | [[Cookbook:Dessert|Dessert]] | [[Cookbook:Outdoor cooking|Outdoor]]

'''S'mores''' are a traditional American campfire treat, prepared over an open fire or even in your own home.

==Ingredients==
*4 [[Cookbook:Marshmallow|marshmallows]]
*4 [[Cookbook:Graham Cracker|graham crackers]] (4&quot; x 2&quot; - 10cm x 5cm)
*2 [[Cookbook:Ounce|oz]] (55g) [[Cookbook:Chocolate|chocolate]] bar

Makes 4 single serving s'mores

==Procedure==
#Build a [[Do-It-Yourself/Campfire|campfire]] for [[Cookbook:Toasting|toasting]] the marshmallows.  
#A long thin stick from the woods is hard to find (a thin, long wooden dowel may be a good substitute but will catch fire easily). The stick, which is usually taken from the ground as part of a dead tree branch, does not have to be sterilized, but simply clear of any dirt. Alternately, you may purchase a metal roaster stick. Don't use a coat hanger or chrome or galvanized metal (like fence wire).  Use stainless steel. 
#Before roasting the marshmallows, one must prepare the pieces of graham cracker, and a layer of chocolate.  Break the crackers in half, so you have 2 2&quot;x2&quot; (5cm x 5cm) squares for each s'more.  Break the chocolate bar into 1/2 oz (15g) pieces.
#Push a marshmallow on to the end of the stick. Using the stick to place the marshmallow directly above the flame or source of heat, toast the marshmallow until it is golden brown around the outside. Some prefer their marshmallow burned.  Others like to burn the marshmallow and peel off the burned outer skin to get to the gooey center.
#Place the toasted marshmallow in between two pieces of graham cracker, with a layer of chocolate bar in between.  The marshmallow should be hot enough to melt the chocolate.  In a family setting, sometimes it is helpful for children to roast the marshmallows, and adults to supervise and assemble the s'more while preventing the child from touching the hot end of the stick.  Enjoy!

If you are not camping, patio/backyard firepits work great.  Here is a way to do it indoors in your own home:

#Prepare the pieces of graham cracker, and a layer of chocolate.  Break the crackers in half, so you have 2 2&quot;x2&quot; (5cm x 5cm) squares for each s'more.  Break the chocolate bar into 1/2 oz (15g) pieces.
#Place the chocolate on one of the pieces of graham cracker, and then place a marshmallow on top.
#Put it in the microwave for 15-25 seconds (depending on the microwave).
#After it has been microwaved, the marshmallow should be much bigger, fluffier, and molten, and the chocolate should be semi-melted. Place the other half of the graham cracker on top of the marshmallow and squish it down.  Enjoy!

==Variations==

70 variations on the basic s'more recipe were published in 2007 in [http://www.smoresbook.com S'mores: Gourmet Treats for Every Occasion] by Lisa Adams. Recipes include:

===The Patriot===

*Milk chocolate
*1 graham cracker, broken in half
*Fresh blueberries
*1 marshmallow
*1 thick strawberry slice

Arrange the chocolate on half of the graham cracker. Set blueberries atop chocolate and melt, being careful not to lose the blueberries in transport. Roast the marshmallow. Once chocolate has melted, remove graham cracker from heat and lightly press blueberries to secure them in place. Top with the strawberry slice, roasted marshmallow, and remaining graham cracker. 

===Minty Brownie===

*1 marshmallow
*A handful of Junior Mints
*2 brownie squares 

Roast the marshmallow. If desired, melt chocolates on the brownie bottom. Once the chocolates have melted, remove brownie from heat. Add roasted marshmallow and top with remaining brownie square.

===Tracey’s Caramel Apple===

*1 marshmallow
*2 chewy caramels
*2 green apple slices, about 1/2 inch thick

Skewer the marshmallow, then the two caramels, on the same roasting stick. Roast the marshmallow and caramels. When the caramels have melted over the top of the marshmallow, and the marshmallow is cooked to your liking, slide the concoction onto one of the apple slices. Top with remaining apple slice. 

===Belgian s'more===

*1 set of s'more ingredients (can be any recipe, but usually the standard one)
*2 red and/or black licorice

Prepare the s'mores as usual, then at the end insert either a strip of red or black licorice (or both.)

{{wikipedia|S&amp;#39;more}}

[[Category:Dessert recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Featured recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Camping recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Chocolate recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Marshmallow recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Recipes with metric units|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Microwave recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>lmsry67xdmt6wbi749w8v8m5p3yj7s1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook talk:S'more</title>
    <ns>103</ns>
    <id>4170</id>
    <revision>
      <id>352735</id>
      <parentid>352734</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-02-02T18:30:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sj</username>
        <id>793</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==page history from [[w:en:S'more]]==

Legend: (cur) = difference with current version, (last) = difference with preceding version, M = minor edit 

*	(cur) (last) . . M 03:15, 29 Jan 2004 . . Gentgeen (formating)
*	(cur) (last) . . 03:14, 29 Jan 2004 . . Gentgeen (transwikied recipe to wikibooks)
*	(cur) (last) . . 10:49, 14 Jan 2004 . . 156.63.85.17 (replaced word)
*	(cur) (last) . . 18:23, 8 Oct 2003 . . 67.66.183.91
*	(cur) (last) . . M 12:33, 28 Sep 2003 . . Modemac
*	(cur) (last) . . M 01:23, 19 Sep 2003 . . Scott Sanchez (Observed practice.)
*	(cur) (last) . . M 09:52, 18 Sep 2003 . . Guppy (italicized correction)
*	(cur) (last) . . M 09:50, 18 Sep 2003 . . Guppy (copy edit, typo, italicized s'more)
*	(cur) (last) . . 09:46, 18 Sep 2003 . . Guppy (new article)

----</text>
      <sha1>8qs4v2w3lbjf4r4l6gxujz4p2yyw9u8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:218.12.72.18</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>4177</id>
    <revision>
      <id>155975</id>
      <timestamp>2004-01-29T11:28:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>218.12.72.18</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">218.12.72.18=tomz</text>
      <sha1>s80nkubaklw0532p5h1bbn2ocex6h50</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>MediaWiki:Loginend</title>
    <ns>8</ns>
    <id>4180</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2232532</id>
      <parentid>1930662</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-12-09T12:16:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pi zero</username>
        <id>75960</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>update secure url</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;div class=&quot;plainlinks&quot; style=&quot;float:right; width:48%; margin-left:1em;&quot;&gt;
{{#switch: {{SERVERNAME}}
| en.wikibooks.org = Please consider logging in on the [https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Special:UserLogin secure server].
| secure.wikimedia.org = &lt;!--Don't warn--&gt;
| #default = &lt;div style=&quot;border:2px solid red; padding:0.5em;&quot;&gt;You are using {{SERVERNAME}} to view this page, which can intercept your password and ''might'' compromise your account. Wikibooks will never ask for any information other than your username, password, and email address. You are '''strongly advised''' to log in on the [https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Special:UserLogin secure server] to avoid becoming a [[w:phishing|phishing]] victim.&lt;/div&gt;
}}

'''Secure your account:'''
* Please use a [[w:password strength|strong password]] consisting of numbers, punctuations (?&amp;%$!@,.), accented letters (&quot;ó&quot; &quot;Â&quot;), and mixed letter casings.
* Do not give your password out to anyone. Your account may be permanently blocked if your account is compromised.
* You may [[Template:User committed identity|safeguard your account]] from impersonation by adding a [[w:Cryptographic hash function|cryptographic hash]] to your [[Special:MyPage|user page]].
* Change your password in [[Special:Preferences|your preferences]] if you believe your password has been compromised.
&lt;/div&gt;</text>
      <sha1>da4kpbf9lsrtat1egi646104wlr9lp5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Doc'Roberts Grilled Vegetable Sandwich</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4207</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2376008</id>
      <parentid>1737619</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-07-10T21:21:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Ingredients */general cleanup, typos fixed: eg- → e.g.- using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{recipesummary|Vegan recipes|1|10 minutes|2}}

{{recipe}} | [[Cookbook:Vegan cuisine|Vegan cuisine]] | [[Cookbook:Sandwiches|Sandwiches]]

==Ingredients==
*2 Slices of [[Cookbook:Bread|Bread]] (preferably [[Cookbook:Organic|organic]] [[Cookbook:Wholemeal|wholemeal]] bread)
*Sliced [[Cookbook:Vegetable|Vegetable]]s (e.g.- [[Cookbook:Mushroom|Mushroom]]s, [[Cookbook:Courgette|Courgette]]s, [[Cookbook:Tomato|Tomatoes]], [[Cookbook:Capsicum|Peppers]], etc.)
*1 [[Cookbook:Tablespoon|tablespoon]] [[Cookbook:Olive oil|Olive oil]]
*1 [[Cookbook:Teaspoon|teaspoon]] [[Cookbook:Oregano|Oregano]]

==Procedure==
#Place two slices of bread next to each other on a baking tray.
#Arrange the vegetables evenly across both slices.
#Drizzle the olive oil over the vegetables, and add liberal sprinklings of oregano.
#Grill on medium-high heat for 5-10 minutes, or until golden brown.

Serve open, or carefully combine the two parts of the sandwich for the ultimate eating pleasure.

[[Category:Vegan recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Vegetable recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Sandwich recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>fucjfol9bty9dl3rw8ob6fz770gzfkj</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Lucid dreaming</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4222</id>
    <redirect title="Lucid Dreaming" />
    <revision>
      <id>944551</id>
      <parentid>909397</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-08-17T00:30:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Lucid dreaming: Autocategorizing using Whiteknight Categorization Gadget</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">#redirect [[Lucid Dreaming]]</text>
      <sha1>7njt9ifjx88p5g6ersw3ia66ml26fei</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Sgh7a</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>4225</id>
    <revision>
      <id>156020</id>
      <parentid>13671</parentid>
      <timestamp>2004-02-03T10:49:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sgh7a</username>
        <id>520</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>&quot;Terme mit Variablen&quot; verschoben!</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Hallo, wir sind die Klasse 7a &lt;br&gt;
Und wir werden euch etwas erklären, &lt;br&gt;
Dass ist klar. &lt;br&gt;
Das Vereinfachen von Termen &lt;br&gt;
Wollen wir euch lernen &lt;br&gt;
Verstehen tun wir aber selber nix &lt;br&gt;
Denn es geht immer nur ums x. &lt;br&gt;
Unser Kopf schwirrt nur noch von Zahlen x² &lt;br&gt;
Das : und · ist natürlich auch dabei. &lt;br&gt;

'''Wer hatte die blöde Idee des da hinzuschreiben?'''

'''PS: Wir wurden dazu gezwungen!!'''

----
Unsere Seite ist jetzt folgendermaßen eingeordnet:

Leitseite -&gt; Mathematik für die Schule -&gt; Algebra -&gt; Terme mit Variablen</text>
      <sha1>g4vlobtkngtpqb3c6ejoy48oppdf0bs</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Lucid Dreaming: Introduction</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>4232</id>
    <revision>
      <id>419494</id>
      <parentid>392945</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-04-05T06:19:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tharenthel</username>
        <id>1048</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* False Awakenings */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Discussion &quot;Misgivings about the book's approach&quot; moved to [[Talk:Lucid Dreaming]].'''

Does anyone else think that this is a little harsh when it talks about the mentally ill?  It seems as though it clumps every mental disorder together and considers the brain unstable for anything.  Is how lucid dreaming affects them proven, or is it just a guess by the authors? Or is this a general consensus among the lucid sleepers? --[[User:Emlnxrz|Emlnxrz]] 15:30, 18 June 2004 (UTC)

: I myself have never heard of all this stuff. [[User:R3m0t|r3m0t]] [[Special:Contributions/r3m0t|(cont)]] [[User talk:r3m0t|(talk)]] 08:13, 19 Jun 2004 (UTC)

Are they &quot;levels&quot; of sleep or &quot;stages&quot;.  Or aren't these actually used synonymously?  --[[User:Spikey|Spikey]] 04:53, 31 Jan 2004 (UTC)

:Synonymous. I will change all uses to levels because they are usually called levels 1 to 4. [[User:R3m0t|r3m0t]] [[Special:Contibutions/r3m0t|(cont)]] [[User talk:r3m0t|(talk)]] 05:02, 31 Jan 2004 (UTC)

:Oh, and welcome to the lucid dreaming wikibook! Got any feedback? How's your dream recall going or have you not done anything? :) [[User:R3m0t|r3m0t]] [[Special:Contibutions/r3m0t|(cont)]] [[User talk:r3m0t|(talk)]] 13:22, 2 Feb 2004 (UTC)

::I haven't really tried any of this yet.  I'll probably start working on my dream recall this summer or next schoolyear.  I'll be heading off to college, and it seems like a good time to start new things like a dream journal.  --[[User:Spikey|Spikey]] 04:06, 3 Feb 2004 (UTC)

:::Cool. Any feedback, please tell me. And by the way, if you become LD obsessed, the ld4all.com forums is a good visit, despite the spiritual stuff floating around in masses. [[User:R3m0t|r3m0t]] [[Special:Contibutions/r3m0t|(cont)]] [[User talk:r3m0t|(talk)]] 08:24, 3 Feb 2004 (UTC)

&quot;We awake quite often throughout the night, but if it is for less than 3 minutes it is usually forgotten by the time we wake up.&quot;
:Really?

::[http://www.here-be-dreams.com/sleep/stages.html source]. Now that I look at it, it seems it only happens after some REM and not after every REM. I'll try to clarify... it's only quasi-awake (or pseudo-awake ;) ) anyway, you get hypnagogic/hypnapompic imagery which probably goes along the same lines as the dream.

:::Why can't I seem to remember hypnagogic/hypnapompic imagery?

::::I have found that it slips away as I get out of bed in the morning. Can't you remember that you have wierd thoughts, illogical, irrational etc. when you are still drowsy in bed? That is hypnagogic/hypnapompic imagery. Also voices and any other vivid odd feelings (such as falling). [[User:R3m0t|r3m0t]] [[Special:Contibutions/r3m0t|(cont)]] [[User talk:r3m0t|(talk)]] 12:27, 25 Feb 2004 (UTC)

The &quot;I can't control my dreams&quot; section is badly written in my opinion. I can't do it better myself, so I just complain here instead. It's not clear if it refers to lucid dreams or not (this is an introduction, most people probably haven't much lucid dream experience yet). Further, I would say there are many levels of lucidity. You might vaguely know that you are dreaming without being able to control the dream, ''especially in the beginning''. Control is something you practice. Moreover, the connection between the Mother Theresa section is quite week. What is it really about?

: I'm glad you realise that you're able to correct it :). I was not referring to lucid dreams, but more the feeling of &quot;watching&quot; a dream and not &quot;acting&quot; in it. There certainly are different levels of lucidity, and lucidity in lucid dreams should generally increase with practice. Now that I look at the second paragraph of that question, I have no clue why I put that in. I'll take it out soon if I don't remember, or link it in more fully if I do. [[User:R3m0t|r3m0t]] [[Special:Contributions/r3m0t|(cont)]] [[User talk:r3m0t|(talk)]] 14:43, 7 Apr 2004 (UTC)

I believe the whole introduction feels more like a &quot;Lucid dreaming FAQ&quot;. It answer questions newbie lucid dreamers might have rather than introducing the reader to the subject.

: It seems to me to get the content through. [[User:R3m0t|r3m0t]] [[Special:Contributions/r3m0t|(cont)]] [[User talk:r3m0t|(talk)]] 14:43, 7 Apr 2004 (UTC)

====Dissociation====

What do you think about the addition I made to the Dissociation section (things you should NOT be experiencing)? It does seem a bit scary to me, is it worth including at all?

[[User:Kaycee|KC]] 23:08, 17 Apr 2004 (UTC)


Yes, it does seem a bit scary -- just about everything in that list has happened to me at one time or another in real life.
&quot;''Finding oneself in a place but unaware of how one got there''&quot; ?
I thought this happened to just about everyone the first few times they wake up in an unfamiliar place.
I remember that happened when I woke up after the first time I spent the night at Grandmom's house.

Perhaps we should move the Dissociation section to a completely different page and merely link to it.
Would [[wikipedia:dissociation]] be appropriate ?

-- anonymous

----

Hello from a wikinewbie! I have had many LD's and would like to offer a few comments, I have chosen to put them all here until I have more time, and hopefully sources other than my (and friends') experiences. Also please inform if I am breaking with convention in this post. 

RE: &quot;signs you weren't&quot;...Entering a dream within a dream is a technique for better lucidity, also some of the most profound are when one already lucid enters another realm, often experienced as going to sleep when you already know you are dreaming. (one ref. would be works by Dr. Alberto Villoldo)

RE: Dissociation: I think it is scary, and maybe misleading. I think it's a great idea to have some mention here, but perhaps it could be shortened and refer to some authority on dissociative behavior. (If community thinks it's important enough to mention, then it's too important for us nonpsychology experts to advise much)
:also on this topic, I feel that some of these things are common (if very brief), and may be a sign of personal progress. e.g. ability to see oneself as other can be healthy analization. I hate to over discourage folks on a good path, so while I'm not able to do better with this page, it strikes me as analogous to quitting playing an instrument if you suddenly play a song very well, or improvise music that is better than you thought yourself capable of.
I would appreciate knowing if I should post differently.
Would it be helpful to this book to find links to forums, or maybe start a &quot;recomended reading list&quot; [[User:GreenTwin|GreenTwin]] 18:36, 15 Oct 2004 (UTC)

: Hello to you! There is no convention you should follow in the talk pages. If you'de like to contribute to the main book though, check [[Talk:Lucid Dreaming]] first for a few basic guidelines.

: Dreams within dreams: I've never heard of that and can't think why it would work (beyond the placebo effect). Besides, that's a different case. That's somebody who ''knows'' about lucid dreams who then becomes lucid and uses that technique in order to gain better lucidity. The fact is, generally people who enter a lucid dream from within a dream aren't really lucid, they're only dreaming that they are.

: Community no more. I don't have an opinion on the dissociation section because I don't understand it.

: (Why did you indent that twice?) What do you mean by &quot;ability to see oneself as other&quot;? What do you mean by things being brief? What is &quot;healthy analization&quot;? Sorry, I don't understand you.

: There is already a &quot;recommended reading list&quot;. It's called &quot;Further Reading&quot; and it's on the nav:
{{LDTOC}}
: It includes links to forums and books. [[User:R3m0t|r3m0t]] [[Special:Contributions/r3m0t|(cont)]] [[User talk:r3m0t|(talk)]] 07:52, 17 Oct 2004 (UTC)

----

I'm a little concerned that the book presents 'symptoms' that only a few may have experienced  as concrete aspects of Lucid Dreaming. Most of the list of dissociations could possibly be explained by other psychological explanations and not related to Lucid Dreaming, and yet here they are being listed as factual symptoms.

It might be better to have this introduced as things that some people have experienced whilst attempted to experience Lucid Dreaming'.

- Matt 18:15, 15 April 2005  (GMT)

====Spinning?====

&quot;Attempting to spin&quot; - what does it mean? If it means literally spin, what is so special about it? And if you use a different meaning, please elaborate.

:Anything that gives your senses input from the dream world is fine. Spinning is a good way to &quot;lock&quot; yourself more into the dream consciousness, by asking your brain to generate more substance to the dream. Another way is to focus on dream visuals to make them more stable. Am I making any sense? [[User:Kaycee|KC]] 22:03, 18 May 2004 (UTC)

:Yes, it means literally spin. It's the sort of thing which somebody who knows about lucid dreaming would do. It's the sort of thing I do in a lucid dream, because it prolongs my dreams (see [[LD Using]] and the above post) [[User:R3m0t|r3m0t]] [[Special:Contributions/r3m0t|(cont)]] [[User talk:r3m0t|(talk)]] 06:21, 19 May 2004 (UTC)

== Reasons to pursue lucid dreaming ==

Thanks for all the work you have put into this wikibook.  When I came upon this subject initially, I had one central question on my mind.  Namely, is lucid dreaming a fruitful pursuit, or merely a frivolous diversion from the transcendental purposes of life?  I decided to give lucid dreaming a try.  I got a notebook and began to record my dreams.  I began to ponder the matter of how I knew during waking moments that I was in the physical world.  I hydrated copiously before  retiring.  In the end I lost interest because I just couldn't convince myself there was transcendental purpose in lucid dreaming.  It would be a great contribution to this Wikibook to have a more fully developed section about the rationale for studying/pursuing lucid dreaming.  Does lucid dreaming enhance one's ability to understand and practice sacrificial love and to make the best use of one's time in this world?  How?  Why is it that the majority of discussion of lucid dreaming seems to be from a purposeless or frivolous perspective?  I think all this would make a very interesting addition to the Wikibook.  [[User:216.160.223.49|216.160.223.49]] 21:41, 3 Jan 2005 (UTC)

: Most people take it as a &quot;frivolous pursuit&quot;. However:
* Some people have said that meditating (or dreaming) within a dream has felt to them particularly deep, that they found it easier to relax, etc.
* You can try shared dreaming from it as well as attempt astral projection.
* Considering that (healthy people) spend about 1/3 of their time sleeping and 1/4 of their time dreaming, I would say that lucid dreaming aids effective use of time. You're using that remaining 1/12 of living life at not much cost to the rest of your time. As some people have reported solving problems in dreams, you might be able to solve some of your own. Also, your artistic side is probably more &quot;open&quot; - pasQuale dreamed up the two most recent designs of [http://ld4all.com LD4all.com].
: I would imagine that there is not much interest in lucid dreaming for spirituality because Stephen LaBerge, who proved lucid dreaming, did not publish any mention of it in his book. Therefore people went along the &quot;fun and silly&quot; route. However, I don't see why this should stop you from trying lucid dreaming, because it honestly is great fun and very satisfying when you become lucid. [[User:R3m0t|r3m0t]] [[Special:Contributions/r3m0t|(cont)]] [[User talk:r3m0t|(talk)]] 07:32, 5 Jan 2005 (UTC) PS You will get more replies by joining a forum or asking on alt.dreams.lucid. Check the &quot;further reading&quot; section.

== last section and hypnosis ==

I believe the last part is way off. Self hypnosis as I understand doesn't lead to any visual/etc experiences and can't really be compared with lucid dreaming. Apart from the fact that you are interacting with your subconscious on a different level.

: Well, it does say '''If'' you often enter a &quot;dream world&quot;' . . . but I see your point. I don't have any strong feelings about it either way; if you want to remove that part, go ahead. —[[User:Tharenthel|Tharenthel]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Tharenthel|(Talk)]] [[Special:Contributions/Tharenthel|(Contribs)]]&lt;/sup&gt; 23:07, 30 January 2006 (UTC)

== False Awakenings ==

The section on false awakenings really needs improvement!  I don't understand what it is about.  Link it or expand it, something needs to be added. -- [[User:Phyzome|Phyzome]] 22:34, 8 March 2006 (UTC)

: I tried to clarify it some. It does still need some work, but it hopefully makes more sense now. —[[User:Tharenthel|Tharenthel]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Tharenthel|(Talk)]] [[Special:Contributions/Tharenthel|(Contribs)]]&lt;/sup&gt; 06:19, 5 April 2006 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>mzkt9gw1pu07rdagpek1rq8tibfgzpe</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Engineering Thermodynamics</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4235</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2255584</id>
      <parentid>2244415</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-01-22T22:49:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Addihockey10 (automated)</username>
        <id>502783</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Contents */Replaceing raster images with vector equivalents, replaced: 25%.png → 25%.svg, 75%.png → 75%.svg using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">__NOTOC__
This book is on engineering thermodynamics.  Rigorous treatment of the molecular basis will be omitted, in favor of formulations most useful for developing intuition and understanding common technologies.  Students of physics will want to pair this text with one on [[Statistical Mechanics]].

== Contents ==
{{Print version}}
# [[/Preface/]]
# [[/Introduction/]]
# [[/Thermodynamic Systems/]] [[File:100%.svg]]
# [[/Zeroth Law/]] [[File:00%.svg]]
# [[/First Law/]] [[File:100%.svg]]
# [[/Second Law/]][[File:100%.svg]]
# [[/Third Law/]] [[Image:25%.svg]]
# [[/Applications/]] [[Image:75%.svg]]
# [[/Appendix/]]
# [[/Further Reading/]]

{{Alphabetical|E}}
{{Subjects|Mechanical engineering}}
{{status|25%}}

[[it:Termodinamica]]</text>
      <sha1>8am5rdgmdzmkrndfamogxdbfuvmeieo</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Wikibooks talk:Naming conventions</title>
    <ns>5</ns>
    <id>4237</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1524950</id>
      <parentid>681405</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-06-08T20:45:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Darklama</username>
        <id>7662</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* category guidelines */ fix code</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">I disagree with this system.  I much prefer the Book:Title system for naming articles.  There shouldn't be that many modules in a book that you'd need a 4X hierarchy. [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] 11:17, 31 Jan 2004 (UTC)

== interwiki ==

Doesn't the : seperater create a problem for inter wiki? Lets say I write a book on wikipedia, the chapters would be called [[wikipedia:something]]. This goes to wikipedia article something insted of the chapter on something. With interwiki growing and the likelyhood of a wiki named the same as a book growing, this may be a bad practice.

Yes, good point.  I agree. [[User:dan_aka_jack|Dan_AKA_Jack]] 17:10, 7 Jan 2005 (UTC)

:I agree. We should be using subpages, but they are not enabled on the main namespace. Please, read my opinion about this topic on [[m:Wikibooks should use subpages]]. [[User:ManuelGR|ManuelGR]] 13:26, 16 Jan 2005 (UTC)

== subpages ==

Now we have subpages, I recommend using them. [[User:ManuelGR|ManuelGR]] 18:17, 29 Jan 2005 (UTC)

: Do we agree on using subpages? If yes, we could put the recommendation on the &quot;about&quot; page itself, placed prominently on top, instead of recommending it only on the &quot;talk&quot; page and listing it as one of many many options. Is there a clear community opinion about this point already? Most of the new books still use the &quot;booktitle:name&quot; convention. I guess newcomers would also be happy about a clear directive for the future. (That does not mean that all existing books should be converted, but some would benefit.)
: I would recomment:
:* Booktitle/chapterdescription
: that is, only one layer of subpages, and use the description of the content instead of the chapter number (which would make including new chapters hard)  --[[User:Andreas Ipp|Andreas]] 14:13, 12 Mar 2005 (UTC)

: While I am in favor of Sub-Pages I may ask: Is there actualy a way of converting pages without leaving hundreds of move pages. i.E. [[:Category:Ada_programming_language|Ada]] has about 103 pages - I would not want to convert that by hand. --[[User:Krischik|Krischik]] 16:06, 12 Mar 2005 (UTC)

:Would using subpages apply just to textbooks or to everything?  I wouldn't want to see [[Cookbook/Rice pudding]], for example, but [[Biology/Chapter 3]] is fine. [[User:TUF-KAT|TUF-KAT]] 16:25, 12 Mar 2005 (UTC)

::I don't see any difference between the two, but I think that the first decission to take is wether to give a clear recommendation for new books to use subpages. I think we should. For current books, that is another issue, probably the best approach is to start promoting subpages and let the authors decide whether to change or maintain their current convention.   Only if the new convention is widely accepted then we can regard it as a new policy. [[User:ManuelGR|ManuelGR]] 00:09, 13 Mar 2005 (UTC)

:I still think that there may be more benefits to real namespaces for books.  Other wiki software packages provide namespace specific recent changes, searches, stylesheets, etc.  I can see a lot of benefits for each book operating as its own somewhat independent wiki.  The only benefit right now for subpages is the automatic linkback to the main page. I have no objection to them being used, but to suggest that all new pages and books be forced to use them is simply not a good idea. [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] 01:40, 13 Mar 2005 (UTC)

:: The mediawiki software currently only allows for 256 different namespaces (it is a TINYINT(2) variable in the SQL database), so the number of books getting the real benefit out of it would be comparatively small. I think, a mixed approach would be best: For the majority of small and medium-sized books subpages are the optimal thing to do, large projects, like &quot;Cookbook:&quot; or &quot;Programming:&quot; could have their own name-space if desired. Let us move the further discussion to [[Wikibooks:Hierachy_naming_scheme]].--[[User:Andreas Ipp|Andreas]] 06:47, 13 Mar 2005 (UTC)

== Real-Namespaces  ==

Just a thought: while 256 Real-Namespaces are not enough for all the books - they would be enough for Bookshelfes.

--[[User:Krischik|Krischik]] 06:49, 4 August 2005 (UTC)

Adding a new namespace requires minor changes to the software, or at least done on a developer level (developers also tend to be very Wikipedia-centric, and thus developments that would greatly help Wikibooks, eg. a way in the software to tell what book a given module is a part of, are held on the back burner).  There was a large movement in the past of moving [[Cookbook]] and [[Programming]] (among others) to separate namespaces, but that idea largely died out - the idea however did transform into the &quot;:&quot; delimiter in [[WB:NC]].  As for bookshelves, part of the bookshelf overhaul was that they'd be moved under the Wikibooks namespace, to reserve the main module space for actual books.  The bookshelves merely serve as an informal way of organizing books that exist.  There are plans to have bookshelf management placed under the [[Wikibooks:Card Catalog Office]], but this is a very new idea that is in serious need of discussion.  [[User:KelvSYC|KelvSYC]] 08:04, 4 August 2005 (UTC)

: Using real namespaces would make it more difficult to move books between bookshelves, should the scope of those bookshelves evolve. The current POV in the CCO-project is to use Categories as much as possible. This way we can classify books not only by our bookshelves, but also by Dewey codes and Library of Congress codes (and anything else we might want to add in later). To change a book's classification would be a simple as changing a single parameter of a template to be included on the book's main page. - [[User:Aya|Aya]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Aya|T]]&amp;nbsp;[[Special:Contributions/Aya|C]]&lt;/sup&gt; 19:43, 4 August 2005 (UTC)

== Template naming conventions ==

moved to [[Wikibooks talk:Naming policy#Template naming conventions]]

== category guidelines ==

Are there any tips or guidelines for using category tags?
(A category tag starts with &quot;&lt;code&gt;[&lt;nowiki&gt;[Category:&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&quot;, then the name of the tag, then ends with &quot;&lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&quot;. When a reader clicks on the tag, wikibooks automagically makes a list of every module that includes that tag -- this is often much more convenient than manually creating and maintaining such a list.)

Such category guidelines would say something like

* make sure the category tag &quot;&lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Category:Programming]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&quot; is on the &quot;main module&quot; of a programming language book, but no other module of the book. For example, you would put it on &quot;[[C Programming]]&quot;, but not on &quot;[[C Programming/Control]]&quot;.
* Put the book-specific category tag on every module and template used in the book. For example, you would put the category tag &quot;&lt;code&gt;[[:Category:C Programming]]&lt;/code&gt;&quot; on both modules &quot;[[C Programming]]&quot; and &quot;[[C Programming/Control]]&quot;, but not on any modules in any other book.
* make sure the category tag &quot;&lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Category:Programming]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&quot; is on the book-specific category page. For example, you would put it on the &quot;&lt;code&gt;[[:Category:C Programming]]&lt;/code&gt;&quot; category page.
* It's fine to have a module or template have several different category tags. In particular, if a template is used in multiple books, put the book-specific category tag from each of those books on that template.

Is there a page for holding guidelines like this?

By the way, what is the difference between &quot;&lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:Category:Programming]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&quot; and &quot;&lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[[:Category:Programming languages]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&quot;?

--[[User:DavidCary|DavidCary]] 18:37, 2 December 2006 (UTC)

: Hi David - you are so right (in my view) to bring this up.  It's one that has been lurking in my mind for a while now.  I see categories as very important and quite often badly handled.  That said you are posting this in quite a remote backwater of Wikibooks which will probably not be seen by many.  If you want to go to [[Category talk:Main page]] I promise I'll join it the conversation there (tho it will be tomorrow it being late in my timezone!).  Browsing [[:Category:Main page]] will give you some idea how good and bad things can be - personally the Wikijunior section is pretty good but the rest ...
: Hopefully see you there and get some discussion going about an important topic.  Regards --[[User:Herbythyme|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;Herby&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;b&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#90F&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Herbythyme|talk thyme]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/b&gt; 19:12, 2 December 2006 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>mlp7v5gt28owwr4upy7vf3hyhgv3e1q</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Orange</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4239</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1703413</id>
      <parentid>856169</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-01-23T00:38:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{fruit}}

[[Image:Ambersweet oranges.jpg|250px|thumb|right|Ambersweet Oranges]]
An '''orange''' is a common [[Cookbook:Citrus|citrus]] [[Cookbook:Fruit|fruit]]. Oranges need not be orange in color; depending on climate and variety, an orange may have green patches when ripe. Some will even experience regreening, which is when an orange-colored orange loses its orange. To deal with this aesthetic problem, oranges are often dyed. Rough brownish patches are indications of abrasion against the tree, which does not affect taste.

The orange has a sweet-tart taste and is commonly peeled and eaten fresh, or squeezed for its juice. It has a thick bitter rind that is usually discarded, but can be used in cooking. The outermost layer of the rind can be scraped off to make [[Cookbook:Zest|zest]], having a similar flavor to the flesh. This is the part which contains orange oil. The white part of the rind is almost always discarded as it is extremely bitter, but it does contain lots of pectin. Orange peel can be made into [[Cookbook:Candied Peel|candied peel]] and used in sweet dishes.

==Varieties==

A number of varieties of orange are now cultivated widely. The '''sweet orange''' (''Citrus aurantium'') was first grown in [[Cookbook:Cuisine of Spain|Spain]], and has become the most popular variety. The sweet orange will grow to different sizes and colors due to local conditions, most commonly with ten ''carpels'' (slices) inside.

A single mutation in an orchard of sweet oranges planted at a monastery in 1820 in [[Cookbook:Cuisine of Brazil|Brazil]] led to the '''navel orange''' (aka Washington, Riverside or Bahia navel). A single cutting of the original was then transplanted to [[Cookbook:California cuisine|California]] in 1870, creating a new market worldwide. The mutation caused a ''diploid'', or twin, fruit, with a smaller orange embedded in the outer fruit near the stem. From the outside the smaller, undeveloped, twin leaves a human navel-like formation at the top of the fruit. Navel oranges are almost always seedless, and tend to be larger than the sweet orange.

The Valencia or Murcia orange is one of the sweet oranges used for juice extraction.  It is a late-season fruit. It is a popular variety when navel oranges are out of season.

The blood orange (sometimes called &quot;ruby orange&quot; by the squeamish) has streaks of red in the fruit, and when squeezed the juice is often reddish. The mandarin is similar, but smaller and sweeter, and the scarlet navel is a variety with the same diploid mutation as the normal naval orange.

Bitter oranges are used in [[Cookbook:Marmalade|marmalade]] and as an ingredient in the liqueurs Triple sec and Curacao.

==Oranges in Cooking==

Orange juice is produced by [[Cookbook:Juicing|juicing]] oranges. Brazil is the world's largest producer of orange juice, followed by Florida. Orange juice is available in fresh-squeezed or 'reconstituted' forms, and in refrigerated or pasteurised long-life bottles. The heat-treated juice is made from whole crushed oranges, including the peel, giving it a much more bitter taste than fresh-squeezed.

In the [[Cookbook:Cuisine of the United States|USA]], orange juice is sometimes also sold in the form of frozen concentrate blocks, so a recipe may say 'one box or block frozen orange juice'. These are not available in [[Cookbook:Cuisine of Australia|Australia]] and some other countries. 

Oranges are not often used in savoury cooking, but they are an important flavouring ingredient of several recipes, including [[Cookbook:Orange Chicken|orange chicken]], and the [[Cookbook:Cuisine of France|French]] dish [[Cookbook:Duck a l'Orange|duck a l'orange]]. Orange zest, candied peel and orange juice are frequently used in making cakes and sweets.

Orange blossom water is sometimes used as an alternative to [[Cookbook:Rosewater|rosewater]] in [[Cookbook:Middle Eastern cuisines|Middle Eastern cookery]], especially in sweet pastries and jams. 

Orange blossom [[Cookbook:Honey|honey]] (really &quot;citrus honey&quot;) is produced by putting beehives in citrus groves during bloom, which also [[w:pollination|pollinates]] seeded citrus varieties. Orange blossom honey is highly prized, and has a distinct &quot;orangey&quot; flavor.

==Orange Recipes==
*[[Cookbook:Tarbes Salad|Tarbes Salad]]
*[[Cookbook:Carrot and Raisin Salad|Carrot and Raisin Salad]]
*[[Cookbook:Madeira Honey Cake|Madeira Honey Cake]] (juice and zest)
*[[Cookbook:Mincemeat Tart|Mincemeat Tart]] (candied peel)
*[[Cookbook:Jamaican Jerk Chicken|Jamaican Jerk Chicken]] (juice)
*[[Cookbook:Chocolate Chip Cookies|Chocolate Chip Cookies]] (zest)

==See also==
*[[Cookbook:Tangerine|Tangerine]]
*[[Cookbook:Kumquat|Kumquat]]
*[[Cookbook:Lemon|Lemon]]
*[[Cookbook:Lime|Lime]]
*[[Cookbook:Grapefruit|Grapefruit]]

{{wikipedia|Orange (fruit)}}


[[Category:Featured ingredients|{{PAGENAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>rt68c0t535m1s4c5vh3ckkfdtuglhq5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook talk:Orange</title>
    <ns>103</ns>
    <id>4240</id>
    <revision>
      <id>353960</id>
      <parentid>156030</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-02-03T05:01:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Uncle G's major work 'bot</username>
        <id>10904</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[Talk:Cookbook:Orange]] moved to [[Cookbook talk:Orange]]: COOKBOT: Renaming talk page to Cookbook talk namespace</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">origional article text adapted from [[en:Orange (fruit)]].

== Featured ingredient ==

This module was the featued ingredient on the main [[Cookbook]] page from June 19, 2004 - ????. [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] 10:25, 19 Jun 2004 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>gxx91h82cm9a4a2q98wrvsgc87xvdcv</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Fairy Cakes</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4241</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2682058</id>
      <parentid>2458167</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-07-16T23:56:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Austncorp</username>
        <id>1540792</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Procedure */ Added baking cat.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{recipesummary|Dessert recipes|18|1 hour|2|Image=[[Image:Fairy cakes close up on tray.jpg|250px]]}}
{{recipe}} | [[Cookbook:Dessert|Dessert]] | [[Cookbook:Cake|Cake]]

'''Fairy Cakes''' are the British term for what Americans call [[Cookbook:cupcakes|cupcakes]]. A common variant on fairy cakes is '''butterfly cakes''', where the top of the cake is cut out and shaped to look like butterfly wings.

==Ingredients== 
*125 grams [[Cookbook:Butter|butter]] 
*3/4 cup [[Cookbook:Caster sugar|caster sugar]] 
*1 tsp [[Cookbook:Vanilla Extract|vanilla]] or [[Cookbook:Lemon extract|lemon extract]] 
*2 [[Cookbook:Egg|eggs]] 
*2 cups [[Cookbook:Flour|self-raising flour]] 
*1/2 cup [[Cookbook:Milk|milk]] 
* If you want to make the '''fairy cakes''' into '''butterfly cakes''':
**1/2 cup jam 
**1/2 cup [[Cookbook:Cream|cream]], whipped
*[[Cookbook:Powdered sugar|icing sugar]] to dust with

==Procedure== 
[[Image:Plain butterfly cake.jpg|thumb|A butterfly cake]]
# Beat the butter, sugar and vanilla or lemon extract until creamy. 
# Beat in the eggs one at a time. 
# Fold in the sifted flour alternately with the milk. 
# Three-quarters fill 18 well-greased paper patty cases or well-greased muffin tins. 
# Bake at 180°C for 12-15 minutes until well risen and golden. Cool on a cake rack. 
# If you want to make the '''fairy cakes''' into '''butterfly cakes''':
## Cut out a small circle in the top of each cake (using a small knife) and cut each circle in half. 
## Spoon a little jam in the centre hollow and top with whipped cream. 
## Arrange the &quot;wings&quot; into the cream.

Dust with icing sugar before serving.

[[Category:Cake recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Baking recipes]]
[[Category:Recipes with metric units|{{PAGENAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>eujttvkym5z5kg6mmjou9sbt8c315y2</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:How to Find a Book</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>4242</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1122820</id>
      <parentid>156032</parentid>
      <timestamp>2008-02-25T02:12:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Remi</username>
        <id>58775</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[Talk:How to find a book]] moved to [[Talk:How to Find a Book]]: naming conventions</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">    * (cur) (last) . . 19:42, Jan 29, 2004 . . Jamesday (mention the invalidity of the contract terms)
    * (cur) (last) . . M 02:32, Jan 24, 2004 . . Jiang
    * (cur) (last) . . 12:01, Jan 11, 2004 . . 212.194.237.229
    * (cur) (last) . . M 19:35, Jan 8, 2004 . . Tim Chambers (&quot;ISBN number&quot; is redundant)
    * (cur) (last) . . 21:53, Jan 2, 2004 . . 209.198.39.210
    * (cur) (last) . . 22:22, Nov 20, 2003 . . 217.255.71.212
    * (cur) (last) . . 21:20, Nov 12, 2003 . . 192.204.1.2
    * (cur) (last) . . 21:19, Nov 12, 2003 . . 192.204.151.38
    * (cur) (last) . . 21:18, Nov 12, 2003 . . 192.204.151.38
    * (cur) (last) . . 21:26, Feb 20, 2003 . . Hhanke (+digital libraries)
    * (cur) (last) . . 12:34, Nov 6, 2002 . . Fred Bauder (WorldCat)
    * (cur) (last) . . 21:06, Sep 6, 2002 . . Ed Poor (spell check (7 changes))
    * (cur) (last) . . M 09:43, Aug 31, 2002 . . 206.15.46.129 (clarified LCSH, this library doesn't have it)
    * (cur) (last) . . 09:32, Aug 31, 2002 . . AxelBoldt
    * (cur) (last) . . 09:31, Aug 31, 2002 . . AxelBoldt
    * (cur) (last) . . 09:29, Aug 31, 2002 . . AxelBoldt (organized links)
    * (cur) (last) . . 09:14, Aug 31, 2002 . . AxelBoldt
    * (cur) (last) . . 09:12, Aug 31, 2002 . . Fredbauder (pricescan link)
    * (cur) (last) . . 09:10, Aug 31, 2002 . . AxelBoldt
    * (cur) (last) . . 09:08, Aug 31, 2002 . . AxelBoldt
    * (cur) (last) . . 08:54, Aug 31, 2002 . . AxelBoldt (rewrite)
    * (cur) (last) . . 07:48, Aug 31, 2002 . . Fredbauder (Amazon and BN links)
    * (cur) (last) . . M 07:37, Aug 31, 2002 . . Fredbauder
    * (cur) (last) . . 07:37, Aug 31, 2002 . . Fredbauder (ISBN.nu link)
    * (cur) (last) . . 07:33, Aug 31, 2002 . . Fredbauder (AddALL used search)
    * (cur) (last) . . 07:27, Aug 31, 2002 . . Fredbauder (AddAll link)
    * (cur) (last) . . 07:21, Aug 31, 2002 . . Fredbauder (change eBay link to books page)
    * (cur) (last) . . 07:20, Aug 31, 2002 . . 213.253.40.27 (-*)
    * (cur) (last) . . 07:15, Aug 31, 2002 . . Fredbauder (Alibris search link)
    * (cur) (last) . . 07:09, Aug 31, 2002 . . Fredbauder (Bibliofind link)
    * (cur) (last) . . 07:03, Aug 31, 2002 . . Fredbauder (ABE advanced search link)
    * (cur) (last) . . 06:50, Aug 31, 2002 . . Fredbauder (removal of AddAll search engine (doesn't work as written))
    * (cur) (last) . . 06:48, Aug 31, 2002 . . Fredbauder (temporary insertion of AddAll search engine will be discussed on mailing list)
    * (cur) (last) . . 07:30, Aug 30, 2002 . . Zadcat
    * (cur) (last) . . 06:30, Aug 30, 2002 . . 217.168.172.202 (about experience)
    * (cur) (last) . . 06:26, Aug 30, 2002 . . Fredbauder (a start)
    * (cur) (last) . . 17:36, Aug 29, 2002 . . Fredbauder (to be worked on later)</text>
      <sha1>c0dx5n4q8umtv8d2l8457n1e3f8fgsf</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>How to Find a Book</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4243</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2508239</id>
      <parentid>2508162</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-04-03T07:19:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/Ellisun|Ellisun]] ([[User talk:Ellisun|talk]]) to last version by Adrignola</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''How to Find a Book''' depends on how much information you have about the book and whether you want to buy it or simply read it. 

== Acquiring information about the book ==

Normally, title and name of the author of a book is enough to locate more information about it. You can then use online bookstores or online library catalogs to identify publisher, publication date, edition and [[w:ISBN|ISBN]]; these items are sometimes required by libraries or bookstores to order the book.

Occasionally, the author's name is misspelled, especially with foreign authors. In this case try searching for the title alone, until you find the proper spelling of the name.

'''If you only have the book's ISBN, you should be aware of the fact that different editions as well as hardcover and soft-cover versions of a book have different ISBNs.''' It is possible that the version of the book with your ISBN is already out of print, while another version is still available. It is therefore best to use an online service to get the author and title information, and then proceed with that information.

Locating a book is much more difficult if you want to educate yourself about a topic but don't have a particular author or title in mind. Library shelves are organized by subject; learn the system used by your library, go to the relevant shelve and browse the books about your topic. Some of this can also be done online: library catalogs allow subject and keyword searches and the Library of Congress permits browsing by call number, which can often locate closely related materials. For an effective subject search, you need to know which subject words are being used; this is contained in the &quot;Library of Congress Subject Headings&quot;, a red five-volume work that many libraries have but can not be found online (most library subjects can be searched and browsed on [http://isbndb.com/d/subject/ ISBNdb.com's subject search]).

Most topics have one or two &quot;standard references&quot;, the generally acknowledged best treatments of the subject. To find these, you need to talk to a specialist in the field. A [[Usenet]] posting to a relevant newsgroup, asking about good books, also often yields excellent results. Closely reading the user-supplied book reviews on amazon.com will also often point you to standard references: they are often only identified by author and everyone seems to know them.

== Acquiring the book ==

You have to decide whether you want to buy the book or just read it. If you want to buy it, you have to decide whether to buy it new or used (the only option if no version of it is in print, unless you can find a new after-market copy or a [[w:Remaindered book|remaindered book]]). 

To buy used books, you can try a local used book store. These can also often help you buy books that they don't have. You may also go to a professional book finder with connections in the used-book markets. These used-book markets are now open to everyone with a web browser and a credit or debit card, and books can also be found via auction websites.  The three best sites for used-books, which between them cover countless thousands of sellers are: [[w:Abebooks|Abebooks]], [[w:eBay|eBay]] and [[w:Amazon.com|Amazon]] (on an Amazon book entry look for the link to &quot;new and used books&quot;, which takes one to many sellers of used books).

A book in print can be ordered at any bookstore and can also be ordered online; several price comparison services exist. By ordering online, you typically save sales tax but you have to pay shipping and handling costs.

Depending on what you need, you may be able to find a book at a public library or a good local college or university library. These can be used by non-students for free or for a small fee. 

If your reading interest is general, or if you want to read a popular novel, a public library is the place to go.  Membership is usually free.  If you cannot find the book on your own, you should visit an information desk because many libraries offer the ability to place &quot;holds&quot; on materials so you can get them when you return. 

At college and university libraries, Research librarians can help you locate books and journal articles of academic interest quickly. On campus, you can often use expensive databases such as [[w:LexisNexis|LexisNexis]] for free. Libraries are connected by an Inter Library Loan network: if the book exists, and is held by a library willing to loan it, you will have it in as little as a week or so.

Most libraries also offer an Inter-library loan service.  This means that items that do not appear in their catalog can be requested from libraries elsewhere.   Depending on the library and how far the book has to travel, there may be charges for this service.

Libraries use [[w:WorldCat|WorldCat]] at [[w:OCLC|OCLC]] in order to find books at other libraries. It is by far the most extensive database of library holdings. Some libraries allow access by their patrons; ask your librarian how to access WorldCat. Unsuccessful ABEbooks searches are directed to WorldCat as unsuccessful WorldCat searches are to ABEbooks. WorldCat attempts to restrict use of its data but such terms are not legally valid under US copyright law, since only the specific and creative original expression, if any, can be protected by copyright and the right to use public domain works cannot be restricted by contract (see [[w:Feist v. Rural|Feist v. Rural]] and [[w:Assessment Technologies v. WIREdata|Assessment Technologies v. WIREdata]])
*&quot;WorldCat® records, metadata and holdings information (&quot;Data&quot;) may only be used by Users (individuals accessing WorldCat via OCLC Web interfaces) solely for the personal, non-commercial purpose of assisting such Users with locating an item in a library of the User's choosing. Users acquire no ownership rights to any Data or portions thereof provided in any form by WorldCat. No part of any Data provided in any form by WorldCat may be used, disclosed, reproduced, transferred or transmitted in any form without the prior written consent of OCLC except as expressly permitted hereunder. Use of WorldCat for cataloging purposes is expressly prohibited. User may not resell or otherwise transfer WorldCat. User shall not omit or obscure any notice of a limitation of warranty, disclaimer, copyright, patent, trademark, trade secret, usage limitation or any logo, splash screen or any other terms and/or conditions intended to be displayed in WorldCat by OCLC or any supplier thereto.&quot;

==External links==

===Library catalogs===
* [http://copac.ac.uk/ COPAC], combined catalog of the British Library and UK and Irish research libraries
* [http://www.cdlib.org/collections/ California Digital Library], combined catalog of the University of California schools
* [http://catalog.loc.gov Library of Congress catalog]
* [http://accesspa.state.pa.us/ Access Pennsylvania Database], provides a catalog in database form for the entire Pennsylvania library system
* [http://www.worldcat.org WorldCat]

===Digital libraries===
There are also digital libraries, where you can find books in electronic form (mostly scanned paper books).  The most famous digital library is [http://gutenberg.org/ Project Gutenberg].

===Digital databases===
* [http://books.google.com/ Google Books], searches books Google has scanned

{{Subjects|Literature}}
{{Alphabetical|H}}
{{status|0%}}</text>
      <sha1>mm1ihvucxsbyq9udps5qczno9b7mqm2</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>