<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>File:2-cyclopropylbutane.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1061</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748811</id>
      <parentid>746288</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-02-09T19:42:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>lftdbfdb9bftwmpa42ewbdhqaw7jksr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:1,3-dicyclopropylpropane.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1063</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748810</id>
      <parentid>746290</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-02-09T19:42:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>lftdbfdb9bftwmpa42ewbdhqaw7jksr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Bicyclo2.1.0pentane.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1064</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748809</id>
      <parentid>746292</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-02-09T19:42:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>lftdbfdb9bftwmpa42ewbdhqaw7jksr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Staggerednewmanprojection.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1073</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748807</id>
      <parentid>746302</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-02-09T19:41:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>lftdbfdb9bftwmpa42ewbdhqaw7jksr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Chairconformationmini.jpg</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1074</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748804</id>
      <parentid>746294</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-02-09T19:41:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>lftdbfdb9bftwmpa42ewbdhqaw7jksr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Methylnewman.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1077</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748803</id>
      <parentid>153207</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-02-09T19:41:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>bqzg6alf693qn5egkcy4lip7de3tqdd</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Spinningnewman.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1078</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748802</id>
      <parentid>746300</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-02-09T19:41:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>lftdbfdb9bftwmpa42ewbdhqaw7jksr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Botany/Introduction</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1085</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2215396</id>
      <parentid>2063482</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-11-20T23:47:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Xania</username>
        <id>40302</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>typo</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;&lt; [[Botany|Contents Page]]
----
== Introduction to the Botany Study Guide == 

This ''Study Guide to the Science of Botany'' is a textbook at '''''Wikibooks''''' shelved at the [[Wikibooks:biology bookshelf]] and intended to establish a course of study in the subject of Botany, utilizing articles provided in '''''[http://www.Wikipedia.org/ Wikipedia]''''', with links to other relevant web sites and other Wikibooks as appropriate. In some cases, portions of the text from  ''Wikipedia'' articles have been used to materially develop introductory text within the Guide.    

For the new user, it need be pointed out that ''Wikipedia'' differs from a standard encyclopedia in two important respects: 1) it is a '''hypertext''' document, and 2) it is open and editable, and therefore '''constantly changing'''. For the student following this or any guide through ''Wikipedia'' to cover a specific subject, it is recommended that each article (page) be read first in its entirety, before any hyperlinks are followed to other topics or explanations.  It is too easy, otherwise, to simply become lost in a maze of links, and miss the main thrust of an article presented as an assignment from the Guide.  Because ''Wikipedia'' is constantly changing (and, it is believed, improving) the quality of each article encountered will be variable.  Some articles are well written and go to adequate depth, whereas others, lacking a proponent, are shallow and incomplete. Short or sloppy looking articles may contain questionable facts. These short-comings should diminish with time, but can be a problem for the student.  

One clear advantage to using this Guide linked to a hypertext like ''Wikipedia'' is the &quot;circular redundancy with serendipity&quot; factor that arises when an article is read and its hyperlinks followed; this factor can be a powerful learning tool. The persistent reader is  subjected to a fairly high degree of repetitive reading, often presenting slightly differing perspectives on the same general topic, with the result that learning comes from redundancy and seeing difficult concepts presented in more than one way. At the same time, some hyperlinks lead down less relevant paths, bringing new and unanticipated knowledge. If, as a student, you are truly interested in mastering the subject of botany, you must be prepared to read beyond the basic assignments; in some cases, beyond Wikipedia to explore other, &quot;outside&quot; web sites.  

It seems likely that the typical user of the ''Study Guide to the Science of Botany'' is not necessarily an active student taking a course in botany at the high school (AP) or college level, but a person with a strong interest in plants&amp;mdash;an amateur naturalist or a gardener.  Therefore the guide must incorporate both the basic biological and physiological aspects of plants as well as extensive taxonomy-based coverage of the diversity of plants and related organisms. The amount of material now available on the web covering the latter subject is becoming nothing short of phenomenal. In effect, one now has access to much of the world's plant diversity, with photographs and descriptions, in many cases from web sites maintained by specialists. One goal of the guide is to provide a systematics-based approach to capturing this kind of information, hopefully giving the student a strong background in plant systematics.  The importance of this approach is not that everyone should become a taxonomist&amp;mdash;or become more familiar with plant taxonomy, a specialized field of botanical science with a relatively narrow following&amp;mdash;but that appreciation for (and understanding of) species diversity is most critical at this time in our earth's history marked by accelerated species extinctions and destruction of native ecosystems by both human population expansion and man-induced spread of non-native species.                 

The ''Study Guide to the Science of Botany'' includes two other &quot;parallel&quot; documents intended to enhance the usefulness of the Guide.  These could also be used separately or independently as source documents for a beginning course in Botany.  They are the ''Discussion'' pages and the ''Laboratory Exercise'' pages. Both are explained in detail in the next Section titled ''[[Botany/How_to_use|How to use this Guide]]''.

[[Category:Botany]]</text>
      <sha1>ry8dxny3ki19utqcslqxzdn9gn34uat</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Botany/How to use</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1086</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2063481</id>
      <parentid>940382</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-03-04T17:59:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Avicennasis</username>
        <id>314063</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WP:AWB/T|Typo fixing]], typos fixed: suceeding → succeeding using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;&lt; [[Botany|Contents Page]]
----

&lt;BIG&gt;&lt;BIG&gt;How to Use the ''Botany Study Guide''&lt;BIG&gt;&lt;/BIG&gt;

The purpose of the ''Study Guide to the Science of Botany'' is to weave - out of the information on Life Science and especially Botany contained in ''Wikipedia'' - a course of study for the student or layman.  It is anticipated that this course will be either supplemental to instruction being received at a school or college, or will be self-directed. In either case, the Guide is not a novel and should not be approached as one. A smooth flow of dialogue is simply not possible and should not be anticipated.  The Guide may be closer to the sometimes disjointed notes generated by a student from a lecture or careful reading of a detailed textbook.

Within each subsection of a Chapter, introductory text is followed by one or more &quot;reading assignments&quot; of the form:

*Read [[Wikipedia:en:Botany|Botany]] (&lt;small&gt;Links need not be pursued at this time&lt;/small&gt;) 

Following (that is ''clicking'' on) the link (to ''Wikipedia'' &quot;Botany&quot; in this case) will open an article intended to provide the details of the Chapter subsection. Recommended articles should be read from top to bottom, and then re-read following some or all of the links embedded in the article to other articles for expanded elucidation or to clarify terms; that is, in most cases, completion of an &quot;assignment&quot; (recommended article) includes at least some or all articles linked to the first.  Obviously, it cannot be the case that all links are followed to articles, whose links are then followed to articles, and so on until no new material is encountered. It is likely there would be no quick end to such a pursuit. The amount of time spent wandering beyond the original article is partly a personal matter of how much the reader is getting out of the foray than anything else. Realize it is certainly possible to wander well off the subject at hand.  As in the example above, notes are provided with assignments giving some direction for pursuing links. An instruction NOT to follow links simply means the additional material will be encountered later in the course of instruction, and going beyond the assigned article may provide too much detail for a beginning student.  The following example: 

* Read [[Wikipedia:en:Science|Science]] (&lt;small&gt;The following links are included:&lt;/small&gt;)
** [[Wikipedia:en:Scientific method|Scientific Method]]
** [[Wikipedia:en:Philosophy of science|Philosophy of Science]]

specifies that two other links ARE part of the assignment.  Other links encountered may be followed to expand your knowledge or, as always, to aid in  understanding of technical terms encountered. Hyperlinks included with the text in the Guide are there simply for convenience, usually to topics somewhat peripheral to the main one.  In all cases, finding your way back to the Guide may become tricky, but we have to leave this up to you to establish, beyond pointing out that your browser's ''Back'' button is intended for this purpose.   

==Discussion Questions==

At the end of each subsection are posted one to several questions.  In general, you will get more out of these questions if you write out your answer on a piece of paper.  You may wish to accomplish this on the re-read, allowing each question to guide your quest for an answer. A discussion page for each chapter provides answers to the questions posed. However, the questions are intended to be thought-provoking, and may not have a single straight-forward answer. Answers on the discussion pages are also necessarily much longer than would be expected of any one student; it is expected that each student answer will fit somewhere within the broad discussion presented.  

== Laboratory Exercises ==

A natural sciences course laboratory unit is supposed to provide hands-on experience in exploring topics raised in the text and lecture units. The best that a website can give towards this goal is a manual that is liberally provided with pictures and diagrams. The student must provide the &quot;hands on&quot; from the neighboring natural world. Fortunately, in botany, this is much easier to accomplish than in almost any other field of science. Both the outdoors, the local market, and (if available) a botanical garden can be sources of materials for study. Indeed, we may teach the structure of a ''pome'' using an apple in the hope that the student will end up with a pear.

In using any of the Laboratory Exercises, it is always best to read through the entire module before actually doing anything.  Resist the temptation to view the material as an instruction manual to be followed in a specific order.  For one thing it is difficult to write a module that covers, at each step, all that the student should know before proceeding on to the next step. The value of any exercise will be significantly enhanced if you have a pretty good idea where it is going in advance.

== General Navigation ==

The ''Study Guide'' is divided into Sections and Chapters which define the subject material of each module.  At the bottom of each text page (main text of a module), is a short version of the Table of Contents, allowing the reader to jump between chapters within a Section.  Here is an example of the &quot;Wiki Contents Table&quot; for Section I:

{{Template:BotanyTOC}} 
 
Note that at the beginning of each module, links are provided to both the previous chapter and the succeeding chapter, as well as to the main Table of Contents. Links to units associated with a module, as for example to a Laboratory Exercise, appear near the end of the module

== Final Note ==
 
As [[Botany/A final note about the Guide|a final note]], read the next Section and consider how you might make a contribution to the Guide.

[[Category:Botany]]
[[Category:Botany]]</text>
      <sha1>raocspr3gewxce0cu49dizk9laphduv</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Botany/Plant structure discussion</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1087</id>
    <revision>
      <id>489714</id>
      <parentid>489713</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-06-17T15:25:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[Botany:Plant structure discussion]] moved to [[Botany/Plant structure discussion]]: naming convention</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">== Further Discussion ==
The questions posed in '''Chapter 3. Plant Structure''' are discussed further on this page. Remember, some questions are intended to be thought-provoking and more than one answer may be &quot;correct&quot;.   

&lt;tt&gt;Question&lt;/tt&gt;:
*''At this point the conceptual differences between cell types, tissues, organs, and organisms may be somewhat confusing. Using the leaf as an example, describe this structure in a way that considers the cell types, tissues, and organs for that part of the leaf where photosynthesis is concentrated.''

Photosynthesis is concentrated in the '''mesophyll''' of the leaf. The ''mesophyll'' is a type of ''tissue'' composed of two layers or arrangements of '''chlorenchyma cells''': an upper '''pallisade layer''' of tightly packed parenchyma (called pallisade chlorenchyma), and a lower '''spongy layer''' of loosely packed parenchyma (or spongy chlorenchyma). One could regard these layers as different tissue types (''simple tissues'') and the mesophyll as a ''complex tissue''. The mesophyll is packed between two protective layers of '''epidermal cells''' (tissue: epidermis of epidermal cells and cuticle), which along with the vascular tissue and perhaps other structural tissues form an ''organ'' called the leaf whose primary function is food production for the ''organsim'': the plant.

Leaves usually have a stem-like structural part called a '''petiole''' by which they attach to another plant organ termed the '''stem'''.  

&lt;&lt; [[Botany/Plant_structure|Chapter 3]]

[[Category:Botany]]</text>
      <sha1>35mzxs3y8my25l4wota376kavcqfe3k</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Botany/A final note about the Guide</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1090</id>
    <revision>
      <id>489676</id>
      <parentid>489674</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-06-17T15:10:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[Botany:A final note about the Guide]] moved to [[Botany/A final note about the Guide]]: naming policy</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Botany]]
----
Both this Guide and all articles in ''Wikipedia'' are [[Wikipedia:en:free_content|free content]] that can be added to or edited by anyone.  It is an opportunity for the user of these documents to contribute information, or even state given information more clearly, simply by editing a page. As a student with a textbook and a lecturer (teacher), you may find yourself in possession of useful facts, another point of view on existing facts, or a report you prepared of exceptional quality.  Any of these can be added to an appropriate page in this Guide or the ''Wikipedia''.  However, this caution is strongly advised: ''Do not place into the Guide any text or pictures taken verbatim (or close to verbatim) from a text book, web site, or other copyrighted source without permission of the copyright holder''.  In general, this means, anything you submit should be your own work.

'''To learn how to edit or contribute material to this textbook, first read the introduction at:''' &lt;big&gt;''[[Wikipedia:en:Wikipedia:introduction|How to Edit]]''&lt;/big&gt;.

[[Category:Botany]]</text>
      <sha1>6beeehn3g6cjwk5swulqh5297xv1v78</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Organic Chemistry/Introduction to reactions/Gibbs free energy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1098</id>
    <revision>
      <id>961191</id>
      <parentid>654586</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-09-07T18:35:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>removing all sub-pages from [[Category:Chemistry]], reformatting book main pages to use {{Subject}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;noinclude&gt;
[[Organic Chemistry/Foundational concepts of organic chemistry/Acids and bases|&lt;&lt; Acids and bases]] |
----
&lt;/noinclude&gt;
'''Gibbs free energy''' is represented by the following equation:

:'''&amp;Delta;G = &amp;Delta;H -T&amp;Delta;S'''

:&amp;Delta;G is the change in Gibbs free energy.
:&amp;Delta;H is the change in potential energy, sometimes known as the enthalpy of a system.
:T is the temperature in Kelvin.
:&amp;Delta;S is a statistical correlation, known as the entropy of a system.

&lt;!-- The main idea is that the lowest energy is favored. FALSE  Whenever there is a reaction for which there also is a reverse reaction, nature favours the one reaction, whose products are lesser in energy. --&gt;

The basic principle is that ''total'' entropy increases. This increase can be because of an increase in the entropy of the chemicals, ''&amp;Delta;S'', or because the reaction has produced heat, increasing the entropy of the environment.

The Gibbs free energy lets us calculate the total increase in entropy, including the effects on the environment, without needing to know anything about the environment.

At ''low'' temperatures, ''&amp;Delta;G'' is approximately ''&amp;Delta;H'', and nature favours the reaction with lowest energy products, which release the most heat. This may ''reduce'' the entropy of the ''system'', but the ''increase'' in the entropy of the ''environment'' more than compensates.

At ''high'' temperatures, ''&amp;Delta;G'' is approximately ''-T&amp;Delta;S'', and nature favours the reaction with high energy products, which may actually absorb heat. This may ''reduce'' the entropy of the ''environment'', but the ''increase'' in the entropy of the ''system'' more than compensates.

Either way, the Gibbs free energy ''always'' decreases.


&lt;noinclude&gt;
----
[[Organic Chemistry/Foundational concepts of organic chemistry|&lt;&lt; Foundational concepts]] | [[Organic Chemistry/Foundational concepts of organic chemistry/Acids and bases|&lt;&lt; Acids and bases]] | Gibbs free energy | [[Organic Chemistry/Alkanes|Alkanes &gt;&gt;]]
&lt;/noinclude&gt;

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>fwpgyu0wu3gcn2vhy97ibjwdtz7l313</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Latin/Appendix G</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1100</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1187821</id>
      <parentid>1128199</parentid>
      <timestamp>2008-05-17T17:33:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Carlo.milanesi</username>
        <id>18654</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Latin Mottoes */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">== Latin Mottoes ==

*Aliena pericula, cautiones nostrae.-
''Others' dangers are our warnings.''

*Anno Domini (A.D)
''In the Year of Our Lord''

*Ante Meridiem (am)
''Before midday''

*Ars Gratia Artis (MGM slogan)
''Art for the sake of art''

*Carpe diem
''Seize the day''

*Caveat emptor
''Let the buyer beware.''

*Cave canem
''Beware of the dog.''

*Cavete a canibus
''Beware of the dogs.''

*Dum Spiro, Spero
''While I breath, I hope''

*E pluribus unum
''Out of many, one''

*Exempli Gratia (e.g.)
''For (the sake of) example''

*Id est (i.e.)
''That is''

*Lapsus linguae
''a slip of the tongue''

*Per se
''In itself''

*Post Meridiem (pm)
''After midday''

*Quod erat demonstrandum (QED)
''What was to be demonstated''

*Quid pro quo
''Something for something''

*Sic semper tyrannis
''Thus always to tyrants''

*Semper fidelis
''Always faithful''

*Semper paratus
''Always ready''

*Tempus fugit
''Time flies''

*Terra firma
''Solid land''

*Veni, vidi, vici
''I came, I saw, I conquered''

*Versus (vs.)
''Turned to (competing against)''

*Vice versa
''The other way around''

[[Latin]]
----
The internet is one of the best media to obtain Latin resources. A few sites to get you started are listed here.

'''[http://www.orbilat.com Orbis Latinus]''' Language information on Latin, Vulgar latin, Early Romance Languages and the Late Romance Languages.

'''[http://www.ku.edu/history/index/europe/ancient_rome/E/Roman/Texts/home.html Lacus Curtius]''' Plentiful supply of Latin texts and translations.

'''[http://www.forumromanum.org/index2.html Forum Romanum]''' Many Latin resources.

'''[http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/ Perseus Digital Library]''' Excellent resource for texts and translations online.
----
[[Latin|^ Latin ^]]

[[Category:Latin]]</text>
      <sha1>aaxjcn8jux5mkddp56dyyov2mpxkdrw</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Latin/Index II</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1101</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2410956</id>
      <parentid>2410954</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-24T21:49:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>89.75.33.165</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>hyphens added</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;big&gt;'''''This Page is incomplete'''''&lt;/big&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
For explanations of terms used in these grammar tables, check the [[Glossary]].

== Declension of Nouns ==

=== 1st Declension Masculine/Feminine (each word has a set gender) puella ===


{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! 1st Declension
! Singular
! Plural
|-
| nominative || puell-a || puell-ae
|-
| vocative || puell-a || puell-ae
|-
| accusative || puell-am || puell-as
|-
| genitive || puell-ae || puell-arum
|-
| dative || puell-ae || puell-is
|-
| ablative || puell-a || puell-is
|}

=== 2nd Declension Masculine/Feminine (each word has a set gender): servus ===


{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! 2nd Declension Masculine
! Singular
! Plural
|-
| nominative || serv-us || serv-i
|-
| vocative || serv-e || serv-i
|-
| accusative || serv-um || serv-os
|-
| genitive || serv-i || serv-orum
|-
| dative || serv-o || serv-is
|-
| ablative || serv-o || serv-is
|}

=== 2nd Declension Neuter: bellum ===


{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! 2nd Declension Neuter
! Singular
! Plural
|-
| nominative || bell-um || bell-a
|-
| vocative || bell-um || bell-a
|-
| accusative || bell-um || bell-a
|-
| genitive || bell-i || bell-orum
|-
| dative || bell-o || bell-is
|-
| ablative || bell-o || bell-is
|}

=== 2nd Declension Masculine: puer ===


{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! 2nd Declension Masculine
! Singular
! Plural
|-
| nominative || puer || puer-i
|-
| vocative || puer || puer-i
|-
| accusative || puer-um || puer-os
|-
| genitive || puer-i || puer-orum
|-
| dative || puer-o || puer-is
|-
| ablative || puer-o || puer-is
|}

=== 2nd Declension Masculine: ager ===


{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! 2nd Declension Masculine
! Singular
! Plural
|-
| nominative || ager || agr-i
|-
| vocative || agr-e || agr-i
|-
| accusative || agr-um || agr-os
|-
| genitive || agr-i || agr-orum
|-
| dative || agr-o || agr-is
|-
| ablative || agr-o || agr-is
|}

=== 3rd Declension Masculine or Feminine (each word has a set gender): rex ===


{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! 3rd Declension
! Singular
! Plural
|-
| nominative || rex || reg-es
|-
| vocative || rex || reg-es
|-
| accusative || reg-em || reg-es
|-
| genitive || reg-is || reg-um
|-
| dative || reg-i || reg-ibus
|-
| ablative || reg-e || reg-ibus
|}

=== 3rd Declension Neuter: mare ===


{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! 3rd Declension Neuter
! Singular
! Plural
|-
| nominative || mar-e || mar-ia
|-
| vocative || mar-e || mar-ia
|-
| accusative || mar-e || mar-ia
|-
| genitive || mar-is || mar-ium
|-
| dative || mar-i || mar-ibus
|-
| ablative || mar-i || mar-ibus
|}

=== 4th Declension Masculine/Feminine (each word has a set gender) gradus ===


{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! 4th Declension
! Singular
! Plural
|-
| nominative || grad-us || grad-us
|-
| vocative || grad-us || grad-us
|-
| accusative || grad-um || grad-us
|-
| genitive || grad-us || grad-uum
|-
| dative || grad-ui || grad-ibus
|-
| ablative || grad-u || grad-ibus
|}

=== 4th Declension Neuter: cornu ===


{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! 4th Declension Neuter
! Singular
! Plural
|-
| nominative || corn-u || corn-a
|-
| vocative || corn-u || corn-a
|-
| accusative || corn-u || corn-a
|-
| genitive || corn-us || corn-uum
|-
| dative || corn-ui || corn-ibus
|-
| ablative || corn-u || corn-ibus
|}

=== 5th Declension Masculine/Feminine (each word has a set gender): res ===


{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! 5th Declension Feminine/Masculine
! Singular
! Plural
|-
| nominative || r-es || r-es
|-
| vocative || r-es || r-es
|-
| accusative || r-em || r-es
|-
| genitive || r-ei || r-erum
|-
| dative || r-ei || r-ebus
|-
| ablative || r-e || r-es
|}

m = masculine
f = feminine
n - neuter

Notes: 4/5th declensions are modified 3rd declensions, thus behave similarily. 3rd declension is either M/F/N, 4th declension is either M/F/N and 5th declension is either M/F. So for 3rd, 4th, and 5th declension is of most importance to memorise the gender because the adjective will still need to agree (ie have the same) with the noun in both case, gender, and number.

The Vocative only changes for the 2nd declension masculine singular (however not for the nouns that leave the -us suffix when in nominative).

There are a few exceptions in the 1st declension which are not feminine. Such nouns are poet-a (1st declension masculine, so to agree you need to use -us on the adjective) and naut-a.

There are a few second declension nouns with irregularities. It is of most importance that you memorise them.

When memorising a noun's meaning, make sure that you also memorise any irregularities the noun has, the gender, and the declension. Without doing this you may have trouble translating. For example, 2nd declension masculines have -us in the nominative singular; however, 4th declension masculines have -us in the nominative singular, nominative plural and accusative plural. This may get you confused if you do not memorise the declension of each noun.


==Single Declension Theory==
If you look at the above list of declensions, you may feel that you are going to be overcome if you have to memorize all of it.  Memorization is indeed the key, but it will be easier than you think.  Each word in Latin has three parts: the root, the stem vowel, and the ending.  There are five vowels in Latin, so there are five stem vowels: A,O,I,U,E. Any word not really having a stem vowel naturally was given to I. If you study the declension patterns enough you will see that there are many similarities in the declensions.  All accusative singulars end in &quot;m&quot; except neuters that sometimes still do.  All accusative plurals end in 's' except neuters that always end in ''a''.  All genitive plurals end in &quot;um&quot;, be it ''ium, rum, uum'' or whatever else.
If you read enough Latin you will actually find that authors would switch a declension of a word at will if it made the sentence clearer.  Thus many words that are of the 4th declension were sometimes written as if 2nd, and 5th declension as if 3rd and vice versa.  Some ending patterns that we use for one declension may also be used in another, again to make the sentence clearer.  Thus &quot;filiabus&quot; would be used in any sentence where we want to make it clear that we are talking about the Daughters and specifically not the Sons.  We also see examples of this in ''animabus''.  Some think that the ''IS'' used in the first and second declensions was actually an abbreviation of ''bus''.
Some students find the ablative difficult since it sometimes looks like the nominative singular, dative plural or neither.  All you really need to do to get the hang of this is to know that in the plural, the ablative always looks like the dative.  If there is no prepostion in front of it then it is probably a dative, unless it is being used in an ablative construction that would likely be apparent.  If there is a preposition and it looks like a dative, just remember that no preposition takes a dative, only ever ablative and sometimes accusative.  Dative plural plus preposition equals ablative.  The ablative singular is really just the root plus the stem vowel with no ending to speak of, since the preposition tells you the grammar of the word.  Some students also get confused by words that are the same in the nominative singular and plural.  Don't worry about that; the verb will tell you which it is since the verb always agrees with the nominative.
It is thought that originally there was only one declension, but during the task of applying it to every word in natural speech it was found that some words naturally changed the way the basic sounds of the original declension worked.  Here is one idea of the original basic declension.


{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! Case
! Root
! Stem Vowel
! Singular
! Plural
|-
| nominative || puell || a || None || es
|-
| genitive || puell || a || is || rum
|-
| dative || puell || a || i || bus
|-
| accusative || puell || a || m || s
|-
| ablative || puell || a || none || bus
|}

When speaking in everyday conversation, Latin speakers would shorten the word in their pronunciation so long as it still made sense.  If you go to New Orleans you will likely hear someone say 'prowly'.  This is not a new dish at a resturaunt or a new new code name for the police, it is actually the local pronunciation of the word ''probably''.  It is ok to shorten this word because when it is shortened everyone can still understand it.  The Latins did the same thing.  It is known that ''I'' can change to ''E'' and vice versa, so we can see that pattern in the dative singular of all declensions.  The ''IS'' of the genitive was kept in the 3rd declension, shortened in the 1st, 2nd, and 5th and slightly altered in the 4th.  The 'add ''M''' rule of the accusative singular is seen in the altering of the stem vowel in the 2nd and 3rd declensions.  The ''ES'' of the nominative plural became ''E'' in 1st, ''I'' in 2nd, and ''US'' in 4th.  The ''RUM'' of the genitive plural was shortened in the 3rd and 4th declensions.  The accusative plural as a rule never changes, but keep in mind that neuter words followed a different pattern of using ''A'' for the accusative plural, and all neuters took the accusative singular or plural for the nominative of the same number.  The ''BUS'' of the dative/ ablative plural was shortened to ''IS'' in the 1st and 2nd declensions but kept in the others.  The 4th declension has a tendency to copy the ''IBUS'' of the 3rd in some authors but retain the ''UBUS'' in others.  When studying Latin declensions you really should strive to memorize the patterns, but also look to see how they are similar to other patterns in the language as it will help you to remember.  Also note that the ''IS'' of the genitive singular is what eventually gave us the word ''HIS'' and the  'add 's'&quot; rule of English.  Latin also gave us the 'add 's'&quot; to make a plural by way of the accusative plural.  If you study other inflexive languages related to Latin, such as Greek, you will notice even similarities across languages.  

[[Category:Latin]]</text>
      <sha1>j2ld0nx1chsbp2mipzjzm4q9t4k4mgb</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Latin/Lesson 2-Genitive and Dative</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1102</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2599737</id>
      <parentid>2566724</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-01-10T17:45:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>146.179.8.134</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* The Genitive */ lower-case common nouns</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Latin}}

==Noun Tables==
{| border=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;5&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot;
|-
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; |
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;header&quot; | '''1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; declension'''
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; class=&quot;header&quot; | '''2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; declension'''
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;header&quot; | '''-a'''
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;header&quot; | '''-us/er'''
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;header&quot; | '''-um (neuter)'''
|-
| ''SINGULAR'' || ''PLURAL''
| ''SINGULAR'' || ''PLURAL''
| ''SINGULAR'' || ''PLURAL''
|-
| nominative || puell'''-a''' || puell'''-ae'''
| serv'''-us'''/pu'''er''' || serv'''-ī'''
| bell'''-um''' || bell'''-a'''
|-
| genitive || puell'''-ae''' || puell'''-ārum'''
| serv'''-ī''' || serv'''-ōrum'''
| bell'''-ī''' || bell'''-ōrum'''
|-
| accusative || puell'''-am''' || puell'''-ās'''
| serv'''-um''' || serv'''-ōs'''
| bell'''-um''' || bell'''-a'''
|-
| dative || puell'''-ae''' || puell'''-īs'''
| serv'''-ō''' || serv'''-īs'''
| bell'''-ō''' || bell'''-īs'''
|}

==The Genitive==
The genitive case is a descriptive case. The genitive case describes the following features of the described noun:
*Possession e.g. The dog of Marcus ''or'' Marcus's dog (canis Marcī)
*Origin e.g. Marcus of Rome (Marcus Romae)
*Relation e.g. A thing of beauty (rēs pulchrae)
*Quantity e.g. A gallon of water
*Quality e.g. Day of wrath (diēs irae)

Quite simply, a word in the genitive case is translated with the preposition &quot;of&quot;. Note that Latin does not have a separate form for the possessive genitive (''Marcus's dog'' vs ''The dog of Marcus''), as English does. A word in the genitive case showing possession can be translated either way. 

===Latin Examples===
{| border=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;5&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
|- style=&quot;font-weight:bold;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; | Latin || colspan=&quot;4&quot; | English
|- style=&quot;background:#ccc;&quot;
| canis || puerī malī || est || bonus || The dog
| of the bad boy || is || good
|- style=&quot;font-style:italic;&quot;
| nominative noun || genitive || verb || nominative adj. || nominative noun
| genitive || verb || nominative adj.
|}

{| border=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;5&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
|- style=&quot;font-weight:bold;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; | Latin || colspan=&quot;4&quot; | English
|- style=&quot;background:#ccc;&quot;
| canis || puerōrum malōrum || est || bonus || The dog
| of the bad boys || is || good
|- style=&quot;font-style:italic;&quot;
| nominative noun || genitive (plural)
| verb || nominative adj. || nominative noun
| genitive || verb || nominative adj.
|}

===Exercise 1===
Indicate the word in the genitive:
#Flavia's dog is good.
#The man has his mother's good taste.
#Māter Flāviae est domina.
#The sword of justice is swift.

==Agreeing with the Adjectives==
When adjectives are used to describe nouns in the genitive case, they must have the same case, number, and gender as the noun to which it refers.

===Example===
;A road of beautiful Rome → Via Romae pulchrae.
:If we look at the bare necessities, namely nouns, in this phrase, then we get &quot;road of Rome,&quot; which is translated as &quot;via Romae.&quot; Now, let's look at the adjective: beautiful (''pulchra''). Its antecedent (the noun it modifies) is Rome. Since Rome is in the genitive case, ''pulchra'' also needs to be in the genitive case. Both are already feminine, so we don't need to change that. 
:To make ''pulchra'' in the genitive singular case, we replace the final &quot;-a&quot; with a &quot;-ae,&quot; and we get ''pulchrae''.

It's that simple.

==The Dative==
The dative case, also known as the indirect object case indicates:
*For whom, e.g., I made this car '''for him'''.
*To whom, e.g., I gave this car '''to him'''.

Latin does not distinguish between &quot;to&quot; or &quot;for&quot;, though this is sometimes the case in English:
*I made this car '''for him'''. ↔ I made '''him''' this car.
*I gave this car '''to him'''. ↔ I gave '''him''' this car.

===Example 1===
{| border=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;5&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
|- style=&quot;background:#ccc;&quot;
| He || made || the desk || for || his friend
|- style=&quot;font-style:italic;&quot;
| nominative noun || verb || accusative || dative prep. || dative
|}

'For' is the preposition indicating a dative. 'For' can be used in some other constructs. To determine whether it is dative, analyse the meaning of the sentence (see Example 3). Practice will enable you to quickly spot the case of a noun in the sentence without much effort.

===Example 2===
''He gave the book '''to John'''''; ''He gave '''to John''' the book''; or ''He gave '''John''' the book''.

This demonstrates how English can use prepositions to change word order and even 'presume' a certain preposition exists that has been left out, giving a dative construct.

===Latin Examples===
{| border=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;5&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
|- style=&quot;font-weight:bold;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; | Latin || colspan=&quot;3&quot; | English
|- style=&quot;background:#ccc;&quot;
| Donō || amīcō meō&lt;ref&gt;Note how the word &quot;meus&quot; become &quot;meo&quot; in order to agree with &quot;amico&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; || donum.
| I gave || my friend || a gift.
|- style=&quot;font-style:italic;&quot;
| verb || dative noun/adj. pair || accusative
| verb || dative noun/adj. pair || accusative
|}

{| border=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;5&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
|- style=&quot;font-weight:bold;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; | Latin || colspan=&quot;3&quot; | English
|- style=&quot;background:#ccc;&quot;
| Feret || mihi&lt;ref&gt;Note that the pronouns have a dative case as well, which can be reviewed in the chapter on pronouns.&lt;/ref&gt; || stylum.
| He brought || me || a pen.
|- style=&quot;font-style:italic;&quot;
| verb || dative pronoun || accusative
| verb || dative pronoun || accusative
|}

{{reflist}}

==Exercise 2: Translate into English==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;3&quot; |
|-
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | &lt;font face=&quot;Arial&quot; size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Latin&lt;/font&gt;
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | &lt;font face=&quot;Arial&quot; size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;English&lt;/font&gt;
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | dō, dāre
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | to give
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | reddō, reddĕre
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | to give back
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | liber, librī (m.)
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | book
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | amīcus, -ī (m.)
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | friend
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | scrībō, -ĕre
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | to write
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | epistula, -ae (f.)
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | letter, message
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | Imperator, Imperatoris (m.)
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | Emperor
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | placeo, -ēre (+dat.)
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | to please, be pleasing to
|}

Note that ''placeo'' requires the dative case, as opposed to the accusative case. Verbs such as this are denoted with ''(+dat.)'' or similar abbreviations. 

{{Latin/Exercise|Questions|
#Do librum amico.
#Amicus meum librum legit et mihi librum reddit.
#Scribo epistulas Imperatori.
#Meae epistulae Imperatori placent.
|
#I give the book to a friend
#The friend read my book and returned the book to me.
#I am writing letters to the Emperor.
#My letters are pleasing to the Emperor.
}}

==Roman Numerals==
The Romans did not use the Hindu-Arabic numerals we use today. They used their own symbols and own numeric system. We still use Roman Numerals today.

{| border=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;5&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
!Roman Numeral
!Latin Number
!English Number
!Hindu-Arabic Numeral
!Spanish Number
!French Number
!Italian Number
!Portuguese Number
|-style=&quot;background:#ccc;&quot;
|I
|ūnus -a -um
|one
|1
|uno
|un
|uno
|um
|-
|II
|duo -ae
|two
|2
|dos
|deux
|due
|dois
|-style=&quot;background:#ccc;&quot;
|III
|trēs, tria
|three
|3
|tres
|trois
|tre
|três
|-
|IV
|quattor
|four
|4
|cuatro
|quatre
|quattro
|quatro
|-style=&quot;background:#ccc;&quot;
|V
|quinque
|five
|5
|cinco
|cinq
|cinque
|cinco
|-
|VI
|sēx
|six
|6
|seis
|six
|sei
|seis
|-style=&quot;background:#ccc;&quot;
|VII
|septem
|seven
|7
|siete
|sept
|sette
|sete
|-
|VIII
|octō
|eight
|8
|ocho
|huit
|otto
|oito
|-style=&quot;background:#ccc;&quot;
|IX
|novem
|nine
|9
|nueve
|neuf
|nove
|nove
|-
|X
|decem
|ten
|10
|diez
|dix
|dieci
|dez
|-style=&quot;background:#ccc;&quot;
|XV
|quindecim
|fifteen
|15
|quince
|quinze
|quindici
|quinze
|-
|XX
|viginti
|twenty
|20
|veinte
|vingt
|venti
|vinte
|-style=&quot;background:#ccc;&quot;
|XXV
|viginti quinque
|twenty-five
|25
|veinticinco
|vingt-cinq
|venticinque
|vinte e cinco
|-
|L
|quinquaginta
|fifty
|50
|cincuenta
|cinquante
|cinquanta
|cinqüenta
|-style=&quot;background:#ccc;&quot;
|C
|centum
|one hundred
|100
|cien
|cent
|cento
|cem
|-
|D
|quingentī, -ae, -a
|five hundred
|500
|quinientos
|cinq cents
|cinquecento
|quinhentos
|-style=&quot;background:#ccc;&quot;
|M
|mille
|one thousand
|1000
|mil
|mille
|mille
|mil
|}

Note the declensions of the first three numbers. ''Nullus'' is the Latin equivalent of zero, for example: ''nullam puellam in agro video'' means ''I see no girl in the field''.

{| border=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;5&quot; cellspacing=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
!Nominative
!Accusative
!Genitive
!Dative
!Ablative
|-
|nullus
|nullum
|nullius
|nulli
|nullo
|-
|nulla
|nullam
|nullius
|nulli
|nulla
|-
|nullum
|nullum
|nullius
|nulli
|nullo
|-style=&quot;background:#ccc;&quot;
|unus
|unum
|unius
|uni
|uno
|-style=&quot;background:#ccc;&quot;
|una
|unam
|unius
|uni
|una
|-style=&quot;background:#ccc;&quot;
|unum
|unum
|unius
|uni
|uno
|-
|duo
|duos
|duorum
|duobus
|duobus
|-
|duae
|duas
|duarum
|duabus
|duabus
|-
|duo
|duo
|duorum
|duobus
|duobus
|-style=&quot;background:#ccc;&quot;
|tres
|tres
|trium
|tribus
|tribus
|-style=&quot;background:#ccc;&quot;
|tres
|tres
|trium
|tribus
|tribus
|-style=&quot;background:#ccc;&quot;
|tria
|tria
|trium
|tribus
|tribus
|}

===Exercise 3===
Write the word form of the numbers in the following sentences in the correct case.

#'''III''' homines me salutant
#magistro '''II''' libros reddo
#'''D''' senatoribus multa (&lt;i&gt;many things&lt;/i&gt;) dico
#'''III''' horas diligenter laboro

[[Category:Latin]]</text>
      <sha1>cxc7e6k8l9shf1tyhtroh4ajsb6hb61</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:Undotwa</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>1105</id>
    <revision>
      <id>153233</id>
      <parentid>2966</parentid>
      <timestamp>2003-09-12T02:19:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Karl Wick</username>
        <id>6</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>answer to emailed question</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Undotwa, the book you have started [[Latin|here]] will live for generations as the basis for many people's learning and undertanding of Latin. Best wishes in your project and thank you for being among the first persons to do serious work in this space. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
----
===Page formatting===
Your question: &quot;Do you have any advice on fixing layout? After editing
the changes the page looks hideous.&quot;

Dan, I'm looking around for some good links on how to format things in Wiki markup language (I just made that term up). Mostly regular HTML works but there are a number of shortcuts .. like to make an external link use a single pair of these things: [ ] with the link inbetween. For an internal link do double: [[ ]] and just put the last part of the link on there, the page name. Is that what you are talking about ? Or other formatting issues .. you can upload images easy too. Do you want a different font, or what ? I'm not the most knowlegable but there are people around that I can find to help you. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]</text>
      <sha1>g5uk397l6mxwdou5uk68c4z44yn73x5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:S-orbital.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1107</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748799</id>
      <parentid>746327</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-02-09T19:40:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>lftdbfdb9bftwmpa42ewbdhqaw7jksr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:P-orbital.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1108</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748798</id>
      <parentid>746329</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-02-09T19:40:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>lftdbfdb9bftwmpa42ewbdhqaw7jksr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Pi-bonding.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1110</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748795</id>
      <parentid>746324</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-02-09T19:40:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>lftdbfdb9bftwmpa42ewbdhqaw7jksr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Spanish/Exercises/Verbs ser And estar - Solutions</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1112</id>
    <revision>
      <id>616051</id>
      <parentid>532398</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-10-18T04:13:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Guanabot</username>
        <id>5478</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>User-controlled Bot: table syntax updated</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Soluciones a los [[Spanish/Exercises/Verbs_ser_And_estar|ejercicios]].
''Solutions to the [[Spanish/Exercises/Verbs_ser_And_estar|exercises]]''
----
Llena los espacios en blanco con la forma verbal correcta del verbo &quot;ser&quot;.
''Fill the blank spaces with the correct form of the ver &quot;ser&quot; (to be).''

{|  border=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot;
|-
| Inglés || Español
|-
| ''English'' || ''Spanish''
|-
| -- || --
|-
| I '''am''' your brother. || Yo '''soy''' tu hermano.
|-
| I '''am''' your sister. || Yo '''soy''' tu hermana.
|-
| You '''are''' my friend. || Tu '''eres''' mi amigo.
|-
| You '''are''' my boss. || Usted '''es''' mi jefe.
|-
| He '''is''' a good man. || Él '''es''' un buen hombre.
|-
| She '''is''' a traveller. || Ella '''es''' una viajera.
|-
| We '''are''' students. || Nosotros '''somos''' estudiantes.
|-
| You '''are''' dangerous. || Vosotros '''sois''' peligrosos.
|-
| You '''are''' Spaniards. || Vosotras '''sois''' españolas.
|-
| They '''are''' persons. || Ellos '''son''' personas.
|}

Llena los espacios en blanco con la forma verbal correcta del verbo &quot;estar&quot;.''Fill the blank spaces with the correct form of the ver &quot;estar&quot; (to be).''

{|  border=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot;
|-
| Inglés || Español
|-
| ''English'' || ''Spanish''
|-
| -- || --
|-
| I '''am''' in my house. || Yo '''estoy''' en mi casa.
|-
| You '''are''' in the correct place.
| Tú '''estás''' en el sitio correcto.
|-
| You '''are''' angry. || Tú '''estás''' enfadado.
|-
| You '''are''' happy. || Usted '''está''' contento.
|-
| He '''is''' in Europe. || Él '''está''' en Europa.
|-
| She '''is''' (temporarily) fat. || Ella '''está''' gorda.
|-
| We '''are''' in the Americas. || Nosotros '''estamos''' en América.
|-
| You '''are''' in África. || Vosotros '''estáis''' en África.
|-
| They '''are''' ill. || Ellos '''están''' enfermos.
|}
----------------------------
Llena los espacios en blanco con la forma verbal correcta del verbo &quot;ser&quot; o &quot;estar&quot;. ''Fill the blank spaces with the correct form of the ver &quot;ser&quot; or &quot;estar&quot; (to be).''

{|  border=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot;
|-
| Inglés || Español
|-
| ''English'' || ''Spanish''
|-
| -- || --
|-
| I '''am''' in China.
| Yo '''estoy''' en China.''(soy/estoy)''
|-
| You '''are''' my friend.
| Tú '''eres''' mi amigo.''(eres/estás)''
|-
| You '''are''' there.
| Tú '''estás''' allí. ''(eres/estás)''
|-
| She '''is''' my sister.
| Ella '''es''' mi hermana. ''(es/está)''
|-
| He '''is''' ill.
| Él '''está''' enfermo. ''(es/está)''
|-
| We '''are''' ready.
| Nosotros '''estamos''' preparados. ''(somos/estamos)''
|-
| We '''are''' intelligent.
| Nosotros '''somos''' inteligentes. ''(somos/estamos)''
|-
| You '''are''' in Europe.
| Vosotros '''estáis''' en Europa. ''(sois/estáis)''
|-
| You '''are''' sad.
| Vosotras '''estáis''' tristes. ''(sois/estáis)''
|-
| They '''are''' sympathetic.
| Ellas '''son''' comprensivas. ''(son/están)''
|-
| They '''are''' interesting people.
| Ellos '''son''' gente interesante. ''(son/están)''
|}
----------------------------------------
[[Spanish/Exercises/Verbs_ser_And_estar|Enlace a los Ejercicios]] ''Link to exercices''

[[Spanish/Lesson_1|Enlace a la lección 1]] ''Link to the lesson 1.''

[[Category:Spanish]]</text>
      <sha1>j2c8bapzyva9j2cdcp8yj5459e2ysaq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>