<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>English in Use/Pronouns</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2288</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2638353</id>
      <parentid>2580342</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-04-26T12:39:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Glennobrien</username>
        <id>434658</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Simple personals */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{English in Use}}
----

A '''pronoun''' is a word used instead of a noun: as,

*&quot;The boy loves his book; he has long lessons, and he learns them well.&quot;

Pronouns are not a requirement of a sentence, and it is possible for them to never to be used in sentences. However, many sentences become unwieldy without them:

*&quot;Alistair is doing what Alistair thinks is best according to Alistair's rights as a human being.&quot;
*Better, &quot;Alistair is doing what he thinks is best according to his rights as a human being.&quot;

The pronouns in English language are twenty-four; and their variations are thirty-two: so that the number of words of this class, is fifty-six.

Pronouns are divided into three classes; personal, relative, and interrogative.

Pronouns also change depending on whether they refer to one person or thing (singular) or a group of people or things (plural).


==Personal pronouns==

A personal pronoun or '''personal''' is a pronoun that shows, by its form, of what person it is: as,

*&quot;Whether it were I or they, so we preach, and so you believed.&quot;&amp;mdash;1 Cor., xv, 11.

The simple personal pronouns are five: namely, ''I'', of the first person; ''you'', of the second person; ''he, she'', and ''it'', of the third person.

The compound personal pronouns are also five: namely, ''myself'', of the first person; ''yourself'', of the second person; ''himself, herself'', and ''itself'', of the third person.

First person pronouns are used when referring to oneself:

*&quot;''I'' think ''I'' am not silly.&quot;

Second person pronouns are used to refer to someone who you are conversing with, the person the sentence is intended to be heard by:

*&quot;''You'' are not very silly.&quot;

Third person pronouns are used when referring to something else that is outside the conversation, either some other person, or an object not capable of understanding or communicating:

*&quot;I don't like the tree because ''it'' is ugly.&quot;
*&quot;I don't like the RIAA because ''they'' sued me.&quot;

Third person singular pronouns are the only pronouns marked for gender. If gender is unknown, use ''he or she'' or use a plural.

==Relative pronouns==

A relative pronoun or '''relative''' is a pronoun that represents an antecedent word or phrase, and connects different clauses of a sentence: as,

*&quot;No people can be great, who have ceased to be virtuous.&quot;&amp;mdash;Dr. Johnson.

The relative pronouns are ''who, which, what, that, as'', and the compounds ''whoever or whosoever, whichever or whichsoever, whatever or whatsoever''.

''What'' is a kind of double relative, equivalent to &quot;that which&quot; or &quot;those which&quot;; and is to be parsed first as antecedent, and then as relative: as,

*&quot;This is what I wanted; that is to say, the thing which I wanted.&quot;&amp;mdash;L. Murray. III.

==Interrogative pronouns==

An interrogative pronoun or '''interrogative''' is a pronoun with which a question is asked: as,

*&quot;Who touched my clothes?&quot;&amp;mdash;Mark, v, 30.

The interrogative pronouns are ''who, which'', and ''what''; being the same in form as relatives.

''Who'' demands a person's name; ''which'', that a person or thing be distinguished from others; ''what'', the name of a thing, or a person's occupation and character.

Pronouns have the same modifications as nouns; namely, persons, numbers, genders, and cases. Definitions universally applicable have already been given of all these things; it is therefore unnecessary to define them again in this place.

The declension of a pronoun is a regular arrangement of its numbers and cases.

==Simple personals==

The simple personal pronouns are thus declined:
&lt;pre&gt;
I, of the first person, any of the genders.

Sing. Nom.  I,             Plur. Nom.  we,
      Poss. my, or mine,         Poss. our, or ours,
      Obj.  me;                  Obj.  us.

You, of the second person, any of the genders.

Nom.  you,
Poss. your, or yours,
Obj.  you.

He, of the third person, masculine gender.

Sing. Nom.  he,            Plur. Nom.  they,
      Poss. his,                 Poss. their, or theirs,
      Obj.  him;                 Obj.  them.

She, of the third person, feminine gender.

Sing. Nom.  she,           Plur. Nom.  they,
      Poss. her, or hers,        Poss. their, or theirs,
      Obj.  her;                 Obj.  them.

It, of the third person, neuter gender.

Sing. Nom,  it,            Plur. Nom.  they,
      Poss. its,                 Poss. their, or theirs,
      Obj.  it;                  Obj.  them.
&lt;/pre&gt;

==Compound personals==

The word ''self'', added to the simple personal pronouns, forms the class of compound personal pronouns; which are used when an action reverts upon the agent, and also when some persons are to be distinguished from others. They all want the possessive case, and are alike in the nominative and objective. Thus:
&lt;pre&gt;
Myself, of the first person, any of the genders

Sing. Nom.  myself,   Plur. Nom.  ourselves
      Poss. ------,         Poss. ---------,
      Obj.  myself;         Obj.  ourselves.

Yourself, of the second person, any of the genders.

Sing. Nom.  yourself,
      Poss. --------,
      Obj.  yourself.

Plur. Nom.  yourselves,
      Poss. ----------,
      Obj.  yourselves.

Himself, of the third person, masculine gender.

Sing. Nom.  himself,  Plur. Nom.  themselves,
      Poss. -------,        Poss. ----------,
      Obj.  himself;        Obj.  themselves.

Herself, of the third person, feminine gender.

Sing. Nom.  herself   Plur. Nom.  themselves,
      Poss. -------,        Poss. ----------,
      Obj.  herself;        Obj.  themselves.

Itself, of the third person, neuter gender.

Sing. Nom.  itself,   Plur. Nom.  themselves,
      Poss. ------,         Poss. ----------,
      Obj.  itself;         Obj.  themselves.
&lt;/pre&gt;

==Relatives and interrogatives==

The relative and the interrogative pronouns are thus declined:
&lt;pre&gt;
Who, literally applied to persons only.

Sing. Nom.  who,      Plur. Nom.  who,
      Poss. whose,          Poss. whose,
      Obj.  whom;           Obj.  whom.

Which, applied to animals and things.

Sing. Nom.  which,    Plur. Nom.  which,
      Poss. ----,           Poss. -----,
      Obj.  which;          Obj.  which.

What, applied ordinarily to things only.

Sing. Nom.  what,     Plur. Nom.  what,
      Poss. ----,           Poss. ----,
      Obj.  what;           Obj.  what.

That, applied to persons, animals, and things.

Sing. Nom.  that,     Plur. Nom.  that,
      Poss. ----,           Poss. ----,
      Obj.  that;           Obj.  that.

As, applied to persons, animals, and things.

Sing. Nom.     as,    Plur. Nom.  as,
      Poss.    ----,        Poss. ----,
      Obj.     as;          Obj.  as.
&lt;/pre&gt;

==Compound relatives==

The compound relative pronouns, ''whoever or whosoever, whichever or whichsoever'', and ''whatever or whatsoever'' are declined in the same manner as the simples. Thus:
&lt;pre&gt;
Whoever or whosoever, applied only to persons.

Sing. Nom.  whoever,     Plur. Nom.  whoever,
      Poss. whosever,          Poss. whosever,
      Obj.  whomever;          Obj.  whomever.

Sing. Nom.  whosoever,   Plur. Nom.  whosoever,
      Poss. whosesoever,       Poss. whosesoever,
      Obj.  whomsoever;        Obj.  whomsoever.

Whichever or whichsoever, applied to persons,
animals, and things.

Sing. Nom.  whichever,   Plur. Nom.  whichever,
      Poss. ---------,         Poss. --------,
      Obj.  whichever;         Obj.  whichever.

Sing. Nom.  whichsoever, Plur. Nom.  whichsoever,
      Poss. ---------,         Poss. --------,
      Obj.  whichsoever;       Obj.  whichsoever.

Whatever or whatsoever, applied ordinarily to things only.

Sing. Nom.  whatever,    Plur. Nom.  whatever,
      Poss. --------,          Poss. --------,
      Obj.  whatever;          Obj.  whatever.

Sing. Nom.  whatsoever,  Plur. Nom.  whatsoever,
      Poss. ---------,         Poss. --------,
      Obj.  whatsoever;        Obj.  whatsoever.
&lt;/pre&gt;

==Unclear Usage of Pronouns==

Although helpful to eliminate repetitiveness of nouns, pronouns, when used too much, can make a sentence extremely vague: as,

*&quot;Pictures on walls make ''it'' look pretty.&quot;

The reader does not know what ''it'' is.

*&quot;The teachers prepared the food. The students ate it. ''They'' had fun.&quot;

The reader does not know who ''they'' are.

==Y'all==

The pronoun ''y'all'' is a contraction of &quot;You all&quot;.  It is traditionally used in the south of the United States, where in the north you all is more common. ''Y'all'' follows the same conjugation rules as ''they''. Very often it is incorrectly spelled ''ya'll''.

==A short syntax==

A pronoun must agree with its antecedent, as &quot;This is the book; it is excellent,&quot; except the following cases: something indefinite, as &quot;Tell me who it was,&quot; a neuter pronoun, as &quot;I cannot view it,&quot; the pronoun ''it'', as &quot;It is not for kings,&quot; the adjective ''many'', as &quot;Many a great genius, they have no friends,&quot; enallage, as &quot;We shall close our remarks,&quot; another sense, as &quot;Lamps is of the plural number,&quot; nominatives, as &quot;Who are you?&quot;, absolute nominatives, as &quot;It need not be any wonder,&quot; possessives, as &quot;Him whose yoke is easy,&quot; objectives, as &quot;Those whom she persuaded,&quot; neuter verbs, as &quot;Whom did you suppose me to be?&quot;, familiar language, as &quot;The man [whom] I trust,&quot; omission of the relative, as &quot;The worst thing [that] could happen,&quot; a collective noun, as &quot;The council were divided,&quot; the conjunction ''or'', as &quot;James or John will favour us with his company,&quot; the conjunction ''and'', as &quot;Saul and Jonathan were pleasant in their lives,&quot; one person or thing, as &quot;This great philosopher and statesman,&quot; empathy, as &quot;The good man, and the sinner too, shall have his reward,&quot; and ''each'', ''every'', or ''no'', as &quot;Every plant and every tree produces others after its kind.&quot;

==Reference==

*A part of the text in this article, was taken from the public domain English grammar [http://www.gutenberg.net/etext/11615 &quot;The Grammar of English Grammars&quot;] by Goold Brown, 1851.

==See also== 

*[[w:Ain't|The Wikipedia article on Ain't]] 
* [[w:Generic you|The Wikipedia article on Generic you]] 
* [[w:Personal pronouns|The Wikipedia article on Personal pronouns]] 
* [[w:Possessive pronoun|The Wikipedia article on Possessive pronouns]] 
* [[w:English relative clauses|The Wikipedia article on Relative pronouns]]
* [[w:Singular they|The Wikipedia article on Singular they]] 
* [[w:Y'all|The Wikipedia article on Y'all]]
* [[w:You|The Wikipedia article on You]] 
* [[w:Who (pronoun)|The Wikipedia article on Who]] 

[[de:Englisch: Personalpronomen]]
[[fr:Anglais:Pronoms]]</text>
      <sha1>fuj291to9e9v4wv3pd0n1n0rf9gu2sq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Zanimum</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>2292</id>
    <revision>
      <id>154323</id>
      <timestamp>2003-11-27T13:59:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>199.43.176.12</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">I'm [[en:user:zanimum]], and I'm mainly at Wikibooks, to try and lead the way in typesetting and publishing the books as they're finished; this will be used as a fundraiser for Wikimedia.</text>
      <sha1>nfny8bbezkk7v0dkzt6g1wd5zlbdc5e</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:TomK32</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>2295</id>
    <revision>
      <id>154326</id>
      <timestamp>2003-11-27T20:55:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TomK32</username>
        <id>111</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[de:Benutzer:TomK32]]
One of the Sysops at the German Wikipedia.</text>
      <sha1>pkpir0txfne4tay476c7ylann32fmr6</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:C Programming/Simple input and output</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2297</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1911349</id>
      <parentid>1841929</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-08-15T06:04:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MithrandirAgain</username>
        <id>347496</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>comment</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Some implementations will let you fflush(stdin) to work as expected, but this does not work on all systems, and I don't think this behaviour is as to the standard, as such I've removed it. [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 01:12, 28 Nov 2003 (UTC)

== merge ==

I suggest merging [[C Programming/Simple Input and Output]] into [[C Programming/Simple input and output]].
--[[User:DavidCary|DavidCary]] ([[User talk:DavidCary|talk]]) 23:00, 8 March 2009 (UTC)

== scanf ==

why are we teaching scanf. we all know we should never use it
: Should we use [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fgets Fgets] instead? It ''does'' terminate after a \n character is found. True, scanf is vulnerable to format string attacks, but in the context of the guide (for beginners) I think scanf is sufficient. --[[User:MithrandirAgain|MithrandirAgain]] ([[User talk:MithrandirAgain|talk]]) 06:04, 15 August 2010 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>m3zsmcrfecct6ny8myphir2iq6uu8ka</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Kalki</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>2299</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2260370</id>
      <parentid>2260169</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-02-01T21:40:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>update</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Sockpuppeteer|checked=yes|evidence=[[w:Wikipedia:Sockpuppet investigations/Kalki|Wikipedia:Sockpuppet investigations/Kalki]]}}</text>
      <sha1>ss3v3incx1c57pbh1krjcilexklwe7k</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Ktsquare</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>2300</id>
    <revision>
      <id>154330</id>
      <timestamp>2003-11-28T05:37:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ktsquare</username>
        <id>307</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">Same person as [http://en2.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Ktsquare Ktsquare]</text>
      <sha1>kc6yik9xqafik8qiv1193uga16joqk7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Botany/Pinophyta</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2301</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2082896</id>
      <parentid>2082845</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-04-15T21:28:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Recent Runes</username>
        <id>66908</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/75.149.222.73|75.149.222.73]] ([[User talk:75.149.222.73|talk]]) to last version by Avicennasis</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;small&gt;&lt;&lt; [[Botany#Contents|Contents Page]] | [[Botany/Equisetophyta|Chapter 13]] | &lt;/small&gt;Chapter 14&lt;small&gt; | [[Botany/Magnoliophyta|Chapter 15]] &lt;/small&gt;
----

== Chapter 14. Pinophyta ==
[[image:Conifers_Sierra.jpg|thumb|250px|right|Conifer trees growing above 6000 ft (1800 m) in the Sierra Nevada of California]]

The '''Division Pinophyta''' in the Kingdom Plantae comprises those species of plants that were formerly classified as the &quot;modern&quot; '''gymnosperms''' of the Class Coniferales&amp;mdash;that is the ''conifers''.  Unlike many of the gymnosperm groups covered in the previous chapter, ''pinophytes'' are today still broadly represented on the landscape, forming extensive forests in both the Northern and Southern hemispheres.  This does not mean this is a recent  group in the paleontological record. Pinophytes are found as fossils as far back as the Upper Carboniferous (Paleozoic Era).  Thus, it is a very ancient group, but one still having significant ecological importance on the planet.  Pinophytes are mostly evergreen trees (some are shrubs) and many have great commercial value for their wood.

* Reread [[Wikipedia:en:Gymnosperm|Gymnosperm]] (&lt;small&gt;Links need not be pursued at this time&lt;/small&gt;)
* Read [[Wikipedia:en:Conifer|Conifers]] (&lt;small&gt;Links need not be pursued at this time&lt;/small&gt;)

These terms, ''gymnosperm'' and ''conifer'' no longer have standing in modern taxonomic treatments of plants. However, both terms are still widely used, so you should have a grasp of what they mean, and how they fit into the taxonomic terms that have replaced them.

* Read [[Wikipedia:en:Pinophyta|Division Pinophyta]] (&lt;small&gt;The following links are included:&lt;/small&gt;)
** [[Wikipedia:en:Pinales|Order Pinales]]
***[[Wikipedia:en:Pinaceae|Family Pinaceae]] (&lt;small&gt;Follow links to '''''Pinus''''' (pines) and read accounts for each of the ''Pinus'' species&lt;/small&gt;)&lt;br&gt;Be sure to read about and understand each of the following terms: '''softwood''', '''evergreen''', '''pine needle''', '''pine cone''', '''pine nuts''', '''resin''', '''wood pulp''', '''timberline'''
***[[Wikipedia:en:Cupressaceae|Family Cupressaceae]] (&lt;small&gt;Follow links to each of the listed genera and read accounts for each species&lt;/small&gt;)&lt;br&gt;Be sure to read about and understand each of the following terms: '''Bald Cypress''', '''cypress knees''', '''Giant Sequoia''', '''redwoods''', '''swamp'''
***[[Wikipedia:en:Taxaceae|Family Taxaceae]] (&lt;small&gt;Follow links to each species&lt;/small&gt;)&lt;br&gt;Be sure to read about and understand each of the following terms: '''aril''', '''yew''', '''alkaloid'''

==Evolution of the Gymnosperms==

Gymnosperms are very different from the earliest vascular plants. Gymnosperms have very reduced gametophyte generations- female ovules and male pollen. Many gymnosperms, like the Pinophytes, have secondary growth from a vascular cambium. While tree ferns are tall and have a trunk resembling a tree, they are only very superficially similar. They do not have woody growth the way trees with secondary growth from a vascular cambium do. A single mutation of a fern or a horsetail could not produce a functioning seed plant. So gymnosperms must be descended from some progymnosperm ancestor that evolved these adaptations from the ferns, but was not fit enough to remain on earth. One possible example of a progymnosperm is the spore bearing woody tree [[Wikipedia:en:Archaeopteris|Archaeopteris]], which was at one point probably prevalent on earth.

[[Botany/Conifer_structure_laboratory|Laboratory Exercises]] for Chapter 14 &gt;&gt;&lt;br&gt;


----

&lt;center&gt;
{{BotanyTOC2}}
&lt;/center&gt;

[[Category:Botany]]</text>
      <sha1>akvy3g4zes7dszb3cnci72xw8akdhf3</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:General Chemistry/Stoichiometry</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2304</id>
    <revision>
      <id>393447</id>
      <parentid>154333</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-03-09T12:48:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[Talk:Stoichiometry (General Chemistry)]] moved to [[Talk:General Chemistry/Stoichiometry]]: naming convention</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Why the Disambiguation?  Stoichiometry only has this use in my experience...  -- [[User:Emperorbma|Emperorbma]] 21:45, 28 Nov 2003 (UTC)

*Oh, nevermind... I feel silly. :P --[[User:Emperorbma|Emperorbma]] 09:36, 16 Dec 2003 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>39pv5o6dzz2i0q9dcwlpqw7dj6chjbk</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Spanish/Exercises/Mathematics</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2305</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1712702</id>
      <parentid>1712646</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-02-05T00:45:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Wutsje</username>
        <id>92180</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/69.114.30.151|69.114.30.151]] ([[User talk:69.114.30.151|Talk]]) to last revision by [[User:Guanabot|Guanabot]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Spanish/Lesson 2| ^Lesson 2^]]
----

The following table shows the Spanish words for the four basic 
arithmetics operations:


{| border=&quot;1&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#FFFF99&quot;
|-
! &amp;nbsp; + &amp;nbsp;
| más  
|-
! &amp;nbsp; - &amp;nbsp;
| menos  
|-
! &amp;nbsp; * &amp;nbsp;
| por  
|-
! &amp;nbsp; / &amp;nbsp;
| entre  
|-
! &amp;nbsp; = &amp;nbsp;
| es/son  
|}

For the equals sign ('''=''') you use '''es''' if the answer is 1, otherwise
you use '''son''':


{| border=&quot;0&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#99FF99&quot;
|-
| ''6-5'': || Seis menos cinco es uno. 
|-
| ''2+2'': || Dos más dos son cuatro.  
|}

== Problemas de matemáticas - ''Math Problems'' ==

Write out as words and then solve the following math problems:

1. ''3 * 3'': ________________________________________

2. ''10 / 2'': ________________________________________

3. ''23 + 42'': ________________________________________

4. ''99 - 9'': ________________________________________

5. ''13 * 7'': ________________________________________

6. ''75 / 3'': ________________________________________

7. ''17 + 4'': ________________________________________

8. ''67 - 66'': ________________________________________

9. ''4 * 25'': ________________________________________

10. ''78 / 13'': ________________________________________

----------------------------------------
[[Spanish/Exercises/Mathematics - Solutions|Soluciones a los ejercicios]] ''Solutions to exercices''

[[Spanish/Lesson 2| ^Lesson 2^]]

[[Category:Spanish]]</text>
      <sha1>6gy9hbpy75t2227tslu8den7tr3lewm</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:World History/World Religions</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2328</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1786770</id>
      <parentid>982791</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-05-04T15:07:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DW5</username>
        <id>353071</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">I would say the Baha'i Faith is indeed a religion... look at the wikipedia entry:
[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bah%E1%27%ED_Faith Baha'i Faith] --- djKianoosh - 17 May 2005

The Baha'i Faith is a cult.  You may want to be politically correct, but it has so few adherents that it can hardly be called a major religion, at any point in history.  That is what this page is meant for.--[[User:Naryathegreat|Naryathegreat]]|[[User talk:Naryathegreat|(talk)]] 04:00, 20 May 2005 (UTC)

I agree - whether Baha'i is a religion or not is only semantics; it hasn't had a large enough impact on world history to merit inclusion in this summary. --[[User:Lady~Macbeth|Lady~Macbeth]] 6 July 2005 22:15 (UTC)

A look into the Kitab-i-Aqdas (the most holy book of the Baha'i) may give any interested person deep insights into the nature of this faith and is therefore strongly recommended. Please note especially the things that are said about the rights of women. Please mark also: the so-called Universal House of Justice, the highest elected Baha'i administrative and legislative council is considered infallible (like the Pope!) in its decisions. It will become, as the Baha'i believe, the world governement in the future, when the majority of mankind will be Baha'i. Only Baha'i have electional rights in the elections of the Universal House of Justice! No woman may be elected to serve in the Universal House of Justice (so much to equal rights).
greetings
seeker


This section is supposed to explain how different religions affected history, not act as a crash course on each religion, imo. Perhaps the title is a misnomer, and this section should be moved into other relevant pages (i.e. Christianity -&gt; Later Roman, Middle Ages pages, Islam -&gt; Middle East, etc.)
--[[User:Tai|Tai]]

== Zoroastrianism ==

you guys have forgot about one of the most important religions.
You cant have a history book without Zoroastrianism. In case you dont know what Zoroastrianism is, look it up. It was the first ever monotheistic religion.

== Organization of Page ==

I'm curious. Why organize this page alphabetically? Is this page meant to be like a glossary?  Otherwise, why not organize it chronologically or regionally and then chronologically?  Just curious. [[User:DW5|DW5]] ([[User talk:DW5|talk]])</text>
      <sha1>jbkmqo5nl9q0y8n96jai7oausks6cfk</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Indonesian/Lessons/Family</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2333</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2711054</id>
      <parentid>2611179</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-07T15:30:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>220.255.1.123</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Bacaan (Reading Comprehension) */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;noinclude&gt;{{Indonesian/Lessons/Level one/Header}}&lt;/noinclude&gt;

[[Indonesian| ^ Indonesian ^]] | [[Indonesian/Lesson 7| &lt;&lt; Lesson 7: Introducing Yourself]]  | Lesson 8: My Family |[[Indonesian Lesson 9| Lesson 9: My Home &gt;&gt;]]

== Bacaan ''(Reading Comprehension)'' ==

Nama saya Mira. Saya tinggal di bae bersama ayah dan ibu. Saya punya seorang kakak laki-laki. Namanya Anto. Saya juga punya adik perempuan. Namanya Wati. Kakak saya dan adik perempuan saya juga tinggal bersama kami.

Ayah kerja di kantor setiap hari. Ibu tinggal dirumah, memasak makanan untuk kami. Setiap hari, saya, kakak dan adik perempuan saya pergi ke sekolah

Terjemahan ''(Translation):''

My name is Mira I live in bae with my father and mother. I have an older brother. His name is Anto.  I also have a younger sister. Her name is Wati.  My older brother and younger sister also live with us.

Father works at the office everyday.  Mother stays at home, cooking food for us. Every day, myself, my older and younger siblings go to school.

== Kosa Kata ''(Vocabulary)'' ==

* adik = younger (brother/sister)
* ayah = bapak = father
* bersama = with
* hari = day
* ibu = mother
* juga = also / too
* kakak = older (brother/sister)
* kerja = work
* laki-laki = male
* makanan = food
* masak = cook
* perempuan = female
* pergi = go
* punya = have
* rumah = home / house
* sekolah = school
* seorang = one person
* setiap = every
* tinggal(*) = stay / live
* untuk = for

&lt;b&gt;Note&lt;/b&gt;: The word &quot;tinggal&quot; is a tricky word. If it is used alone (not conjugated), it means to live or to stay. However, if you conjugate it, it means to leave or to die. Many people got confused with this. Think of it from an Indonesian cultural perspective. Many indigenous Indonesians believe that when a person dies, the soul is here to stay.

=== Family Structure ===

* ''Ayah'' is synonymous with ''bapak'', which means ''father''.You can use it interchangeably when referring to a father (or your father).  Note that we call adult males as ''bapak'' for courtesy, but we never call them ''ayah''. The word ''ayah'' is exclusively for the father-child relationship (whether by consanguinity or by law such as a stepfather).

* ''Ibu'' means ''mother''. Here, we don't make any distinction like ''bapak'' / ''ayah''.

* •	Notice from the vocabulary list that Indonesian words for siblings are gender-free.  The word ''&quot;kakak&quot;'' is used to describe an older sibling (older brother or older sister). The word ''&quot;adik&quot;'' is used to describe a younger sibling (younger brother or younger sister). In order to further distinguish the gender, we use gender words, e.g., ''&quot;laki-laki&quot;'' for male or ''&quot;perempuan&quot;'' for female. Other gender-free words are made distinct in a similar fashion.

* Other family members:
** Suami = husband
** Istri = wife
** Anak = child / children
** Kakek = grandpa
** Nenek = grandma
** Paman = uncle
** Bibi = aunt
** Sepupu = cousin
** Keponakan = nephew / niece
** Saudara = brother / sister
** Saudara ipar = (brother/sister)-in-law
** Ayah mertua = father-in-law
** Merah mudini = mother &amp; father-in-law
** Ibu mertua = mother-in-law

== Grammar ==
=== Awalan Me- ''(Me- prefix)'' ===

In the passage, you'll notice the first prefix in Indonesian: ''me-''. It's the most important and commonly used in Indonesian.

When it's combined with verbs like above (masak &amp;rarr; memasak), it means the same as the infinitive form. The only thing is that we emphasize that now the verb is in active form.

Almost all verb can be conjugated using ''me-'', but not all. Unfortunately, in order to know which verbs can go with ''me-'' , you must read a lot. The general rule of thumb is that if the verb is reflexive (i.e. doing it to ourself), it usually can't be conjugated with ''me-''. Even more so, don't think that the sense of reflexivity is the same to that of your language. Below is some words that &lt;b&gt;cannot&lt;/b&gt; be conjugated with ''me-'', unless the meaning changes completely differently:
* tinggal = stay (&amp;rarr; meninggal = to die)
* tidur = sleep
* duduk = sit
* bangun = wake up (&amp;rarr; membangun = to build)
* berdiri = get up
* tawa = laugh

The prefix ''me-'' can also apply to other type of words, such as noun and adjectives. However, the rough goal is still the same: To make an active verb. So, you can ''verbize'' a noun or an adjective. Details on these will be covered later.

Note also that when words are conjugated with ''me-'', the spelling is changed a little bit. The spelling change is called ''inflection''. The inflection depends solely on the first letter of the original word. The rule on how the spelling changes can be viewed here: [[Indonesian/prefix me|Prefix me-]] chapter.

=== Akhiran -an ''(Suffix -an)'' ===

Suffix ''-an'' is to ''nominalize'' a verb. Note the example from the passage: makan &amp;rarr; makanan. Analoguous to the prefix ''me-'', you can virtually ''nominalize'' almost any verb you want using ''-an'' suffix, as long as it makes sense.

Note, however, that the nominalisation of the verb does not correspond with the gerundive form (-ing form) expressing the ''action'' or ''state of action'' like in case of Western languages (i.e. eating), but the ''target'' or ''object'' of said action (i.e. food). You can think of it as &quot;things that do what the verb says&quot;.

Some of the verbs may also function as nouns already. For example: ''tidur'' (= sleep), which can be noun and verb at the same time. In this case, you cannot add ''-an'' suffix on it to make a noun out of it. (Note that the word ''tiduran'' does exist, but the meaning is &quot;to lie down casually&quot;, not &quot;sleep&quot;).

Note also that some words may have dual meanings, like ''bangun'', which may mean ''to wake up'' or ''to build''. Of course, if you add ''-an'' suffix, the second meaning is taken, i.e.:
* Bangun (= build) &amp;rarr; Bangunan (= &quot;things that was built&quot; &amp;rarr; building)

TODO: Load the chapter on suffix -an.

=== Awalan Se- ''(Prefix se-)'' ===

Prefix ''se-'' combined with noun would mean &quot;one of that noun&quot;. In the example above, ''orang'' means ''person''. Therefore, ''seorang'' means ''one person''. In English, ''se + noun'' usually translates into ''a / an''.

The ''se + noun'' word compounds are often used as a measure word, akin to those in Chinese. The measure words can be pretty complex. However, as being mentioned in the previous chapters, ''sebuah'' should be fine for most of the things. You must use ''seorang'' to indicate that the noun is a person, and use ''seekor'' for animals.

TODO: Load the chapter on prefix se-.

=== Grammar Summary ===

A simplified grammar summary for this chapter:
* Me + verb &amp;rarr; active verb
* Verb + an &amp;rarr; noun
* Se + noun &amp;rarr; one of that noun



&lt;hr&gt;

[[Indonesian| ^ Indonesian ^]] | [[Indonesian/Lesson 7| &lt;&lt; Lesson 7: Introducing Yourself]]  | Lesson 8: My Family |[[Indonesian Lesson 9| Lesson 9: My Home &gt;&gt;]]

[[Category:Indonesian]]
&lt;noinclude&gt;{{Indonesian/Lessons/Level one/Footer}}&lt;/noinclude&gt;

[[fr:Enseignement de l'indonésien/Leçons/Famille]]</text>
      <sha1>1cg6k2ftutb78zdwxqioubqcmnm1zts</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>German/Lesson 5B</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2345</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1709739</id>
      <parentid>1709444</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-02-01T02:53:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>fixed link</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">:&lt;small&gt;''This page represents a very advanced ''[[../Lesson 5/]]'', with additional vocabulary and further discussion of grammar concepts introduced in the Advanced Lessons 1A through 5A. A portion of a short article in German, along with a vocabulary of words not already introduced in previous lessons (1 through 5 and 1A through 5A) is presented for the student to read and translate.&lt;/small&gt;

&lt;small&gt;&lt;&lt; [[German/Level III/Der Engländer in Österreich|Lektion 5A]] | '''Lektion 5B''' | [[German/Lesson 6|Lektion 6]] &gt;&gt; &lt;/small&gt;
----

&lt;big&gt;&lt;big&gt;Lektion Vier&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/big&gt;

== Lesestück 5-1 ~ Eine Geschichte über St. Pölten ==
&lt;div style=&quot;float:right;margin:0 0 1em 1em;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;[[Image:Map at sankt pölten.png|250px|alt text]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;''Karte: St. Pölten in Österreich
''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

Niederösterreich ist sowohl flächenmäßig als auch nach Einwohnern das größte der neun österreichischen Bundesländer. Sankt Pölten ist die Landeshauptstadt von Niederösterreich. Der Name St. Pölten geht auf den heiligen Hippolytos zurück, nach dem die Stadt benannt wurde.

Die Altstadt befindet sich dort, wo vom 2. bis zum 4. Jahrhundert die Römerstadt ''Aelium Cetium'' stand. 799 wurde der Ort als &quot;Treisma&quot; erwähnt. Das Marktrecht erhielt St. Pölten um 1050, zur Stadt erhoben wurde es 1159. Bis 1494 stand St. Pölten im Besitz des Bistums Passau, dann wurde es landesfürstliches Eigentum. Bereits 771 findet sich ein Benediktinerkloster, ab 1081 gab es Augustiner-Chorherren, 1784 wurde deren Kollegiatsstift aufgehoben, das Gebäude dient seit 1785 als Bischofssitz. Zur Landeshauptstadt von Niederösterreich wurde St. Pölten mit Landtagsbeschluss vom 10. Juli 1986, seit 1997 ist es Sitz der Niederösterreichischen Landesregierung.
 
&lt;div style=&quot;float:right;margin:0 0 1em 1em;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;[[Image:Stpoelten luftbild.jpg|Aerial view of St. Pölten]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;''Luftbild von St. Pölten''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

=== Vokabeln 5B ===

 Die Altstadt                   old town
 Der Augustiner                 Augustinian
 Der Besitz                     possession, holding
 Das Bistum                     diocese
 Der Bischofssitz               bishop's see (a seat of a bishop's authority)
 Die Bundesländer               federal states
 Die Chorherren                 men's choir 
 Das Eigentum                   proprietorship
 Die Einwohner                  inhabitants
 Das Gebäude                    premises
 Die Geschichte                 history
 Das Jahrhundert                century
 Das Kloster                    monastery, friary
 Das Kollegiatsstift            monastery college
 Die Landeshauptstadt           regional or state capital city
 Die Landesregierung            provincial (state) government
 Der Landtagsbeschluss          day of jurisdictional reorganization
 Das Marktrecht                 right to hold markets
 Der Name                       name
 Der Ort                        place, spot, city
 Die Römerstadt                 Roman town
 Der Sitz                       official place

 Bistum Passau                  a dioecian region in Bavaria
 sowohl... als auch             both... and
 zurück auf                     goes back to

 aufheben (hob auf, aufgehoben) merged in (or turned into?)
 befinden sich                  situated, located
 (befand sich, haben sich befunden)
 finden sich*                   found (located)
 benennen (benannte, benannt)   call (as to label)
 erhalten (erhielt, erhalten)   receive
 erheben (erhob, erhoben)       arise, raise
 erwähnen (erwähnte, erwähnt)   mention
 stehen (stand, gestanden)      stand (stood, stood)
 werden (wurde, [ist]geworden)  become

 ab                             from
 auf                            up
 bereits                        already
 bis                            until, by, up to
 flächenmäßig                   (no direct translation) ~ when measured in surface
 heilig                         holy
 landesfürstlich                baronial or princely (holdings)
 nach                           in terms of 
 um                             around

(* one short form of anfinden: findet sich (an); in colloquial language you can cut the &quot;an&quot;; but in THIS special case it is the short form of &quot;(be)findet sich (dort)&quot;)

&lt;small&gt;[[German/Appendices/Alphabet|Pronunciation Guide]] &gt;&gt; &lt;/small&gt;

* Read more about [http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Pölten St. Pölten] at the German Wikipedia (source of article above).

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>6ao6bb060hv3ffyx66ngkga7208136a</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Wikibooks talk:Natural sciences bookshelf</title>
    <ns>5</ns>
    <id>2381</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1483272</id>
      <parentid>1483270</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-04-27T20:04:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Wight</username>
        <id>64340</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* New textbook: Chemical Principles */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">This seems to be an exciting project. But if we're ever going to build up a useful resource in science, people should add references to their work. At least if this information should ever be used for academic purpose - which I have very strong doubts about. - [http://en2.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Mendalus Mendalus]
: If people are using external references - I'm sure they'll add it. Most of us are writing texts from our own knowledge (so we own the copyright to the material - see [[en:Wikipedia:Copyrights]] - we fall under the same licensing). [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 10:34, 1 Dec 2003 (UTC)

:: By academic standards - which this project need to follow if they're ever going to be used for academic purposes - you try to look up references (mainly published scientific articles) even though you write out of your own knowledge. :) If you've got a textbook in a subject, take a look at the references given there. You do not infringe any copyrights by using some of those references. Anyways, you're doing a great job! Keep on! - [http://en2.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Mendalus Mendalus] [[User:129.177.45.112|129.177.45.112]] 14:48, 3 Dec 2003 (UTC)

Well yes, but most textbooks put a bibliography at then end of the book, not as they go along. Remember these are textbooks not scientific papers [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 16:05, 3 Dec 2003 (UTC)

==Medical wiki==

Don't want to spoil anybody's plans here but I have been maintaining a separate wiki for medicine the past few months now. You can see it here. [http://mednotes.net Mednotes.net] [http://en2.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Weiming Weiming] --[[User:82.35.40.201|82.35.40.201]] 23:02, 23 Jun 2004 (UTC)
: Note:  This is not really &quot;spoiling&quot; anything.  Wikibooks is a good way to help collect information, and certainly Wikibooks could be a mirror/fork of a project that is done elsewhere... particularly if it is released with a copyright license that is compatable with the GFDL.  There are some high school science textbooks that are being done exactly this way.  An advantage to having the content here is that you don't have to maintain the server, and it is likely that this server will be around for a few years, as opposed to a private server.  [[User:Robert Horning|Rob Horning]] 3 July 2005 11:12 (UTC)

== Medicine as a separate bookshelf ==

I think Medicine is too vast a subject and too heavy to be listed in the Science bookshelf. It is more appropriate that this bookshelf is listed independently. This is not to say it does not belong to &lt;tt&gt;Science&lt;/tt&gt;. It invariably does but it deserves a separate, independent category of its own!!

[[User:Bduttabaruah|BDB]] 08:38, 25 September 2005 (UTC)

== QUESTION ==

Are wikibooks ever finished?? like do they close to edits?

==Rename entry for Ethology in bookshelf==
I have been working on the [[Animal Behavior|Animal Behavior Book]] for some time. On the book shelf it is listed as the much more restrictive term ethology, which automatically redirects to - animal behavior. Would somebody in the know be so kind to rename the entry in the book shelf so it is directly listed as [[Animal Behavior]] instead of ethology?
[[User:Robert Huber|Robert Huber]] 18:33, 12 September 2007 (UTC)

: {{done}}. Darklama fixed it in the {{tl|Biology bookshelf}} template, which is transcluded here -- I don't see any mention of &quot;ethology&quot; now. --[[User:DavidCary|DavidCary]] ([[User talk:DavidCary|talk]]) 05:04, 27 January 2009 (UTC)

== New textbook: [[Chemical Principles]] ==
I am nearly halfway finished creating a textbook for first-year college students called [[Chemical Principles]].  It is based on a traditional textbook of the same title and is used with the explicit written permission of the authors (Dickerson, Gray and Haight).  Can someone please tell me
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to get the text linked to the Natural Sciences and Chemistry pages, along with the other Chemistry textbooks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to get authorized to review/approve the pages (as my students are entering information)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
Thanks. [[User:wight|Chuck Wight]] 20:01, 27 April 2009 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>35mqbh6omhb0r8x4zc3t1dkzwjp2fjr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Latin/Appendix B</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2382</id>
    <revision>
      <id>616140</id>
      <parentid>518196</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-10-18T04:20:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Guanabot</username>
        <id>5478</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>User-controlled Bot: table syntax updated</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Classical Latin is pronounced in a highly phonetic manner.


{|
|-
| &lt;B&gt;Vowels:&lt;/B&gt;
|-
| a (short): as &lt;B&gt;a&lt;/B&gt; b&lt;B&gt;a&lt;/B&gt;t
|-
| a (long): as &lt;B&gt;a&lt;/B&gt; f&lt;B&gt;a&lt;/B&gt;ther
|-
| e (short): as &lt;B&gt;e&lt;/B&gt; b&lt;B&gt;e&lt;/B&gt;t
|-
| e (long): as &lt;B&gt;a&lt;/B&gt; in l&lt;B&gt;a&lt;/B&gt;te
|-
| i (short): as &lt;B&gt;i&lt;/B&gt; in b&lt;B&gt;i&lt;/B&gt;t
|-
| i (long): as &lt;B&gt;ee&lt;/B&gt; in b&lt;B&gt;ee&lt;/B&gt;t.
|-
| o (short): as &lt;B&gt;o&lt;/B&gt; in g&lt;B&gt;o&lt;/B&gt;t.
|-
| o (long): as &lt;B&gt;oa&lt;/B&gt; in b&lt;B&gt;oa&lt;/B&gt;t.
|-
| u: as &lt;B&gt;u&lt;/B&gt; in p&lt;B&gt;u&lt;/B&gt;t.
|}

Diphthongs:
*Ae is pronounced as a long 'i'.
*Oe is pronounced as a short 'i'.

Digraphs:
*Ph is pronounced as an aspirated 'p', like ph in 'tophat'. It is equivalent to the Greek letter φ 'phi'. *Often, however, it is just pronounced 'f' as in fat'.
*Th is pronounced as an aspirated 't', like th in rat hall'. It is equivalent to the Greek letter θ 'theta'. *Often, however, it is just pronounced 'th' as in 'threat'.
*Qu is pronounced 'kw' like in English.

*Y is pronounced 'u' as in put. It is equivalent to the Greek letter υ 'upsilon'.
*J, a form of consonantal i used in Medieval Latin texts, is pronounced like a 'y'. Similarly, i, when is used as a consonant, is pronounced with a 'y' sound.

*C is always pronounced hard (velar [k] - as in English 'cat'), even when it follows an 'e' or 'i'.  It is never pronounced as English 'c' in 'cell'. 

*G is always pronounced hard (velar [g] - as in English 'go'), even following 'e' and 'i'.  It is never pronounced as in English 'gel'.

*R was probably trilled or tapped, closer to modern Italian than to English.  

*Classical latin texts used only capital letters, and the same letter, 'V', was used for what are now spelt as 'u' and 'v' in most texts.  This is still reflected in some modern Latin texts, where a capital 'u' is spelt 'V'.  When used as a consonant, 'V' was pronounced much like English 'w'.

b, d, f, h, k, l, m, n, p, q, s, t, x, and z are pronounced as they are normally pronounced in English.

[[Category:Latin]]</text>
      <sha1>e578r2oywomurzdrle1diyda9benap5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:English in Use/Nouns</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2385</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1864075</id>
      <parentid>1464904</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-06-28T20:57:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Adding {{WikiProject Languages}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{WikiProject Languages}} 

Trying to describe a noun is hard! Words are just text labels for objects, concepts, actions, attributes, or simply &quot;things&quot; which fulfil certain functions within the languages which use them. Nouns are words which are associated with physical objects, or with abstract concepts, or with the names of people or objects or concepts.

I am not sure that it is OK to say that &quot;Nouns are just names&quot;!

Further, I do wonder whether it makes sense to do this section without using images. Mention is made of a chair, but this does not make sense to anyone who does not already know a word for chair, or who has not seen a chair or used one. [[User:David Martland|David Martland]] 11:06, 1 Dec 2003 (UTC)

I copied the exercises here, this article is already much too long. Adding the whole Wikipedia article on plurals there made it a mess. Perhaps the articles should be in a separate article, as a long article with many exercises in the middle is almost impossible to follow. [[User:Tkorrovi|Tkorrovi]] ([[User talk:Tkorrovi|talk]]) 15:39, 11 April 2009 (UTC)

==Exercises==

'''Write the plurals. Follow the examples.'''

'''Exercise 1'''
Most plurals ? noum + -s.
* e.g.: book ? ''books'' 
 
 
 cat        ____________________________________ 
 
 chair      ____________________________________ 
 
 girl       ____________________________________ 
  
 sofa       ____________________________________ 
 
 student    ____________________________________ 
 

'''Exercise 2'''
Nouns ending in -s,-ss,-sh,-ch,-x,-z ? noum + -es, which is spelled -es if the word does not already end with -e.  
* e.g.: glass ? ''glasses'', phase ? ''phases'' 

 
 dish       ____________________________________ 
 
 witch      ____________________________________
 

'''Exercise 3'''
Nouns ending in -y preceded by a vowel ? noum + -s.
* e.g.: boy ? ''boys''

 
 day        ____________________________________
 
 monkey     ____________________________________
 
 key        ____________________________________
 

'''Exercise 4'''
Nouns ending in -y preceded by a consonant ? -y + -ies
* e.g.: cherry ? ''cherries''

 
 lady       ____________________________________
 

'''Exercise 5'''
Nouns ending in –o ? noun + -es

* e.g.: hero ? ''heroes'' 
 
 
 potato     ____________________________________
 
 volcano    ____________________________________ 
 

Exeptions:


a) Some foreign words (especially from Latin). 
? noun + -s
* e.g.: kilo ? ''kilos''


b) All nouns ending in –o preceded by a vowel.
? noun + -s
* e.g.: radio ?	''radios''


c) Some nouns ending in –o have two plural forms. 
? noun + -s or -es
* e.g.: volcano	? ''volcanos'' or ''volcanoes''

 
 buffalo    ____________________________________
 
 mango      ____________________________________
 

'''Exercise 6'''
A few nouns ending in -f or -fe ? -ves
* e.g.: calf ? calves

  
 elf        ____________________________________
 
 half       ____________________________________
 
 knife      ____________________________________
 
 leaf       ____________________________________
 
 life       ____________________________________
 
 loaf       ____________________________________
 
 sheaf      ____________________________________
 
 shelf      ____________________________________
 
 thief      ____________________________________
 
 wife       ____________________________________
 
 wolf       ____________________________________
 

'''Exercise 7'''
Many words ending in -f or -fe  ? noun + -s
* e.g.: cliff ? ''cliffs''  
 
 
 proof      ____________________________________   
  
 roof       ____________________________________   
  

Note: Some words have both forms.
* e.g.: staff ?	''staffs'' or ''staves''


'''Exercise 8''' 
[http://web2.uvcs.uvic.ca/elc/studyzone/330/grammar/plural1.htm Regular Plurals of Nouns - Gap-fill exercise] (External link)</text>
      <sha1>kjw0npxvrmuq4jvpghv58k720ml5vu6</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Ugen64</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>2407</id>
    <revision>
      <id>154433</id>
      <timestamp>2003-12-01T22:48:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ugen64</username>
        <id>317</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>created</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">I'm ugen, and I originally hail from [http://www.wikipedia.org Wikipedia]. I will focus mostly on [[mathematics]], [[history]], and [[science]], and there seems to be a nice [[Computer Game Walkthroughs]] section...</text>
      <sha1>4jmg4l4a9ir0stp2okqe4jm8s63v1k5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:Ugen64</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>2409</id>
    <revision>
      <id>154435</id>
      <timestamp>2003-12-02T01:05:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dysprosia</username>
        <id>32</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>short greets</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Hi Ugen :) I hope you feel at home here as well as Wikipedia :) [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 01:05, 2 Dec 2003 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>a6tygiay1jcz74n83x4f8r0tm838v1z</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Spanish/Pronunciation</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2410</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2201608</id>
      <parentid>2162277</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-10-26T17:03:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>76.185.154.52</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* About Spanish &quot;Q&quot; */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{WikiProject Languages|spanish=yes}} 

== Audio Recording ==

Speaking from personal experience from learning foreign languages, it is really useful to have an AUDIO recording of the pronunciation of the various sounds in a language.

Having approximations like &quot;'A' as in 'father'&quot; etc. is all very well, but it really is no substitute for hearing a native make the sound and then replicating it. Written words are subject to the variances of dialect and accent- for example while &quot;Pen&quot; might be pronounced &quot;Pehn&quot; in the UK and USA, in New Zealand it is pronounced &quot;Piin&quot;. Reliance on written approximations of a sound is thus quite dangerous and restrictive for a self-learner of a language. 

If you think about it, the reason books used these approximations back in the day, was that it was a &lt;u&gt;BOOK&lt;/u&gt; BACK IN THE DAY. It's 2009 for freaks sake- on the internet!! The ability to integrate audio into the learning of a language is a marvellous opportunity that we should capitalise on! The old book format of self-learning was subject to the technological limitations of yesteryear. We should be availing of the ease of audio integration that is at our disposal to provide a dynamic language learning experience.

I therefore '''request that a native record each sound''': perhaps saying the sound alone, then in a word, repeated, and then as a sound alone again. This could easily be inserted as an mp3 beside each individual sound. It will only really take about an hour's work or so and would REALLY contribute to learning that the wikibook seeks to provide!

All the best,
Jack

== Ch, Ll, Ñ ==

While Ch and Ll have now been added to &quot;c&quot; and &quot;l&quot; in the ''Real Academia Española'' dictionaries and other dictionaries, keep in mind that in '''ALL''' the Spanish-Spanish dictionaries, ''Ñ/ñ'' is a letter by its own, and hasn't (nor has a reason to) been eliminated from the order of ''M, N, Ñ, O'' in the dictionaries.

== Common pronunciation of Ll ==

Is the 'proper' pronunciation of ll as 'gl' like in Italian actually exist in the Spanish-speaking world?  It seems it exists solely academically.

More to the point, while the 'll' is often pronounced like the 'y' in English, in many areas it is actually closer to the 'zh' sound and, notably in many parts of Argentina, quite nearly the English 'sh' sound.  Anecdotally, I have used both the 'y' and the 'zh' versions and have never had it questioned, even by academics.  I believe the fair student can stick with either of these and avoid the unusual sounding 'gl'.  Just an opinion.

[[User:156.56.73.196|156.56.73.196]] 18:00, 11 April 2006 (UTC)
*I removed the whole &quot;properly&quot; nonsense. There are numerous proper ways to say the letter ll. Castilian Spanish is not any more &quot;proper&quot;.

==Hablan==
it says that hablan is pronounced HA- BLAN not A- BLAN like it should be [[User:144.138.190.1|144.138.190.1]] 07:33, 23 March 2007 (UTC)
*huh? Hablan is pronounced AH-blahn, with emphasis on the first syllable. This is the rule of stress for words ending in the letter N but that do not have an accent to signify stress.

== alignment on page 5 ==

The left and right columns have their &quot;middle&quot; aligned. This is confusing. They should have their TOP aligned.Š

== d, touching teeth ==

&quot;Between vowels, the tongue should be lowered so as to not touch the teeth (somewhat similar to the ''th'' in ''the'').&quot;

But the tongue '''does''' touch the teeth in ''the'', in English - could this please be clarified? --[[User:Chriswaterguy|Chriswaterguy]] ([[User talk:Chriswaterguy|talk]]) 17:55, 5 August 2008 (UTC)


==N==
&quot;Like n in no. Before '''p, b,''' f and v (and in some regions m) sounds as m in important...&quot; never write n before a B or a P, always, mp and mb
'''Bold text'''

== What is &quot;over-cultism&quot;? ==

The section on the letter 'v' states that pronouncing 'v' like 'v' instead of 'b' is an 'over-cultism'. An internet search sheds absolutely no light on the meaning of this phrase. Curious students who doubt the veracity of this wiki page (because anyone can edit it) will wonder if the phrase 'over-cultism' might mean something along the lines of being a widely held belief thoroughly known to be wrong to those in the know. No one can be sure though. Is it a neologism? If 'over-cultism' is synonymous with 'common misconception', that might be a better word choice.

For me, a beginner, it seems possible that v is a sort of cross between an English v and b, with at least a different mouth shape from a Spanish 'b'. Does it vary region to region, or is it really so absolute?

[[Special:Contributions/76.176.35.14|76.176.35.14]] ([[User talk:76.176.35.14|discuss]]) 19:43, 29 August 2011 (UTC)

== About Spanish &quot;Q&quot; ==

On this page it says that &quot;qu&quot; can substitute &quot;cu&quot; before &quot;a&quot; or &quot;o&quot;. Is this true, and how common is it?</text>
      <sha1>7ks8tmrilrs7u9fkmsa4s7eakb6rvyh</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Internet Technologies/Domain names</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2413</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2239893</id>
      <parentid>1697607</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-12-23T04:26:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jfmantis</username>
        <id>427643</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Marked for dewikification</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Dewikify}}

The '''Domain Name System''', most often known as simply '''DNS''', is a core feature of the [[Internet]]. It is a distributed database that handles the mapping between host names ('''domain names'''), which are more convenient for humans, and the numerical [[Wikipedia:IP_address|Internet addresses]]. For example, ''www.wikipedia.org'' is a domain name and ''130.94.122.199'' the corresponding numerical internet address. The domain name system acts much like an automated phone book, so you can &quot;call&quot; ''www.wikipedia.org'' instead of ''130.94.122.199''. So, it converts human-friendly names such as &quot;www.wikipedia.org&quot; into computer-friendly (IP) addresses such as 130.94.122.199. It can also handle the reverse mapping, meaning that we can query for a name for ''130.94.122.199'', that return ''larousse.wikipedia.org''

DNS was first invented in 1983 by [[Wikipedia:Paul_Mockapetris|Paul Mockapetris]]; the original specifications are described in [[Wikipedia:RFC|RFC]] 882.  In 1987 RFC 1034 and RFC 1035 were published which updated the DNS specifcation and made RFC 882 and RFC 883 obsolete.  Subsequent to that there have been quite a few RFCs published that propose various extensions to the core protocols.

DNS implements a hierarchical name space by allowing name service for parts of a name space known as zones to be &quot;delegated&quot; by a [[Wikipedia:Name_server|name server]] to subsidiary name-servers. DNS also provides additional information, such as alias names for systems, contact information, and which hosts act as mail hubs for groups of systems or domains.

The present restriction on the length of domain names is 63 characters, excluding the ''www.'' and ''.com'' or other extension. Domain names are also limited to a subset of [[Wikipedia:ASCII |ASCII]] characters, preventing many languages from representing their names and words correctly. The [[Wikipedia:Punycode|Punycode]]-based [[Wikipedia:IDNA|IDNA]] system, which maps [[Wikipedia:Unicode |Unicode]] strings into the valid DNS character set, has been approved by [[Wikipedia:ICANN|ICANN]] and adopted by some [[Wikipedia:domain_name_registry|registries]] as a workaround.

The DNS system is run by various flavors of DNS software, including:

* [[Wikipedia:BIND|BIND]] (Berkeley Internet Name Domain), the most commonly used namedaemon.
* [[Wikipedia:DJBDNS|DJBDNS]] (Dan J Bernstein's DNS implementation)
* [[Wikipedia:MaraDNS|MaraDNS]]
* [[Wikipedia:NSD|NSD]] (Name Server Daemon)
* [[Wikipedia:PowerDNS|PowerDNS]]

Any [[Wikipedia:Internet protocol|IP]] computer network can use DNS to implement its own private name system. However, the term &quot;domain name&quot; is most commonly used to refer to domain names implemented in the public [[Wikipedia:Internet|Internet]] DNS system. This is based on thirteen &quot;root servers&quot; worldwide, all but three of which are in the [[Wikipedia:United_States_of_America|United States of America]]. From these thirteen [[Wikipedia:root_nameserver|root servers]], the rest of the Internet DNS name space is delegated to other DNS servers which serve names within specific parts of the DNS name space.

An 'owner' of a domain name can be found by looking in the [[Wikipedia:whois|WHOIS]] database: for most TLDs a basic WHOIS is held by ICANN, with the detailed WHOIS maintained by the domain registry which controlls that domain. For the 240+ Country Code TLDs the position is usually that the registry holds the entire authorative WHOIS for that extension, as part of their many functions.

The current way the main DNS system is controlled is often criticized. The most common problems pointed at are that it is abused by monopolies or near-monopolies such as [[Wikipedia:VeriSign|VeriSign]] Inc., and problems with assignment of [[Wikipedia:top-level_domain|top-level domain]]s. 

Some also allege that many implementations of DNS server software fail to work gracefully with dynamically allocated IP addresses, although that is the failure of specific implementations and not failures of the protocol itself.

DNS uses [[Wikipedia:Transmission_Control_Protocol|TCP]] and [[Wikipedia:User_Datagram_Protocol|UDP]] [[Wikipedia:computer_port|port]] 53.  Most DNS queries (such as name resolution requests) use UDP connections as the amount of data transferred is small and the session establishment overhead would introduce unnecessary traffic and load on nameservers.  DNS zone file transfers between nameserver peers use TCP connections as the volume of data transferred is potentially much larger.

A DNS domain definition (sometimes referred to as a 'zone file') consists of individual DNS records.  There are several record types in common usage:
* '''SOA''' or Start Of Authority records contain parameters for the domain definition itself.
* '''A''' records resolve names into an IP addresses
* '''PTR''' records resolve IP addresses to names
* '''NS''' records define the authoritative nameservers for the domain.
* '''CNAME''' or Canonical Name records allow aliasing of one name to another.
* '''MX''' or Mail Exchange records define the mail server associated with a domain or A record.
* '''HINFO''' or Hardware Information records can be used to hold descriptive text about a specific device.

Virtually all modern operating systems and network applications contain resolver libraries or routines for interrogating DNS services.  However, OSs generally provide a command line interface for querying DNS servers.  The Windows NT family of operating systems provides the 'nslookup' command.  Unix-based operating systems may also offer 'nslookup' or 'dig' tools.

'''nslookup''' can either be used interactively, or non-interactively.  An example of non-interactive usage follows.  In this example, we gather the A record for www.wikipedia.org from the client's default nameserver:

''nslookup www.wikipedia.org''

Nslookup is somewhat more powerful when used interactively.  An example of this follows.  In the example, we find the mail servers for the domain wikipedia.org:

''nslookup''

''&gt; set q=MX''

''&gt; wikipedia.org''

''Non-authoritative answer:''

''wikipedia.org   MX preference = 50, mail exchanger = mormo.org''

''wikipedia.org   MX preference = 10, mail exchanger = mail.wikimedia.org''

''&gt;''

See also: [[Wikipedia:cybersquatting|cybersquatting]], [[Wikipedia:dynamic_DNS|dynamic DNS]], [[Wikipedia:ICANN|ICANN]], [[Wikipedia:DNSSEC|DNSSEC]]

==External links==
* [http://www.bind9.net/ DNS &amp; BIND Resources]
* [http://www.dnssec.net/ DNS Security Extensions (DNSSEC)]
* [http://www.hostfaqs.info/Domains.php Domain Name FAQs]
* [http://www.root-servers.org/ www.root-servers.org]
* [http://ietf.org/rfc/rfc0882 RFC 882]
* [http://ietf.org/rfc/rfc0883 RFC 883]
* [http://ietf.org/rfc/rfc1034 RFC 1034]
* [http://ietf.org/rfc/rfc1035 RFC 1035]

[[Category:Internet Technologies]]</text>
      <sha1>i9i67ph56h11iq7yrvp8yg263anr5iv</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Wikibooks:How to obtain public domain books</title>
    <ns>4</ns>
    <id>2420</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2453341</id>
      <parentid>2345915</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-12-05T10:42:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Chriswaterguy</username>
        <id>15950</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Other */ Replace dead University of Florida link (viewable at http://web.archive.org/web/20031205122550/http://www.fcd.ufl.edu/PublicMaterials.asp ) with a Northern Arizona University page (almost the same content)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{useful}}

There are many resources available on the net that are in the [[w:public domain|public domain]], and therefore freely usable without restrictions for Wikimedia universe (this includes Wikibooks) content. 

There are also many [[w:copyright|copyright]]ed resources whose licensing terms are liberal enough that they can generally be used as well. For these, see [[w:Wikipedia:Free or semi-free non-Public-Domain information resources|free or semi-free non-Public-Domain information resources]] and [[w:Wikipedia:GNU Free Documentation License resources|GNU Free Documentation license resources]] (includes images).

This page is intended as a list of only true public domain text resources. For public domain images, see [[w:Wikipedia:Public domain image resources|public domain image resources]].

'''CAVEAT''': Because there is no concept of [[w:public domain|public domain]] in [[w:Japan's copyright law|Japan's copyright law]], even though the materials are claimed public domain, there can be some restrictions such as about commercial use, which has a conflict with [[m:GFDL|GFDL]]. Also, unlike the United States, most English speaking commonwealth countries exert [[m:Crown copyright|Crown copyright]]. Please make certain that in any particular jurisdiction government agencies will allow you to copy materials without permission.

India government sites also seem to be copyright by default.  Quoting from [http://www.maharashtra.gov.in/english/login/userAgreement.htm]: ''Unless otherwise stated, copyright and all intellectual property rights in all material presented on the site (including but not limited to text, audio, video or graphical images), trademarks and logos appearing on this site are the property of Government of Maharashtra and are protected under applicable Indian laws. Any infringement shall be vigorously defended and pursued to the fullest extent permitted by law.''

== Please don't data dump! ==

The resources below are valuable, but many are very old, context-dependent, written from biased points of view, and otherwise are not ''in themselves'' good encyclopedia articles. The [[w:1911 encyclopedia|1911 encyclopedia]] discussed below is a good example of this - it contains some useful information, but also antiquated writing style and innumerable errors of fact. 

So please, if you copy material from these sources, make sure you take some time to verify the actuality of the information, edit, '''update''', introduce, or otherwise produce a good article out of it rather than just [[wiktionary:dump|dump]]ing it here verbatim. But if you can't do that, put it in anyway because somebody else will come by and tweak it.  Wikibooks books are living texts, because everybody has the power to edit them.  An entry that starts out incorrect, as a stub or even as something very inane will eventually be tweaked and evolve into something much more sophisticated.

== Encyclopedic or general resources ==

=== US Government ===
* Most publications of the United States Federal Government.  Under the Federal Copyright Act material that is originated by the Federal government is not subject to copyright.  In some cases, material may originate with a private contractor which assigns the copyright to the agency.  However, material that is generated by the Federal government which doesn't have a notice can be copied. Entries below marked &quot;(US Federal Govt.)&quot; belong to this category. Note this only applies to the *Federal* government.  United States state governments can copyright materials.

=== Canadian Government ===

* While the Canadian government claims Crown copyright there are images archives at the National Library of Canada that are in the public domain. They include:
**[http://www.nlc-bnc.ca/earlyimages/index-e.html Early Images of Canada] 550 images
**[http://www.nlc-bnc.ca/cin/index-e.html Canadian Illustrated News] 4000 half-tone images from 1869-1883

=== Dictionaries ===
* [http://smac.ucsd.edu/cgi-bin/http_webster Hypertext Webster Gateway] A searchable interface to a 1913 public-domain Webster's dictionary, downloadable here: [http://msowww.anu.edu.au/~ralph/OPTED/ Public Domain Dictionary]

=== Other ===
*&lt;!-- [http://www.pdbooksonline.com Public Domain Books: Online] Visitors can read and download 1,000s of public domain books.--&gt;
* [http://www.promo.net/pg Project Gutenberg] See in particular The Project Gutenberg Encyclopedia (although only [ftp://ibiblio.org/pub/docs/books/gutenberg/etext95/pge0112.txt Vol 1] of this seems to be available). Note that not all of the Project Gutenberg text are fully in the public domain. Read the license of the respective texts carefully.
* [http://www.1911encyclopedia.org 1911 Encyclopedia] A scanned version of the 1911 Encyclopædia Britannica. The OCR quality is not very high. Some articles end in the middle and continue on the next page. The writing style is antiquated and archaic, contains a fair amount of bias, and the material contains many factual errors. Anything taken from here needs extensive fact-checking and editing. See [[Wikipedia:1911 Encyclopaedia Britannica]] for ways of best using this material.  
* [http://www.cairns.net.au/~sharefin/Cyclopedia/contents.html The Household Cyclopedia]
* [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/ The Catholic Encyclopedia (1908)]
* [http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/index.jsp The Jewish Encyclopedia (1901-1906)]

:This website contains the complete contents of the 12-volume Jewish Encyclopedia, which was originally published between 1901-1906. The Jewish Encyclopedia, which recently became part of the public domain, contains over 15,000 articles and illustrations. This online version contains the unedited contents of the original encyclopedia. Since the original work was completed almost 100 years ago, it does not cover a significant portion of modern Jewish History (e.g., the creation of Israel, the Holocaust, etc.). However, it does contain an incredible amount of information that is remarkably relevant today.

:We are considering inviting the Internet community to help us update the encyclopedia -- if you are interested in volunteering (as a writer, editor, etc.) please join our Mailing List. By putting this important work on the Internet, we hope to improve the quality of Jewish information available online -- and stimulate new discussion. Therefore, we have sections &quot;Discussion Forums&quot; and &quot;Internet Links&quot; which allow our visitors to converse and identify related websites.

* [http://www.ibiblio.org/ ibiblio.org] is a major repository of information, &quot;the public's library and digital archive&quot;. All collections on ibiblio are assumed to be in the public domain unless otherwise noted. Check for copyright notices on any material you wish to use.

* [http://answers.google.com/answers/main?cmd=threadview&amp;id=189815 Web sites that contain collections that are copyright free] - a lot of duplication here but it might be some are new.

*[http://www.hti.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?sid=ea572df9991f9af0379d042a95658221&amp;idno=ajk6207.0001.001&amp;xc=1&amp;c=moa&amp;cc=moa&amp;g=moagrp&amp;seq=23 A Pronouncing dictionary of Biography and Mythology.] Contains a large number (10000+) short [[WB:NPOV|NPOV]] biographical entries many of which could be copied and pasted to form stubs (due to its focus it contains information on many 19th and 18th century figures not yet covered in Wikibooks).

* [http://www2.nau.edu/~d-elearn/faq/answers_524 What resources are available in the Public Domain?] - Northern Arizona University.

== Philosophy, mathematics and natural science ==
* [http://www.csudh.edu/oliver/pubdomdb.htm Public domain databases of interests to scientists]

=== Astronomy and astrophysics===
* (US Federal Govt.)  [http://vesuvius.jsc.nasa.gov/er/seh/seh.html Space Educators' Handbook]
* (US Federal Govt.)  [http://www-istp.gsfc.nasa.gov/stargaze/Sgloss.htm NASA glossary of terms] - appears to be in the PD, please check
* (US Federal Govt.) [http://roland.lerc.nasa.gov/~dglover/dictionary/content.html NASA DICTIONARY OF TECHNICAL TERMS FOR AEROSPACE USE] (originally NASA report SP-7, written in 1965, some pages updated since then: may not be fully up-to-date)

=== Biology ===
* (US Federal Govt.)  [http://www.fs.fed.us/database/feis/plants/tree/psemeng/index.html US Forest Service Fire Effects Database] Database of current information on a wide variety of tree, shrub, grass, mammal, bird, reptile and amphibian species found largely in North America -- great reference material

=== Chemistry ===
''Note:  
Phenethylamines I Have Known And Loved i.e.: PIHKAL and TIHKAL, formerly listed here, are ''not'' in the public domain, so cannot be listed here''

=== Geology and Earth science ===
* (US Federal Govt.)  [http://minerals.usgs.gov/ USGS Mineral Resources Program] - &quot;The Mineral Resources Program provides and communicates current, impartial information on the occurrence, quality, quantity, and availability of mineral resources.&quot;
* (US Federal Govt.)  [http://www.giss.nasa.gov/ref/glossary.html NASA GISS glossary of climate terms]
* (US Federal Govt.)  [http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/Library/glossary.php3?mode=all NASA Earth Observatory Glossary]
* (US Federal Govt.) [http://www.ngs.noaa.gov/PUBS_LIB/Geodesy4Layman/toc.htm Geodesy for the Layman]

=== Mathematics ===
* [http://www.maths.tcd.ie/pub/HistMath/People/RBallHist.html biographies of mathematicians] - from a 1908 history of mathematics. See the discussion at [[w:Rouse History of Mathematics|Rouse History of Mathematics]]

=== Philosophy ===

=== Physics ===
* [http://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/einstein/works/1910s/relative/ Relativity: The Special and General Theory] by Albert Einstein
* [http://www.physicsforfree.com Physics for Free] has three public domain physics books by former Yale professor Frank Firk. One about basic physics, one about groups and particles and one about Einstein's theories.

=== Statistics ===

== Social sciences ==

=== Anthropology ===
=== Archaeology ===
=== Economics ===
=== Geography  and maps===
* (US Federal Govt.)  [http://www.census.gov U.S. Census Bureau] Has an enormous range of facts and figures which we will find helpful in fleshing out articles about cities and states.
* (US Federal Govt.) [http://www.census.gov/ipc/www/idbsum.html Summary Demographic Data by Country from the US Census Bureau]

* (US Federal Govt.)  [http://www.cia.gov/cia/publications/factbook/ CIA World Factbook] Contains basic facts on all the countries of the world.
* (US Federal Govt.)  [http://www.state.gov/r/pa/bgn/ U.S. State Dept.: Background notes on the countries of the world]. Also see their [http://www.state.gov/r/pa/rls/index.cfm?docid=3797 copyright notice], which, as you'll see, places material ''that is not explicitly copyrighted'' in the public domain.
* (US Federal Govt.) [http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/cshome.html] - Library of Congress area country studies.  It explicitly states that it is not copyrighted
* (US Federal Govt.) the NIMA www.nima.mil GEOnet Names Server contains approximately 3.88 million named geographical features outside the United States, with 5.34 million names [http://earth-info.nima.mil/gns/html/]
* (US Federal Govt.) the USGS Geographic Names Information System claims to have almost 2 million physical and cultural geographic features within the United States
* [http://www.lib.utexas.edu/maps/index.html Perry-Castañeda Library Map Collection] at the University of Texas (Check [http://www.lib.utexas.edu/usage_statement.html Usage statement] and verify public domain status.)

=== History ===
* (US Federal Govt.) [http://www.archives.gov/welcome/index.html United States National Archives and Records Administration], the U.S. federal government's official archive site
* [http://www.lib.utexas.edu/maps/historical/index.html Historical Maps] of the Perry-Castañeda Library Map Collection at the University of Texas (Public domain [http://www.lib.utexas.edu/usage_statement.html usage statement] - &quot;Courtesy of The General Libraries, The University of Texas at Austin.&quot;)
* (US Federal Govt.) [http://bioguide.congress.gov/biosearch/biosearch1.asp Biographical Directory of the United States Congress] - biographical information on everyone who ever served in Congress, including a good number of presidents

=== History of science and technology ===

=== Language and Linguistics ===

=== Political science ===
* (US Federal Govt.)  [http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/ Library of Congress Country Studies] An on-line version of the Library of Congress Country Studies with information on 101 countries, including detailed histories. See [[Wikipedia:Library of Congress Country Studies|Library of Congress Country Studies]] for ways on using this material.  

=== Psychology ===
* [http://psychclassics.yorku.ca/index.htm ''Classics in the History of Psychology''] is a collection of classic public domain works in psychology collected by Christopher D. Green: see [http://psychclassics.yorku.ca/copyright.htm here] for a note about the copyright status of the individual documents in the collection.

== Applied arts and sciences ==

=== Agriculture ===

=== Architecture ===

=== Business and industry ===
* (US Federal Govt.) [http://www.eia.doe.gov US Energy Information Agency] - statistics and info on energy industry (mostly US but some stuff for the world) - they appreciate but do not require acknowledgement (copyright info [http://www.eia.doe.gov/neic/aboutEIA/copy_right.htm here])

=== Communication ===
* (US Federal Govt.)  Federal Standard 1037C, a telecommunications glossary, appears to be mostly in the public domain based on these principles, and is a source of a large number of bits of useful material. A few items are derived from copyrighted sources: where this is the case, there is an attribution to the source. ''Note: only those articles that have substantial content and are from 100% public domain sources are appropriate to be used in Wikibooks''
* (US Federal Govt.)  [http://www-comm.itsi.disa.mil/ DISA site about commercial telecommunications standards] From the site: &quot;This site is maintained by the Commercial Standards Division of the Defense Information Systems Agency (DISA) to provide information about the current status of commercial telecommunications standards.&quot;

=== Computer science ===
* (US Federal Govt.)  [http://www.nist.gov/dads/terms.html NIST Dictionary of Algorithms, Data Structures, and Problems]: Huge, high-quality resource. All entries are in the public domain except for a few that carry an explicit copyright notice.
* [http://www.cs.utexas.edu/users/djimenez/utsa/ Public domain lecture notes]: &quot;Introduction to Computer Science&quot;, &quot;Data Structures&quot; and &quot;Analysis of Algorithms&quot;
* [http://catb.org/jargon/ The Jargon File] Eric S. Raymond's definitive work on geek-speak.

=== Education ===

=== Employment===
* (US Federal Govt.)  [http://www.bls.gov/oco/ Occupational Outlook Handbook] Contains descriptions of a great many occupations.

=== Engineering ===

=== Law ===
* [http://www.constitution.org/bouv/bouvier.htm Bouvier's Law Dictionary (1856)]

=== Medicine ===
* (US Federal Govt.) [http://cdc.gov Centers for Disease Control and Prevention] &quot;In general all information presented in these pages and all items available for download are for public use. However, you may encounter some pages that require a login password and id. If this is the case you may assume that information presented and items available for download therein are for your authorized access only and not for redistribution by you unless you are otherwise informed.&quot;
* (US Federal Govt.)  [http://medlineplus.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/disclaimer.html Medline at the NIH] copyright terms [http://medlineplus.nlm.nih.gov/ here] indicating materials in public domain unless indicated otherwise
* (US Federal Govt.)  [http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health/urolog/urolog.htm NIH public domain publications on urology]
* (US Federal Govt.)  [http://www.nimh.nih.gov/practitioners/patinfo.cfm NIMH Patient education materials (Public Domain)]
* (US Federal Govt.) [http://www.nal.usda.gov/fnic/foodcomp/ USDA Nutrient Data Laboratory] Contains nutritional information on loads of foods. (From FAQ), &quot;USDA food composition data is in the public domain and there is no copyright. We would appreciate it if you would list us as the source of the data and when possible we would like to see the product which uses the data or be notified of its use.&quot; 
* (US Federal Govt.)  [http://www.ninds.nih.gov/health_and_medical/disorders/ A large collection of public domain information sheets on various neurological disorders]
** ''Note:'' This [http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=nih+publication+%22not+copyrighted%22+site%3A.gov Google search for &quot;nih publication &quot;not copyrighted&quot; site:.gov&quot;] should help uncover more NIH public domain documents
* [http://aitl.uc.edu/reference/elec/Etext.cfm University of Cincinnati etexts]: Contains a nice edition of 1918 Gray's Anatomy with illustrations.
* (US Federal Govt.)  [http://ntp-server.niehs.nih.gov/ U.S. National Toxicology Program]: copyright notice [http://ntp-server.niehs.nih.gov/main_pages/disc_cpy.html here], typical U.S. govt terms.
* The Bad Bug Book at http://www.cfsan.fda.gov/~mow/intro.html appears to be in the public domain: but please check each section individually for public domain status.
* [http://www.well.ox.ac.uk/asthma/public/ Asthma genetics - Public domain data]
* (US Federal Govt.) [http://www.surgeongeneral.gov/library/mentalhealth/toc.html Mental Health: A Report of the Surgeon General] (needs positive confirmation before use: some diagrams within the text say &quot;used by permission&quot;, which implies that they are copyrighted -- however, the rest appears to be written by U.S. govt employees)
* (US Federal Govt.) The [http://www.nci.nih.gov/cancerinfo/terminologyresources NCI thesaurus] is a massive public domain repository of definitions of medical terms

=== Military ===
* (US Federal Govt.)  [http://www.navy.mil/ U.S. Navy], [http://www.chinfo.navy.mil/navpalib/ships/ Info on specific ships]
* (US Federal Govt.)  [http://www.af.mil/ Air Force Link]

=== Public affairs ===
* (US Federal Govt.)  [http://www.fema.gov Federal Emergency Management Agency]: Not sure how much of this is useful, but anyway it's under the same terms as the U.S. Department of State site: all in the public domain ''unless it carries an explicit copyright notice.''
* (US Federal Govt.)  [http://www.epa.gov U.S. Environmental Protection Agency]: copyright notice [http://www.epa.gov/region4/home/notice.html here], typical U.S. gov't terms.  Does have some good information for people patient enough to find it.
* (US Federal Govt.)  [http://www.voanews.com/ Voice Of America] - All text, audio and video material produced exclusively by the Voice of America is public domain. However, some images and graphics are licensed for use and covered by all applicable copyright laws.

=== Technology ===

=== Transport ===

== Culture ==
* UNESCO Public Domain Resources and Virtual Library [http://www.unesco.org/webworld/public_domain/public_inf.html at this URL]

=== Arts and Entertainment ===

=== Classics ===
* Harpers Dictionary of Classical Antiquities (1898) can be found via http://www.art.man.ac.uk/clah/links/searchency.htm
* [http://digital.library.upenn.edu/webbin/gutbook/lookup?num=3327 Bulfinch's mythology from project Gutenberg]

=== Cooking ===
*US Department of Agriculture [http://www.fsis.usda.gov/index.htm Food Safety and Inspection Service] maintains many articles about meat products.

=== Libraries ===
* [http://ftp.std.com/obi/ Online Book Initiative]
* [http://pdreader.org Public Domain Reader]: Public domain works in HTML, PDF, iSilo .pdb, Rocket eBook .rb and Plain text formats.(dead link)
* [http://digital.library.upenn.edu/books/ The Online Books Page]: A comprehensive index of books available on the Internet. Most are public domain, but not all; check for copyright restrictions.
* [http://www.publicbookshelf.com/ Public Book Shelf]

=== Literature ===

* [http://www.bibliomania.com/2/3/174/frameset.html Brewer's Reader's Handbook], published in 1898, states that &quot;the object of this Handbook is to supply readers and speakers with a lucid but very brief account of such names as are used in allusions and references, whether by poets or prose writers&quot;. Contains many short articles, some on obscure topics.

=== Music ===
* [http://www.cpdl.org/ The Choral Public Domain Library] describes itself as 'A Free Sheet Music Archive'
* [http://www.ibiblio.org/mutopia/ Mutopia]: a collection of public domain sheet music.
* [http://www.ibiblio.org/gutenberg/music/ Project Gutenberg music section] 

=== Recreation ===

=== Religion ===
* [http://www.site-berea.com/dicionarios.html Biblical dictionaries]: Some late nineteenth century Biblical dictionaries; these might need work to render unbiased and up to date.
** A number of articles already contain most of the useful text from [[w:Easton's Bible Dictionary (1897)|Easton's Bible Dictionary (1897)]]
** Hitchcock's Bible Dictionary's list of Biblical names has been used as a source for the [[w:List of Biblical names|List of Biblical names]].
** [[w:Smith's Bible Dictionary|Smith's Bible Dictionary]] is another 19th century Bible dictionary, with much useful but dated text
* [http://www.bible.org/public/readme.htm Public Domain Biblical references]
* [http://www.ccel.org/ Christian Classics Ethereal Library]: A project similar to Project Gutenberg, but focusing on Christian texts.
* [http://www.ebible.org/bible/asv/ American Standard Version of the Holy Bible (1901)]
* [http://www.ebible.org/bible/kjv/ King James Version of the Holy Bible with Apocrypha]

=== Sports ===

== Photos ==

* Please see [[w:Public domain image resources|public domain image resources]].

== Miscellaneous ==
* [http://www.vectorsite.net/ Writings by Greg Goebel]: Science, technology, military history, introductions to classical and relativistic physics.
* [http://www.infoanarchy.org Infoanarchy]: a weblog dedicated to copyright issues. All original material is in the public domain, although some redistributed articles may be under copyright.
* [http://www33.brinkster.com/ethical/ &quot;Ethical treatment for all youth&quot;], a website that documents therapy and detention of children and juveniles for consensual sexual activity. Author wrote to [[User:Eloquence|me]] in a personal email: &quot;Certainly, I intend everything at my site to be in the public domain, to be used freely by anyone else.  Of course, I would appreciate it if people who use it would link to my site, since I can use all the exposure I can get.&quot;

== To be filed ==
''please file these resources under the appropriate topic headings above''
* ''There are no more entries to be filed at the moment''
----

== Sources for finding public domain resources ==

Here are some web searches which may help discover U.S. Federal Government and other public domain documents.  Please note that you must still manually verify that documents are in the public domain. Please note that not all sites in the .gov domain are U.S. federal government sites: some may be U.S. state or other local government sites.

&lt;!--* [http://www.pdbooksonline.com Public Domain Books: Online] - Visitors can read &amp; download 1,000's of free books from the Public Domain.--&gt;
* This [http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;q=%22not+copyrighted%22+site%3A.gov Google search for '&quot;not copyrighted&quot; site:.gov'] finds documents on websites in the .gov domain that contain the text &quot;not copyrighted&quot;. 
* This [http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;q=%22public+domain%22+site%3A.gov Google search for '&quot;public domain&quot; site:.gov']  finds documents on websites in the .gov domain that contain the text &quot;public domain&quot;. 
Google searches for links or exact phrases:
*[http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=%22this+document+is+in+the+public+domain%22 &quot;this document is in the public domain&quot;] (estimated 2500+ hits)
*[http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=%22this+page+is+in+the+public+domain%22 &quot;this page is in the public domain&quot;] (estimated 1000+ hits)
*[http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=%22this+information+is+in+the+public+domain%22 &quot;this information is in the public domain&quot;] (extimated 1000+ hits)
*[http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=%22this+text+is+in+the+public+domain%22 &quot;this text is in the public domain&quot;] (estimated 2000+ hits)
*[http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=%22placed+in+the+public+domain%22 &quot;placed in the public domain&quot;] (estimated 24000+ hits, but many instances refer to other things)
*[http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=%22www.primarilypublicdomain.org &quot;www.primarilypublicdomain.org&quot;] (find links confirming that a site is Primarily Public Domain)
*[http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;oe=UTF-8&amp;q=link:uzMVB-CIT4kC:creativecommons.org/licenses/publicdomain Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication]

The Creative Commons initiative may become a valuable new resource  for Wikibooks authors. The project provides a &quot;wizard&quot; for licensing information under various open content licenses (including the public domain, which is not a license), and also features a [http://creativecommons.org/works/ directory] of these works. (See also [[w:Creative Commons License|Creative Commons License]])

Book:
* ''[http://www.pdinfo.com/source/N374339.htm The Public Domain: How to Find &amp; Use Copyright-Free Writings, Music, Art &amp; More]'' by Stephen Fishman, ISBN  0873374339

Lists of general resources:
* [http://www.primarilypublicdomain.org Registry for material that is in the public domain &quot;except as noted&quot;] 
* [http://people.wiki.bin.org  Open People network for people adding original content, in the locations they specfiy, in the Public Domain except as noted] 
* [http://www.savetz.com/pd/ Unmaintained list of public domain resources] by Kevin Savetz
* [http://www.banis-associates.com/pdlist/ Banis Associates list of public domain resources]
* [http://www.pdinfo.com/default.htm Public Domain Music website]
* [http://www.bin.org/pd/ Brian Waters' list of public domain resources]
* [http://www.kingkong.demon.co.uk/ngcoba/ngcoba.htm New General Catalog of Old Books and Authors] tracking old books and author's dates for determining copyright expiration

Lists of U.S. Government resources:
* [http://apps.fss.gsa.gov/pub/fed-specs.cfm Index of Federal Specifications, Standards and Commercial Item Descriptions]
* [http://www.itl.nist.gov/fipspubs/ Federal Information Processing Standards home page]
* [http://stinet.dtic.mil/str/dodiss4_fields.html DOD Index of Specifications and Standards]
* [http://dodssp.daps.mil/ Department of Defense Single Stock Point for MilSpecs and Standards]
* [http://www.nist.gov/public_affairs/database.htm NIST Data Resources index]
* [http://www.access.gpo.gov/su_docs/locators/cgp/index.html Catalog of U.S. Government Publications]
* [http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/ Country Study] - copyright free

See also:
* [[Wikipedia:Free or semi-free non-Public-Domain information resources]]</text>
      <sha1>1lplih16wunlw0q8jhzzc7w0r06reve</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>