<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>File:Pxpypz.jpg</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>946</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748854</id>
      <parentid>153080</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-02-09T19:54:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">diagram of p orbitals

I tied together some balloons and photographed them in my bathtub, then played with the image in Photoshop and then Illustrator. Would have used some cool open source software to do it if I had some. Maybe when I get my Linux box running. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

:I think that the GIMP now runs on windows, though I haven't actually tried it [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 21:31, 4 Sep 2003 (UTC)

{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>btk4t6b4ur0euqzuunruf5r97h0jshy</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Sp2.jpg</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>948</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748852</id>
      <parentid>153082</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-02-09T19:54:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">is this sp2 ? I cant remember .. could use for carbocation I think ..

Yes i'm pretty sure it is [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 21:19, 4 Sep 2003 (UTC)
:Actually come to think of it it's sp2 plus p, but that's what you meant anyway wasn't it ? [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 21:21, 4 Sep 2003 (UTC)

{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>lhm09dzvjhpy84ftudn9jb2bnyxwyv1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Sanskrit</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>950</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2073096</id>
      <parentid>2072181</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-03-23T19:49:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>YMS</username>
        <id>112461</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Undid revision 2072181 by [[Special:Contributions/Bepe|Bepe]] ([[User talk:Bepe|discuss]]) - why?</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==General Sanskrit lessons==
*[[/Introduction|Introduction to Sanskrit]]
*[[/Basic grammar/]]
*[[/Nouns/]]
*[[/Verbs/]]
*[[/Pronouns/]]
*[[/Adjectives/]]
*[[/Sandhi/]]
*[[/Everyday_Phrases|Words and Phrases]]

==Cultural==
*[[/History|History]]
*[[/Culture|Culture]]
**[[/Clothing|Clothing]]

== The Sanskrit script ==
*[[Devanagari]]
*[[/Transliteration|Transliteration]]

== Glossary ==
*[[/Vocabulary nouns|Nouns]]
*[[/Vocabulary verbs|Verbs]]
*[[/Vocabulary adjectives|Adjectives]]
*[[/Numbers|Numbers]]
*[[/Everyday Phrases|Phrases and idioms]]

==See also==
Wikner's [http://www.danam.co.uk/Sanskrit/Sanskrit%20Introductory/Sanskrit%20Introductory.html introduction to Sanskrit] is a good start.

''Sanskrit: An Easy Introduction to an Enchanting Language'' by Professor Ashok Aklujkar is also recommended.

{{Subjects|Languages of Asia}}
{{alphabetical|S}}
{{status|0%}}
__NOTOC__</text>
      <sha1>8wmm5vcar8prb3jw8z61mrqtpk57dwb</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:Marshman</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>951</id>
    <revision>
      <id>793988</id>
      <parentid>793948</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-03-20T13:55:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Robert Horning</username>
        <id>1227</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Your De-Adminship */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Welcome to Wikibooks! Now that your user page is here, you are one of us who suffer dual addiction, both Wikiholic and Wikiworm :).
I wish you well in linking Botany to the 'Pedia.
Again, Welcome aboard! ..[[User:LouI|LouI]] 19:13, 4 Sep 2003 (UTC)
:Thanks!  I was contemplating how one could develop study outlines for topics at Wikipedia, and discovered WikiBooks. The idea is more suited to this project. - [[User:Marshman|Marshman]] 20:47, 4 Sep 2003 (UTC)
----
A suggestion: You don't need to copy an entire article from the 'pedia to protect your references from future editing. You can simply refer to a specific historic version. Thus [http://www.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plant_cell Plant cell] gets the current page, while [http://www.wikipedia.org/w/wiki.phtml?title=Plant_cell&amp;oldid=1407735 Planr cell oldid=1407735] always returns a specific historic version.

There is probably a shorter way (without full URL) to get to the Wikipedia namespace, and I'll ask in the staff lounge. [[User:LouI|LouI]] 05:01, 8 Sep 2003 (UTC)
:Actually, I was not concerned about protecting any particular version on Wikipedia from being edited.  I am attempting/intending to improve the Wikipedia entries if I find the deficient, otherwise I welcome each articles improvement with time.  I do intend to bring over material when it is introductory in nature and therefore useful to simply have the text in Wikibook ''Guide'' to set the stage for suggested readings of articles. I will either write that material myself, or grab a good start from off of Wikipedia.  
:Seems like I was told there would eventually be a shorter way to get to Wikipedia namespaces, and I have seen &quot;en:&quot; used, but was unsure if that was available yet. - [[User:Marshman|Marshman]] 08:06, 8 Sep 2003 (UTC)

----
I want to nominate you to be an admin but can't find the nomination page. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
:I don't know where it is! Thanks for support. I did get admin at Wikipedia and have not done too much damage over there. 8} - [[User:Marshman|Marsh]] 17:22, 24 Sep 2003 (UTC)
::I see it happened, presumably less formal here than at Wikipedia as probably required by the present small crowd at Wikibooks.  Anyway, thanks, whomever is/was responsible. Sysop [[User:Marshman|Marsh]]

----
Hi Marsh. Thanks for your comments on my talk page. I realize that your intention for the introduction was to just point out the similarities between English and German words. However, I've heard that it's best to also write down the proper article right from the beginning where you introduce a new word.[[User:ThomasStrohmann | Thomas]]

-----
Hi Marshman, you've put the comment to Robbyjo on his user page, not his [[User talk:Robbyjo|talk page]]. I'd move it myself but that wouldn't look right :)  [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 09:13, 25 Oct 2003 (UTC)
:Thanks it was late at night. He had a blank user page, so I clicked on &quot;Discuss this Page&quot;, but did not watch what came up! - [[User:Marshman|Marsh]]

==Moving Botany pages==
Marsh, this new naming scheme looks like a bad idea to me. &quot;Biology Botany&quot;? That does not seem any better than Botany. Worse, rather. Did they do it to you or did you consent ? Its a trifling thing but bugs me, I'd like to see if we could undo it. Comments ? --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
::From what I can gether, Botany was selected as an example page. I was not asked.  Although '''Biology_Botany''' is not too thrilling to me, the rest of the system, say '''Botany_Introduction_How_to_use''' seems like a logical approach.  Of course it can all be undone, with a little work. I agree, a discussion should be set up separate from the Staff Lounge, especially if changes are going forward. - [[User:Marshman|Marsh]] 04:03, 27 Oct 2003 (UTC)

::Marsh-dogg, who did this act ? I would like to communicate with them. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

::Marshman! Why not set up a discussion page for the subject. I responded to the initial change, but I was not logged in (found out later) so it is bnot recorded in my contributions list. But should be on the page history? - [[User:Marshman|Marsh]] 07:41, 27 Oct 2003 (UTC)

: Why not Biology:Botany, like I've done with Discrete mathematics:''whatever'' ? [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]]

::Actually, I'm not proposing any system; See [[Wikibooks:Staff_lounge]] for what discussion has taken place to date (not much) - [[User:Marshman|Marsh]] 08:31, 27 Oct 2003 (UTC)

:: Sorry about before - I missed the SL discussion to the matter. [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 05:29, 5 Nov 2003 (UTC)

::Which has not gone very far by the way &amp;mdash; but it is generally pretty quiet over here compared with Wikipedia. No problem, I;m cool 8^) but I was in the process of changing the traditional &quot;tight&quot; form of page names to one more open when you came along almost (a day or two) after me and &quot;reverted&quot;.  Since these are &quot;books,&quot; I'm thinking the look of every line has a bit more impact than is the case for an encyclopedia article, so I've opted for now to go with the open look (hope you do not mind) - [[User:Marshman|Marsh]] 05:51, 5 Nov 2003 (UTC)

----
Hi Marsh, I've listened to the alphabet recording and I don't think the 'B' and 'E' sound English. However, recording with my $10 microphone, the initial sounds of 'B' and 'P' (which are the same as in English I think) do not come out as clearly as they could be. If I get the chance, I'll make a better recording some time later. [[User:ThomasStrohmann|Thomas]]
: I listened again and the Bay is ok, just a tad towards Bee. The Ay seems more towards an EE (english), but both shifts could be the microphone. It is great you can produce these, so I'm not complaining. Great additions to the text! - [[User:Marshman|Marsh]] 17:58, 29 Oct 2003 (UTC)

----
About the main page width. I think it must be a browser issue. What browser are you using ?  [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 22:04, 4 Nov 2003 (UTC)

----
Hi Marsh, the layout for vocabulary can be done by leaving the first character of a line blank, for example:

 das Wort        word
 der Buchstabe   character

[[User:ThomasStrohmann|Thomas]]

:Shoot. I did read that when I first showed up at Wikipedia. Thanks - [[User:Marshman|Marsh]] 06:04, 6 Nov 2003 (UTC)

==Link format==
Marshman, following is a short, tidy format for writing working links into the main Wikipedia: [[en:wiki|wiki]]. (That is, if you did not know this already). And I am talking about the format the link is written in, not where this particular link leads .. hope I am not confusing the issue. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
:Thanks. I see what you are saying. I'll try that format. I originally used &lt;nowiki&gt;En:Wikipedia|wiki&lt;/nowiki&gt; and that worked, but then one day stopped working. I'm told &lt;nowiki&gt;Wikipedia:en:wiki|wiki&lt;/nowiki&gt; is the correct form.

==Pictures==
Marshman -- do you take your own pictures ? Where do you get them ? They are beautiful and bring a real level of professional image to the site. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
:Thanks for the compliment.  Yes, I take them myself.  I bought a Nikon Coolpix 950 a few years ago, and have been using it to illustrate reports, websites, etc.  Nice thing about digital, you can just click away without regard to film costs.  I've taken over 7000 pictures in those few years, but have kept only perhaps 1000 or a little less.  It has been a very good camera, but I will probably need a new one pretty soon. - [[User:Marshman|Marsh]] 02:29, 9 Feb 2004 (UTC)

:Wow I am impressed. I'd buy the old camera off of you if you are going to sell it... --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

::I will let you know ! - [[User:24.94.82.245|24.94.82.245]] 01:20, 10 Feb 2004 (UTC) - [[User:Marshman|Marsh]] 01:21, 10 Feb 2004 (UTC)

:::Marshman,

:::Hello, I hope that you have been well lately. 

:::I was just looking at some beautiful botanical photos and remembering your Nikon Coolpix 950. Do you still have it? Still want to sell it? If so, I’ll make you an offer.--[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]] 19:51, 22 Jun 2005 (UTC)

::Hey Karl. You're back!  That camera is starting to get difficult to use. I'm debating whether to get a new one or get it fixed.  You are right, it is a great camera and that model is no longer available (Nikon Coolpix 950).  I think we can both do much better in terms of functionality, but I've not had time to research that. Let me see if I can replace the camera for myself and get that one fixed for a reasonable price.  Then we can talk.  As is, I could not put much value on it to sell although it does still work and I continue to turn out good photos, but I'm having a battery problem (may not have anything to do with the camera) that I need to solve. - [[User:Marshman|marsh]] 04:21, 23 Jun 2005 (UTC) 

----

Marshman: do you have an image or images that we could use on the main page of the [[General Biology|general biology textbook]]? --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
:Have lots of images. Do you have anything special in muind? - [[User:Marshman|Marsh]] 18:27, 4 Mar 2004 (UTC)

:I didn't think about a picture till just after I put the recipe up.  I didn't cook at home last night, was cooking for my grandmother and just used what I had on hand, and it turned out really good.  Next time, I'll bring a camera with me. :~) [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] 06:08, 5 Mar 2004 (UTC)
::Photographing food is a real art; but would certainly enhance any recipe to have a photo of the finished product - [[User:Marshman|Marsh]] 16:57, 5 Mar 2004 (UTC)
----
Dear Marshman,

I only learned about the wiki concept recently, and (like everybody around it seems) I think it is great. I have started to contribute to the Botany textbook, mainly on chapter 6, and created missing chapters and updated the content page and TOC. I have done a PhD in molecular plant virology, therefore my interest in chap 6. After general introductions, I focus the text there mostly on plant pathogens, since they are of most interest for those studying botany (and hopelessly ignored in the wikipedia virology and bacteria articles)
Please have a look at the book when you have time, and give me feedback on my work. Thank you, and best wishes, [[User:Alettaka|Aletta]] 21:15, 24 Mar 2004 (UTC)
:Wiki concept is great if you like to write or edit. You are certainly welcome to help out here with the Botany text project (add some info to the contributors page when you get a chance) and I like seeing you have a strong  background in microbes!.  The concept of this textbook is one of providing some general introductory text for each chapter, then links that are essentially reading assignments to appropriate articles at Wikipedia. I usually spend most of my time working on those Wikipedia articles to insure that they are useful to the textbook as well as to the wikipedia.  However, there is no hard and fast rule about how much information should and should not go into the textbook.  Eventually, we may want to include most of the information at Wikipedia over here as well, although I do not forsee that happening soon. That is to say, I would not import wikipedia articles into the textbook to make this book &quot;more complete&quot;.  But put as much original writing into each chapter of the textbook as you want, then adjust the reading assignments accordingly. - [[User:Marshman|Marsh]] 02:05, 25 Mar 2004 (UTC)

== Help reviewing books ==

Hi Marshman. I saw you downgraded some of the [[Help:Development stages|development stages]] {{stage short|100%|Jan 12, 2005}} I gave to the chapters of your book. That is quite some brave thing to do, and just in the spirit of a critical review! Of course, as the author you know your work best. Would you help me to review one or another book of your choice in a similar way on the [[Science bookshelf]]? You can use the template as explained in [[Help:Development stages|Development stages]]. There is no hurry, do it when you want to browse some other book. Thanks! --[[User:Andreas Ipp|Andreas Ipp]] 21:51, 12 Jan 2005 (UTC)
:Can do. I'll go look at some of the other &quot;biological sciences&quot; texts.  I got the impression you were either being very generous, or just putting in the &quot;symbols&quot; so that the authors could modify them to what looks more likely a status of each chapter. I do agree that &quot;100%&quot; is not necessarily the same as &quot;done, no more additions anticipated&quot; but really means the user can expect to get something close to full value out of that chapter, even if the author plans to tweek it a lot more. - [[User:Marshman|marsh]] 04:07, 13 Jan 2005 (UTC)


----


[[German:_Lesson_6]]:I'm from Germany and I don't understand &quot;Mutti sagt Hallo.&quot; Say me, please - what do you want to say with &quot;Mutti sagt Hallo.&quot; ?
:Danke for getting back to me. The brother is trying to say &quot;Mother says (to say) hello&quot;. That is, he is visiting from home, and brings greetings from their mom. Can you help clarify or improve that? - [[User:Marshman|marsh]]

== [[Basic Ecology Contents]] ==

Why did you revert my edits without any justification? You are deliberately violating naming policy. Such use of revert function makes me wonder if you really should be a sysop. Taking a look at [http://en.wikibooks.org/w/index.php?title=Special%3ALog&amp;type=&amp;user=Marshman&amp;page= operation log] gives me no clue why you became one. --[[User:Derbeth|Derbeth]] [[User talk:Derbeth|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]] 11:29, 21 January 2006 (UTC)
:Man, where did they find you? I've been here working on Wikibooks for a long long time and I know the rules about policy, the first being that &quot;policy&quot; as you now call your banners is suggestion and therefore cannot be violated. I do not appreciate stupid banners (essentialy a form of vandalism) being placed on the books I am working on and find your attitude more than bit aggressive, violating the cardinal rule at Wikipedia of making personal attacks on other editors. I did expain the revert on the page. - [[User:Marshman|marsh]] 18:38, 22 January 2006 (UTC)
:: Call it a personal attack but it occured that you don't use your sysop right for things other than your books cleanup. I can't see if you revert vandals or not, but your part of log shows no vadalised pages you deleted. In fact, you are not doing any administrative tasks. And calling cleanup templates &quot;vandalism&quot; is nothing more than arrogance from you. --[[User:Derbeth|Derbeth]] [[User talk:Derbeth|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]] 22:17, 22 January 2006 (UTC)
:::I deleted your vandalising of the pages I watch. And they are vandalism because of where you place them (more so because it appears there really is no such naming policy in place). Sorry I do not fit your definition of what I should be doing here, but then I may have missed the vote where you were elected king. I am a contributor to textbooks, and I will not be subjected to attacks by you. I have plenty of other things to do with my time. Please do not write on my user page again. - [[User:Marshman|marsh]] 00:52, 24 January 2006 (UTC)  

==Releasing a first PDF edition of Botany? ==

I have recently proposed that some Wikibooks are ready for a first PDF edition. Botany is a likely candidate.  The first edition would contain a prominent link saying &quot;If you wish to edit, correct or contribute to this book please click here&quot;. The idea is to use some of the better and more complete books as an example. What do you think? See:

http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Wikibooks:Staff_lounge#The_management_of_book_publishing_-_a_policy_suggestion

[[User:RobinH|RobinH]] 16:25, 22 January 2006 (UTC)

:Happy to consider it, although not sure the Botany t5ext is really far enough along - [[User:Marshman|marsh]] 18:38, 22 January 2006 (UTC)

== German: Level 3 ==

This needs a total remake, it is not even funny. It is very silly and useless to have '''a whole''' different sub-section, with all the lessons of level 2, and the only thing which is different is a small, little advance page for each lesson. It needs different, and harder lessons. Isn't that the whole reason for a different sub-section page? We need all the complex grammer and difficult words of German in this level, or put the easier parts of complex German grammer and vocabulary of it here, and make a Level 4 and put the more difficult parts of complex German grammer and vocabulary in there. Derbeth even said we had to do something. And it is time. We need to get a plan together. -- [[User:German Men92|German Men92]][[User talk:German Men92|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]] 1:03, 17 Feb 2006 (UTC)
:I'm not real clear on your complaint, but I think you do not like the idea of having a Level 3 in the German textbook.  It was an idea for having a more advanced course that built easily on the Level 2&amp;mdash;that was the plan. Of course, we could as well just mush together each &quot;advanced&quot; page with the corresponding Level 2 page and by that process create a new or separate Level 3 textbook. And of course, when you say &quot;what it needs&quot; you must back up a minute and realize that while some lessons are more or less complete, most others are just a shell of what could be done. So the obvious response to seeing a deficient subsection page (or any page) is to add to it, not complain about it. And I will not address what I think about your statement &quot;Derbeth even said we had to do something&quot;; is Derbeth a contributor to this textbook? - [[User:Marshman|marsh]] 19:01, 24 February 2006 (UTC)
No, but he is an admin here, and that is really why I pushed forward with seperate lessons, because he asked me or a main contributorto fix it. -- [[User:German Men92|German Men92]][[User talk:German Men92|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]] 21:22, 1 Mar 2006 (UTC)
:No problem, really. I just have serious reservations about Derbeth. But YOUR ideas are what is important here, so I won't be side-tracked. I'll check in and see how you develop the (is it now five levels?) lessons the way you are going. - [[User:Marshman|marsh]] 06:06, 2 March 2006 (UTC)  

== Proposal to remove your sysop rights ==

Marshman

I'm dropping you this note as I note another user has made a request on [[WB:RFA]] for your account to lose sysop rights. If you would like to comment on the matter, please do so there. Kind regards, [[User:Jguk|Jguk]] 17:49, 17 February 2006 (UTC)

* Actually, a vote is under way to remove the sysop rights from 10 admins.  I think [[User:Jguk|Jguk]] left you a note because you are the only active editor subject to such a vote, and perhaps because he voted to oppose removing your sysop rights.  I have been leaving notes with all 10 admins concerning the vote.  Even though [[User:Jguk|Jguk]] has already informed you of the vote, it seemed strange for me to leave you out.  Here is the note I have been leaving:

:: A vote is being held to remove your sysop privileges.  The basis for this vote is lack of use of these privileges.  You may want to participate at [[Wikibooks:Requests_for_adminship#Marshman_.28_talk_.7C_email_.7C_contribs_.29]].  See also the discussion at [[Wikibooks:Staff_lounge#Removing_Sysop_Status]]. --[[User:JMRyan|JMRyan]] 23:04, 17 February 2006 (UTC)

Thanks for at least showing that much respect - [[User:Marshman|marsh]]

:Marshman, I am definitely against your sys-op rights being taken away. Where is the appropriate place to make that known publicly? Thank you, --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]] 20:27, 18 March 2006 (UTC)

== [[:Image:Fernsehturm Stuttgart.jpg]] ==

I have been using a script [[User:Kernigh/monobook.js]] (copied from [[Commons:MediaWiki:Extra-tabs.js]]) to examine image uploads. Thus I noticed that you have many untagged images. Most of them indicate the author credit and copyright license very clearly, and at some point someone will tag them {{tl|GFDL}}.

However, [[:Image:Fernsehturm Stuttgart.jpg]] (which you uploaded two years ago at 9 March 2004) claims to be from the &quot;German Wikipedia&quot; but gives no license information. I checked the same filename in de.wikipedia and commons.wikimedia and found nothing. Do you know the license information? If so you could add a [[WB:ICT|copyright tag]]. Otherwise it might be better to delete the image; it is on the [[German Grammar]] page and we could probably replace it with something else. --[[User:Kernigh|Kernigh]] 06:40, 17 April 2006 (UTC)

==Policy review==

Policy is not the most exciting subject at Wikibooks but we do have some major unresolved issues.

The most important issue, in my opinion, is [http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Wikibooks:Dispute_resolution Dispute resolution] which starts by declaring that:

'''&quot;Currently there is no official organized process to resolve disputes between users&quot;'''

The suggested remedy for this is: [[Wikibooks:Ad hoc administration committee]] which puts into place the absolute minimum in terms of an enforcement apparatus.

The second most important is [[Wikibooks:No personal attacks]] where a vote has recommended the policy be enforced but it still languishes as &quot;proposed&quot;.

The third policy that is needed and which will prevent edit disputes from getting out of hand is [[Wikibooks:Editing disputes policy]].

Other policies that need consideration are at: [http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Wikibooks:Policies_and_guidelines Policies and guidelines].

Please spare a minute or two to peruse these issues and add a comment and/or a vote. [[User:RobinH|RobinH]] 12:26, 28 April 2006 (UTC)

== Template:Classis ==

*Is {{tl|Classis}} a holding spot/building block for another template?  I was going to nominate it for deletion, but I wanted to check with you first as the creator.&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; [[User:MrDolomite|MrDolomite]] | [[User talk:MrDolomite|Talk]] 01:02, 29 July 2006 (UTC)

== Your De-Adminship ==

Hello. I would like to inform you that you will have your sysop rights removed here on 20 Apr 2007 due to inactivity. If you would like to discuss the matter, please see [[WB:RFA]]. You can re-apply for adminship at a later date if you wish. Thanks. -[[User:Withinfocus|&lt;font color=&quot;#000000&quot;&gt;'''within'''&lt;/font&gt;]][[User talk:Withinfocus|&lt;font color=&quot;#7A7A7A&quot;&gt;'''focus'''&lt;/font&gt;]] 13:23, 20 March 2007 (UTC)

I would like to add here that I am not completely convinced that there is a need to deadmin inactive users.  Some very convincing arguments have been made in the past to keep admins around, and very weak reasons (admittedly I made the first suggestions) to remove admin status.  Others like Karl Wick (mentioned above) certainly have your support.

Regardless, don't take this as an insult in any way, as you are certainly welcome to come back and continue editing Wikibooks at any time.  And if you ever want to have the admin tools back (I'm  fatalistic as I think the current mood with several active Wikibookians is to strip your admin rights), count on me to be one of your hardcore supporters.  You have done nothing wrong except to deal with life and not let this project become an obsession.  That, IMHO, is an admirable trait.  --[[User:Robert Horning|Rob Horning]] 13:55, 20 March 2007 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>5uecywe5bm5tgjumh5tj3h0arg2thjt</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Wikibooks:Study guides bookshelf</title>
    <ns>4</ns>
    <id>954</id>
    <restrictions>edit=autoconfirmed:move=autoconfirmed</restrictions>
    <revision>
      <id>2279816</id>
      <parentid>2255719</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-03-02T23:25:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{deprecated bookshelf|[[Subject:Standard curricula]]}}
{{bookshelves}}
{{bookshelf|Study guides bookshelf}}
{{stages}}
----

__TOC__

{{Requested books}}

==[[Subject:GCE Advanced Level|A-level]]==

{{bookshelf|A-level bookshelf}}

{{Requested books}}

==[[:Category:Advanced Placement|Advanced Placement]]==

* [[AP Biology]]{{stage|25%|Dec 2008}}
* [[AP Chemistry]]{{stage|75%|Dec 2008}}
* [[AP Computer Science]]{{stage|50%|Dec 2008}}
* [[AP European History]]{{stage|100%|Dec 2008}}

{{Requested books}}

==GCSE==
{{wikipedia|GCSE}}
For 14-16 year old pupils

* [[GCSE Mathematics]]{{stage|00%}}
* [[GCSE Science]]{{stage|00%}}
* [[GCSE Short Course ICT]]{{stage short|00%|}}

{{Requested books}}

==[[Subject:Higher School Certificate|HSC]]==
* [[HSC Biology]] {{stage short|00%|Dec 02, 2007}}
* [[HSC_Extension_1_and_2_Mathematics | Mathematics, Mathematics Extension 1, Mathematics Extension 2]] {{stage short|25%|Dec 02, 2007}}
* Mathematics (General)
* [[HSC_Geography|HSC Geography]] {{stage short|25%|Dec 02, 2007}}
* [[Information_Processing_and_Technology|HSC Information Processing and Technology]] {{stage short|00%|Oct 21, 2007}}
* [[HSC_Physics|HSC Physics]] {{stage short|00%|Dec 02, 2007}}

{{Requested books}}

== Information technology ==

* [[A Plus Certification|A+]] {{stage|50%|April 22, 2006}}
* [[AQA Information and Communication Technology]] {{stage|25%|unknown}}
* [[LPI Linux Certification]]{{stage short|25%|unknown}}
* [[Network plus exam cram]]
* [[Network Plus Certification|Network+]] 
* [[Certification:SCDJWS|SCDJWS]]{{stage short|25%|unknown}}
* [[Weblogs:An Introduction]]{{stage short|00%|01. Aug 2005}}

{{Requested books}}

==[[International Baccalaureate]]==

* [[IB Biology]] {{stage|75%|April 26, 2006}}
* [[IB Chemistry]]
* [[IB Computer Science]]{{stage|25%|April 8, 2008}}
* [[IB Economics]] {{stage|25%|April 26, 2006}}
* [[IB European History]]{{stage|75%|February 18, 2006}}
* [[IB Geography]] {{stage|75%|February 18, 2006}}
* [[IB Music]]{{stage|75%|February 18, 2006}}

{{Requested books}}

==[[Understanding the National Certificate of Educational Achievement|NCEA]]==
NCEA is the national examinations sat by Year 11-13 students in New Zealand.

* [[NCEA Level 1 Science|Level 1 Science]]

{{Requested books}}

== Other ==

* [[AVCE Information and Communication Technology]]
* [[How To Become A Good Student]] {{stage|75%|Jan 22, 2006}}
* [[The Natural Step for Communities Study Circle Guide]]
* [[College Guide]]

{{Requested books}}

== Professional Certifications ==

* [[CCNA Certification]] {{stage|00%|August 2, 2006}}
* [[General Securities Representative Exam]]
* [[Microsoft Certified Professional Developer]]
* [[.NET Development Foundation]] {{stage|50%|December 18, 2007}}
* [[Microsoft Certified IT Professional]]

{{Requested books}}

== US College and Graduate Admissions ==

* [[ACT]] {{stage|50%|August 29, 2005}}
* [[SAT Study Guide]]{{stage|25%|February 18, 2006}}
* [[GRE]] {{stage|75%|February 18, 2006}}
* [[LSAT Prep Guide]] [[Image:50%.svg]]
* [[Past LSAT Explained]] [[Image:50%.svg]]

== VCE (Victorian Certificate of Education) ==
{{Wikipedia|Victorian Certificate of Education}}

* [[VCE Chemistry]]

==External Sources==
* [[Wikisource:On Marquez's One Hundred Years of Solitude]]


[[Category:Wikibooks bookshelves|{{PAGENAME}}]]

[[it:Ripiano Guide allo studio]]</text>
      <sha1>8jtgd2hyvf4osjk1pkip0o6nkyp5a40</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Discrete Mathematics/Functions and relations</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>958</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2359588</id>
      <parentid>2101540</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-05T09:07:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BCW</username>
        <id>267038</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Weird Approvals of Property Changes */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Lots of material there, maybe enough for several &quot;modules&quot;. Would it make sense to divide it up ? -- [[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

I'd be against the idea, in my opinion. If someone's trying to study the material, it'd be a great deal more difficult jumping back and forth through linking to other modules. Anyway, this module's almost done, just going to cover Hasse diagrams and some questions/answers and I'm done with this bit, I think. [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 10:20, 5 Sep 2003 (UTC)

== Confusion about Cartesian product definition of Function ==

I was reading the '''Other function notation''' section of this module and was a bit confused by the wording of the last sentence:

''So using set notation, a function can be expressed as the Cartesian product of its domain and range.''

Shouldn't that read ''a function can be expressed **as a subset of** the Cartesian product of its domain and range.''? 
Otherwise, the function would be defined as F={(1,1),(1,4),(1,9),(2,1),(2,4),(2,9),(3,1),(3,4),(3,9)}.

Or perhaps my understanding of a Cartesian product is incorrect. Just wanted some clarification. Thank you.
:This confuses me too. [[User:Tim J Tylor|Tim J Tylor]] ([[User talk:Tim J Tylor|talk]]) 11:06, 23 April 2008 (UTC)


I think there is a short coming in the discussions of functions nothing has been mentioned one to one function or generally the types of functions

== OR or XOR in trichotomy ==

I just added an example in the Trichotomy section but I'd like to know if the or we have is a strict OR (XOR) or not. If it is then my example is incorrect (since sometimes both aRb and bRa hold).

Thanks for your help :)

how can we find the union,intersection,complement, difference of two sets named R &amp; S?

== New Introduction and other fixes ==

Hi, I've taken the liberty to add an introduction and some other (less major) fixes.  I'd like to know what everyone thinks. --[[User:BCW|Brian C. Wells]] ([[User talk:BCW|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/BCW|contribs]]) 05:37, 22 May 2011 (UTC)

== Weird Approvals of Property Changes ==

I just undid a change that removed &quot;Transitive&quot; as one of the properties of equality.  Equality ''is'' transitive: a = b and b = c implies a = c.  In fact, the transitive property is one of the three necessary properties of an equivalence relation, of which equality is the classic example.

I have also seen other examples changed to false answers, but what bothers me more than these erroneous edits by random IPs is that they are being ''approved'' by Wikibookians with the rights to do so.  I'm fairly new here, so I don't know what Wikibookians' common problems are, but what's going on here?  Are they just too busy to make a detailed review?  Does nobody care what's right and wrong here?  Or is there something else I'm missing?  Thanks in advance.  --[[User:BCW|Brian C. Wells]] ([[User talk:BCW|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/BCW|contribs]]) 09:07, 5 June 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>6pzjav9rociarp01q1tnrwst7dttuhj</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Latin</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>959</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2708937</id>
      <parentid>2680501</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-01T09:29:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>50.181.112.130</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */ changed URL to point directly to Gutenberg</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Featured book}}
{{Wikipedia}}
{{Wiktionary|Index:Latin}}
{{Print version|Latin/Print Version}}
{{PDF version|Latin}}

This is an elementary Latin course accompanied with a detailed grammar based upon Kennedy's Public School Latin Grammar designed to introduce one to the world of [[w:classical languages|classical languages]].  A basic understanding of [[w:grammar|grammatical terminology]] would be helpful; however, it is not required.  Basic definitions of terms will be explained in Lessons 1 and 2, and later elaborated as needed.

For detailed explanations and examples of English grammatical terms, please consult the [[English Grammar]] textbook.  However, Latin grammar is quite different from English, and thus it requires different grammatical terms to explain the concepts.  These will be taught as needed.

==Note==
Parts of this book may have been edited by people who do not speak English as their first language. All Wikibooks are written in the particular English dialect of the writer, which may not be standard usage. If you see something particularly unclear, please feel free to correct it. But ''please'' alter this article in a constructive manner.

This book will attempt to teach the reader Latin from the ground up. Please consult the Appendix or [http://www.thefreedictionary.com Latin-aware Dictionary] if you are confused about the presentation of Latin grammatical elements compared to English concepts.

Please read the Introduction carefully, as it introduces the concept of a stem.
As is typical in many other languages, the infinitive stem (present tense, active voice) is used for conjugating verbs.
[The introduction of additional information in parentheses is done simply to avoid confusing a student who has already had exposure to Latin.]

If something doesn't make sense to you, note your grade level in the summary, and delete what you don't understand, e.g., &quot;grade 12 [grade]  American [system] revert?&quot; The &quot;revert&quot; keyword allows your editors to know that you are not a skilled editor but are just trying to learn, and are confused. Your changes are not permanent.

Edit this book responsibly:
* As this is a textbook, readers will want denotational indication of macrons. If you do not know how to do this in HTML, please refer to [[wikipedia:Macron|Wikipedia's article]] on the topic. 

*Always use the genitive in presentation, or present the nominative and the genitive side by side, clearly indicating which one is which (&quot;nom.&quot; for nominative and &quot;gen.&quot; for genitive). Different pages may use their own layout rules, but they should be left-justified and clear to the student.

*Check with other commercial textbooks and study guides to see if what you are doing is factually accurate and pedagogically sound. Wikibooks trusts you to make that judgment on your own, but this is a book - not an article. A person who is either bold or rash might make an error or mistake in layout or explanation that will take a long time to find and correct.

==A Progressive Latin Grammar and Exercises ==

Introduction to the origins and structure of Latin:
# [[/How to study a language on the Internet and in your head/]]
# [[/Special consideration: How to use a Wikibook when progress may mean inaccuracy/]]
#[[/Lesson 1|Grammatical Introduction to Latin]] ''The origin and structure of Latin'' 
#[[/Lesson 2|Basic Grammar]] ''Grammatical introduction.''

----

Chapter 1: Basic Sentences
#[[/Lesson 1-Nominative|The Nominative Case]] '' Create basic Latin sentences, with adjectives and the verb &quot;to be&quot;''
#[[/Lesson 2-Adjectives|Adjectives]] '' A short introduction to adjectives ''
#[[/Lesson 3-Present Verbs|Present indicative active construct]] ''An introduction to verbs, and the present tense of regular verbs.''  
#[[/Lesson 4-Adverbs and Prepositions|Adverbs &amp; Prepositions]] ''More on adjectives, and an overview of adverbs and prepositions.''
#[[/Lesson 5-Accusative|The Accusative Case]] '' Learn to create sentences with transitive verbs.'' 
#[[/Lesson 6-Pronouns|Pronouns]] ''Summary of Pronouns''
#[[/Chapter 1 Verse|Chapter 1 Verse]]

----

Chapter 2: Complex Sentences
#[[/Lesson 1-Imperfect|The Imperfect Tense]] ''The imperfect tense, working in the past.''
#[[/Lesson 2-Genitive and Dative|The Genitive and Dative Cases]] '' Indicate indirect objects and possession.''
#[[/Lesson 3-Future|The Future Tense]] ''Verbs in the Future''
#[[/Lesson 4-Ablative|The Ablative and Vocative Case]] '' Indicate an ablative construct / directly address someone''
#[[/Lesson 5-Declensions|The 3rd, 4th and 5th declensions]] ''All remaining categories of nouns''
#[[/Lesson 6-Irregular Verbs|Irregular Verbs &amp; Revision]] ''Review of all five declensions and the conjugation of present imperfect indicative active verbs.''
#[[/Lesson 7-Translation|Translation Exercise]] ''Translate a passage.''
#[[/Lesson 8-Imperfect and Future|Imperfect and Future indicative active constructs]] 
#[[/Chapter 2 Verse|Chapter 2 Verse]]

----

Chapter 3: Advanced Sentences
#[[/Lesson 1-Imperative|Imperatives]] ''Ordering or Telling People What to Do.''
#[[/Lesson 2-Active v Passive|Active v. Passive Verbs]] 
#[[/Lesson 3-Passive|Indicative Passive Verbs]] '' Present, imperfect, and future passives.''
#[[/Lesson 4-Principal Parts|Principal Parts]] ''Principal verb parts and verb conjugation.''
#[[Latin/Lesson 5-Perfect Indicative|The Perfect Indicative Tense]] ''The uses and formation of the perfect indicative tense.''
#[[Latin/Lesson 6-The Perfect Passive|The Perfect Indicative Passive Verbs]] '' Use the perfect with the passives.'' 
#[[/Lesson 7-Future and Past Perfect|Future and Past Perfect Indicative Tenses]] 
#[[/Lesson 8-Ablative Absolute and Accusative Infinitive|Ablative Absolute and Accusative Infinitive Constructions]]
#[[/Chapter 3 Verse|Chapter 3 Verse]]
----

Chapter 4: The Subjunctive Mood and Complex Sentences
#[[/Lesson 1-Subjunctive|The Subjunctive Mood]] '' Subjunctive vs. Indicative moods, conjugate the Subjunctive present.''
#[[/Lesson  2-Subjunctive Use |The Uses of the Subjunctive]]
#[[/Lesson 3-Subjunctive Imperfect|The Subjunctive Imperfect]] '' Conjugation and uses of the imperfect subjunctive.''
#[[/Lesson 4-The Subjunctive Passive|The Subjunctive Passive Verbs]] '' Conjugate the present and imperfect subjunctives.''
#[[/Lesson 5-The Subjunctive Perfect|The Subjunctive Perfects]] ''The perfect endings for the Subjunctive.''
#[[/Lesson 6-The Subjunctive Perfect Passive|The Subjunctive Perfect Passive Verbs]] '' Perfect auxiliary verbs for the subjunctive passives.''
#[[/Lesson 7-The Gerund and Participles|The Gerund and Participles]] ''Verbal Nouns.''
#[[/Lesson 8-Conditional Clauses|Conditional Clauses]] ''Conditional sentences in the indicative and subjunctive mood''
#[[/Lesson 9-Revision|Revision]] ''Review of all five declensions and the conjugation of the active subjunctive verbs.''
#[[/Lesson 10-Idioms|Idioms]] ''An overview of idiomatic phrases used in Latin.''
#[[/Lesson 11-Translation|Translation]] ''Translate a passage from the Vulgate Bible.'' [[Image:Gaius_Julius_Caesar_(100-44_BC).JPG|thumb|100px|right|Bust of Julius Caesar]]
#[[/Chapter 4 Verse|Chapter 4 Verse]]
#[[/Chapter 5 Verse|Verse from the Gospels]]

----

Chapter 5: Review
#[[/Lesson 1|Revision]] ''Review of all five noun and adjective declensions.''
#[[/Lesson 2|Revision]] ''Revise work on all verb conjugations and learned forms.''
#[[/Lesson_3-Translation|Translation]] ''Translate a passage from Catullus.''
#[[/Lesson 5-Accusative|Exercises]] ''Review of subjunctive forms.'' 
#[[/Lesson 2-Genitive and Dative|Exercises]] ''Review of passive forms.'' 
#[[/Lesson 4-Ablative|Translation]]
#[[/Lesson 6-Pronouns|Revision]] '' Ideas and memory tools for language patterns in conjugation and declining.''
#[[/Chapter 5 Verse|Chapter 5 Verse]]
#[[Latin/Lesson 9-Poem|Poem about Latin]]

==Spoken Latin==
This is a test chapter to teach those who wish to learn Latin which they can use in their daily lives.
# [[/Spoken|Spoken Latin Wikibook]]

== Appendices ==
:[[/Verb Synopsis|Verb Synopsis]]
:[[/Index II|List of Declensions]]
:[[/Phonology|Phonology of Latin]] ''(pronunciation)''
:[[/Accents and Scansion|Accents and Scansion]]
:[[/Morphology|Morphology of Latin]]
:[[/Medieval Latin|Ecclessiastical &amp; Medieval Latin]]
:[[/Grammar|Latin Grammatical Definitions]]  
:[[/Dictionary|Latin Dictionary]]
:[[/Appendix G|Latin Mottos and Phrases]] ''Used today.''
:[[/Appendix F|Latin Abbreviations]] ''Used today.''
:[[/Common phrases/]]
:[[/Appendix H|Latin Resources]]
:[[/Texts|Library of Graded Latin Texts for Translation]]  
:[[World History/The Roman Empire|Roman History]]
:[[/Roman Culture|Roman Culture]]
:[[/Spoken Latin|Spoken Latin]]
:[[/Words and their Flexion/]]
:[[/Prefixes and Suffixes/]]
:Advanced: [[/Stylistic Features of Latin Verse and Prose/]]

== About the Book ==
#[[/Authors|Authors]] 

Please leave ideas for additional chapters on the [[Talk:Latin|talk]] page.

==  External links  ==
*A complete textbook for spoken Classical Latin, G.J. Adler's &quot;A Practical Grammar of the Latin Language for Speaking and Writing Latin&quot; can be found on Google Books: http://www.google.co.uk/books?id=GJgAAAAAYAAJ
** This textbook can be heard read out aloud here: http://edu-archive.org/protect.php?url=http://latinum.mypodcast.com. This podcast has received over 3 million episode downloads.
*Another free textbook  is [http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/18251 ''Latin for Beginners''] by B. L. D'Ooge. There is an answer key available from [http://edu-archive.org/protect.php?url=http://www.textkit.com/learn/ID/158/author_id/13/ Textkit]. Also available in audio on Latinum, along with Adler.
*If you are looking to learn '''Biblical Latin''', try the course at http://www.learnlangs.com/biblelatin , which allows you to read the Vulgate Bible in Latin right from lesson 1.
*If you are more interested in Romans and history, an extensive free course in '''Classical Latin''' is available from http://edu-archive.org/protect.php?url=http://www.learnlangs.com/latin .
*More free language-learning materials for Latin are available at Textkit's website at   http://edu-archive.org/protect.php?url=http://www.textkit.com
*A large set of lessons are available at http://edu-archive.org/protect.php?url=http://www.du.edu/~etuttle/classics/latin/learnlat.htm

{{Subjects|Latin language}}
{{alphabetical|L}}
{{status|100%}}

[[de:Latein]]
[[es:Latín]]
[[eo:Klasika Latina]]
[[fr:Latin]]
[[hr:Latinski jezik]]
[[it:Latino]]
[[he:לטינית]]
[[ka:ლათინური ენა]]
[[nl:Latijn]]
[[ja:ラテン語]]
[[no:Latin]]
[[pl:Łacina/Okładka]]
[[ru:Латинский язык]]
[[fi:Latinan kieli]]
[[uk:Латинська мова]]
[[zh:拉丁语]]</text>
      <sha1>eqt12x8jt2nl5ph8vd741tgvnawofmq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Latin/Lesson 1</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>960</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2710402</id>
      <parentid>2579070</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-05T21:48:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>186.64.176.118</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Other */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Latin}}
----
=What is Latin?=
&lt;small&gt;
''Parts of this introduction were taken from [[Wikipedia:en:Latin|The Latin Language]] on the [[en:Main Page|Wikipedia]].''
&lt;/small&gt;

Latin was the language originally spoken in the region around the city of Rome called Latium. It gained great importance as the formal language of the Roman Empire. 

All Romance languages descend from a Latin parent, and many words in [[English]] and other languages today are based on Latin roots. Moreover, Latin was a ''lingua franca'', the learned language for scientific and political affairs in Europe, for more than one and a half thousand years, being eventually replaced by [[French]] in the 18th century and English by the middle of the 20th. Latin remains the formal language of the Roman Catholic Church to this day, and as such is the official national language of the Vatican. 

Romance languages are not derived from Classical Latin, the language spoken by Caesar and Cicero, but rather from Vulgar Latin, the language spoken by the common people, or '' vulgus, '' of Rome. Classical Latin and Vulgar Latin (Romance) differ (for example) in that Romance had distinctive stress whereas Classical had distinctive length of vowels. In [[Italian]] and Sardo logudorese, there is distinctive length of consonants and stress, in [[Spanish]] only distinctive stress, and in French even stress is no longer distinctive. 

Another major distinction between Classical and Romance is that modern Romance languages, excluding [[Romanian]], have lost their case endings (suffixes at the end of the word used in place of prepositions) in most words (some pronouns being exceptions). Romanian is still equipped with several cases (though some, notably the ablative, are no longer represented).

It is also important to note that Latin is, for the most part, an inflected language — meaning that the endings change to show how the word is being used in the sentence.

=Introduction to the Latin Language=

== Simple and Compound Words ==

In Latin, words are either:
* ''' simple ''' (words that consist of only one part). For example:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width: 300px&quot;
|-
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | &lt;font face=&quot;Arial&quot; size=&quot;4&quot;&gt;Latin&lt;/font&gt;
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | &lt;font face=&quot;Arial&quot; size=&quot;4&quot;&gt;English&lt;/font&gt;
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''eo'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''I go'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''fero'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''I carry'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''do'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''I give'''
|}
* ''' compound ''' (words that consist of more than one part, for example, a root word combined with a prefix). For example:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width: 300px&quot;
|-
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | &lt;font face=&quot;Arial&quot; size=&quot;4&quot;&gt;Latin&lt;/font&gt;
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | &lt;font face=&quot;Arial&quot; size=&quot;4&quot;&gt;English&lt;/font&gt;
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''abeo'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''I go away'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''transfero'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''I carry across'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''reddo'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''I give back'''
|}

==Word Parts==

Inflected words (i.e., words having ending- or spelling-changes according to their grammatical functions in the sentence) have a '''stem''' and a '''root.''' 

&lt;B&gt;The Stem&lt;/B&gt;

The stem is the part of the word to which various suffixes are added. The final suffix determines either the role of the word in the sentence (for example, when a Roman slave wished to address his ''dominus'' (master), he used the vocative form ''domine'' -- equivalent to &quot;O master&quot; in English) or the person involved in the action (for example, &quot;I dominate&quot; may be expressed as &quot;domin-or&quot;, and &quot;they dominate&quot; as &quot;domin-antur&quot;). In these cases, ''domin-'' is the stem and ''-us'', ''-e'', ''-or'' and ''-antur'' are suffixes. The addition of such suffixes is called ''inflection''. This is discussed further in the [[#Summary|Summary]].

&lt;B&gt;The Root&lt;/B&gt;

The root is the part of the word that carries the essential meaning. For example the stem of ''agito'' (I drive onward) is ''agit-'', whose root is ''ag'' (do, drive), which is in common to words of similar meaning: ''ago'' (I do, drive), ''agmen'' (that which is driven, such as a flock), etc. Notice the essential difference between a root and a stem. To the root &quot;ag&quot; has been added a suffix &quot;(i)to-&quot; which denotes frequency of action (so &quot;agit-&quot; means to do or drive more than once, hence &quot;agit-o&quot;, I agitate, I keep (something) moving, I urge, I impel).

In contrast, English uses word order more than inflection to determine the function of a word within a sentence. English also uses words like pronouns (I, she, etc.) and prepositions (to, at, etc.) where Latin generally prefers inflexions. Thus &quot;dom-i&quot; (noun -- &quot;at home&quot;), &quot;ag-unt&quot; (verb -- &quot;they do/drive&quot;).

&lt;B&gt;Primitives&lt;/B&gt;

Primitives occur when both the stem and the root are the same. For example, in the word ''agere'' (to do, drive) both the stem and the root are the same: &quot;ag-&quot;.

&lt;B&gt;Derivatives&lt;/B&gt;

Derivatives occur when the root or stem is modified. For example, the stem ''flamm-'' from the noun ''flamma'' has the root &quot;flag&quot; (&quot;blaze&quot;), &quot;nosco&quot; (I know) from the verb &quot;noscere&quot; has the root &quot;gno-&quot; (&quot;know&quot;).

&lt;B&gt;Suffixes&lt;/B&gt;

Latin attaches suffixes (&quot;endings&quot;) to stems to turn them into words (most stems and roots cannot be used in sentences without an ending). This inflection is essential to forming Latin sentences. The various suffixes and their translations will be learned in the later lessons.

=Types of Words used in Latin=

==Nouns==

A noun (Latin: ''nomen'') is &quot;something perceived or conceived by the mind.&quot;

There are two kinds of nouns: Substantives and Pronouns. 

1. &lt;B&gt;Substantive&lt;/B&gt; (''nomen substantivum'') is a name simply denoting something perceived or conceived: ''psittacus'' - the parrot, ''nix'' - the snow, ''virtus'' - virtue.

2. &lt;B&gt;Pronoun&lt;/B&gt; (''pronomen'') is a word used in place of a ''substantivum'', usually when the ''substantivum'' is already known: ''ea'' - she, ''ille'' - that man

Nouns have changing endings on the stem (known as declension) and three incidents: number, gender and case. Number concerns whether the thing referred to is singular or plural (and the ending shows this); gender classifies a substantive as masculine, feminine or neuter (this determines how the endings of adjectives and pronouns behave) and case (where the ending must show how the noun fits in to the sentence). Adjectives and Pronouns must agree in all incidents when they refer to a substantive.

==Verbs==

Verbs (''verba'') express an action or a state of being, e.g., ''ago'' (I do), ''dixit'' (he said), ''venis'' (you come). &quot;Conjugation&quot; is the term for adding inflections to verb stems to indicate person (first, second or third), number (singular or plural), tense (present, future, imperfect, perfect, pluperfect or future perfect), voice (active or passive), and mood (indicative, subjunctive or imperative).

A verb can be either ''finite'' or ''infinite'':

1. &lt;B&gt;Finite&lt;/B&gt; verbs (''verba finita'') are inflected and have a subject, e.g., I run, you run, he runs, they drive, the computer is turned on.

2. The &lt;B&gt;infinite&lt;/B&gt; verbs (''verba infinita'') are not inflected and have no subject, e.g. to run, to drive, to turn on, to have drawn. ''Participles'', which are inflected as substantives rather than as verbs, may also be considered infinite, e.g., the ''running'' boy.

==Modifiers==

1. &lt;B&gt;Adjectives&lt;/B&gt; (''adiectiva'') are used to describe nouns. They indicate a quality perceived or conceived as inherent in, or attributed to, something denoted. E.g., ''vir &lt;U&gt;magnus&lt;U&gt;'' (the &lt;U&gt;great&lt;U&gt; man), ''puella &lt;U&gt;pulchra&lt;U&gt;'' (the &lt;U&gt;fair&lt;U&gt; girl)

2. &lt;B&gt;Adverbs&lt;B&gt; (''adverbia'') are similar to adjectives, except that they are used to qualify verbs, adjectives or other adverbs, rather than nouns. In practice, they restrict the meaning of the verb or adjective by specifying how or how much. E.g., ''curro &lt;U&gt;celeriter&lt;/U&gt;'' (I run &lt;U&gt;quickly&lt;/U&gt;), ''pugnat &lt;U&gt;fortiter&lt;U&gt;'' (he fights &lt;U&gt;bravely&lt;/U&gt;), &quot;&lt;U&gt;vere&lt;/U&gt; jucundus est&quot; (he's &lt;U&gt;really&lt;/U&gt; nice&quot;), &quot;&lt;U&gt;incredibile&lt;/U&gt; callida est&quot; (she's &lt;U&gt;incredibly&lt;/U&gt; clever).

==Other==

Particles are uninflected words that provide extra meaning.

1. &lt;B&gt;Prepositions&lt;/B&gt; (''praepositiones'') are little words which tell you how one word is behaving in relation to another word (&quot;the &lt;U&gt;duck&lt;/U&gt; was &lt;B&gt;near&lt;/B&gt; the &lt;B&gt;pond&lt;/B&gt;&quot;, &quot;&lt;U&gt;she&lt;/U&gt; went &lt;B&gt;towards&lt;/B&gt; the &lt;B&gt;wood&lt;/B&gt;&quot;). In Latin, the noun that follows a preposition takes a particular ending (called a &quot;case&quot;), depending on the nature of the relationship, or on the nature of the preposition itself. E.g., ''ad'' (by), ''in'' (in), ''sub'' (under). What all this means is that a preposition is a sort of adverb, telling you how something is done. For example, &quot;you go&quot; is a simple statement, but &quot;you go in&quot; suggests that you don't just &quot;go&quot;, you go so as to enter something, and so you need a noun for the &quot;something&quot;. In English, we might say &quot;you go &lt;B&gt;into&lt;/B&gt; the house&quot;. In Latin, this would be: &quot;&lt;B&gt;in&lt;/B&gt; domum inis&quot;. Notice the form &quot;in domum&quot;, which means &quot;into&quot; the house -- you're going into it, you're not yet exactly inside it (the ending -um of &quot;domum&quot; is called &quot;accusative&quot;). When you are inside the house, what you do is &quot;in&quot; the house, which is &quot;in domo&quot; (the ending -o of &quot;domo&quot; is called &quot;ablative&quot;).

2. &lt;B&gt;Conjunctions&lt;/B&gt; (''coniunctiones'') join together clauses and sentences. E.g., ''et'' (and), ''atque'' (as well as), ''sed'' (but).

3. &lt;B&gt;Interjections&lt;/B&gt; (''interiectiones'') are exclamations used to express feeling or to gain attention. E.g., ''o!'' (oh!) ''eheu!'' (alas!) ''ecce!'' (behold!)

==Articles==
Latin has '''NO articles''' (words for 'the' and 'a').  When translating Latin into English, insert a 'the' or 'a' when appropriate.

=Summary=


{| BORDER
|-
| COLSPAN=&quot;2&quot; | &lt;center&gt;&lt;big&gt;&lt;big&gt;'''Parts of Speech'''&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
|-
| '''Inflected''' || '''Uninflected'''
|-
| ''Substantives:'' things perceived or conceived
| ''Adverbs:'' describe adjectives, verbs, and other adverbs
|-
| ''Adjectives:'' indicate a quality perceived or conceived as inherent of something in the substantive
| ''Prepositions:'' help nouns define their relations to other nouns
|-
| ''Pronouns:'' nouns used in place of substantives and adjectives
| ''Conjunctions:'' Join clauses and sentences
|-
| ''Verbs:'' mark the beginning of an independent [[wikipedia:clause|clause]]. The verb in Latin is inflected so that we know the subject (&quot;I learn&quot;), and its tense (to what general or specific time the clause relates to). We call the inflection of a verb '''conjugation'''
| ''Interjection:'' exclamation
|}
&lt;TR&gt;&lt;TD&gt;

=Exercises=

1. What is the shared root in the following English words? &lt;br/&gt;
* actor, reaction, radioactive
* transfer, fertile, interference
2. In the following English words, what is the stem and what is the ending? &lt;br/&gt;
* knights
* riding
* horses
* jumped
3. What parts of speech are each of the English words in (2), as well as the following:
* with
* and
* because
* hooray
* silently
* never
4. Answer the following questions about the Latin language:
* In what area of Italy was Latin originally spoken?
* Name the two varieties of Latin that existed in antiquity.
* What major organization still uses Latin today?
[[Category:Latin]]</text>
      <sha1>o0stlhz1xunnwf1j90wbl4int3mke6t</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Latin/Lesson 2</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>961</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2631040</id>
      <parentid>2611574</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-04-16T23:03:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Avjewe</username>
        <id>1526328</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Exercises */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Latin}}
----
==Pronunciation==
Latin pronunciation has varied somewhat over the course of its long history, and there are some differences between Classical Latin, as spoken in the Roman Republic and Roman Empire, and Medieval or Ecclesiastical Latin, as spoken in the Middle ages and in the Catholic Church. This text focuses on the classical pronunciation.

{|
|a || /a/, about, between ah and uh, ad is pronounced almost like &quot;odd&quot;
|-
|e || /ɛ/, get or bed
|-
|i || /ɪ/, hit, pin, in
|-
|i || (Before vowel and not accented) /j/, Y as in yes
|-
|j || Sometimes used in place of the letter I when making a /j/ sound, as above
|-
|o || /ɔ/, on, cot
|-
|u || /ʊ/, put, foot
|-
|ā || /aː/, father
|-
|ē || sounds like saying the letter &quot;A&quot;, /eː/, hay
|-
|ī || sounds like saying the letter &quot;E&quot;, /iː/, eat
|-
|ō || sounds like saying the letter &quot;O&quot;, /oː/, clover
|-
|ae || (Diphthong) sounds like saying the letter &quot;I&quot;, /aɪ/, aisle
|-
|au || (Diphthong) /aʊ/, brown, how
|-
|oe || (Diphthong) /ɔɪ/, oil, boy
|-
|ou || (Diphthong) oo
|-
|ui || (Diphthong) we
|-
|bs || (At the end of word) the B sounds a P
|-
|bt || (At the end of a word) the B sounds a P
|-
|ch || /kʰ/, pronounced separately as in archaic, not like in church
|-
|gn || /ŋn/ han'''gn'''ail, sin'''g n'''ow
|-
|ph || u'''p h'''ill, never sounds an F in philosophy
|-
|th || Pronounced separately as in po'''t h'''ole, never like this or theater
|-
|c || /k/, always hard as in cat
|-
|g || /g/, always hard as in get, never soft like adage
|-
|r || Rolled like in the Spanish and Italian languages
|-
|s || Always voiceless as in see, never voiced as in ease
|-
|v || /w/, equivalent to an English W, never sounding an English V (sounds U as a consonant), some texts will write the &quot;v&quot; as a &quot;u&quot; when it serves as a vowel
|-
|x || Equivalent to an English Ks as in box, never like exert
|-
|(y) || Rarely exists in Latin except in words borrowed from Greek
|-
|(z) || Rarely exists in Latin except in words borrowed from Greek
|-
|}

Note that Latin, as written by the Romans, did not include macrons (the longmarks over long vowels) or the letters J and U. Macrons are used today as pronunciation guides and do not necessarily need to be written. The sound value of the letter U was filled by the letter V, which sounded either /w/ or /ʊ/ depending on context. Modern texts often preserve the V when it is making a /w/ sound and change it to a U when making a /ʊ/ sound. The letter J is sometimes used in modern times (this Wikibook not included) when the letter I is being used in diphthongs.

==Declension Tables==
The following tables will be both referenced and explained in all of the following sections, and hence are placed here.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;
|+Singular Nouns
!Declension (Gender)
!1st (F) !! 2nd (M/N) !!3rd (M/F/N) !! 4th (M/N) !! 5th (F)
|-
|'''Nominative'''&lt;br/&gt;Subject || puell'''a''' || serv'''us''' || rēx || grad'''us''' || r'''ēs'''
|-
|'''Genitive'''&lt;br/&gt;Possessive || puell'''ae''' || serv'''ī''' || rēg'''is''' || grad'''ūs''' || r'''ēī'''
|-
|'''Dative'''&lt;br/&gt;Indirect Object || puell'''ae''' || serv'''ō''' || rēg'''ī''' || grad'''uī''' || r'''ēī'''
|-
|'''Accusative'''&lt;br/&gt;Object || puell'''am''' || serv'''um''' || rēg'''em''' || grad'''um''' || r'''ēm'''
|-
|'''Ablative'''&lt;br/&gt;Modifies or Limits Verb|| puell'''ā''' || serv'''ō''' || rēg'''e''' || grad'''ū''' || r'''ē'''
|-
|'''Vocative'''&lt;br /&gt;Direct Address || puell'''a''' || serv'''e''' || rēx || grad'''us''' || r'''ēs'''
|}

Note that nouns in the 3rd declension nominative can have any ending, hence why none is given in bold.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;
|+Plural Nouns
!Declension (Gender) !! 1st (F) !! 2nd (M/N) !! 3rd (M/F/N) !! 4th (M/N) !! 5th (F)
|-
|'''Nominative''' || puell'''ae''' || serv'''ī''' || rēg'''ēs''' || corn'''ūs''' || r'''ēs'''
|}

==Grammar Part 1: Nouns and Their Role in Sentences==
[[w:Noun|Noun]]s in Latin are [[w:Inflected language|inflected]], which means that endings (also known as [[w:suffix|suffix]]es or ''suffices'') are appended to the end of the [[w:stem|stem]] to denote these things:
#Number (whether the noun is singular or plural)
#[[w:Declension|Case]] of the noun (role of the noun in the sentence)
#[[w:Grammatical gender|Gender]] (the gender of the word - one of masculine, feminine, or neuter)

Most nouns in English can be modified to indicate number (cat versus cats), and many pronouns can be modified to indicate case (who versus whose) or gender (he versus she, his versus hers). Case is especially important in Latin as meaning cannot be determined by word order as it can be in English, but purely by word endings, or &quot;inflection&quot;. Indeed, the words in a Latin sentence can appear in almost any order with little change in meaning. Two sentences with the word orders &quot;Sam ate the orange&quot; and &quot;The orange ate Sam&quot; could potentially mean the same thing in Latin, though the spellings of &quot;orange&quot; and &quot;Sam&quot; would have to change slightly to denote which was the subject (the one eating) and which was the object (the one being eaten).

It is important to note here that although the genders of many words make sense (for example, &quot;puella&quot;, meaning a girl, is feminine) many are simply assigned and hold no real meaning. Luckily, as you will find, the gender can often be determined by the spelling of the word (words ending in &quot;us&quot; are almost always masculine, and words ending in &quot;a&quot; are almost always feminine). For many words, however, you will simply have to memorize their gender. 

[[w:Adjective|Adjective]]s themselves must match the number, case, and gender of the noun (be it a substantive or a pronoun) they modify. If a noun is nominative singular feminine (see [[#case|case table]] below), then the adjective describing it must also be nominative singular feminine. If the noun is accusative plural masculine, then the adjective must be accusative plural masculine. This will be expanded on in the [[#Adjectives|Adjectives]] section below. The advantage of this system is that adjectives do not need to be adjacent to their respective nouns, as one would be able to tell which noun they modify by which noun they appear to agree with.

===Declension===
'''All substantives''' are part of one of 5 categories, called '''declensions'''. Each declension has a set of standard suffixes that indicate case and number. Usually gender is indicated by the suffix, although there are many exceptions. Therefore, you must memorize the gender of every substantive you learn.

By familiarizing yourself with the [[#Declension Tables|above tables]], you could deduce that originally the suffix indicating number, case, and gender was the same for every noun. However, as the language developed, nouns with a common stem formed declensions and sounds changed. Similar processes happen continually over time, even today.

The above tables allow you to familiarize yourself with the existence of each declension, though by no means are you expected to memorize it now. Nonetheless, you will have to memorize it as you are formally introduced to individual cases and declensions in future lessons. Because of its introductory purpose, it is considerably simplified and incomplete, and therefore should not be used as a reference in the future.

Adjectives are also classed into declensions:
#'''1st/2nd declension adjectives'''...
##...Use 1st declension suffixes from the substantive declension table when describing feminine nouns.
##...Use 2nd declension masculine suffixes from the above table when describing masculine nouns.
##...Use 2nd declension neuter suffixes (''not'' found in the above table) when describing neuter nouns.
#'''3rd declension adjectives''' behave as 'i' stem substantives unless specified. Masculine and Feminine suffixes (which are the same) will be used if describing masculine and feminine nouns, and Neuter suffixes will be used when describing neuter nouns.

Pronouns are not part of any declension, as they are all irregular, and simply have to be memorized.

===Case===
Cases (Latin: ''casus'') determine the role of the noun in the sentence in relation to other parts of the sentence. 

There are six cases, Nominative, Vocative, Accusative, Genitive, Dative and Ablative. Vocative (Lesson 3) can be considered a sort of miniature case, generally not being accepted as a true one. Additionally, some nouns have a locative case, which will be covered later. As nominative and accusative are the most basic, these will be taught first (the rest will be covered in later lessons).

{| border=&quot;1&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;
|-
! colspan=&quot;4&quot; |'''The Use of the Cases'''&lt;br/&gt;(all words in bold are in the case specified in the first column)
|-
! Case
! Role in sentence
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | Example (Latin)
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | Example (English)
|-
| Nominative || Subject (performs the verb)
| bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''Vir''' lupum vult.
| bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''The man''' wants a wolf.
|-
| Genitive || Description and possession
| bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | Lupus '''virī''' est.
| bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | It is the '''man's''' wolf/It is the wolf ''of'' the '''man'''.
|-
| Dative || Indirect object (receives the direct object)
| bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''Lupō''' dedit vir.
| bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | The man gave to '''the wolf'''.
|-
| Accusative || Direct object (receives the action of the verb)
| bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | Vir '''lupum''' videt.
| bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | The man sees '''the wolf'''.
|-
| Ablative || Various (modify or limit nouns by ideas of where, when, how, etc.)
| bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | Ā quō datum? '''Ā virō'''.
| bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | By whom given? '''By a man'''.
|-
| Vocative || Direct address (speaking to somebody directly)
| bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | Salvē, '''Brute'''!
| bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | Hello, '''Brutus'''!
|}

===Gender===
'''All substantives''', including inanimate objects, have a particular gender (genera), which is either masculine, feminine, or neuter.

For example, Vir, &quot;a man,&quot; is masculine. Marītus, &quot;a husband,&quot; is also masculine. Puella, &quot;a girl,&quot; is feminine. Māter, &quot;a mother,&quot; is feminine. Even inanimate objects are assigned gender, including all the moons, stars, trees, tools, and so forth. Logic will give you little help in determining what the genders of inanimate objects are, and with many nouns memorization is required. Luckily, for many nouns, the spelling of the word indicates the gender.

Certain rules may be utilized to determine the gender of an inanimate substantive. Declension is a good indication of gender, especially for 1st and 2nd declension substantives. 1st declension substantives (substantives with an -a suffix) are usually feminine and second declension nouns (substantives with an -us suffix) are usually masculine or neuter. There are a few exceptions, and they will have to be learned. 3rd declension nouns can be either masculine, feminine or neuter (thus the gender will often have to be memorized). 4th declension nouns are usually masculine, sometimes neuter while 5th declension nouns are usually feminine.

1st/2nd declension adjectives alternate the set of endings depending on the gender of noun it describes (see above: Agreement of the Gender of Nouns and the Adjective). If the adjective describes a feminine noun, the adjective must use 1st declension endings, if the adjective describes a masculine noun, the adjective must use 2nd declension masculine endings, if the adjective describes a neuter noun the adjective must use 2nd declension neuter endings.

3rd declension adjectives use the same set of endings for masculine and feminine nouns. However, a slightly different set of endings are used when describing neuter nouns.

==Adjectives==
As stated above, adjectives must match the gender, number, and case of the noun (be the noun a substantive, or a pronoun) they modify. However, there are many occasions where logic cannot be used to determine the gender of inanimate objects, as genders are generally arbitrary when the noun has no literal gender. Furthermore, the declension of the noun, often determined by the spelling, can in turn be used to determine the gender, especially for the 1st and 2nd. However, this is never the case for the third declension, as the declension itself is not primarily assigned to any gender and the spelling of the nominative (&quot;default&quot;) stem is random, leaving you with no hints.

A noun and its adjective must also be in the same case. Otherwise, it is impossible to tell which nouns pair up to their respective adjectives in a sentence, as the words in a Latin sentence can appear in any order. See the examples below.

{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot;
|+align=&quot;bottom&quot;|Notice how &quot;magna&quot; changes to &quot;magnae&quot; to agree with the pluralized &quot;puellae&quot;.
!bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|Latin
!bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|English
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|Puella (nominative sing., fem.)
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|Girl
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|Puella magna
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|The big girl
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|Puellae (nominative '''pl.''', fem.)
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|Girls
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|Puellae magnae
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|The big girls
|}

{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot;
|+align=&quot;bottom&quot;|Notice how &quot;magna&quot; becomes &quot;magnus&quot; to agree with the masculine word &quot;servus&quot;. Also notice that &quot;magnus&quot; changes to &quot;magnum&quot; to agree with the noun it's describing in case, though do not concern yourself with the difference between cases for the time being.
!bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|Latin
!bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|English
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|Servus (nominative sing, mas.)
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|Slave
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|Servus magnus
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|The big slave
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|Servum ('''accusative''' sing, mas.)
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|Slave
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|Servum magnum
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|The big slave
|}

{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot;
|+align=&quot;bottom&quot;|Notice that &quot;magna&quot; is feminine because &quot;arbor&quot; is feminine, despite that it does not end in &quot;a&quot; like &quot;puella&quot;. The word &quot;arbor&quot; is one of the situations where you will simply have to memorize the gender.
!bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|Latin
!bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|English
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|Arbor (nominative sing, fem.)
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|Tree
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|Arbor magna
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|The big tree
|}

==Recapitulation==
*Declensions are used to categorize nouns in groups. There are 5 declensions total.
*Each of the five declensions has a distinct set of endings which are appended to nouns of that declension.
*The endings indicate the case and number when appended to the stem of a noun.
*A substantive may use only the endings of the declension of which it is a part.
*Each substantive has a predefined gender which almost never changes and is separate from the suffix.
*Adjectives are a part of the 1st/2nd declension and 3rd declension.
*Adjectives use the gender of the noun that they modify.

'''Therefore:'''
*An adjective of the 1st/2nd declension uses 1st declension endings when describing a feminine noun, a 2nd declension masculine ending when describing masculine noun, and 2nd declension neuter when describing a neuter noun.
*An adjective of the 3rd declension uses the same set of endings when describing masculine and feminine nouns and another set of endings when describing neuter nouns. (Actually, there are 3-termination, 2-termination, and 1-termination 3rd declension adjectives. If the adjective is 3-termination, e.g., acer (f. sing.), acris (m. sing.), acer (n. sing.), acres (f. pl.), acres (m. pl.), or acria (n. pl.), then use the appropriate ending; if the adjective is 2-termination, then one termination will be masculine/feminine and the other neuter; if the adjective is 1-termination, the common form is used.)

Before you proceed to the next lesson, complete the exercises below so you will be able to apply this knowledge to Latin.

==Exercises==
{{Latin/Exercise|Questions|
#What are the three genders?
#What is the number (singular/plural) of the following English words:
##cow
##dogs
##genders
##adjective
##children
##slice
##mice
##geese
#Describe the relationship between an adjective and the noun which it modifies.
#How many declensions are there?
#Determine the declension of each Latin word:
#*puella (''girl'')
#*ianua (''door'')
#*amicus (''friend'')
#*ludus (''game'')
#*casa (''house'')
#*rex (''king'')
#What gender are 1st declension substantives mostly?
#What genders are 2nd declension substantives mostly?
#What grammatical features of a word that can be determined by looking at its ending?
|
#Masculine, Feminine, and Neuter
#What is the number (singular/plural) of the following English words:
##S
##P
##P
##S
##P
##S
##P
##P
#The adjective takes on the number, case and gender (but not always the declension) of the noun it describes
#Five
#Determine the declension of each Latin word:
##1st
##1st
##2nd
##2nd
##1st
##3rd
#Feminine
#Masculine
#It varies slightly from word-to-word; Declension/Case, Number, and sometimes Gender.
}}

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>2schu6yzlnlqtrc8vgtrtfgpj9rqu3x</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:211.28.95.17</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>962</id>
    <revision>
      <id>153095</id>
      <parentid>2545</parentid>
      <timestamp>2003-09-06T00:46:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Karl Wick</username>
        <id>6</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>quick yet important question for Daniel Canaris</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&quot;from Wikipedia. &quot; Where? A link to the actual article is needed. --[[User:Maveric149|mav]]
----
Hey Dan, this thing is beautiful !! A real work of art. I just want to make sure, all of this material is original to you, or is from a public domain document, right ? If we ever have someone copy in stuff from a copyrighted source it would be a legal liability. Keep up the great work man, my sister's eyes lit up when I told her someone had started a Latin textbook on the site. -- [[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]</text>
      <sha1>3ii96xcd3qn9370hsnkve51fvnei510</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Latin/Lesson 1-Nominative</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>963</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2699154</id>
      <parentid>2688967</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-09-10T00:25:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mirogeorgiev1997</username>
        <id>1768677</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Notes on Vocabulary */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Latin}}

==The Nominative Case==

The nominative case refers to the subject of the sentence. It is also one of the three cases of modern English. Every sentence must have a subject. For example:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Caesar is emperor of Rome.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Caesar is the subject of this sentence therefore Caesar is given in the nominative case.

&lt;blockquote&gt;Caesar's army entered Rome&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Above is the genitive case which shows possession; the army was Caesar's army. We have changed the case of the word &quot;Caesar&quot; by altering its end. The nominative case has been changed to the genitive case by the addition of an apostrophe and the letter &quot;s&quot;.  

Latin cases are formed in the same way. The first step is to learn some words in their nominative case so as to become familiar with their endings which will later be changed to form the other cases.

==Notes on Vocabulary==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; | &lt;b&gt;Lesson Vocabulary&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | &lt;font face=&quot;Arial&quot; size=&quot;4&quot;&gt;Latin&lt;/font&gt;
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | &lt;font face=&quot;Arial&quot; size=&quot;4&quot;&gt;English&lt;/font&gt;
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''magn-us -a -um'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''great'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''bon-us -a -um'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''good'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''mal-us -a -um'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''bad'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''puell-a -ae''' (f.)
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''girl'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''puer''' (m.)
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''boy'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''māter''' (f.)
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''mother'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''domin-a''' (f.)
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''mistress'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''domin-us''' (m.)
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''master'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''lūd-us''' (m.)
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''school'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''triclīni-um''' (n.)
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''dining room'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''templ-um''' (n.)
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''temple'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | &lt;B&gt;esse&lt;/B&gt;&lt;BR&gt;(ego) sum&lt;BR&gt;(tū) es&lt;BR&gt;'''est'''&lt;BR&gt;(nōs) sumus&lt;BR&gt;(vōs) estis&lt;BR&gt;'''sunt'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | &lt;B&gt;to be&lt;/B&gt;&lt;BR&gt;I am&lt;BR&gt;you (singular) are&lt;BR&gt;'''(he/she/it) is'''*&lt;BR&gt;we are&lt;BR&gt;you (plural) are&lt;BR&gt;'''(they) are'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''ambula-t''', '''ambula-nt'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''(he/she/it is) walking, (they are) walking'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''curri-t''', '''curru-nt'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''(he/she/it is) running, (they are) running'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''nōn'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | An adverb placed before a verb meaning 'not' thus negating the verb.
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; | Some second declension masculine end in ''-r'' instead of ''-us'' in the nominative case — boy is ''puer'', not ''puer-us''. Of the nouns discussed on this page, this rule only applies to ''puer''.
|}

Of the &quot;to be&quot; verbs listed in the table, only '''est''' and '''sunt''' will be covered in this lesson. The table simply allows you to familiarize yourself with them, as verbs will be covered more in future lessons.

The nominative case is used for the subject of the sentence (or any noun that is the equivalent of the subject). 

In this chapter, the following conventions will be used for nouns:
*''m.'' = masculine
*''f.'' = feminine
*''n.'' = neuter

*First and second declension substantives are given with at least the nominative case. (We will add the genitive singular as time permits. It is not strictly necessary, but you should get in the habit now of declining nouns based on the genitive stem and not the nominative. &lt;B&gt;This chapter is therefore slightly misleading in this regard.&lt;/B&gt;)
*Third, fourth, and fifth declension substantives are given with the nominative and genitive singular.

{{Latin}}

==Overview of Adjectives==
An adjective is simply any word that describes a noun, such as an object or subject in a sentence. Of course, whole phrases may be used to describe nouns, but adjectives are individual words. For example:
{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot;
!bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|English
!bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|Latin
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|The '''good''' ''boy'' walks.
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|''Puer'' '''bonus''' ambulat.
|}

An adjective can also be used in a sentence opposite a form of &quot;to be.&quot; The &quot;to be&quot; verb simply serves as a linking verb, as &quot;the good boy&quot; is an incomplete sentence, but &quot;the boy is good&quot; is a complete sentence.
{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
!bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|English
!bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|Latin
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|The boy ''is'' '''good'''.
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|Puer '''bonus''' ''est''.
|}

As shown above, the same is true in Latin.

==Adjectives in Latin==
Like nouns, adjectives in Latin are declined. The vast majority take either the first and second declension (''antiquus -a -um'') or the third declension (''ferox, ferocis''). All such adjectives must agree with the nouns they describe in gender, number, and case, '''but not necessarily declension'''.

*First and second declension adjectives have three distinct genders. Feminine adjectives require the first declension, masculine the second, and neuter the second. First/second declension adjectives use all three gender suffixes: -us, -a, -um (masculine, feminine, and neuter, respectively). This is because description is not limited to a single gender. For example, being good is not a quality limited to a single gender. Boys can be good, girls can be good, and things can be good. So, since all three genders must apply, we don't label adjectives as particularly ''m.'', ''f.'', or ''n.''.
*Third declension adjectives are given with the nominative and genitive singular. '''This, however, is only true for third declension adjectives of one termination, so again this chapter is misleading in this regard.''' Most third declension adjectives do not have separate masculine and feminine forms. (Neuter adjectives follow the third declension neuter pattern.)

These words will look like the adjective '''antiquus''' (old, ancient):
:''antiquus'' (masculine), ''antiqua'' (feminine), ''antiquum'' (neuter). 

Third declension adjectives typically look more like '''ferox''', '''ferocis''' (wild, bold). This is because the third declension has no stem assigned to the nominative singular and is a &quot;wild card&quot; in that regard.

Adjectives &lt;u&gt;often&lt;/u&gt; come '''after the word they describe'''. (But since word order is not central to the meaning of a Latin sentence, the adjective &lt;u&gt;may appear anywhere&lt;/u&gt; within the sentence. In poetry, for example, several words often separate an adjective from the noun it modifies.)

For example:
'''Nota bene:''' In the following examples the ''-us'' ending stands for the '''masculine (m.)''' gender, 
the ''-a'' for the '''feminine (f.)''' gender, and the ''-um'' stands for the '''neuter (n.)''' gender. 
So '''magnus''' is masculine, '''magna''' is feminine and '''magnum''' is neuter. 

{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot;
!bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|Latin
!bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|English
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|Puella bona est.
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|The girl is good.
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|Dominus bonus est.
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|The master is good.
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|Templum magnum est.
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|The temple is big.
|}

''Bona'' is an adjective describing a feminine substantive, such as ''puella''.&lt;br&gt;
''Bonus'' is an adjective describing a masculine substantive, such as ''dominus''.

==Grammar: Pluralizing Nominatives==
{| align=&quot;center&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot; width=&quot;85%&quot;
|-
! Number
! First declension feminine
! Second declension masculine
! Second declension neuter
|-
| Singular || puell-'''a''' || lūd-'''us''' || triclīni-'''um'''
|-
| Plural || puell-'''ae''' || lūd-'''ī''' || triclīni-'''a'''
|}

To pluralize most first and second declension nouns, replace the singular suffix with the equivalent plural suffix. All adjectives that describe the noun must be pluralized as well because adjectives must agree in case, number, and gender (but not necessarily declension). With the adjectives given, use first declension with feminine nouns and second declension with masculine nouns. In English we use the same nominative plural endings for words we have borrowed from Latin, so it may be helpful to remember we say one vertebr-a but two vertebr-ae, one radi-us but two radi-ī, and one medium but multi-medi-a.

==Basic verbs==
Verbs in Latin work quite differently than those in English. Study the following table, then view the examples below, though keep in mind that you only need to fully understand the difference between numbers for the time being.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! !! English !! Latin
|-
|Number || Only pluralize the noun that is being pluralized, not the adjectives that describe it or the verb that it is performing. || All three are pluralized. In this context, singular verbs end in &quot;-t&quot; (es'''t''', ambula'''t'''), and plural verbs end in &quot;-nt&quot; (su'''nt''', ambula'''nt''').
|-
|Tense || The ending is sometimes changed, though the words surrounding the verb can also be used to denote tense. Consider these examples: &quot;he will walk, he is walking, he walks, he walked&quot;. || The stem is used to denote the tense, though this will be covered in a future lesson. In this lesson, only the present tense is being taught.
|-
|Person || The subject of the sentence is used to determine the person. If I am the subject of the sentence, then the sentence is in the first person. If you are the subject, then the second person, and so forth with the third. In this lesson, only the third person is being taught, which refers to anyone other than the speaker or the listener. || The stem also denotes the person, though as previously stated, only third person is being taught in this lesson.
|}

===Examples===
{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;
|+align=&quot;bottom&quot;|Notice how &quot;magnum&quot; changes to &quot;magna&quot; to agree with the pluralized &quot;triclīnia&quot;.
!bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|Latin
!bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|English
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|puell-a bon-a es-t.
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|The girl is good.
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; | ''And to pluralize:''
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|puell-ae bon-ae su-nt
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|The girls are good.
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; | Note that verbs do not have gender, in that they do not change to the gender of the word that they are describing.
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;| Puer bon-us ambula-t.
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;| The good boy is walking.
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; | ''And to pluralize:''
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|Puer-ī bon-ī ambula-nt
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;| The good boys are walking.
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; | You will notice that neither the linking verbs &quot;est&quot; nor &quot;sunt&quot; appear in the previous two sentences. The meaning of the linking verbs are assumed in Latin sentences, as their respective meanings already exist in the verb stems.
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|triclīni-um magn-um es-t
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|The dining room is large.
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; | ''And to pluralize:''
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|triclīni-a magn-a su-nt
|align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|The dining rooms are large.
|}

==Further Examples==
===Example 1===
{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; width=&quot;85%&quot;
|-
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | Latin
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | English
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | templum magnum est
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | The temple is big.
|}

;Notes
*The adjective ''magnus -a -um'' must agree with ''templum'' in gender, number, and case, so the correct form is ''magnum'' (neuter nominative singular).
*Something like ''templum magnus est'' is '''incorrect''' because ''magn-us'' does not agree with ''templ-um''. To a Latin speaker, this would sound like nonsense.

===Example 2===
{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; width=&quot;85%&quot;
|-
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | Latin
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | English
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | puella magna est.
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | The girl is big.
|}

'''Notes:''' In the same way, the adjective ''magnus -a -um'' must agree with ''puella'' in gender, number, and case, so the correct form is ''magna'' (feminine nominative singular, a-declinatio).

===Example 3===
{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; width=&quot;85%&quot;
|-
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | Latin
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | English
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|Puer currit.
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|The boy is running.
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot;|Puerī currunt.
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot;|The boys are running
|}

'''Notes:''' You may notice that, when pluralized, &quot;curr'''i'''t&quot; becomes &quot;curr'''u'''nt&quot;. The original spelling was probably &quot;currint&quot;, but changed to &quot;currunt&quot; over time to make it easier to say. This is true of any pluralized verbs that would otherwise be ending in &quot;-int&quot;. 

===Example 4===
{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; width=&quot;85%&quot;
|-
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | Latin
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | English
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | lūdī magnī sunt
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | The schools are big.
|}

'''Notes:''' The adjective ''magnus -a -um'' in this case must agree with ''lūdī'' in gender, number, and case, so the correct form is ''magnī'' (masculine nominative plural).

==Third Declension Nouns and Adjectives==
Third declension nouns and adjectives follow a different pattern. The nominative singular stem is not defined, and as such, any letter (or letters) can serve as a third declension stem. For example, ''Māter'' (mother) is a third declension noun in the nominative case. When pluralized, it becomes ''Mātrēs''. &quot;-ēs&quot; is attached to the end of a third declension noun to pluralize it, as opposed to changing the ending completely, because there is no uniform way to do so given the third declension's random nature.

You may have also noticed that that the &quot;e&quot; in &quot;Māter&quot; was dropped when pluralized. This often happens when a stem is attached to a third declension noun of similar spelling (example, &quot;Pater&quot; (father) becomes &quot;Patrēs&quot;)

Examples:
{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; width=&quot;85%&quot;
|-
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | Latin
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | English
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | māter bona est
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | The mother is good.
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | mātrēs bonae sunt
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | The mothers are good.
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | pater magnus est
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | The father is large.
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | patrēs magnī sunt
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | The fathers are large.
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | amīcus fortis est
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | The friend is strong.
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | amīcī fortēs sunt
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | The friends are strong
|}

Third declension nouns are listed with the nominative case and the genitive case to provide the main stem, which will be covered in a few lessons. All other nouns are also listed with the genitive for standardization, but often just the genitive ending is given. For example:
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot;
|-
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | &lt;font face=&quot;Arial&quot; size=&quot;4&quot;&gt;Latin&lt;/font&gt;
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | &lt;font face=&quot;Arial&quot; size=&quot;4&quot;&gt;English&lt;/font&gt;
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''pater, patris'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''father'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''oratio, orationis'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''speech'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''uxor, uxoris'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''wife'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''canis, canis'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''dog'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''proelium, -ī'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''battle'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''oculus, -ī'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''eye'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''amīcus, -ī'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''friend'''
|}

All other types of nouns are also generally listed with the genitive

Adjectives with a nominative ending in -is and the same stem in the nominative and in the other cases (eg. fortis) end in -e in the neuter and -ia in the neuter plural.

For example:
*dies difficilis = the difficult day
*proelium difficile = the difficult battle
*proelia difficilia = the difficult battles

==Exercises==
{{Latin/Exercise|Translation|
#Translate the following Latin words into English.
##dominus bonus 
##ludus malus 
##puella magna
##triclinium est magnum 
#Translate into Latin.
##the good boy
##the large master
##The temple is large.
##The master is bad.
|
#Translate the following Latin words into English.
##The good master
##The bad school
##The big girl
##The dining room is large
#Translate into Latin.
##Puer bonus
##dominus magnus
##templum magnum est
##dominus malus est
}}</text>
      <sha1>977uto2z4epy648kgnlke7qri8d4rjd</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Latin</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>966</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2314002</id>
      <parentid>2121214</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-04-28T04:09:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Panic2k4</username>
        <id>2865</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Wikibooks:Naming policy */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{WikiProject Languages}} 

It is always SO exciting to see people working on a project. This work will be the basis of many people learning about this subject ... We leave behind a legacy with every bit of work. Thank you, welcome, and good luck with your efforts. Any questions ask me or one of the oldtimers .. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

== Introduction Completed ==

After going over things many, many times, I think I have completed the Lesson 1 and Lesson 2 pages (which are both counted now by me as 'Introduction').

I have merged the nominative and accusative lessons in one, because I think it is important to learn both cases at the same time, and I think it offers a better introduction to the meaning of the the suffixes, and it allows students to construct real sentences not just 'he is good' etc. at the very beginning.

Also, I might just show students all the 5 cases at the very beginning. I don't think it will overwhelm them because what we are doing is starting from the two basic cases (nominative and accusative) and gradually building up to all 6 and at the end touch on locative.

Also, who is in favour of using instead of 'present, future, imperfect and perfect, future perfect, pluperfect' rather Present Imperfect, Future Imperfect, Past Imperfect, Present Perfect, Future Perfect, Past Perfect.

And from there students can use the planned 'Advance Latin Course', to be used for later years. It is to be a course for students who know a little latin and want to build their knowledge. Anyway, it will start from ground zero, and will assume the student knows nothing, but the student must be intelligent, and very dedicated. It will go through all aspects of the language, and won't offer exercises, because the student is expected to simply to take notes.

== Some thoughts... ==

I like the ideas put forth so far, and would love to help out on this project.  I'll also touch on the ideas you presented with my own - we agree on a good deal of the points:

As we learn different parts of speech and noun constructions at different times in our natural English educations, I think a similarly-presented Latin lesson plan is appropriate.  What I'm suggesting is to mention all the cases and their most &lt;b&gt;basic&lt;/b&gt; usages (with respect to English constructions) up front:  &lt;em&gt;Nominative&lt;/em&gt; is for subjects, &lt;em&gt;Accusative&lt;/em&gt; is for direct object, etc.  

Then, start with basic sentences involving the Present Imperfect of &lt;em&gt;esse&lt;/em&gt;, subjects, predicate nominatives, and prepositions taken with the Ablative - &lt;em&gt;Pueri in campo sunt&lt;/em&gt;.  Toss in some possessives - &lt;em&gt;Ciceronis frater miles est&lt;/em&gt;.  Obviously the vocab. in that last example was a bit steep as it would be wise to start with just the first or second declension.  The point of this is just to teach Latin in the same manner English was taught.  Certainly in English we learned how to say &quot;I kicked the ball in the field&quot; (place where) before learning to say &quot;I kicked the ball in the field with amazing vigor&quot; (manner) or &quot;I kicked the ball in the field with my foot&quot; (means).

While it certainly is neat (and very viable) to have students constructing &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; (i.e., substantial) sentences by the end of the first lesson, I worry about how many students may be turned off by such a rapid approach.

As for your verb tense naming scheme, I think the latter name scheme provides better insight into what the tenses actually imply, so my vote goes for that option.  It took me the longest time as a student to make the distinction between Imperfect and Perfect with regards to the action's &quot;completeness.&quot;

I'd be more than happy to make whatever contributions I can to this thing, just let me know what I can do to help!  Cheers!

C. Seth Lester (http://www.sethlester.com/)

== Systematic Approach ==

The problem is I want a systematic approach for latin.

As you can see I have a table for all the cases in Lesson 1 or 2. The first two lessons, as I had arranged it give a complete introduction into the terminology used. And in the 3rd lesson (which is quite a mess) you start to apply it to real Latin, starting with the Nominative and Accusative cases. I think it is important to start off comparing nominative and accusative, and getting students to recognize the forms as once you can do that, it is all a matter of memorizing suffixes (only nominative and accusative for lesson 3).

Also I think it would be appropriate to give simple rules to the suffixes and stem changes in the third declension so by the end of lesson 3 you would be able to:

Decline (only nominative and accusative) 1st declen, 2nd declen., 3rd declen, 4th declen. and 5th declen. including adjectives.

Pronouns will be introduced on the last lesson on nouns, also the effect of dropping the subject noun.

1st and 2nd persons will not be dealt with until we start learning to conjugate verbs which will be quite later down the track (I think nouns (which include substantives, adjectives and pronouns) are the MOST important things to get out of the way.

Constructions with the 3rd persons of to be (est, sunt, erit, erunt, erat, erant, fuit, fuerunt, fuerit, fuerit, fuerat, fuerant) can be learnt but it must be emphasized that these verbs take the NOMINATIVE.

If you wish, you can drop me an email at daniel_canaris@yahoo.com.au

== Latin Dictionary... ==
I have been reading some of Des Cartes writings (which is in latin), and he employs peculiar Latin. Namely due to the fact that Latin &quot;evolved&quot; somewhat, but I have no clue what he is saying. If anyone has a philosopher Latin-English dictionary, or a link to an online one, that would be supper to put on!
Cheers!
Pablo

If we can find a good link on it, the one on www.perseus.tufts.edu would be the best.  It includes all the classics and all the philosophers and all the big dictionaries (except the OLD.)

== Formatting. ==

I try to help as much as I can, but unfortunately, since I'm actually using this book to learn Latin, I can't contribute in that manner. However, I ''can'' contribute by fixing / formatting tables, removing typos or tags that show though the page, and things like that.

That brings me to my question: is there some kind of set formatting that's been agreed upon? I've just been alternating the rows with grey and white where appropriate, but I'm not sure if I should do anything with the heading or use different colors.

Like I said, I'm trying to help, but I can't help if I don't know what to do.

Also, is there going to be a non-introductory Latin course? If not, then each of the parts (Part 1, Part 2, etc.) can be made into a header and the &quot;Introductory Latin Course&quot; header can be removed. This  will make sure that the table of contents works correctly, although I'm not particularly sure that it's necessary to have a table of contents for a table of contents.

On the front page, a note has been added by someone asking for macrons to be used to indicate vowel length.  I see that there is no need for such a thing, because there different ways in which latin can be pronounced.

'''This is true, however the macron must be used for the ablative singular (otherwise it gets confusied with the nominative pluaral. --source of &quot;Note&quot;. It is also best used for the acc. to distingush for novices between the English plural -s and the 1st declension accusative plural since English has a much broader concept of plural which doesn't always depend on case. So I just made sure to point to people how to do this. (Technical skills are also covered in many textbooks.) I struggled to figure out how to do it.

I am also learning Latin through this text, and Latin via Ovid.

== Speaking Latin??? ==
There is now an enormous online audio course for spoken Latin, with many thousands of users. This is Latinum, and it is delivered by podcast.
There are also a huge number of colloquies, dialogues etc that were written for beginners to learn colloquial Latin (heavily influenced by Terence and Plautus,of course ). A google search for Latinum, or 'latin podcast' will bring up the Latinum podcast, which is free.
There is also a community of Latin speakers who communicate regularly through Schola.ning.com.

Hi,

I ´m wondering if it is reasonable to make a section for speaking Latin.
I would like to work upon this section, altough I am not that experienced in spoken Latin.
But I think some might be interested in basic speaking exercises and phrases you may use some time. So I think , actually speaking Latin is not taught at school neither at University, so maybe it could be an interesting thing for (advanced) Latin learners.
Tell me your opinon upon this please.

Sincerely,

Kay Lorenz
: There are universities that teach spoken classical Latin, and definitely a lot of religious schools that teach &quot;church latin.&quot;  And, despite what anyone says, we do know a lot about colloquial Latin, how things were pronounced, colloquialisms and slang, etc.  So yes, at least pronunciation and at most a steady stream of spoken Latin should be inected into this book.  --[[User:Mrcolj|Mrcolj]] 04:55, 14 August 2006 (UTC)
: I just saw this: http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Spoken_Latin  --[[User:Mrcolj|Mrcolj]] 05:28, 14 August 2006 (UTC)

:I am fluent in spoken Latin and let me tell you that it is used more then just in university courses on in the Church.  Not to be hostile but I also take exception to the characterization of Church Latin as somehow being different, wierd or bad.  This may not have been your intention but it came across to me that you meant that by putting it in &quot;quotes&quot;.  The kind of Church Latin that you find in the liturgy or in set prayers like the Our Father is an idiom of Latin that is different but not significantly different from everyday Latin or the Latin used for formal meetings.  We know that Issac Newton, regardless of what you think of him, didn't write in the idiom of Latin used in the liturgy but he did write in the common Latin idiom of his time that was intelligible to almost all litterate people of that time.  Just like Biblical Greek is different from Ancient Greek due to the inclusion of and direct translations from Hebrew and other Semetic languages, they were both used in the Church, one for the liturgy and bible and the other for everyday communication.  The modern version of Latin that exist and is decended from the Latin that Newton and his peers used is not only used by the Church but by anyone that respects the language enough to allow it to grow and start to include new words and used new letters like the now demonized letter J.  Much of this has come about by teachers that want to teach very specifically Classical Latin.  I respect their decision to teach Classical Latin as it is an important idiom of the Language that is important form many people to learn but I do take issue when people begin to say that ONLY Classical Latin is correct.  They start to want to expunge books of the letter J, accent marks and any words not used by Cicero or Ceasar.  Keep in mind that Classical Latin only existed for about 100 to 200 years.  Anything else is simply an immitation of it.  Latin has a 3000 year history and mother tounge speaker living in a very wide area that used slightly different vobaculary and had local idioms.  Are we to tell them that they are all wrong, us who come to Latin as a second Language, tell the ancients who were Native speakers and maybe didn't even know any other language that they are wrong.  Certainly not.  There is more to Latin then just the simple form of Classical Latin or the very complicated form of Liturgical Latin.  Latin is a full and complete language and one should never be afraid or embarassed to learn to speak it.

== Exercises ==

I have realised how little thought has been put into the exercises even many points of existing grammar.   I believe we should pick passages for every page which relate to the grammatical concepts introduced in the chapter in addition to revised exercises.  I shall spend quite some time this week revising pages and making additional entries.



==Comments from a Latin Student==

I have a number of comments on how everything is done - and, I want people to keep in mind, I mean it in a good way. It seems to me that at certain points some things are introduced far too soon - subjunctive, for example, and declining adjectives (although that should be fine as long as we stick to first and second declension!) - while other things are brought up too slowly. For example, I think we could teach all the cases at once, which I realize the author is considering - maybe leave out the Vocative, as it's not particularly useful and not technically a case - or something to that extent.

Just a thought; it seems to me that the way some of it is organized is inconsistent, which can make it hard to follow.

Some things also don't make sense to me - for example, how can an adjective be a noun? Something can't modify itself. I just have a bunch of little nitpicks; however, I'm not a professional, just a student, so feel free to correct me!

Awesome work, though - a really tough project! Hope I can help out too.

--Chiyo

PS - My vote goes to the former system, as in the one with Pluperfect, but that's only because that's what I was taught and it's what I'm the most used to. Don't care much either way, though.

-----
Reply:  I agree many things need to be improved in layout and presentation.  Please feel free to make changes as you see fit.

Now concerning the 'Noun'.  Latin grammarians, like Donatus, considered the adjectives, pronouns and substantives to all be 'nouns'.  And in fact, many of the older grammar also do this as well.  Nouns to the ancient grammarians were words which were declined which include adjectives, pronouns and substantives. - Daniel Canaris

What are those two new additions on the title page?  What are they there for?

== declensions and cases ==

I'm using your text to learn latin, not very hard at any rate.  As a person who is more or less oblivious this crazy Latin grammar, I find you explain most of it well enough, although it may be a little technical.  Declension is the part that gets me.  I see that the nouns are modified depending on their use in the sentence, but what's with the 5 declensions?  I think this is something that needs clarification.  I'm assuming the different declensions just mean you decline differently, like conjugating verbs differently in spanish depending on the ending?  Also, the different cases could use a little clarification, I get the feeling that everything but nominative and accusative has some pretty complex nuances.  It seems pretty good for being a work in progress, albeit a bit complicated for a new latin student (or just me?).  Just trying to give you a learner's perspective.


- REPLY 

Your assumption is right.

Don't worry about 'nuances' at the beginning.  Datives are used more than just 'giving', genitives more than just origin etc. but don't worry about it.  You'll learn it gradually.

The final vowel (or consonent) of the stem of the noun determines what declension a noun is.  From analysing the different declensions and the case endings you can see that each case ending of one declension shares something in common with another.  A 'm' sound is typical for singular accusatives (like Greek) and 'um' for genitive plurals (like the greek on).  Different indo-european languages also share common case endings.  The endings though become corrupted and certain elisions occur dependant on the final vowel or consonent.  All the nouns with the vowel 'a' as the final vowel of the stem fall under the catagory of 1st declension nouns.  'o' nouns are the second declension, 'consonents or i' 3rd declension, u 4th declension and 'e' 5th declension.  By reading a bit of basic linguistics it's not hard to see how this occurs.  

In Spanish you have verb conjugations, and the concept is not dissimilar.

hablo
hablas
habla
hablamos
hablaís
hablan

and other 'a' verbs conjugate like this in spanish

form the 'a' conjugation which all conjugate alike (the a conjugation in Spanish is very regular, which is to do with the vowel 'a', because in Latin the 'a' nouns and verbs are the most stable as well)

amo
amas
amat 
amamus
amatis
amant

and other 'a' verbs conjugate like this in english.

'a' nouns in Latin nearly all decline like 'puella' (puella, puellam, puellae, puellae, puella, puellae, puellas, puellarum, puellis, puellis)
'o' nouns in Latin nearly all decline like 'servus'
'consonent' and 'i' nouns in Latin nearly all decline like 'civis' or 'rex'
'u' nouns nearly all decline like cornus
'e' nouns decline like 'res'.

== Imperatives ==

I have noticed that there is not a section on imperatives.  Imperatives are rather simply as far as I recall from school. Imperatives are commands!

First Conjuagtion

S Ama = (You) Love!
P Amate = (You) Love! 

Second Conjugation

S Mone = (You)Advise!
P Monete = (You) Advise!

Third Conjugation

S Rege = (You) Rule!
P Regite = (You) Rule!

Except for: (Mnemonic &quot;Dick had a Duck with fur on its face&quot;)

- Dic Dicite
- Duc Ducite
- Fer Ferte
- Fac Facite

Fourth Conjugation

S Audi = (You) Hear!
P Audite = (You) Hear!

-- Reply to Reply

An easier way to remember the declensions, and the way in which I was taught, being a Latin student myself, is to have a song that you can sing to yourself that identifies them.  For example, I was taught &quot;One is -o, -are; Two is -eo, -ere; Three is -o, -ere; Four is -io, -ire; and Third -io is -io, -ere.&quot;  I was taught that the &quot;fourth declension&quot; here was the &quot;third -io&quot; and the &quot;fifth&quot; was the &quot;fourth,&quot; which may or may not be confusing to you...  The numbers in the song are the declensions, and the first ending is the first-person nominative singular form, whereas the second ending is the ending for the infinitive.  When you look up a word in almost any Latin/English dictionary, only the first- person nominative singular form and the infinitive form will be listed, so if you look in a Latin/ English dictionary, or you happen to know these two forms of the word, you will be able to identify the declension of that word.  Hope this was helpful!!!

[[User:68.107.196.191|68.107.196.191]] 23:47, 17 December 2006 (UTC)Natsirk

== Answers To Exercises ==

I think the answers for all of the exercises should be given somewhere, otherwise it defeats the purposes of the exercises. I would go ahead and add them, but I am student and am not very confident with the accuracy of my answers.

== Advanced ==

perhaps after all the basic grammatical bases have been covered there could be added an introduction to Latin meter and where it is used?

== Learning unused languages ==

It is always suggested that people practice the language they are learning by using it. The problem: no one speaks languages like Latin or Greek anymore (two that I would like to learn). This is a huge obsticale to learning. Does anyone have any ideas/suggestions on how to practice with people? I am thinking the best way is to find a friend that also wants to learn, and learn at the same time. --[[User:Loplin|Loplin]] 02:46, 18 October 2005 (UTC)

::See William Harris' excellent essay [http://community.middlebury.edu/~harris/LatinBackground/SilentReading.html the Sin of Silent Reading] for some trenchant views on learning Latin.  It might be hard to find another student but you can always read out loud.  --[[User:Kwhitefoot|kwhitefoot]] 15:40, 2 March 2006 (UTC)

Just a comment and I don't mean to be snide but I am pretty sure people still speak Greek in Greece as it is the only official language.  Modern Greek is a little different form Ancient Greek but learning it would help you a lot to learn to speak Ancient Greek.  Many people do still use Latin and many people still speak Latin but the problem is that modern writers or speakers of Latin are painted as strange, religious fanatics by people that support ONLY Classical Latin. 

== Long Vowels ==

I looked over this Latin course and I noticed that you didn't use long vowels (ā, ē, ī, ō, ū). They are necessary to correctly determine stress, so should they be added? [[User:Gandalf1491|Gandalf1491]] 15:29, 16 February 2006 (UTC)

Added long vowels up to Lesson 10. [[User:Gandalf1491|Gandalf1491]] 16:13, 1 March 2006 (UTC)

== Hard Going ==

Although I can understand this course, I have a nagging suspicion that I can only understand because I learned it all years ago. I think that some simpler explanations would help, perhaps it would be useful to have some explanations on linked pages. What do people think? [[User:Gaius Calvus|Gaius Calvus]] 13:28, 22 February 2006 (UTC)

Amen to that.  [[User:216.178.90.41|216.178.90.41]] 02:17, 2 May 2006 (UTC)TC

== Missing Stuff ==

I have noticed that a certain construction is missing.  Where is the ablative absolute?  The ablative absolute is probably the bane of anyone learning to translate latin.  An example would be ''caesare in absentia'' which would be translated as ''When/While Caesar was absent''.--[[User:IKnowNothing|IKnowNothing]] 00:39, 3 March 2006 (UTC)

Sorry another clause strung to mind the Double Dative.  The soldiers were for a hinderance to Hannibal.
--[[User:IKnowNothing|IKnowNothing]] 00:52, 3 March 2006 (UTC)

== [[Wikibooks:Naming policy]] ==

&lt;nowiki&gt;{{mergefrom|Spoken Latin}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;

To avoid confusion, all pages of the book called [[Latin]] should start with the word [[Latin]]. The majority of the pages already do this, but I suggest a move of [[Spoken Latin]] and other such pages. I might attempt to move the pages myself. --[[User:Kernigh|Kernigh]] 04:43, 21 March 2006 (UTC)

Hi Kernigh.  Changed your tag to a merge tag as I couldn't see any incorrectly named pages in the Latin book which needed fixing.  Cheers Ad --[[User:AdRiley|AdRiley]] 12:03, 3 May 2007 (UTC)

== Comments from a different Latin student ==

As far as I can see, there are a few organizational problems.  I think that all five cases should be introduced at once, or at least very quickly.  After all, what good is the nominative by itself?  The way I was taught (which worked well) was to introduce all five cases quickly, but do the declensions less quickly.  It isn't that difficult to come up with sentences using only first declension.

Also, I think that there should at least be an introduction to verbs in the first or second lesson (maybe just present tense).  This way, the student can practice with simple sentences and thoroughly memorize 1st declension, which is absolutely necessary.  After that, 2nd declension is not that different from 1st, and imperfect isn't that different from present, etc.

More extensive selected vocabulary would also be nice, because dictionaries are a little bit intimidating, especially if you don't know what priciple parts are, etc.  Also, just knowing what to learn is a setback.  People just being introduced don't have to know arbitrary words such as orca, orcae, f. -- a pot with a large belly.

e.g. my original vocab consisted of: illa, hic, agricola, fabula, familia, femina, fenestra, ferula, filia, ianua, mensa, patria, pictura, poeta, provincia, puella, regina, sella, silva, tabula, terra, via, villa, vita, murus, pavimentum, puer, stilus, in, cum, amo, habito, laudo, narro, voco, sum, and et.  Memorizing basic words such as these makes learning latin a lot easier when it is at first taught with simple words.

Did I miss the section on deponent verbs?

Tables of irregular verbs would be nice.  Sum, Fero, Volo, Nolo, Malo, etc.

So far, it's pretty good, though, despite my criticism.

[[User:216.178.90.41|216.178.90.41]] 02:16, 2 May 2006 (UTC)TC

== And another student.. ==

It's rather difficult to navigate my way around this site, so forgive me if I missed this earlier on somewhere else..

As a person who has no prior knowledge of Latin whatsoever, it is difficult to grasp some of the things presented here. For me, at least, it would help a great deal if somebody could include a brief table or something that defined (translated) all the terms/phrases  used in any give lesson. It would make a great deal more sense to me, as I can understand grammatically what it being explained sometimes, but I am unsure still of what exactly is being said.

As the person before me mentioned, I would greatly appreciate it if somebody could do up an appendix that is linked from the first page of basic vocab in one tense, just so I could at a very minimal level get started with simple phrases and sentences, and build up from there.

All in all, though, it is a formidable undertaking to learn a language from a textbook, and all the more daunting to teach one. I greatly applaud all the effort gone into the work so far, and eagerly await the completion of this text.

: While this course is under construction, try the free courses I created at [http://www.learnlangs.com/latin.htm]. [[User:Junesun|Junesun]] 19:14, 4 March 2007 (UTC)

== Orphans ==

These pages are not linked to from anywhere in this book. Please either incorporate them into the text or mark them for deletion with {{tl|delete}}.

* [[Latin/Appendix A]]
* [[Latin/Appendix B]]
* [[Latin/Appendix E]]
* [[Latin/Index II]]
* [[Spoken Latin]]

Thanks! --[[User:Hagindaz|hagindaz]] 01:29, 28 July 2006 (UTC)
== Ideas for Revisions==

Currently my biggest issue with the book, besides some inaccuracies I've been fixing, is the order of chapters. Students learn the vocative and ablative absolute before they can say &quot;pater est bonus.&quot;

As it is, I'm going to make some revisions to the order. If this is disliked, a revert will fix that immediately!

My plans are to subdivide the course into grades. That is grade 1 would have the basics, nominative, accusative, and present tense verbs, as well as the first few declensions of nouns, and a basic overview of verbs, adjectives, and so forth.


As an update, I have done that which I hoped to do to make the book more understandable and useful for the beginner. Unfortunately, I think I may have butchered the formating from earlier times into an irrecoverable state. For that I apologize greatly. Nonetheless, I have tried to simplify some complicated topics(such as the imperfect and future, genative and dative, etc. all being one topic instead of two or more, and invite anyone to help with this. Also, many of the perfects are completely, for lack of a better word, wrong. I think help with that would also be great. 

Again, apologizing, --[[User:Asv|Asv]] 20:00, 4 April 2007 (UTC)


==Thinking of Helping==

I am a Latin teacher and have developed an iterestin way of teaching Latin that I find works very well.  However, I teach Latin generally and I teach students to use what I call the easy pronunciation where C and G change before an EE type sound. It looks to me that the kind of Latin being taught here and the Latin that I teach are incompatible with each other.  Many people make arguement about Classical Latin and I certainly have no problem with people teaching Classical Latin but let us remember that the Classical Idiom is but one of the many idioms that existed and it only existed for a small time period when compared to the whole of the language.  I teach Latin as a complete language and I would hope that my students could read Classical, pre Classical, post Classical or any other type of Latin you could throw at them.  To get to the point I don't suppose you would be willing to reconsider your policies regarding the other idioms of Latin.  If not them I would suggest with all humility that this particular module be rename Classical Latin so that it could be more accurate and advertise exactly what is being taught here and open up the more general name of Latin for those of us who want to teach all of Latin.--[[User:Billiot|Billiot]] 10:32, 14 June 2007 (UTC)

==Pre/Suffixes==

Could any of you tell me in which part of this book I could write a section or two on prefixes and suffixes? They obviously aren't a large part of latin that your everyday student would need to learn to be able to translate a latin text, but there isn't a lot in Wikiland about these. I'm writing about the diminutive suffix in latin at Vicipaedia, but I'm sure that the page won't be done justice there. --&lt;font face=&quot;Courier new&quot; size=&quot;4&quot;&gt;[[user:Harris Morgan|Harris]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Harris Morgan|Morgan]]&lt;/font&gt; 18:23, 7 September 2007 (UTC)

==An alternative book==
I was thinking about making an alternative Latin book. Now before you kill me, I want you to look at some other language books and see what they teach first and what the emphasise; they teach &quot;greeting people&quot; and &quot;conversing&quot; first, learning how to introduce oneself. They don't slap a bunch of declension and conjugation tables in your face. Therefore I propose we create another lesson, which teaches Latin in order to make the student good at &quot;speaking&quot; Latin. To say how much something costs, to say which way to the bank and to order a hamburger. Sure some might say &quot;why learn that? you don't need to order hamburgers in Latin&quot;, well why not? Some people who have learned Latin for many years don't know how to say &quot;my name is xxx&quot;, and only know how to say &quot;sic transit gloria mundi&quot; and something like that. Now what do you say? I personally don't think that this would make it too complex for the students, and that it only make learning more fun. Then later, when people have mastered some helpful phrases and sentences (not &quot;the girls carry the water&quot;), we can teach them about the cases and grammar. I think this will make many kids aspire to learn Latin; &quot;hey guess how you say &quot;fuck you&quot; in Latin??&quot;. Hilarity ensues! --[[User:BiT|BiT]] 16:34, 25 September 2007 (UTC)

Why do u want to teach people to order hamburgers in latin sorry? my view is the crowd for studying latin don't learn it to speak it they learn it to be able to translate and appreciate such writers like Virgil or Horace. To read that stuff, you'll need to know your tables solid from the beginning. I see where your coming from, its a nice hook maybe to get people in, but you might be wasting your time writing more than a few chapters for the crowd you'll get though. [[Special:Contributions/220.253.21.32|220.253.21.32]] 10:14, 19 November 2007 (UTC)

== Wow! ==

I just want to congratulate and thank all the fabulous people who have worked on and continue to work on this wikibook. It is simply outstanding, and I can already see myself making leaps and bounds in my latin thanks to you.

== Spoken Latin ==

You know, casual Classic Latin.

== Diagramming ==

Shouldn't we include diagramming somewhere around here? It is highly essential to a through understanding of Latin grammar. Also, is ''Henle Latin'' included as a resource? Thanks, [[User:Laleena|Laleena]] ([[User talk:Laleena|talk]]) 01:30, 11 December 2007 (UTC)

== Wikijunior ==

The Latin Wikijunior article needs  a bit of help to make it to publishable status. Could some please help? [[User:Laleena|Laleena]] ([[User talk:Laleena|talk]]) 19:45, 16 December 2007 (UTC)

== Serious lack of example sentences ==
There is something very frustrating about seeing someone try to create useful material without knowing what a student really needs.
:As a matter of fact, I am studying Latin myself using the Memoria Press curriculum. (''Prima Latina'', then ''Latina Christiana'', and so on.) You could say that these people know what a student needs-plenty of review, a new list of vocab/grammar every week, and continual review. I can read some Latin and write the same (Maria occupat mensarum ex Romam, which means &quot;Mary seizes tables out of Rome&quot;). Thoughts? [[User:Laleena|Laleena]] ([[User talk:Laleena|talk]]) 14:00, 8 January 2008 (UTC)

== Chapter five ==

why are all the chapter five links going to places that their name doesn't imply?

&lt;nowiki&gt;[[/Latin/Lesson 1-Nominative|Translation]] ''Translate a passage from Catullus.''&lt;/nowiki&gt;

&lt;nowiki&gt;[[/Lesson 5-Accusative|Exercises]] ''Review of subjunctive forms.'' &lt;/nowiki&gt;

&lt;nowiki&gt;[[/Lesson 2-Genitive and Dative|Exercises]] ''Review of passive forms.'' &lt;/nowiki&gt;

&lt;nowiki&gt;[[/Lesson 4-Ablative|Translation]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;

&lt;nowiki&gt;[[/Lesson 6-Pronouns|Revision]] '' Ideas and memory tools for language patterns in conjugation and declining.''&lt;/nowiki&gt;

things labled 'translation' go to grammer exercises, and none of the things labled as grammar exercises match their titles. Is this deliberate? if so it is very confusing. [[User:Storeye|Storeye]] ([[User talk:Storeye|talk]]) 03:10, 21 June 2008 (UTC)

== Orphaned page ==

[[Latin/Introduction to Nouns (L1)]] is not linked to by this book.  Please link to it, merge it into another page and mark it with {{tlx|now merged|destination page}}, or if it is not needed mark it with {{tlx|delete|reasoning}}.  Thanks. -- [[User:Adrignola|Adrignola]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Adrignola|talk]] [[Special:Contributions/Adrignola|contribs]]&lt;/sup&gt; 02:11, 3 August 2009 (UTC)

== Clarifications ==

I think that we should explain everything, like where sentences come from and such, right from the start. I think the best way to do this would be to make a new page under the first chapter. I'm a very new memberand am not sure of how to do this.

== Major revisions and restructuring needed ==
This book needs some fundamental restructuring and fixes. For example, i have found that it is incredibly difficult to learn without the presence of macrons, especially for first-time students with no prior knowledge of Latin whatsoever. Additionally, all of the cases should be introduced at once, not over a series of lessons. The page on the uses of the subjunctive is severely lacking. Use of linguistic terms in articles without defining them can confuse first-time foreign language learners. Frankly, this book is not of featured quality, in my opinion. It is incomplete and needs serious improvements.

Please offer your opinions. If I receive no feedback to the contrary within the next three days, I will begin a massive restructuring to the likes of that which I have described above. Thank you. [[User:Cuine|Cuine]] ([[User talk:Cuine|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Cuine|contribs]]) 01:05, 25 May 2011 (UTC)

: OMG, yes. I found the structure of the book perplexing, the sentences inconsistent, the vocabulary choices strange (I'd start with English-like ones first, and include English words derived from the Latin to make memorization easier), and the amount of information in the first parts overwhelming. I only say this because I've been studying Latin formally for three years, and have seen many, many examples of Latin grammars. --[[User:Robert.Baruch|Robert.Baruch]] ([[User talk:Robert.Baruch|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Robert.Baruch|contribs]]) 19:53, 14 June 2011 (UTC)

: Perhaps rather than a major restructuring, a new book should be written? --[[User:Robert.Baruch|Robert.Baruch]] ([[User talk:Robert.Baruch|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Robert.Baruch|contribs]]) 13:17, 15 June 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>cka7kgjfare95b9a3q1sgz0pg4h05hm</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Latin/Appendix F</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>967</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943300</id>
      <parentid>943298</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-08-15T12:47:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>205.206.115.53</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>ibid</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Common English abbreviations from Latin.

{| border=1
!Abbreviation!! Latin        !! Meaning    
|--------------------------------------------------
|A.D.        || anno dominī    || year of (our) lord
|--------------------------------------------------
|A.M.        || ante meridiem  || before noon     
|--------------------------------------------------
|C(a).        ||Circa  || Around(used in dates, as in c. 900)
|--------------------------------------------------
|cf.         || confer         || compare         
|--------------------------------------------------
|e.g.        || exemplī gratia || for example     
|--------------------------------------------------
|et al.      || et aliī        || and others      
|--------------------------------------------------
|etc.        || et cetera      || and so on       
|--------------------------------------------------
|Ibid.       || ibidem         || Same (in a footnote, when referring to the same source as the last footnote)
|--------------------------------------------------
|i.e.        || id est         || that is         
|--------------------------------------------------
|P.M.        || post meridiem  || after noon      
|--------------------------------------------------
|P.S.        || post scrīptum  || postscript      
|--------------------------------------------------
|q.e.d       || quod erat dēmōnstrandum || what was to be shown (Science)
|--------------------------------------------------
|q.v.        || quo vide       || which see (when referencing another article in an encyclopedia)
|--------------------------------------------------
|v. or vs.   || versus         || against         
|}



[[Category:Latin]]</text>
      <sha1>amzjgz5bl2aiehev5aqaicu6tcrmzob</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Latin/Authors</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>968</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2098826</id>
      <parentid>1701109</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-05-20T19:13:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Swfarnsworth</username>
        <id>324928</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>I rewrote some of the earlier chapters.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;!---
If you wish to be listed as an author here, please add your name to the bottom of the list, and if possible add a link to your user page as well.  This can be done quickly by using the following text:

#~~~  (using three tildes {~} characters is automatically processed by the MediaWiki software as your user name).
!---&gt;
Authors of the [[Latin]] Wikibook include the following contributors:
#[[User:swfarnsworth|Steele W. Farnsworth]]

and many anonymous Wikibooks contributors.

[[Category:Latin]]</text>
      <sha1>cq1hd0d9jrqrjinuk8uxo7ziskiu9xi</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Latin/Appendix E</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>979</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518197</id>
      <parentid>406356</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-07-11T20:24:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Latin]]
----
This page provides a list of Latin phrases and their English translations.

This page is copied from the [[en:Main Page|Wikipedia]] article [[en:List_of_Latin_phrases|List of Latin phrases]]. Check that page to see the latest changes to this page.
----

== A ==

:'''''A pedibus usque ad caput'''''
:&quot;From feet to head.&quot;

:'''''[[Ab urbe condita]]''''' or '''''Anno urbis conditae''''', abbreviated [[A.U.C.]]
:&quot;from [[founding of Rome|the founding]] of the city&quot; (of [[Rome]]);  [[753 BC|753 B.C.]], according to [[Livy|Livy's]] count; used as a reference point by the Romans for establishing dates, as we use A.D. today.

:'''''A bene placito'''''
:&quot;at your pleasure&quot;

:'''''Ad Calendas Graecas'''''
:&quot;To the Greek Kalends&quot;, ''i.e.'' &quot;to a date that does not (or will not) exist&quot; (Emperor [[Augustus]], in [[Suetonius]], in the sense of &quot;never&quot; - Kalends were part of the Roman calendar, not of the Greek, so it is used of a false or unlikely promise)

:'''''Ad captandum vulgus'''''
:&quot;To appeal to the crowd&quot; -- often used of politicians who make false or insincere promises appealing to popular interest.

:'''''[[Ad hoc]]'''''
:&quot;For a particular purpose (improvised, made up in an instant)&quot;

:'''''[[Ad hominem]]'''''
:&quot;To the man&quot;, meaning 1) an argument designed to appeal to personal interest rather than objective fact; 2) an argument criticizing one's opponent rather than his ideas.

:'''''Ad interim'''''
:&quot;in the meantime&quot;, as in the term &quot;chargé d'affaires ad interim&quot; for a diplomatic officer who acts in place of an ambassador

:'''''Ad infinitum'''''
:&quot;to infinity&quot;, going on forever

:'''''Ad libitum (ad lib)'''''
:&quot;Freely; at ease&quot;, just ramble

:'''''Ad majorem Dei gloriam'''''
:&quot;to the greater glory of God&quot;

:'''''Ad multos annos'''''
:&quot;To many years!&quot;, i.e. &quot;Many happy returns!&quot;

:'''''Ad nauseam'''''
:&quot;to the point of [[nausea]]&quot;

:'''''Ad valorem'''''
:&quot;by the value&quot;, e.g. ad valorem tax

:'''''Adde parvum parvo manus acervus erit.'''''
:&quot;Add little to little and there will be a big pile.&quot; [[Ovid]]

:'''''Alea iacta est'''''
:&quot;The die is cast&quot; ([[Julius Caesar]] in [[Suetonius]] uses it as an imperative &quot;Alea jacta esto&quot;: &quot;Let the die be cast&quot;)

:'''''Alma mater'''''
:&quot;nourishing mother&quot; - used for the university one has attended

:'''''Alter ego'''''
:&quot;Another self&quot; - usually refers to a [[pseudonym]] but can refer to another person.

:'''''A mari usque ad mare'''''
:&quot;From sea to sea&quot; - motto of [[Canada]]

:'''''Amicus curiae'''''
:'Friend of the court&quot; (adviser), a person who can obtain or grant access to the favour of powerful people (like [[Romana curia]]).  In current US legal usage, a brief submitted to the court by a third party.

:'''''Ante litteram'''''
:&quot;before the letter&quot;, a qualifier for an expression when applied to something that existed before the expression itself was introduced or became common. For example, one could say that [[Alan Turing]] was a computer scientist ''ante litteram'', since the profession of &quot;computer scientist&quot; was not recognised in Turing's day.

:'''''Ars gratia artis'''''
:&quot;Art for art's sake&quot; (motto of [[MGM]])

:'''''Ars longa, vita brevis'''''
:&quot;Art is long, life is short&quot;.  This is the [[Latin]] translation by [[Horace]] of a phrase from [[Hippocrates]], and is often used out of context. The ''art'' referred to in the original aphorism was the craft of medicine, which took a lifetime to acquire. 

:'''''Aurea mediocritas'''''
:&quot;Golden Mean&quot; (in [[Horace]], Odi, an ethical goal)

:'''''Ave atque vale'''''
:&quot;Hail and farewell!&quot;

----

== B ==

:'''''Bona fide'''''
:&quot;In [[good faith]]&quot; 

----

== C ==

:'''''Cacoethes scribendi'''''
:&quot;An insatiable urge to write.&quot;  From [[Juvenal]]

:'''''Carpe diem'''''
:&quot;Seize the day&quot; ([[Horace]] to Leuconoe: ''carpe diem, quam minimum credula postero'', reap the day, believing as little as possible in the morrow)

:'''''[[Casus belli]]'''''
:&quot;an event that causes or justifies war&quot;

:'''''Caveat emptor'''''
:&quot;Let the buyer beware&quot;, ''i.e.'' the onus of responsibility is on the purchaser of goods.

:'''''Cave canem'''''
:&quot;Beware of the dog&quot;

:'''''Ceteris paribus''''' : 
:&quot;All other things being equal&quot;

:'''''Christus Rex''''' :
:&quot;[[Jesus Christ|Christ]] the King&quot;

:'''''Circa'''''
:&quot;About, approximately, around&quot;, ''e.g.'' of a date: &quot;Jesus Christ was actually born ''circa'' 6 B.C.&quot;

:'''''[[Cogito ergo sum]]'''''
:&quot;I think, therefore I am&quot; ([[René Descartes]]) 

:'''''[[Compos mentis]]'''''
:&quot;Of sound mind&quot; (sometimes used rather humorously)

:'''''Conditio sine qua non'''''
:&quot;Condition without which not&quot;, or &quot;indispensable condition&quot;.

:'''''Corpus delicti'''''
:&quot;body of the crime&quot; - something that proves a crime

:'''''Cui bono'''''
:&quot;Whom does it benefit?&quot; - a maxim sometimes used in the detection of crime.

:'''''Cui prodest'''''
:&quot;Whom does it benefit?&quot; (short form for ''cui prodest scelus, is fecit'' in [[Seneca]]'s ''Medea'' - the murderer is the one who gains by the murder)

:'''''Cum grano salis'''''
:&quot;With a grain of salt&quot; (just a bit of wise attention)

:'''''Curriculum vitae'''''
:&quot;course of life&quot; - a résumé

----

== D ==

:'''''Damnant quod non intellegunt'''''
:&quot;They condemn what they do not understand.&quot;

:'''''[[De facto]]'''''
:&quot;in fact&quot;, &quot;in practice&quot;

:'''''[[De gustibus non disputandum est]]'''''
:&quot;there is no disputing matters of taste&quot;

:'''''[[De jure]]'''''
:&quot;by law&quot;

:'''''[[De minimis]] non curat [[praetor]]''''' (or ''rex'' or ''lex'')
:&quot;The authority&quot; (or &quot;king&quot;, or &quot;law&quot;) &quot;does not care about trivial things&quot;

:'''''De novo'''''
:&quot;Anew&quot;

:'''''[[Deus ex machina]]'''''
:&quot;A contrived or artificial solution&quot; (literally, &quot;a god from a machine&quot;). Refers to the practice in Greek drama of letting [[Zeus]] resolve awkward plots when a mechanical device would lower an actor playing Zeus onto the stage near the end of a play, as though he were descending from Olympus.)

:'''''Deus vult!'''''
:&quot;God wills it!&quot;  (Slogan of the [[Crusade]]s)

:'''''Divide et impera'''''
:&quot;Divide and govern&quot;, attributed to [[Philip II of Macedonia]] and meaning that if you encourage rivalries and jealousies among your people, you will rule them more easily

:'''''Dominus Illuminatio Mea'''''
:&quot;The Lord is my light&quot; (the motto of [[Oxford University]]).

:'''''Dum spiro, spero'''''
:&quot;As long as I breathe, I hope&quot; (also &quot;When I die, I hope&quot; - ''spiro'' means also 'I breathe the last breath')

:'''''Dura lex, sed lex'''''
:&quot;The law is harsh, but it is the law&quot;

----

== E ==

:'''''E pluribus unum'''''
:&quot;From many, one&quot; - the motto of the [[USA]].

:'''''Ecce homo'''''
:&quot;Behold the man!&quot; -- in the [[Gospel of John]] these words are spoken by [[Pilate]] as he presents [[Christ]] crowned with thorns to the crowd.

:'''''Emeritus'''''
:&quot;Honorary; by merit&quot;

:'''''Esto perpetua'''''
:&quot;Let it be everlasting&quot; -- used by the historian [[Fra Paolo Sarpi]] of his native Venice.

:'''''Et alii'''''
:&quot;And others&quot;, often written ''et al''. (''Alii'' strictly means &quot;male others&quot;, but is also used for groups of men and women; ''et aliae'' is used when the &quot;others&quot; are all female.)

:'''''Et cetera'''''
:&quot;And the other ones&quot;, also abbreviated as 'etc.' (nowadays used for &quot;and the rest&quot;)

:'''''[[Et in Arcadia ego]]'''''
:&quot;I, also, am in Arcadia&quot; (See ''[[List of Latin phrases#M|memento mori]]'')

:'''''Ex animo'''''
:&quot;From the heart&quot; (sincerely)

:'''''Ex ante'''''
:&quot;Before the event, beforehand&quot; (economics: based on prior assumptions)

:'''''[[Ex Cathedra]]'''''
:&quot;From the chair&quot; -- a phrase applied to the [[Pope]] when he is speaking infallibly and, by extension, to others who speak with supreme authority or arrogance.

:'''''Excelsior'''''
:&quot;Ever upward&quot;

:'''''Exempli gratia'''''
:&quot;For the sake of example&quot;, also abbreviated as 'e.g.'

:'''''Exeunt'''''
:See ''exit''.

:'''''Ex hypothesi'''''
:&quot;from the hypothesis&quot; (i.e. the one under consideration)

:'''''Exit'''''
:&quot;he / she leaves;&quot; '''''Exeunt omnes''''': they all leave

:'''''[[Ex libris]]...'''''
:&quot;From the books (library) of...&quot;

:'''''Ex nihilo nihil fit'''''
:&quot;Nothing comes from nothing&quot; - you need to work for something

:'''''Ex officio'''''
:&quot;From the office&quot; - when someone holds one position by virtue of holding another, e.g. the U.S. vice president is ex officio president of the Senate

:'''''Ex post facto'''''
:&quot;After the fact&quot; (also ''post facto'')

:'''''[[Extra Ecclesiam Nulla Salus]]'''''
:&quot;Outside the Church [there is] No Salvation&quot; -- a phrase of much disputed significance in [[Roman Catholicism|Roman Catholic]] [[theology]].

----

== F ==

:'''''Fiat justitia (et ruat c&amp;aelig;lum)'''''
:&quot;Let justice be done (though the heavens fall)&quot;

:'''''Fidei Defensor'''''
:&quot;Defender of the Faith&quot; -- a title given to [[Henry VIII]] of England by Pope [[Leo X]] before Henry became an [[heresiarch]].

:'''''Fons et origo'''''
:&quot;The wellspring and origin&quot;

----

== G ==


:'''''Genius loci'''''
:&quot;the spirit of the place&quot;

:'''''Gloria in excelsis Deo'''''
:&quot;glory to God in the highest&quot;

----

== H ==

:'''''[[Habeas corpus]]'''''
:&quot;You must have the body&quot;, i.e. you must justify an imprisonment. (From the Writ to bring a prisoner to court - [[Charles II of England]], Habeas corpus Act - 1679)

:'''''Habemus papam'''''
:&quot;We have a pope&quot; - used at the announcement of a new pope (see [[conclave]])

:'''''Hic jacet...'''''
:&quot;Here lies....&quot; -- written on gravestones or tombs.

:'''''Honoris causa''''' (h.c.)
:as in &quot;doctorate h.c.&quot;, an honorary degree

:'''''Horribile dictu'''''
:&quot;Horrible to tell&quot;

----

== I ==

:'''''Imperium in imperio'''''
:&quot;An empire within an empire,&quot; i.e. a [[fifth column]], a group of people within an nation's territory who owe allegiance to some other leader.

:'''''In absentia'''''
:&quot;in the absence&quot; (of a defendant in court)

:'''''Infinitus est numerus stultorum''''' 
:&quot;Infinite is the number of fools&quot; [[Ecclesiastes]] 1:15 (Vulgate)

:'''''In flagrante delicto'''''
:&quot;In flaming crime,&quot; i.e. &quot;red-handed&quot; -nowadays used when you are in found in a compromising situation with a sexual partner

:'''''In memoriam'''''
:&quot;In memory of&quot;

:'''''[[In necessariis unitas, in dubiis libertas, in omnibus caritas]]'''''
:&quot;In necessary things unity, in doubtful things liberty, in all things charity&quot; -- a [[theology|theological]] phrase often misattributed to [[Augustine of Hippo|St Augustine]].

:'''''In situ'''''
:&quot;In place&quot;; in the original location and environment.

:'''''In toto'''''
:&quot;In total&quot; (altogether)

:'''''In vino veritas'''''
:&quot;Drink brings out the truth&quot; (literally, &quot;in wine, truth&quot;)

:'''''Incredibile dictu'''''
:&quot;Incredible to say&quot;

:'''''Ipso facto'''''
:&quot;By the fact itself&quot;

:'''''Iunctis viribus'''''
:&quot;By united efforts&quot;

:'''''Ius primae noctis'''''
:&quot;Right of the first night&quot; - [[droit de seigneur]]

----

== L ==

:'''''Labor omnia vincit'''''
:&quot;Labor conquers all&quot;

:'''''Lapsus calami'''''
:&quot;A slip of the pen&quot;

:'''''Lapsus linguae'''''
:&quot;A slip of the tongue&quot;

:'''''Lapsus memoriae'''''
:&quot;Memory lapse&quot;

:'''''[[lorem ipsum]]'''''
:A fragment of Latin from [[Cicero]], used as filler by copy editors.

----

== M ==

:'''''Magna cum laude'''''
:&quot;With great honor&quot;

:'''''Magnum opus'''''
:&quot;Masterpiece&quot; (great work); also ironically.

:'''''Mala fide'''''
:&quot;In bad faith&quot; -- aomething which is done fraudulently.

:'''''[[Malum in se]]'''''
:&quot;Wrong in itself&quot; a crime that is inherently wrong, as opposed to ''malum prohibitum''.

:'''''Malum prohibitum'''''
:&quot;A prohibited wrong&quot; a crime that society decides is wrong for some reason, not inherently evil.

:'''''Mea (maxima) culpa'''''
:&quot;By my own (very great) fault&quot; -- used in Christian prayers and confession.

:'''''[[Memento mori]]'''''
:&quot;Remember that you will die.&quot; 

:'''''Mirabile dictu'''''
:&quot;Wonderful to tell&quot;

:'''''Modus operandi'''''
:&quot;way of working&quot; - usually used to describe a criminal's methods, often abbreviated M.O.

:'''''Modus vivendi'''''
:&quot;way of life&quot; - an accommodation between disagreeing parties

:'''''Multum in parvo'''''
:&quot;Much in little&quot; -- e.g. &quot;Latin phrases are often ''multum in parvo'', because they convey much in few words.&quot;

:'''''Mutatis mutandis'''''
:&quot;The necessary changes having been made.&quot;

----

== N ==

:'''''Nemo me impune lacessit'''''
:&quot;No-one provokes me with impunity&quot; -- a famous [[Scotland|Scottish]] motto.

:'''''Nolens (aut) volens'''''
:&quot;Willing or not&quot;

:'''''Noli me tangere'''''
:&quot;Touch me not&quot; -- according to the [[Gospel of John]], this was said by Christ to [[Mary Magdalene]] after the [[Resurrection of Jesus Christ|Resurrection]].

:'''''[[Non compos mentis]]''''' or '''''Non compos sui'''''
:&quot;Of unsound mind&quot;

:'''''[[Non sequitur]]'''''
:Statement that doesn't follow logic (Literally, &quot;It does not follow.&quot;)

:'''''[[Non serviam]]'''''
:&quot;I will not serve&quot;

:'''''Nosce te ipsum'''''
:&quot;Know thyself&quot;

:'''''Nota bene'''''
:&quot;note it well&quot; - an important note

----

== O ==

:'''''[[Oderint dum metuant]]'''''
:&quot;Let them hate, so long as they fear.&quot;  Attributed by [[Seneca]] to the [[playwright]] [[Lucius Accius]], and said to be a favourite saying of [[Caligula]]'s. 

:'''''Odi et amo'''''
:&quot;I hate (her), and I love (her).&quot;  From [[Catullus]]

:'''''[[Odium theologicum]]'''''
:&quot;Theological hatred&quot; -- a special name for the hatred generated in [[theology|theological]] disputes.

:'''''Ora et labora'''''
:&quot;Pray and work&quot; - [[Benedictine]] motto

----

== P ==

:'''''[[Pacta sunt servanda]]'''''
:&quot;agreements must be honoured&quot;

:'''''Parens patriae'''''
:&quot;Parent of the country&quot; 

:'''''Pari passu'''''
:&quot;With equal step&quot; - moving together

:'''''Parturiunt montes, nascetur ridiculus mus'''''
:A line from [[Horace]]: &quot;The mountains are in labour, and a ridiculous mouse shall be born&quot; (i.e. much ado about nothing).

:'''''[[pater familias]]'''''
:&quot;father of the family&quot;

:'''''Pax tecum'''''
:&quot;Peace be with you (singular)&quot;

:'''''Pax vobiscum'''''
:&quot;Peace be with you (plural)&quot;

:'''''Per annum'''''
:&quot;Per year&quot;

:'''''Per ardua ad astra''''' or '''''Per aspera ad astra'''''
:&quot;Through hardship to the stars,&quot; motto of the [[Royal Air Force]].

:'''''Per caput, per capita'''''
:&quot;Per person&quot; (literally, &quot;by head(s)&quot;)

:'''''Per se'''''
:&quot;By or in itself, without referring to anything else, intrinsically&quot;, see for instance [[negligence per se]]

:'''''Perpetuum mobile'''''
:something in [[perpetual motion]]

:'''''Petitio principii'''''
:&quot;[[begging the question]]&quot;

:'''''Post hoc, ergo propter hoc'''''
:&quot;After this, therefore because of this&quot; (a [[fallacy]]).

:'''''Post mortem'''''
:&quot;after death&quot;

:'''''Primum non nocere'''''
:&quot;First, do no harm&quot;

:'''''Principiis obsta'''''
:&quot;Resist the beginnings&quot; 

:'''''Pro bono publico'''''
:&quot;For the public good&quot; - a [[lawyer]]'s work is said to be ''pro bono'' if he does not charge for it.

:'''''Pro rata'''''
:&quot;For the rate&quot; (per hour for example)

:'''''Pro tempore'''''
:&quot;For the time being&quot; 

:'''''Persona non grata'''''
:&quot;Person not wanted&quot; 

:'''''Pulvis et umbra sumus'''''
:&quot;We are dust and shadow&quot; --- from [[Horace]]

----

== Q ==

:'''''Qu&amp;aelig;re'''''
:&quot;(You might) ask. . .&quot;  Used to introduce questions, usually rhetorical or tangential questions.

:'''''Quid pro quo'''''
:&quot;A thing for a thing&quot;, i.e. a favor for a favor.

:'''''Quidnunc?''''' or '''''Quid nunc?'''''
:&quot;What now?&quot;  As a noun, a ''quidnunc'' is a busybody or a gossip.  

:'''''Quis custodiet ipsos custodies?'''''
:A line from [[Juvenal]]: &quot;Who will watch the watchmen?&quot;

:'''''Quieta non movere'''''
:&quot;Don't move settled things&quot;, or: &quot;Don't rock the boat.&quot;

:'''''Quod erat demonstrandum''''', abbreviated as [[Q.E.D.]]
:&quot;that which was to be demonstrated.&quot;  This abbreviation is often written at the bottom of a completed proof.

:'''''Quo vadis'''''
:&quot;Where are you going?&quot; (according to [[Christian]] legend, [[St. Peter]] meeting [[Jesus]] on the [[Appian way]] in [[Rome]] asks: &quot;[[Quo vadis|Quo vadis, Domine?]]&quot;, or &quot;Where goest thou, Lord?&quot;) 

----

== R ==

:'''''Rara avis'''''
:&quot;A rare bird&quot;, i.e. an extraodinary or unusual thing (from [[Juvenal]]'s ''Satires'': ''rara avis in terris nigroque simillima cycno'', &quot;a rare bird on the earth, and very like a black swan&quot;.)

:'''''Regnat populus'''''
:&quot;Let the People rule&quot;

:'''''Requiescat in pace''''' (RIP)
:&quot;Rest in peace&quot;

:'''''[[Res ipsa loquitur]]'''''
:&quot;the thing speaks for itself;&quot; a phrase from the [[common law]] of [[tort]]s that refers to situations when it's assumed that a person's injury was caused by the negligent action of another party because the accident was the sort that wouldn't occur unless someone was negligent. 



:'''''Risus abundat in ore stultorum'''''
:&quot;Abundant laughs in the mouth of the foolish&quot; - too much hilarity means foolishness

:'''''Rosa rubicundior, lilio candidior, omnibus formosior, semper in te glorior'''''
:&quot;Redder than the rose, whiter than the lilies, fairer than everything, I will always glory in thee.&quot;

----

== S ==

:'''''Salus populi suprema lex esto'''''
:&quot;Let the good of the people be the supreme law&quot;

:'''''Salva veritate'''''
:&quot;With truth preserved&quot;

:'''''Sapere aude'''''
:&quot;Dare to be wise&quot;

:'''''Semper fidelis'''''
:&quot;Always faithful&quot;

:'''''Semper paratus'''''
:&quot;Always prepared&quot;

:'''''Sic'''''
:&quot;Thus&quot;, &quot;just so&quot;.  Used to state that quoted material appears exactly that way in the source, usually despite errors of spelling, grammar, usage, or fact.

:'''''Sic semper tyrannis'''''
:&quot;Thus always to tyrants&quot; -- Motto of the American state of [[Virginia]] and said to have been shouted by [[John Wilkes Booth]] after the assassination of [[Abraham Lincoln]].

:'''''Sic transit gloria mundi'''''
:&quot;Thus passes the glory of the world&quot;

:'''''SPQR''''' or '''''Senatus Populusque Romanus'''''
:&quot;The Senate and the People of Rome&quot; -- &quot;SPQR&quot; was carried on battle standards by the [[Legion]]s.

:'''''Status quo'''''
:&quot;Existing state of affairs&quot; (from &quot;statu quo ante&quot;, prior or current situation)

:'''''Sub iudice''''' (or '''''Sub judice''''')
:&quot;under a judge&quot;, i.e. a case that cannot be publicly discussed until it is finished.

:'''''[[subpoena|Sub poena]]'''''
:&quot;under penalty&quot;, ''i.e.'' on pain of punishment

:'''''Sub rosa'''''
:&quot;under the rose,&quot; secretly (a rose was placed above a door to indicate that what was said in the room beyond was not to be repeated outside)

:'''''[[sui generis]]'''''
:literally meaning ''of its own gender/genus''

:'''''Summa cum laude'''''
:&quot;With the highest honor&quot;

:'''''Summum bonum'''''
:&quot;The supreme good&quot;

:'''''Sutor, ne ultra crepidam'''''
:&quot;Cobbler, no further than (your competence on) the sandal&quot; -- It is said that [[Greece|Greek]] [[painter]] [[Apelles]] was one day painting a warrior but he was uncertain on how to render his sandals (''crepida''). He asked the advice of a cobbler (''sutor''), but after a time the cobbler started offering advice on other parts of the painting and was rebuked by Apelles with this phrase (but in [[Greek language|Greek]]).

----

== T ==

:'''''Tabula rasa'''''
:&quot;A scraped slate&quot; (Romans used to write on wax tablets, easy to erase).

:'''''Terra firma'''''
:&quot;Solid ground&quot;

:'''''Terra incognita'''''
:&quot;Unknown land&quot;

:'''''Tu autem'''''
:&quot;You, also.&quot; (See ''[[List of Latin phrases#M|memento mori]]'')

----

== U ==

:'''''Ubi mel ibi apes'''''
:&quot;Where honey, there bees&quot;, i.e., if you want support, you must offer something in return.

:'''''Ubi revera''''' or '''''Ubi re vera'''''
:&quot;When, in reality...&quot;

:'''''Ultima ratio'''''
:&quot;last reason&quot; - the last resort

:'''''Urbi et orbi'''''
:&quot;to the city [Rome] and to the globe&quot; - a blessing of the pope

----

== V ==

:'''''Vade mecum'''''
:&quot;Come with me.&quot; A vade-mecum is an item one carries around, especially a handbook.

:'''''Veni, vidi, vici'''''
:&quot;I came, I saw, I conquered&quot; ([[Julius Cesar]] describing his campaign in ''De Bello Gallico'')

:'''''Via'''''
:&quot;By way of&quot;

:'''''Via media'''''
:&quot;Middle path&quot;, often used of the [[Church of England]], which was said to be a ''via media'' between the errors of [[Roman Catholicism]] and extreme [[Protestantism]].

:'''''Vice versa'''''
:&quot;A reverse of order or meaning&quot;

:'''''Vivat, crescat, floreat!'''''
:&quot;May he/she/it live, grow, and flourish!&quot;

:'''''Vivat Rex!/Vivat Regina!'''''
:&quot;Long live the King!/Long live the Queen!&quot;

:'''''Volenti non fit iniuria.'''''
:&quot;A person who consents does not suffer injustice.&quot;

from [[en:Main Page|Wikipedia]], the Free encyclopedia.
----
[[Latin|^ Latin ^]]

[[Category:Latin]]</text>
      <sha1>5gpi2ouc8ae6v1uh034w152mbqt52ql</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Latin/Lesson 5-Accusative</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>980</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2559814</id>
      <parentid>2557951</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-09-23T18:42:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Recent Runes</username>
        <id>66908</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/208.122.107.254|208.122.107.254]] ([[User talk:208.122.107.254|talk]]) to last version by Herr Beethoven</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Latin}}



== Exercises ==
{{Latin/Exercise|Give the accusative singular.|
Give the accusative singular for:

# lud-us
# magn-us
# triclīni-um
# bell-um
# puell-a
# serv-us
# ager
|
# lud'''um'''
# magn'''um'''
# triclīni'''um'''
# bell'''um'''
# puell'''am'''
# serv'''um'''
# agr'''um'''
}}

{{Latin/Exercise|Give the accusative plural.|
Give the accusative plural for:

# lud-us
# magn-us
# triclīni-um
# bell-um
# puell-a
# serv-us
# ager
|
# lud'''os'''
# magn'''os'''
# triclīni'''a'''
# bell'''a'''
# puell'''as'''
# serv'''os'''
# agr'''os'''
}}

{{Latin/Exercise|Give the nominative singular.|
Give the nominative singular for:

# bon-ī
# bell-a
# triclīni-a
# puell-am
# agr-ōs
# serv-ōs
# puell-ae
|
# bon'''us'''
# bell'''um'''
# triclīni'''um'''
# puell'''a'''
# ager
# serv'''us'''
# puell'''a'''
}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot;
|-
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; | &lt;b&gt;Lesson Vocabulary&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | &lt;font face=&quot;Arial&quot; size=&quot;4&quot;&gt;Latin&lt;/font&gt;
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | &lt;font face=&quot;Arial&quot; size=&quot;4&quot;&gt;English&lt;/font&gt;
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''vendit'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''he/she sells'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''videt'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''he/she sees'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''amat'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''he/she loves'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''cist-a -ae''' (f.)
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''box'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''ferox, ferocis''' (m/f.)
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''wild'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''ager''' (m.)
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''field'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''bell-um''' (n.)
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''war'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''serv-us''' (m.)
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''slave'''
|}

== Grammar: The Accusative ==

As you learned in the last lesson, the verb 'esse' (to be) usually takes the nominative case, because then the word after it is a complement.  Most other verbs take the 'accusative' case. 

In a sentence, the accusative is the &quot;what&quot; - in English grammar, this is known as the direct object.

&lt;b&gt;For example:&lt;/b&gt;
The girl sells the box.

What did the girl sell? The box. Thus, box is the direct object, and when we translate it into Latin:

{| cellpadding=&quot;2&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; | '''Example'''
|-
| ''English:'' || The girl|| sells|| the box.
|-
| ''Latin:'' || Puella|| vendit|| cistam.
|-
| ''Explanation:'' || NOMINATIVE || VERB
| ACCUSATIVE
|}

Cistam, then, is in the accusative, because it is the direct object.

Again, when an adjective describes a noun in the accusative case, the adjective must agree in number, case, and gender.

{| cellpadding=&quot;2&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
| colspan=&quot;5&quot; | '''Example'''
|-
| ''English:'' || The girl|| sells|| the big || box.
|-
| ''Latin:'' || Puella|| vendit|| magnam || cistam.
|-
| ''Explanation:'' || NOMINATIVE || VERB || ADJECTIVE ACCUSATIVE|| NOUN ACCUSATIVE
|}

Because Latin uses cases to mark the subject and the object of a sentence, word order does not matter. Consider:

{| cellpadding=&quot;2&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
| puer puellam videt || The boy sees the girl
|-
| puerum puella videt || The girl sees the boy
|-
| puellam puer videt || The boy sees the girl
|-
| puella puerum videt || The girl sees the boy
|}

== Examples of Adjectives Agreeing with the Nominative and Accusative Case ==

{| cellpadding=&quot;2&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
| colspan=&quot;6&quot; | '''Explanation'''- The ''good'' boy loves the ''wild'' dog.
|-
| ''Latin:'' || puer || '''bonus''' || amat || canem (acc) || '''ferocem''' (acc).
|-
| ''English:'' || [The] boy || '''good''' || [he] loves || [the] dog || '''wild'''. 
|}

''Bonus'', a first and second declension adjective, is masculine, nominative, and singular to agree with ''puer'', the word it is describing.

''Ferocem'', a third declension adjective, is masculine, accusative, and singular to agree with ''canem''. ''Canem'' is accusative because it is the object of ''amat''.

Here is an example of plural adjectives:

{| cellpadding=&quot;2&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
| colspan=&quot;6&quot; | '''Explanation'''- The ''good'' boys love the ''wild'' dogs.
|-
| ''Latin:'' || Pueri (plur) || '''boni''' (plur)|| amant (plur) || canes (plur, acc) || '''feroces''' (plur, acc).
|-
| ''English:'' || [The] boys || '''good''' || [they] love || [the] dogs || '''wild'''. 
|}

The words  ''bonus'' and ''ferocem'' become ''boni'' and ''feroces'' to agree with the plurals ''pueri'' and ''canes''.

However, if a girl ([[wiktionary:en:puella#Latin|puella]]) happened to love that boy:

{| cellpadding=&quot;2&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
| colspan=&quot;6&quot; | '''Explanation'''- The ''good'' girl loves the ''good'' boy.
|-
| ''Latin:'' || Puella || '''bona'''|| amat || puerum (acc) || '''bonum''' (acc).
|-
| ''English:'' || [The] girl|| '''good''' || [she] loves || [the] boy|| '''good'''. 
|}

''Bonus'' must become ''bona'' in order to modify ''puella'', which is feminine.

Finally, if the girl isn't good, but rather wild:

{| cellpadding=&quot;2&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
| colspan=&quot;6&quot; | '''Explanation'''- The ''wild'' girl loves the ''good'' boy.
|-
| ''Latin:'' || Puella || '''ferox'''|| amat || puerum (acc) || '''bonum''' (acc).
|-
| ''English:'' || [The] girl|| '''wild''' || [she] loves || [the] boy|| '''good'''. 
|}

Even though ''puella'' is first declension, ''ferox'' remains third declension. In the same way, a good lion would be ''bonus leo''.

== Exercise 3 ==

Determine whether the adjective agrees with the substantive in all three categories: case, gender, number.


{| border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! Questions:
! Does it Agree?
|-
| 1. magn-us agr-ōs || True/False
|-
| 2. magn-a puella || True/False
|-
| 3. poet-a* bon-us || True/False
|-
| 4. magn-um serv-um || True/False
|-
| 5. poet-ae* magn-ae || True/False
|-
| 6. bell-a magn-a || True/False
|}

:''* Nota bene: ''Poeta'' (meaning poet) is a masculine noun, even though it ends in '''-a'''.''

{{Latin/Exercise|Answer|
See table above. Determine whether the adjective (magnus, bonus..) agrees with the substantives (ager, puella, poeta) in both case (nominative, accusative...), gender (masculine, female and neuter) and number (singular and plural).
|
# '''False.''' ''Magnus'' doesn't agree with ''agrōs''; in number and case.
#:''Magnus'': Masculine, singular, nominative.
#:''Agrōs'': Masculine, plural, accusative.
# '''True.''' ''Magna'' agrees with ''puella''.
#:''Magna'': Feminine, singular, nominative.
#:''Puella'': Feminine, singular, nominative.
# '''True.''' ''Bonus'' agrees with ''poeta''.
#:''Bonus'': Masculine, singular, nominative.
#:''Poeta'': Masculine, singular, nominative.
# '''True.''' ''Magnum'' agrees with ''servum''.
#:''Magnum'': Neuter, singular, nominative.
#:''Servum'': Neuter, singular, nominative.
# '''False.''' ''Magnae'' doesn't agree with ''poetae''; in gender.
#:''Magnae'': Feminine, plural, nominative.
#:''Poetae'': Masculine, plural, nominative.
# '''True.''' ''Bella'' agrees with ''magna''.
#:''Bella'': Neuter, plural, nominative.
#:''Magna'': Neuter, plural, nominative.
}}

==Grammar: The Use of the Accusative==


{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot;
|-
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; | &lt;b&gt;Lesson Vocabulary&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | &lt;font face=&quot;Arial&quot; size=&quot;4&quot;&gt;Latin&lt;/font&gt;
! bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | &lt;font face=&quot;Arial&quot; size=&quot;4&quot;&gt;English&lt;/font&gt;
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''curri-t'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''he/she runs'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''porta-t'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''he/she carries'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''specta-t'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''he/she watches'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | '''da-t'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | '''he/she gives'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | &lt;B&gt;fuisse&lt;/B&gt;&lt;BR&gt;fuī&lt;BR&gt;fuistī&lt;BR&gt;(puer) fuit&lt;BR&gt;fuimus&lt;BR&gt;fuistis&lt;BR&gt;fuērunt
| align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFCC&quot; | &lt;B&gt;to have been&lt;/B&gt;&lt;BR&gt;I have been&lt;BR&gt;you have been&lt;BR&gt;(the boy) has been&lt;BR&gt;we have been&lt;BR&gt;you (pl.) have been&lt;BR&gt;they have been
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; | Nota Bene: 'fuisse' and all the forms of it, the past tense of 'esse', behaves exactly like the present tense.
|}


The newly introduced verbs, ama-t, curri-t, and porta-t take the accusative as the 'object'.  Unless specified, any verb you look up in the dictionary will take the accusative, not the nominative. This means that they are '''transitive verbs''', verbs that happen to someone or something, e.g.:

 I heal '''you'''. (''acc.'')
 You make '''my day'''. (''acc.'')
 She hit '''your arm'''. (''acc.'')

In the examples above, the '''bold''' words are the subject of the sentence clause. Because something happens &quot;to&quot; them, they can't be in nominative.

==Grammatical Explanation Using English Sentences==


{| cellpadding=&quot;2&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; | '''Grammatical Explanation 1'''
|-
| ''English:'' || The boy || hits || the car.
|-
| ''Explanation:'' || NOMINATIVE || VERB
| ACCUSATIVE
|}


{| cellpadding=&quot;2&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; | '''Grammatical Explanation 2'''
|-
| ''English:'' || The girl || hugs || the boy.
|-
| ''Explanation:'' || NOMINATIVE || VERB
| ACCUSATIVE
|}


{| cellpadding=&quot;2&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
| colspan=&quot;5&quot; | '''Grammatical Explanation 3'''
|-
| ''English:'' || He who || flees, || deserves || the guillotine.
|-
| ''Explanation:'' || NOMINATIVE || VERB
| VERB || ACCUSATIVE
|}

=== Exercise 4: Find the Nominative and Accusative ===
{{Latin/Exercise|Find the Nominative and Accusative (if present) in each the sentence.|
Find the Nominative and Accusative (if present) in each the sentence.

# The boy is good.
# The girl kisses the boy.
# The boy gives the book.
# The child watches the TV.
# Whom it concerns.
# To the kitchen I run
# I eat the pizza.
|
# The boy {nom} is good {nom}.
#: ''Puer {nom} est bonus {nom}''.
# The girl {nom} kisses the boy {acc}.
#: ''Puella {nom} puerum {acc} basiat.''
# The boy {nom} gives the book {acc}.
#: ''Puer {nom} librum {acc} dat.''
# The child {nom} watches the TV {acc}.
#: ''Infans {nom} televisorium {acc} videt.''
# Whom {acc} it {nom} concerns.
#: ''???''
# To the kitchen {acc} I {nom} run.
#: ''Ad culinam {acc} [ego {nom}] curro.
# I {nom} eat the pizza {acc}.
#:''Pittam {acc} [ego {nom}] edo.''
}}

{{Latin/Exercise|In the following sentences, identify the accusative and nominative. Then translate.|
In the following sentences, identify the accusative and nominative. Then translate.

# Puer est bonus.
# Puella puerum amat..
# Puer cistam portat.
# Fīlius virum spectat.
# Ad culīnam currit.
|
# Puer {nom} est bonus {nom}.
#: The boy {nom} is good {nom}.
# Puella {nom} puerum {acc} amat.
#: The girl {nom} loves the boy {acc}.
# Puer {nom} cistam {acc} portat.
#: The boy {nom} carries the box {acc}.
# Fīlius {nom} virum {acc} spectat.
#: The son {nom} watched the husband {acc}.
# Ad culīnam {acc} currit.
#: To the kitchen {acc} [he {nom}] runs.
}}


[[Category:Latin]]</text>
      <sha1>smldm6dzy14v386ka29t7blccuf7oid</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>English in Use/Nouns</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>982</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2674856</id>
      <parentid>2606320</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-06-19T01:35:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>137.111.13.200</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Individual nouns */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{English in Use}}
----

:''This page is written in English, and therefore needs to be translated at a later date to other languages for it to become more useful.''
{| class=&quot;toccolours&quot; style=&quot;float:right; margin:0 1em 0.5em 1em; clear:right; width:35%;&quot;
! style=&quot;{{#if:#ffffaa|background:#ffffaa;}} padding: 3px 5px 3px 5px; font-size:larger;&quot; | '''Examples'''
|-
| style=&quot;font-size:100% !important; padding:0 5px 0 5px;&quot; | 
*'''Janet''' is the '''name''' of a '''girl'''.
*'''Apple''' is a '''fruit''' and a computer '''company'''.
In the above sentence, &quot;computer&quot; is an adjective because it is describing &quot;company&quot;.
*'''Cleanliness''' is next to '''Godliness'''.
*The '''World Wide Web''' has become the least expensive '''way''' to publish '''information'''. 
|}

A '''noun''', or '''noun substantive''', is a part of speech (a word or phrase)  which functions as the head of a noun phrase. The word &quot;noun&quot; derives from the Latin ''nomen'' meaning &quot;name&quot;, and a traditional definition of nouns is that they are only those expressions that refer to a person, place, thing, event, substance, quality, or idea. They serve as the subject or object of a verb and as the governed term of a preposition, and can co-occur with articles and attributive adjectives.

There are different groups of nouns:

*'''Common nouns'''&amp;mdash;&quot;''chair''&quot;,
*'''Proper nouns'''&amp;mdash;&quot;''Fred''&quot;,
*'''Abstract nouns'''&amp;mdash;&quot;''love''&quot;,
*'''Collective nouns'''&amp;mdash;&quot;''gaggle''&quot;,
*'''Compound nouns'''&amp;mdash;&quot;''butterfly''&quot;,
*'''Verbal nouns'''&amp;mdash;&quot;''triumphing''&quot;.

Each of these different groups of nouns has different properties, each making them different in how we use them.

Thus, nouns are names of objects, places, people and things. They are used with adjectives to describe something, and with verbs to show an action.


==Concrete nouns==

Concrete nouns are proper nouns and common nouns.

===Proper nouns===

'''Proper nouns''' are the names of people, places, groups or dates: as, ''Adam'', ''Boston'', ''the Hudson'', ''the Romans'', ''the Azores'', ''the Alps''. They almost always have a capital letter as their first letter. Example:

*&quot;''Timmy'' is not someone to be toyed with.&quot;No one likes to hear other people boast their talents

===Common nouns===

'''Common nouns''' are the names of a sort, kind, or class, of beings or things: as, ''beast'', ''bird'', ''fish'', ''insect'', ''creatures'', ''persons'', ''children''. They often refer to objects or things which we can see, touch and feel, like the word ''chair''. Example:

*&quot;I sat at the ''table''.&quot;

====Individual nouns====
Their refer to only one thing of the same kind, for eg: man, player, cow, chicken, minister.

====Collective nouns====

'''Collective nouns''' are the names of a groups of objects or many individuals together: as, ''council'', ''meeting'', ''committee'', ''flock''. Example:

*&quot;They are a ''group''.&quot;

==Abstract nouns== 

'''Abstract nouns''' are the names of some particular qualities considered apart from its substance: as, ''goodness'', ''hardness'', ''pride'', ''frailty''. They are often names of the things that we cannot touch or see, but are there all the same. Example:

*&quot;I think I've fallen in ''love''!&quot;

===Attribute===

===Verbal nouns===

'''Verbal nouns''' or '''participial nouns''' are the names of some actions, or states of being; and are formed from a verb, like a participle, but employed as a noun: as,

*&quot;The ''triumphing'' of the wicked is short.&quot;&amp;mdash;Job, XX, 5.

===Sui generis===

A thing '''sui generis''', (i.e., of its own peculiar kind,) is something which is distinguished, not as an individual of a species, but as a sort by itself, without plurality in either the noun or the sort of thing: as, ''galvanism'', ''music'', ''geometry''.

==Words and word groups used as nouns==

===Adjectives made nouns===

*&quot;The Ancient of days did sit.&quot;&amp;mdash;''Bible''.
*&quot;Of the ancients.&quot;&amp;mdash;''Swift''.
*&quot;For such impertinents.&quot;&amp;mdash;''Steele''.
*&quot;He is an ignorant in it.&quot;&amp;mdash;''Id''.
*&quot;In the luxuriance of an unbounded picturesque.&quot;&amp;mdash;''Jamieson''.
*&quot;A source of the sublime;&quot;&amp;mdash;''Burke''.
*&quot;The vast immense of space:&quot;&amp;mdash;''Murray''.
*&quot;There is none his like.&quot;&amp;mdash;''Job, XLI, 33''.
*&quot;A little more than a little, is by much too much.&quot;&amp;mdash;''Shakespeare''.
*&quot;And gladly make much of that entertainment.&quot;&amp;mdash;''Sidney''.
*&quot;A covetous man makes the most of what he has.&quot;&amp;mdash;''L'Estrange''.
*&quot;It has done enough for me.&quot;&amp;mdash;''Pope''.
*&quot;He had enough to do.&quot;&amp;mdash;''Bacon''.
*&quot;All withers here; who most possess, are losers by their gain, stung by full proof, that bad at best, life's idle all is vain.&quot;&amp;mdash;''Young''.
*&quot;Nor grudge I you the much the Grecians give, nor murmuring take the little I receive.&quot;&amp;mdash;''Dryden''.

===Pronouns made nouns===

*&quot;A love of seeing the what and how of all about him.&quot;&amp;mdash;Story's Life of Flaxman: Pioneer, Vol. i, p. 133.
*&quot;The nameless he, whose nod is Nature's birth.&quot;&amp;mdash;Young, Night iv.
*&quot;I was wont to load my she with knacks.&quot;&amp;mdash;Shak. Winter's Tale.
*&quot;Or any he, the proudest of your sort.&quot;&amp;mdash;Shak.
*&quot;I am the happiest she in Kent.&quot;&amp;mdash;Steele.
*&quot;The shes of Italy.&quot;&amp;mdash;Shak.
*&quot;The hes in birds.&quot;&amp;mdash;Bacon.
*&quot;We should soon have as many hes and shes as the French.&quot;&amp;mdash;Cobbet's E. Gram., Para. 42.
*&quot;If, for instance, we call a nation a she, or the sun a he.&quot;&amp;mdash;Ib., Para. 198.
*&quot;When I see many its in a page, I always tremble for the writer.&quot;&amp;mdash;Ib., Para. 196.
*&quot;Let those two questionary petitioners try to do this with their whos and their whiches.&quot;&amp;mdash;Spect: Ash's Gr., p. 131.
*&quot;Such mortal drugs I have; but Mantua's law is death to any he that utters them.&quot;&amp;mdash;Shak.

===Verbs made nouns===

*&quot;Avaunt all attitude, and stare, and start theatric.&quot;&amp;mdash;Cowper.
*&quot;A may-be of mercy is sufficient.&quot;&amp;mdash;Bridge.
*&quot;Which cuts are reckoned among the fractures.&quot;&amp;mdash;Wiseman.
*&quot;The officer erred in granting a permit.&quot;
*&quot;Feel darts and charms, attracts and flames.&quot;&amp;mdash;Hudibras.
*&quot;You may know by the falling off of the come, or sprout.&quot;&amp;mdash;Mortimer.
*&quot;And you have talked of sallies and retires.&quot;&amp;mdash;Shak.
*&quot;For all that else did come, were sure to fail; yet would he further none, but for avail.&quot;&amp;mdash;Spenser.

===Participles made nouns (gerunds)===

*&quot;For the producing of real happiness.&quot;&amp;mdash;Crabb.
*&quot;For the crying of the poor and the sighing of the needy, I will arise.&quot;&amp;mdash;Bible.
*&quot;Surely the churning of milk brings forth butter, and the wringing of the nose brings forth blood; so the forcing of wrath brings forth strife.&quot;&amp;mdash;Prov., xxx, 33.
*&quot;Reading, writing, and ciphering, are indispensable to civilized man.&quot;
*&quot;Hence was invented the distinction between doing and permitting.&quot;&amp;mdash;Calvin's Inst., p. 131.
*&quot;Knowledge of the past comes next.&quot;&amp;mdash;Hermes, p. 113.
*&quot;I am my beloved's, and his desire is toward me.&quot;&amp;mdash;Sol. Song, vii, 10.
*&quot;Here's&amp;mdash;a simple coming-in for one man.&quot;&amp;mdash;Shak.
*&quot;What are your rents? What are your comings-in? O Ceremony, show me but your worth.&quot;&amp;mdash;Id.

===Adverbs made nouns===

*&quot;In these cases we examine the why, the what, and the how of things.&quot;&amp;mdash;L'Estrange.
*&quot;If a point or now were extended, each of them would contain within itself infinite other points or nows.&quot;&amp;mdash;Hermes, p. 101.
*&quot;The why is plain as way to parish church.&quot;&amp;mdash;Shak.
*&quot;It is heaven itself that points out an hereafter.&quot;&amp;mdash;Addison.
*&quot;The dread of a hereafter.&quot;&amp;mdash;Fuller.
*&quot;The murmur of the deep amen.&quot;&amp;mdash;Sir W. Scott.
*&quot;For their whereabouts lies in a mystery.&quot;&amp;mdash;Book of Thoughts, p. 14. Better.
*&quot;Bid them farewell, Cordelia, though unkind; you lose here, a better where to find.&quot;&amp;mdash;Shak.

===Conjunctions made nouns===

*&quot;The if, which is here employed, converts the sentence into a supposition.&quot;&amp;mdash;Blair's Rhet.
*&quot;Your if is the only peacemaker; much virtue is in if.&quot;&amp;mdash;Shak.
*&quot;So his lordship decreed with a grave solemn tone, decisive and clear, without one if or but&amp;mdash;that whenever the nose put his spectacles on, by daylight or candlelight&amp;mdash;eyes should be shut.&quot;&amp;mdash;Cowper.

===Prepositions made nouns===

*&quot;O, not like me; for mine's beyond beyond.&quot;&amp;mdash;Shakspeare: Cymb., iii, 2.
*&quot;I.e., her longing is further than beyond; beyond anything that desire can be said to be beyond.&quot;&amp;mdash;Singer's Notes.
*&quot;You whirled them to the back of beyont to look at the auld Roman camp.&quot;&amp;mdash;Antiquary, i. 37.

===Interjections or phrases made nouns===

*&quot;Come away from all the lo-heres! and lo-theres!&quot;&amp;mdash;Sermon.
*&quot;Will cuts him short with a 'What then?'&quot;&amp;mdash;Sermon.
*&quot;With hark and whoop, and wild halloo.&quot;&amp;mdash;Scott.
*&quot;And made a pish at chance and sufferance.&quot;&amp;mdash;Shak.
*&quot;A single look more marks the internal wo, than all the windings of the lengthened oh.&quot;&amp;mdash;Lloyd.

==Countable and uncountable nouns==

==Inflections of Nouns==

Nouns have modifications of genders, numbers, and cases.

===Genders===

Genders, in grammar, are modifications that distinguish objects in regard to sex.

There are three genders; the masculine, the feminine, and the neuter:

#The '''masculine''' gender is that which denotes persons or animals of the male kind: as, ''man, father, king''.
#The '''feminine''' gender is that which denotes persons or animals of the female kind: as, ''woman, mother, queen''.
#The '''neuter''' gender is that which denotes things that are neither male nor female: as, ''pen, ink, paper''.

Hence, names of males are masculine; names of females, feminine; and names of things inanimate, literally, neuter.

* Masculine nouns make regular feminines, when their termination is changed to ''ess'': as,

:''Hunter, huntress; prince, princess; lion, lioness''.

* In some instances the syllable ''ess'' is simply added: as,

:''Accuser, accuseress; advocate, advocatess; archer, archeress; author, authoress; avenger, avengeress; barber, barberess; baron, baroness; canon, canoness; cit, cittess; coheir, coheiress; count, countess; deacon, deaconess; demon, demoness; diviner, divineress; doctor, doctoress; giant, giantess; god, goddess; guardian, guardianess; Hebrew, Hebrewess; heir, heiress; herd, herdess; hermit, hermitess; host, hostess; Jesuit, Jesuitess; Jew, Jewess; mayor, mayoress; Moabite, Moabitess; monarch, monarchess; pape, papess; or, pope, popess; patron, patroness; peer, peeress; poet, poetess; priest, priestess; prior, prioress; prophet, prophetess; regent, regentess; saint, saintess; shepherd, shepherdess; soldier, soldieress; tailor, tailoress; viscount, viscountess; warrior, warrioress''.

* In other instances, the termination is changed, and there is no increase of syllables: as,

:''Abbot, abbess; actor, actress; adulator, adulatress; adulterer, adulteress; adventurer, adventuress; advoutrer, advoutress; ambassador, ambassadress; anchorite, anchoress; or, anachoret, anachoress; arbiter, arbitress; auditor, auditress; benefactor, benefactress; caterer, cateress; chanter, chantress; cloisterer, cloisteress; commander, commandress; conductor, conductress; creator, creatress; demander, demandress; detractor, detractress; eagle, eagless; editor, editress; elector, electress; emperor, emperess, or empress; emulator, emulatress; enchanter, enchantress; exactor, exactress; fautor, fautress; fornicator, fornicatress; fosterer, fosteress, or fostress; founder, foundress; governor, governess; huckster, huckstress; or, hucksterer, hucksteress; idolater, idolatress; inhabiter, inhabitress; instructor, instructress; inventor, inventress; launderer, launderess, or laundress; minister, ministress; monitor, monitress; murderer, murderess; negro, negress; offender, offendress; ogre, ogress; porter, portress; progenitor, progenitress; protector, protectress; proprietor, proprietress; pythonist, pythoness; seamster, seamstress; solicitor, solicitress; songster, songstress; sorcerer, sorceress; suitor, suitress; tiger, tigress; traitor, traitress; victor, victress; votary, votaress''.

* In a few instances the feminine is formed as in Latin, by changing ''or'' to ''rix''; but some of these have also the regular form, which ought to be preferred: as,

:''Adjutor, adjutrix; administrator, administratrix; arbitrator, arbitratrix; coadjutor, coadjutrix; competitor, competitress, or competitrix; creditor, creditrix; director, directress, or directrix; executor, executress, or executrix; inheritor, inheritress, or inheritrix; mediator, mediatress, or mediatrix; orator, oratress, or oratrix; rector, rectress, or rectrix; spectator, spectatress, or spectatrix; testator, testatrix; tutor, tutoress, or tutress, or tutrix; deserter, desertress, or desertrice, or desertrix''.

* The following are irregular words, in which the distinction of sex is chiefly made by the termination:

:''Amoroso, amorosa: archduke, archduchess; chamberlain, chambermaid; duke, duchess; gaffer, gammer; goodman, goody, or goodwife; hero, heroine; landgrave, landgravine; margrave, margravine; marquis, marchioness; palsgrave, palsgravine; sakeret, sakerhawk; sewer, sewster; sultan, sultana; tzar, tzarina; tyrant, tyranness; widower, widow''.

===Numbers===

Numbers, in grammar, are modifications that distinguish unity and plurality.

There are two numbers; the '''singular''' and the '''plural'''.

The singular number is that which denotes but one: as,

*&quot;The boy learns.&quot;

The plural number is that which denotes more than one: as,

*&quot;The boys learn.&quot;

* Plurals in meaning and form:

:''Analects, annals, archives, ashes, assets, billiards, bowels, breeches, calends, cates, chops, clothes, compasses, crants, eaves, embers, estovers, forceps, giblets, goggles, greaves, hards or hurds, hemorrhoids, ides, matins, nippers, nones, obsequies, orgies, piles, pincers or pinchers, pliers, reins, scissors, shears, skittles, snuffers, spectacles, teens, tongs, trowsers, tweezers, umbles, vespers, victuals''.

* Plurals by formation, derived chiefly from adjectives:

:''Acoustics, aeronautics, analytics, bitters, catoptrics, commons, conics, credentials, delicates, dioptrics, economics, ethics, extraordinaries, filings, fives, freshes, glanders, gnomonics, goods, hermeneutics, hustings, hydrodynamics, hydrostatics, hydraulics, hysterics, inwards, leavings, magnetics, mathematics, measles, mechanics, mnemonics, merils, metaphysics, middlings, movables, mumps, nuptials, optics, phonics, phonetics, physics, pneumatics, poetics, politics, riches, rickets, settlings, shatters, skimmings, spherics, staggers, statics, statistics, stays, strangles, sundries, sweepings, tactics, thanks, tidings, trappings, vives, vitals, wages, withers, yellows''.

* Plurals by composition:

:''Backstairs, cocklestairs, firearms, headquarters, hotcockles, spatterdashes, self-affairs. To these may be added the Latin words, aborigines, antipodes, antes, antoeci, amphiscii, anthropophagi, antiscii, ascii, literati, fauces, regalia, and credenda, with the Italian vermicelli, and the French belles-lettres and entremets''.

====Regular plurals====

The plural form is usually represented orthographically by adding ''s'' to the singular form. The phonetic form of the plural morpheme is {{IPA|[z]}} by default. When the preceding sound is a voiceless consonant, it is pronounced {{IPA|[s]}}. Examples: ''boy'' makes ''boys''; ''girl'', ''girls''; ''chair'', ''chairs''; ''cat'', ''cats''. 

Where a noun ends in a sibilant sound, the plural is formed by adding ''es'' (pronounced {{IPA|[?z]}}), which is spelled ''es'' if the word does not already end with ''e'': ''glass'' makes ''glasses''; ''dish, dishes; witch, witches; phase, phases; judge, judges''.

Most nouns ending in ''o'' preceded by a consonant also form their plurals by adding ''es'' (pronounced {{IPA|[z]}}): ''hero'' makes ''heroes''; ''potato, potatoes; volcano, volcanoes''.

Nouns ending in a ''y'' preceded by a consonant drop the ''y'' and add ''ies'' (pronounced {{IPA|[iz]}}): ''cherry'' makes ''cherries''; ''lady, ladies''.

Proper nouns (particularly those for people or places) ending in a ''y'' preceded by a consonant form their plurals regularly: ''Harry'' makes ''Harrys''; ''Germany, Germanys''.

This does not apply to words that are merely capitalised common nouns: as, ''P&amp;O Ferries''.

A few common nouns ending in a ''y'' preceded by a consonant form their plurals regularly: ''henry'' makes ''henrys''; ''zloty, zlotys''.

Words ending in ''ey'' form their plurals regularly, in order to avoid the unpleasant-appearing vowel sequence ''eie'': ''monkey, monkeys''.

====Almost-regular plurals====

Many nouns of Italian or Spanish origin are exceptions to the '''oes rule''': ''canto'' makes ''cantos''; ''piano, pianos; portico, porticos; quarto, quartos; solo, solos''.

Many nouns ending in a voiceless fricative mutate that sound to a voiced fricative before adding the plural ending. In the case of {{IPA|[f]}} changing to {{IPA|[v]}} the mutation is indicated in the orthography as well: ''calf'' makes ''calves''; ''bath, baths; mouth, mouths; house, houses''.

Some retain the voiceless consonant: ''proof'' makes ''proofs''; ''moth, moths; place, places; dwarf, dwarfs or dwarves; hoof, hoofs or hooves; staff, staffs or staves; turf, turfs or turves; roof, roofs or rooves''.

====Irregular plurals====

There are many other less regular ways of forming plurals. While they may seem quirky, they usually stem from older forms of English or from foreign borrowings.

====Irregular Germanic plurals====

The plural of a few Germanic nouns can also be formed from the singular by adding ''n'' or ''en'', stemming from the obsolete weak declension: ''ox'' makes ''oxen''; ''child, children''.

The plural is sometimes formed by simply changing the vowel sound of the singular, in a process called umlaut (these are sometimes called ''mutated plurals''): ''foot'' makes ''feet''; ''goose, geese; louse, lice; man, men; mouse, mice; tooth, teeth; woman, women''.

Some nouns have singular and plural alike, although they are sometimes seen as regular plurals: as, ''aircraft, sheep, deer, fish, cod, trout, head, cannon''.

Generally, plurals refer to several species or kinds of animal, while the unmarked plural is used to describe multiple individual animals; one would say ''the classification of fishes'', but ''five fish in an aquarium''.

====Irregular plurals of foreign origin====

Such nouns often retain their original plurals. In some cases both forms are still vying: for a librarian, the plural of ''appendix'' is ''appendices''; for physicians, the plural of ''appendix'' is ''appendixes''. A radio engineer works with ''antennas'' and an entomologist deals with ''antennae''. The &quot;correct&quot; form is the one that sounds better in context. Correctly formed Latin plurals are the most acceptable, in academic and scientific contexts. In common usage, plurals with ''s'' are sometimes preferred.

* Final ''a'' becomes ''ae'' (also ''æ'') or just adds ''s'':

:''Formula'' makes ''formulae'', ''lamina'', ''laminae''; ''macula'', ''maculae''; minutia, ''minutiae''; ''nebula'', ''nebulae''; ''siliqua'', ''siliqiuae''; ''dogma'', ''dogmas'' or ''dogmata''; ''exanthema'', ''exanthemas'' or ''exanthemata''; ''miasm'' or ''miasma'', ''miasms'' or ''miasmata''; ''stigma'', ''stigmas'' or ''stigmata''.

:''Saliva'' and ''scoria'' have no occasion for the plural.

* Final ''ex'' or ''ix'' becomes ''ices'' (pronounced {{IPA|[??si?z]}} or {{IPA|[??siz]}}) or just adds ''es''. Of nouns in ''x'', there are few, if any, which ought not to form the plural regularly, when used as English words; though the Latins changed ''x'' to ''ces'', and ''ex'' to ''ices'', making the ''i'' sometimes long and sometimes short: as,

:''Apex, apices, for apexes; appendix, appendices, for appendixes; calix, calices, for calixes; calx, calces, for calxes; calyx, calyces, for calyxes; caudex, caudices, for caudexes; cicatrix, cicatrices, for cicatrixes; helix, helices, for helixes; index, indices, for indexes; matrix, matrices, for matrixes; quincunx, quincunces, for quincunxes; radix, radices, for radixes; varix, varices, for varixes; vertex, vertices, for vertexes; vortex, vortices, for vortexes''.

:Some Greek words in ''x'' change that letter to ''ges'': as, ''larynx, larynges, for larinxes; phalanx, phalanges, for phalanxes''. ''Billet-doux'', from the French, is ''billets-doux'' in the plural.

* Final ''is'' becomes ''es'' (pronounced {{IPA|[?i?z]}}. Of nouns in ''is'', some are regular: as, ''trellis, trellises: so, annolis, butteris, caddis, dervis, iris, marquis, metropolis, portcullis, proboscis''.

:Some seem to have no need of the plural: as, ''ambergris, aqua-fortis, arthritis, brewis, crasis, elephantiasis, genesis, orris, siriasis, tennis''.

:But most nouns of this ending follow the Greek or Latin form, which simply changes ''is'' to ''es'': as, ''amanuensis, amanuenses; analysis, analyses; antithesis, antitheses; axis, axes; basis, bases; crisis, crises; diaeresis, diaereses; diesis, dieses; ellipsis, ellipses; emphasis, emphases; fascis, fasces; hypothesis, hypotheses; metamorphosis, metamorphoses; oasis, oases; parenthesis, parentheses; phasis, phases; praxis, praxes; synopsis, synopses; synthesis, syntheses; syrtis, syrtes; thesis, theses''.

:In some, however, the original plural is not so formed; but is made by changing ''is'' to ''ides'': as, ''aphis, aphides; apsis, apsides; ascaris, ascarides; bolis, bolides; cantharis, cantharides; chrysalis, chrysalides; ephemeris, ephemerides; epidermis, epidermides''.

:So ''iris'' and ''proboscis'', which we make regular; and perhaps some of the foregoing may be made so too.

* Final ''ies'' remains unchanged: as, ''series, species''.

* Final ''on'' becomes ''a''. Of nouns in ''on'', derived from Greek, the greater part always form the plural regularly: as, ''etymons, gnomons, ichneumons, myrmidons, phlegmons, trigons, tetragons, pentagons, hexagons, heptagons, octagons, enneagons, decagons, hendecagons, dodecagons, polygons''.

:So ''trihedrons, tetrahedrons, pentahedrons'', etc., though some say, these last may end in ''dra''.

:For a few words of this class, however, there are double plurals in use; as, ''automata'' or ''atomatons'', ''criteria'' or ''criterions'', ''parhelia'' or ''parhelions''; and the plural of ''phenomenon' appears to be always ''phenomena''.

:The plural of ''legumen'' is ''legumens'' or ''legumina''; of ''stamen'', ''stamens'' or ''stamina'': of ''cherub'', ''cherubs'' or ''cherubim''; of ''seraph'', ''seraphs'' or ''seraphim''; of ''beau'', ''beaus'' or ''beaux''; of ''bandit'', ''bandits'' or ''banditti''.

* Final ''um'' becomes ''a'' or just adds ''s'': as, ''addendum'' makes ''addenda'', ''medium'' makes ''media'' or ''mediums''. Of nouns in ''um'', some have no need of the plural: as,

:''Bdellium, decorum, elysium, equilibrium, guaiacum, laudanum, odium, opium, petroleum, serum, viaticum. Some form it regularly; as, asylums, compendiums, craniums, emporiums, encomiums, forums, frustums, lustrums, mausoleums, museums, pendulums, nostrums, rostrums, residuums, vacuums. Others take either the English or the Latin plural; as, desideratums or desiderata, mediums or media, menstruums or menstrua, memorandums or memoranda, spectrums or spectra, speculums or specula, stratums or strata, succedaneums or succedanea, trapeziums or trapezia, vinculums or vincula. A few seem to have the Latin plural only: as, arcanum, arcana; datum, data; effluvium, effluvia; erratum, errata; scholium, scholia''.

* Final ''us'' becomes ''i'' (second declension), ''era'', ''ora'' (third declension), or just adds ''es'' (especially in fourth declension, where it would otherwise be the same as the singular): as, ''alumnus'' makes ''alumni'', ''viscus viscera, corpus corpora, prospectus prospectuses''.

:But such as have properly become English words, may form the plural regularly in ''es''; as, ''chorus, choruses'': so, ''apparatus, bolus, callus, circus, fetus, focus, fucus, fungus, hiatus, ignoramus, impetus, incubus, isthmus, nautilus, nucleus, prospectus, rebus, sinus, surplus''.

:''Radius'' makes ''radii'' or ''radiuses''. ''Genius'' has ''genii'', for imaginary spirits, and ''geniuses'', for men of wit. ''Genus'', a sort, becomes ''genera'' in Latin, and ''genuses'' in English. ''Denarius'' makes ''denarii'' or ''denariuses''.

:Of nouns in ''us'', a few have no plural: as, ''asparagus'', ''calamus'', ''mucus''.

:Some have only the Latin plural, which usually changes ''us'' to ''i'': as, ''alumnus, alumni; androgynus, androgyni; calculus, calculi; dracunculus, dracunculi; echinus, echini; magus, magi''.

:Final ''us'' in nouns of Greek origin &quot;properly&quot; add ''es''. These words are also heard with the Latin ''i'' instead, which is sometimes considered &quot;over-correct&quot;, but this is so common as to be acceptable in most circumstances, even technical ones: ''cactus'' makes ''cactuses'' or ''cacti''; ''hippopotamus, hippopotamuses or hippopotami, octopus, octopuses, octopi, or octopodes; platypus, platypuses, rhinoceros, rhinoceroses or rhinoceri, uterus, uteruses or uteri''.

* Final ''as'' in one case of a noun of Greek origin changes to ''antes'': ''Atlas'' makes ''Atlantes''; ''atles, atlases''.

* Final ''ma'' in nouns of Greek origin add ''ta'': ''stigma'' makes ''stigmata''; ''stoma, stomata; zeugma, zeugmata''.

:Though some take ''s'' more commonly: ''schema'' makes ''schemata'' or ''schemas''; ''dogma'', ''dogmata'' or ''dogmas''; ''lemma'', ''lemmata'' or ''lemmas''.

* Some nouns of French origin add ''x'': ''beau'' makes ''beaux''; ''chateau, chateaux; bureau, bureaus or bureaux''.

* Nouns from Slavic languages: ''kniazhestvo'' makes ''kniazhestvos'' or ''kniazhestva''; ''kobzar'', ''kobzars'' or ''kobzari'', ''oblast'', ''oblasts'' or ''oblasti''.

* Nouns of Hebrew language origin add ''im'', ''ot'' (generally m/f), or just ''s'': ''cherub'' makes ''cherubim'' or ''cherubs''; ''seraph, seraphim or seraphs; matzoh, matzot or matzos''.

:The Hebrew plurals ''cherubim'' and ''seraphim'', being sometimes mistaken for singulars, other plurals have been formed from them.

* Some nouns of Japanese origin have no plural and do not change: as, ''samurai, otaku''.

:However, other nouns such as ''kimonos'', ''futons'' and ''tsunamis'' are more often seen with a regular English plural.

*In New Zealand English, nouns of Maori origin can either take an ''s'' or have no separate plural form: as, ''waka'' makes ''waka''; ''marae, marae; kohwai, kohwai or kohwais; tui, tuis or tui, kiwi, kiwi or kiwis''.

*Nouns from languages that have donated few words to English, and that are spoken by relatively few English-speakers, generally form plurals as if they were native English words: ''canoe'' makes ''canoes''; ''kayak, kayaks; igloo, igloos; kangoroo, kangoroos; sauna, saunas; cwm, cwms; pizza, pizzas; kindergarten, kindergartens''.

:In Canada and Alaska, some words borrowed from Inuktitut retain traditional plurals: ''Inuk'' makes ''Inuit''; ''inukshuk, inukshuit''.

*Some words of foreign origin are much better known in the plural. In common usage, the proper plural is considered the singular form. Back-formation has usually resulted in a regularized plural: ''candelabra'' makes ''candelabras''; ''data, data; agenda, agendas or agendae; graffiti, graffiti; insignia, insignias; algae, algae or algaes; opera, operas; viscera, viscera; panini, paninis; phalanx, phalanges; magazine, magazines''.

===Cases===

Cases, in grammar, are modifications that distinguish the relations of nouns or pronouns to other words.

There are three cases; the nominative, the possessive, and the objective.

====The nominative case====

The nominative case is that form or state of a noun or pronoun, which usually denotes the subject of a finite verb: as,

*&quot;The boy runs;&quot;
*&quot;I run.&quot;

The subject of a finite verb is that which answers to who or what before it: as,

*&quot;The boy runs.&quot;
*Who runs? &quot;The boy.&quot;

Boy is therefore here a noun in the nominative case, or '''nominative'''.

For example:
* I eat an orange 
* I buy a chocolate
* I love my family
* I love yellow

====The possessive case==== 

The possessive case is that form or state of a noun or pronoun, which usually denotes the relation of property: as,

*&quot;My hat;&quot;
*&quot;The boy's hat.&quot;

Boy is here a noun in the possessive case, or '''possessive'''.

The possessive case of nouns is formed, in the singular number, by adding to the nominative ''s'' preceded by an apostrophe; and, in the plural, when the nominative ends in ''s'', by adding an apostrophe only: as, singular, boy's; plural, boys'; sounded alike, but written differently.

====The objective case====

The objective case is that form or state of a noun or pronoun which usually tells the object of a verb, participle, or preposition: as, 

*&quot;I know the boy, having seen him at school; and he knows me.&quot;

The object of a verb, participle, or preposition, is that which answers to whom or what after it: as,

*&quot;I know the boy.&quot;
*I know whom? &quot;The boy.&quot;

Boy is therefore here a noun in the objective case, or '''objective'''.

The nominative and the objective of nouns, are always alike in form, being distinguishable from each other only by their place in a sentence, or by their simple dependence according to the sense.

For example:
* I am playing with my football.
* I take her bag.
* Anoud's room is dirty.

====The declension of nouns====

The declension of a noun is a regular arrangement of its numbers and cases. Thus:
&lt;pre&gt;
Sing. Nom.  friend,    Plur. Nom.  friends,
      Poss. friend's,        Poss. friends',
      Obj.  friend;          Obj.  friends.

Sing. Nom.  man,       Plur. Nom.  men,
      Poss. man's,           Poss. men's,
      Obj.  man;             Obj.  men.

Sing. Nom.  fox,       Plur. Nom.  foxes,
      Poss. fox's,           Poss. foxes', 
      Obj.  fox;             Obj.  foxes.

Sing. Nom.  fly,       Plur. Nom.  flies,
      Poss. fly's,           Poss. flies', 
      Obj.  fly;             Obj.  flies.
&lt;/pre&gt;

==The noun as a modifier==

==A short syntax==

The subject must be in the nominative case, as &quot;You say it.&quot;

The subject is placed before the attribute, as &quot;Peace dawned on his mind,&quot; except the following cases: a question, as &quot;How many loaves have you?&quot; imperative mood, as &quot;Go you,&quot; strong feeling, as &quot;May she be happy!&quot; a supposition, as &quot;Were it true,&quot; ''neither'' or ''nor'', as &quot;Neither shall you touch it,&quot; emphasis, as &quot;Here am I,&quot; no regimen, as &quot;Echo the mountains round,&quot; dialogue, as &quot;My name is Hassan,&quot; and the adverb ''there'', as &quot;There lived a man.&quot;

A noun in apposition is put in the same case as the noun it explains, as &quot;But he, our gracious master, knows us.&quot;

A possessive is governed by the name of the thing possessed, as &quot;Man's life.&quot;

A possessive comes immediately before the governing noun, as &quot;Nature's peace,&quot; except the following cases: an intervening adjective, as &quot;Flora's earliest smells,&quot; affirmation or denial, as &quot;The book is not John's,&quot; a possessive without sign, as &quot;Brother Absalom's house,&quot; or &quot;David and Jonathan's friendship.&quot;

The predicate is governed by attribute in objective case, as &quot;I found her.&quot;

A noun or a pronoun put after a non-transitive verb or participle, agrees in case with a preceding noun or pronoun referring to the same thing, as &quot;The child was named John.&quot;

The case of absolute noun or pronoun depends on no other word, as &quot;Your fathers, where are they?&quot;

==References==
* A part of the text in this article, was taken from the public domain English grammar [http://www.gutenberg.net/etext/11615 &quot;The Grammar of English Grammars&quot;] by [[w:Goold Brown|Goold Brown]], 1851.
* [http://www.gutenberg.org/files/14006/14006-h/14006-h.htm An English Grammar] by [[w:William Malone Baskervill|W. M. Baskervill]] and [[w:James Witt Sewell|J. W. Sewell]], 1895.
* [[w:Collective noun|The Wikipedia article on Collective noun.]]
* [[w:Count noun|The Wikipedia article on Count noun.]]
* [[w:English plural|The Wikipedia article on English plural.]] 
* [[w:Mass noun|The Wikipedia article on Mass noun.]]  
* [[w:Noun|The Wikipedia article on Noun.]]</text>
      <sha1>41w3i8ebo9myd0vuw37u6sq23r8ag3f</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Organic Chemistry/Analytical techniques</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>983</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1570810</id>
      <parentid>961245</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-07-16T20:16:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Removed navigation that is no longer correct - previous and next pages don't exist/were merged</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve"># [[Organic Chemistry/Analytical techniques/Elemental analysis|Elemental analysis]] {{stage short|00%|Jan 12, 2005}}
# [[Organic Chemistry/Analytical techniques/Chromatography|Chromatography]] {{stage short|75%|Jan 12, 2005}}
# [[Organic Chemistry/Spectroscopy|Spectroscopy]] {{stage short|00%|Jan 12, 2005}}

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>jpbbuglsn4xb3brvorpk5rf0hdm7xeg</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Organic Chemistry/Analytical techniques/Elemental analysis</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>984</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1570802</id>
      <parentid>852009</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-07-16T20:10:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>+category</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Elemental analysis''' is the process for determining the partial or complete chemical formula for a substance.  Most commonly, it involves the complete combustion in air or oxygen of the substance and then quantifying the amount of elemental oxides produced.  In the case of organic compounds, the carbon is converted to carbon dioxide and the hydrogen to water.  From these, the percent carbon and percent hydrogen in the substance can be found and compared with a proposed chemical formula for the substance at hand.

Element test: Put a small amount of the solid into a small piece of Na metal then roll it around the solid, followed by introduction into a fusion tube. The tube is heated with a gentle flame at a slow rate (in order not to evaporate N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; present in solid) then strong heating till the bottom of the tube become red hot. The tube is then put in a beaker containing a minimal amount of water then heated, cooled, filtered and the filtrate divided into three parts.

1. &lt;u&gt;Test for nitrogen&lt;/u&gt;:
The filtrate and ferrous sulphate are boiled and cooled and dilute sulphuric acid is added. If green or blue color occurs the solid contain nitrogen.

&lt;b&gt;The chemistry behind what happened&lt;/b&gt;:&lt;br&gt;
Na+C+N --&gt; NaCN&lt;br&gt;
FeSO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;+NaCN gives Fe[CN]&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Fe[CN]&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;+4NaCN give the complex Na&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;[Fe(CN)&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;]&lt;br&gt;
ferrous oxidizes to ferric by the acid so
3Na&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;[Fe(CN)&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;]+4Fe&lt;sup&gt;3+&lt;/sup&gt; --&gt; Fe&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;[Fe(CN)&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;]&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;

2. &lt;u&gt;Test for sulphur&lt;/u&gt;:
The filtrate is exposed to dilute acetic acid and lead acetate, yielding a brown or black precipitate. 

&lt;b&gt;The chemistry behind what happened&lt;/b&gt;:&lt;br&gt;
Na+S --&gt; Na&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;S&lt;br&gt;
Na&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;S +Pb(CH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;H)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; yields lead sulphide, a black precipitate.

or:
The filtrate and sodium nitro prusside yield a violet color 

Na&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;S+Na&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;[Fe(CN)&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;NO] --&gt; Na&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;[Fe(CN)&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;NOS] = violet color

3. &lt;u&gt;Test for chlorine&lt;/u&gt;:

a) In the absence of N or S:
The filtrate is exposed to dilute nitric acid and silver nitrate. Formation of a white precipitate suggests the presence of chlorine.

b) In the presence of N and/or S :

The filtrate is exposed to dilute sulphoric acid then boiled to 1/3 initial volume and cooled. Formation of a white precipitate after the addition of dilute nitric acid and silver nitrate suggests the presence of chlorine.

&lt;b&gt;Equations&lt;/b&gt;:

NaCN+AgNO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; --&gt; AgCN white ppt&lt;br&gt;
Na&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;S+AgNO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; gives Ag&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;S black ppt&lt;br&gt;
&lt;b&gt;In the presence of N or S these two precipitates may interfere with the white colour of the result of the chlorine test.  Therefore dilute sulphoric acid is added because in the presence of N or S&lt;/b&gt;:
Na&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;S+ dilute H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;SO&lt;/sub&gt;4 gives H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;S gas
NaCN+ dilulte H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;SO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; gives HCN gas 

There is no interference with the white colour expected from the chlorine test in solid.

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>fveuodnc7zlw36biop05k74a8xt1sad</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Organic Chemistry/Analytical techniques/Chromatography</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>985</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2578823</id>
      <parentid>1972092</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-11-05T09:28:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>112.205.212.146</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Paper chromatography */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Chromatography''' involves the physical separation of a mixture of compounds.  Chromatography can be used as a purification method but also sees wide use for the identification of compounds based on their chromatographic behavior.

=Theory=

There are many variations of chromatography, but all involve the dissolution of an analyte into a fluid known as the '''mobile phase''' and the passage of this fluid solution across a '''stationary phase''', often a solid or liquid-coated solid.

As the mobile phase comes into contact with the stationary phase, some of the analyte molecules dissolve or adsorb onto the mobile phase.  The more the molecules of that substance are retained, the slower their progress through the chromatographic apparatus.  Different substances will then move through at different rates, ideally resulting in distinctly identifiable '''retention times''' for each substance.

Commonly used chromatographic techniques are identified through the nature of the stationary and mobile phases used, the method for passing the mobile phase through the apparatus, and how separated components are identified.

=Paper chromatography=

In '''paper chromatography''' the stationary phase is a specialized paper made to absorb water to a high level. The mobile phase is usually water or a concentrated salt solution. Paper chromatography has many uses in forensic chemistry due to it's simplicity and availability. However, paper chromatography is limited by the characteristics that only water soluble components can be separated and inaccuracy in RF values. This makes paper chromatography mostly useful to distinguish the differences between two residues rather than their similarities.

[[Image:Paper_Chromatography_SH.png|thumb|Paper chromatography separation in the visible spectrum.]]

=Thin layer chromatography=

In '''thin layer chromatography''' (TLC) a plastic or glass plate is coated with the stationary phase, often alumina, silica, or alkylated silica.  The analyte is dissolved in a quick-drying solvent and spotted near the bottom of the plate.  The edge of the plate beneath the spot or spots is then dipped and left in a solution of the mobile phase, either an organic solvent or aqueous solution (depending on the nature of the analyte and stationary phase).  Capillary action is then allowed to draw the '''solvent front''' through the spotted analyte, carrying with it and in the process separating out the analyte's components.

=Gas chromatography=

In '''gas chromatography''' (GC) the analyte and mobile phase must both be gases or be readily introduced into the gas phase by heating. The mobile phase gas must be inert and not reacting with the sample to be analysed. Examples of inert gases are helium and nitrogen gas.

The gases are passed through a long, narrow (and most often, coiled) tube either packed with a porous stationary phase or whose inner walls are coated with a stationary phase, and the analyte components are detected as they emerge from the far end of the tube. The tube is commonly known as GC column.

Often a time-varying temperature gradient, from lower temperature to higher temperature, is applied to the tube.  This first allows the analyte components to partition into the stationary phase and then, as the temperature rises, to differentially force them back into the mobile phase.

Common detectors for gas chromatography are flame ionization detector (FID), electron capture detector (ECD) and mass spectrometry (MS). Different types of sample analysis would require the use of a different type of detectors.

=Column chromatography=

'''Column chromatography''', like gas chromatography, uses a tube packed with a stationary phase, but the mobile phase is a liquid instead of a gas (It is sometimes known as '''liquid chromatography''' or LC). Instead of temperature gradients, a gradient in the composition of the liquid phase can be used to separate components.

Column chromatography can be performed on larger molecules which may not be readily introduced into the gas phase.  On the other hand, because of the increased viscosity of liquids compared with gases, liquid chromatography can be a more ponderous process.  '''HPLC''' (variously ''high-pressure liquid chromatography'' or ''high-performance liquid chromatography'') speeds the process and improves its selectivity and sensitivity to a significant degree by forcing the mobile phase through the chromatographic column with high-pressure pumps.

=Detection methods=

The root of the word '''chromatography''', ''chroma'' (Greek &lt;i&gt;khrōma, color&lt;/i&gt;) and grafein is &quot;to write&quot;,  indicates that the separated components in some forms of the technique can be identified by their color alone.  But chromatography has now long been performed on colorless compounds that can be identified in other ways.

Analyte components on thin-layer chromatography plates are often identified under ultraviolet light, or by chemical staining in, for example, an iodine chamber or potassium permanganate.  Gas chromatographic analytes are detected by changes in the ionization levels of a flame at the output end of the column or by changes in the electrical conductivity of the gas mixture at the end of the column.  Liquid chromatography fractions are often analyzed through spectrophotometric techniques, notably UV-visible spectroscopy. When separation with GC or LC is performed in tandem with mass spectrometry (the &quot;hyphenated&quot; techniques of GC-MS and LC-MS), masses of individual fractions are rapidly determined. These methods are frequently employed in analytical and forensic science.

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>1uwyqytok1zfk5qvvvton49t9h4zbjv</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>