<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>Spanish/Parts of Speech</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3839</id>
    <revision>
      <id>532439</id>
      <parentid>492934</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-07-22T07:42:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[../Grammar Index/]]
----
*[[../Adjectives/]]
*[[../Adverbs/]]
*[[../Nouns/]]
*[[../Verbs/]]

[[Category:Spanish]]</text>
      <sha1>pvin3syk52bkxz97ej2n0ow4lt03467</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Vietnamese/Personal pronouns</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3842</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2368803</id>
      <parentid>2175122</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-26T03:38:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>84.249.98.96</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Singular pronouns */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Vietnamese is a bit different than [[w:Romance language|Romance languages]], in that Vietnamese doesn't just use different pronouns for casual or formal situations, but Vietnamese actually uses different pronouns depending on the relation between the speaker and his/her audience. This relation takes gender, age, and status into account. Basically, Vietnamese refer to everyone as a family member. Also, it is common to use a third person personal pronoun in the first person. 

== Singular pronouns ==
;'''bạn (friend)'''
:informal, but not casual; a general-purpose version; use with caution
;'''anh (brother)'''
:to a male who is the same age as the speaker
;'''bà (grandmother, old lady)'''
:formal; to a female who is older than the speaker
;'''chị (sister)'''
:informal; to a female who is the same age as or older than the speaker
;'''con (child)'''
:from an adult to a child
;'''em(younger sister or brother)'''
:to a female who is the same age as the speaker, or to a person (of either gender) who is younger than the speaker (such as a child)
;'''mày (you)'''
:informal, even rude or insulting; to a person younger than the speaker, or to a person held in low esteem; use with caution
;'''ông (grandfather, old man)'''
:formal; to a male who is older than the speaker
;'''cô (father's sister)'''
:formal; to an older woman as old as one's father, a young (usually unmarried) woman

In addition, there are different pronouns for each kind of relative. For a listing of those pronouns, see [[Vietnamese/Family|Family]].

''(More to come.)''

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>60a38ifq73m8r5es9g4hh5tevxws2xu</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Spanish/Vocabulary/Emergency Room</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3845</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2120832</id>
      <parentid>2120831</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-06-14T11:46:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>84.79.151.4</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Conversaciones */ Problema is male noun</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">== Sustantivos ==
: ''' La sala de urgencias/emergencia: ''' '' emergency room ''
: ''' La ambulancia: ''' '' ambulance ''
: ''' El/la doctor/a: ''' '' doctor ''
: ''' El/la enfermero/a: ''' '' nurse ''
: ''' La medicina, el medicamento: ''' ''medicine
: ''' La jeringa: ''' '' syringe ''
: ''' La inyección: ''' '' injection ''
: ''' Los puntos: ''' '' stitches ''

== Verbos ==


== Conversaciones ==
:''' ¿Dónde te duele? ''' '' Where does it hurt?''
:''' ¿Estás embarazada? ''' '' Are you pregnant?''
:''' ¿Tienes una historia de problemas médicos, de riñon, pulmón, o corazón? ''' '' Do you have a history of medical problems, in the kidneys, lungs, or heart?''
:''' ¿Eres diabético? ''' '' Are you diabetic?''
:''' ¿Tienes alergias? ''' '' Do you have any allergies?''
:''' ¿Estas tomando algún medicamento? ''' '' Are you taking any medicine?''
:''' ¿Cuantos años tienes? ''' '' How old are you?''

[[Category:Spanish|{{SUBPAGENAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>mzqdhty5l51hmfrpibkgqi03d5cbgvu</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Bicycles/Degreaser</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3846</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2567155</id>
      <parentid>488978</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-10-16T15:38:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">A degreaser is useful in removing greasy dirt from parts.  Traditionally petroleum based products have been used. DO NOT use gasoline.  Although it is an effective degreaser, its volatility (i.e. tendency to explode) make it a poor choice for shop work.  If you must use a petroleum product, choose naphtha (usually available in hardware stores) or kerosene.  A better choice is a modern, biodegradable water based degreaser.  Specific blends for bicycle cleaning are available from bike shops and online retailers.  You can probably save some money, though, by purchasing degreaser from an auto parts retailer.  Whatever you use, after cleaning moving parts with a degreaser, always follow up with lubrication. All residual degreaser should be wiped off the parts before applying lubrication, as it would otherwise dilute the lubricant.

[[Category:Bicycles]]</text>
      <sha1>q5ns1ddvq690g9ayqlff6k32egd0yh0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>HyperText Markup Language/Textual Formatting</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3850</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2053529</id>
      <parentid>1276442</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-02-22T03:24:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Avicennasis</username>
        <id>314063</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>clean up, typos fixed: refered → referred, world-wide web → World Wide Web using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Editor note|This page can be deleted. It is redundant to [[../Text Formatting]].}}

As with almost all programming languages and Markup Languages there are several different ways of formatting text. HTML is no exception. 

A popular way to format HTML is to use specific HTML tags such as &lt;nowiki&gt; &lt;b&gt;, &lt;i&gt; and &lt;u&gt;.&lt;/nowiki&gt; The World Wide Web consortium (W3C) suggest these tags may not be supported in future and that you use &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;strong&gt;, &lt;em&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt; to add formatting to text on the HTML page. 

In practice, these methods are both fine to use, but are limited in the ways that text can be formatted.

Thus, many HTML authors are shifting towards using CSS (Cascading Style Sheets) which employs &quot;style sheets&quot; and &quot;inline styles&quot; to add formatting to text. It should be noted that using CSS one can redefine the appearance of text inside all tags of a particular type. See the section on classes below for details.

== Inline styles ==
Through CSS (Cascading Style Sheets) you can reuse code using &quot;classes&quot; which contain &quot;styles&quot; (ways of formatting text). You can also put CSS styles inline, as in the following:

 &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;font-weight: bold; font-size: 200%&quot;&gt;This is a paragraph of double-size bold text&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;

results in

&lt;div style=&quot;font-weight: bold; font-size: 200%&quot;&gt;This is a paragraph of double-size bold text&lt;/div&gt;

== Classes ==
&lt;!-- ToDo: explain tagname.class format.  --&gt;
Classes can be defined in two places; in style tags in HTML documents and in external files, the &quot;style sheets&quot; referred to in the name &quot;Cascading Style Sheets&quot;.  The term &quot;cascading&quot; refers to the mechanism by which the correct style is chosen when multiple style sheets are to be applied to the same document.

An example style tag:

&lt;pre&gt;
&lt;style type=&quot;text/css&quot;&gt;
a { font-weight: bold; }
a.special { color:red; }
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


An example of the contents of a style sheet file:
&lt;pre&gt;
a { font-weight: bold; }
a.special { color:red; }
&lt;/pre&gt;

[[Category:HyperText Markup Language]]

[[it:HTML/Organizzare il testo]]</text>
      <sha1>hoc8f599uqpae7mqgddtf6zxs32z0le</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Wikibooks portal</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3852</id>
    <redirect title="Main Page" />
    <restrictions>move=sysop:edit=sysop</restrictions>
    <revision>
      <id>1085309</id>
      <parentid>694017</parentid>
      <timestamp>2008-01-17T14:51:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>redirecting this old page to point to the current main page, where all visitors to this site should be going by default.  if you type &quot;www.wikibooks.org&quot;, you no longer come to this page.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">#REDIRECT: [[Main Page]]</text>
      <sha1>ntuuspqfqkyvfvinlqhkomm0dmwo50p</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Envia</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>3862</id>
    <revision>
      <id>155707</id>
      <timestamp>2004-01-14T18:59:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>218.39.19.101</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">I've looked forward to open textbooks. Now we can make them, thanks to wikibookians and wikipedians.</text>
      <sha1>qmo8hm1ensac2h5qg4et3x0ymae0hj0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Heat Transfer</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3865</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1928551</id>
      <parentid>1856103</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-09-05T20:02:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>status=25%</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''About this book''' {{Wikipedia|Heat Transfer}}

An introductory text which should be of particular interest to students of chemical or mechanical engineering.

'''Contents'''

[[/Introduction/]]  The basics

[[/Heat Balances/]] What goes in must come out

[[/Conduction/]] A mechanism of heat transfer

[[/Convection/]] A mechanism of heat transfer

[[/Radiation/]] A mechanism of heat transfer

[[/Heat Transfer with Phase Change/]]  Different rules apply when this happens

[[/Heat Exchangers/]] Industrial devices for heating, cooling and saving energy

[[/Appendices/]] There may be something in here later

[[/Bibliography/]] Recommended for more in-depth study

=== See also ===
* [[Subject:Physics]]
* [[Engineering Thermodynamics]]

{{Alphabetical|H}}
{{Subjects|Mechanical engineering|Chemical engineering}}
{{status|25%}}</text>
      <sha1>g3stn93wmwh8f5x4hrsnjwl8b0j0283</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>The Voynich Manuscript</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3867</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2691211</id>
      <parentid>2384478</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-14T04:01:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>66.27.174.138</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* People who claim to have broken the VM's code */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Welcome==
[[File:Voynich Manuscript (32).jpg|thumb|A floral illustration on page 32. The colors are still vibrant.]]
The '''Voynich manuscript''', described as &quot;the world's most mysterious manuscript&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = Brumbaugh, Robert S. | title = The World's Most Mysterious Manuscript | publisher = [[Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson]] | location = London | year = 1977 }}&lt;/ref&gt; is a work which dates to the early 15th century, possibly from northern Italy.&lt;ref name=ngvideo&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.newyorkfestivals.com/winners/tvf2011winners/pieces.php?iid=413203&amp;pid=1|year=2011|accessdate=November 6, 2011 | title = The Voynich Code&amp;nbsp;— The World's Mysterious Manuscript | author = Steindl, Klaus; Sulzer, Andreas | format = video }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;physorg&quot;&gt;{{cite web | author = Stolte, Daniel |date = February 10, 2011 | publisher = [[PhysOrg]] | url = http://www.physorg.com/news/2011-02-experts-age.html | title = Experts determine age of book 'nobody can read' | accessdate = February 10, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It is named after the book dealer [[/Wilfrid Michael Voynich/]], who purchased it in 1912.

Some pages are missing, but the current version comprises about 240 [[wikipedia:vellum|vellum]] pages, most with illustrations. Much of the manuscript resembles [[/herbal manuscripts/|herbal manuscripts]] of the time period, seeming to present illustrations and information about plants and their possible uses for medical purposes. However, most of the plants do not match known species, and the manuscript's [[/VMS writing system/|script]] and [[/VMS language/|language]] remain unknown and unreadable. Possibly some form of encrypted [[wikipedia:ciphertext|ciphertext]], the Voynich manuscript has been studied by many professional and amateur cryptographers, including American and British codebreakers from both World War I and World War II. As yet, it has defied all decipherment attempts, becoming a ''cause célèbre'' of historical cryptology. The mystery surrounding it has excited the popular imagination, making the manuscript a subject of both fanciful theories and novels. None of the many speculative solutions proposed over the last hundred years has yet been independently verified.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ciphermysteries.com/the-voynich-manuscript/voynich-theories|title=Voynich theories|author=Pelling, Nick|accessdate=December 4, 2011|publisher=ciphermysteries.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Voynich manuscript was donated to Yale University's Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library in 1969, where it is catalogued under call number ''MS 408'' and called a &quot;Cipher Manuscript&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=MS 408|publisher=Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library|url=http://brbl-net.library.yale.edu/pre1600ms/docs/pre1600.ms408.htm|accessdate=December 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;online&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://beinecke.library.yale.edu/digitallibrary/voynich.html|title=Voynich Manuscript|accessdate=December 4, 2011|publisher=Beinecke Library}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Perhaps the appeal of Voynich research is that (a) it is truly cross-disciplinary, and (b) it rewards endeavour and persistence. This wikibook is intended to help you get started on what has already been (for some) a long road of (self-)discovery - the page you may find most useful at first is the [[/Jargon|Guide To Voynich Jargon]].

==Table of contents==
#[[/Content/]]
#[[/History/]]
#[[/Jargon/]]

==What we know about VMS==

* Illustrated medieval folio written in an undeciphered script.
* From the illustrations – hairstyles and features of the human ﬁgures – as well as the shapes of the glyphs, the manuscript is posited to have been created in Europe. Carbon-dating at the University of Arizona has found that the vellum was created in the 15th century, and the McCrone Research Institute has asserted that the ink was added shortly afterwards.
* The manuscript is divided into quires – sections made out of folded parchment, each of which consists of folios, with writing on both sides of each folio (Reeds, 2002).
* Including blank pages and pages with no text, there are 240 pages, although it is believed that some are missing (Pelling, 2006)
* 225 pages include text, and most are illustrated.
* The text was probably added after the illustrations, and shows no evidence of scratching or correction.
* The text is written left to right in paragraphs that are left-aligned, justiﬁed, and divided by whitespace into words. Paragraphs do not span multiple pages.
* Under the most used transcription, as there are ambiguities, the VMS is comprised of 8114 word types, and 37919 word tokens.
* Based on the illustrations, the manuscript has traditionally been divided into six sections: (1) herbal, containing drawings of plants; (2) Astronomical, containing zodiac-like illustrations; (3) Biological, mainly containing drawings of female human ﬁgures; (4) Cosmological, consisting of circular illustrations; (5) Pharmaceutical, containing drawing of small containers and parts of plants, and (6) Stars (sometimes referred to as Recipes), containing very dense text with drawings of stars in the margins.
* Currier (1976) observed from letter and substring frequencies that the text is comprised of two distinct ‘languages’, A and B. Interestingly, the Biological and Stars sections are mainly written in the B language, and the rest mainly in A.
* The word frequency distribution follows Zipf’s law, which is a necessary (though not sufﬁcient) test of linguistic plausibility. We also ﬁnd that the unigram word entropy is comparable to the baseline texts.

Source: What we know about the Voynich manuscript, by Sravana Reddy and Kevin Knight. http://www.isi.edu/natural-language/people/voynich-11.pdf

==Page-by-page commentary==
''See: [[The Voynich Manuscript/Page-by-page commentary]]''

The Voynich Manuscript has more than 200 pages, divided up into twenty quires (as per the following links). The first 7 quires are standard quires consisting of 4 nested bifolios each. Quire
8 once consisted of 5 such bifolios but only 2 remain. From quire 9 onwards, quires often
consist of only one or two multiple folding bifolios. Exceptions are quires 13 (5 standard bifolios)
and 20 (7 standard bifolios of which 6 remain). Further details are available at the description
of each quire.

The web-pages linked onwards from there are intended to summarise the debate relating to individual pages - what could they mean? To what are they similar? What interesting (visual or statistical) properties do they have? ''(etc)''
:Main herbal section - Quires 1-7
:Mixed quire - Quire 8
:Astronomical/cosmological section - Quires 9-10 ''(note that quire 10 also contains the start of the zodiac section!)''
:Zodiac section - Quires 11-12 
:Biological/balneological (bathing nymph) section - Quires 13-14 ''(contains the &quot;9-rosette&quot; fold-out page)''
:Pharmacological+herbal section - Quires 15-19
:Recipe / calendar / almanacke section - Quire 20

==Cross-page commentary==
This section is designed to contain commentaries on features spanning multiple pages of the VMs.
:[[/Currier Languages (A &amp; B)/]]
:[[/Statistical features of the text/]]
:[[/Neal Keys/]]
:[[/Page ordering/]]
:[[/Titles/]]
:[[/Nymphs/]]
:[[/Long gallows/]]
:[[/Paints/]]
:[[/Inks/]]
:[[/Marginalia/]]
:[[/Emendations/]]
:[[/Alphabet/]]

==Timeline/provenance==
:[[/Abbot Beere|Abbot Beere (Bere) of Glastonbury]]
:[[/Dee and Kelly|John Dee and Edward Kelly]]

==People who claim to have broken the VM's code==
:[[/William Romaine Newbold/]]
:[[/Robert Brumbaugh/]]
:[[/Leonell Strong/]]
:[[/Leo Levitov/]]
:[[/John Stojko/]]
:[[/Gordon Rugg/]]
:[[/Claude Martin/]]
:[[/Michael Sasscer/]]
:[[/Stephen Bax/]]
:[[/Jutta Kellner/]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==External Resources==
*http://www.voynich.net/ - starting point for the English-language VMs. mailing list (started originally in 1991).
*[[w:Voynich manuscript|Voynich MS entry in Wikipedia]]
*http://www.voynich.nu/
*http://voynich-ms.de/wiki/Hauptseite - German VMS wiki

{{Subjects|Nonfiction literature}}
{{Alphabetical|V}}
{{status|0%}}
__NOTOC__</text>
      <sha1>6jcmtmjdyu0gjohxzkoyerahp0fe9oy</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Vietnamese/Glossary/A-K</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3871</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2368275</id>
      <parentid>542100</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-24T16:21:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>84.249.98.96</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* C */ em is for younger, chị is for same age or little older</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">This glossary covers only the words used in this textbook. For a more complete listing of Vietnamese words and phrases, please see [[wikt:Wiktionary:Vietnamese index|Wiktionary]].

==A==
;'''anh'''
:[[Wiktionary:man|man]];
:[[Wiktionary:you|you]] (to a male who is the same age as the speaker)

==B==
;'''bà'''
:[[Wiktionary:woman|woman]];
:[[Wiktionary:you|you]] (formal; to a female who is older than the speaker, or to the speaker's grandmother);
:[[Wiktionary:grandmother|grandmother]]
;'''bạn'''
:[[Wiktionary:friend|friend]];
:[[Wiktionary:you|you]] (informal, but not casual; a general-purpose version; use with caution)

==C==
;'''chị'''
:[[Wiktionary:you|you]] (informal; to a female who is the same age as or older than the speaker)
;'''con'''
:[[Wiktionary:child|child]];
:[[Wiktionary:you|you]] (from an adult to a child)
;'''Cô'''
:[[Wiktionary:Mrs.|Mrs.]]; (formal)

==E==
;'''em'''
:[[Wiktionary:you|you]] (to a female who is the same age as the speaker, or to a person who is younger than the speaker, such as a child)

[[Category:Vietnamese]]</text>
      <sha1>rl3ktcdvj37zwuupx9nsw8ia9fjgzdl</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Bicycles/Maintenance and Repair/Tools and Supplies/Multi-tool</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3872</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2257422</id>
      <parentid>1498636</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-01-27T12:51:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Armchair</username>
        <id>77084</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">A '''multi tool''' combines several tools into one package.The individual tools may,for example,all fold into the handle. The [[ w:swiss army knife|swiss army knife]] is an example of a general purpose multi tool. In recent years, a number of manufacturers have produced multi tools specifically intended for bicycle repair.  For example:
[[File:Bicycle multi-tool.JPG|thumb|right|400px|A bicycle multi-tool.   They do not replace the convenience of conventional hand tools, but can be carried on the person and contain the items that are of most use in a breakdown situation.]]
*Blackburn

*Crank Brothers

*Park

*Pedros

*Topeak

[[Category:{{FULLBOOKNAME}}|{{FULLCHAPTERNAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>d03jqxqmfnaj0tuamkzskd3vbilcva1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Latin/Lesson 4-Principal Parts</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3874</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2121444</id>
      <parentid>2095421</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-06-16T05:25:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>184.57.240.103</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Principal Parts */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Latin}}

== Principal Parts ==

All Latin verbs are identified by four principal parts. By using the four principal parts, one can obtain any and all forms of the verb, including participles, infinitives, gerunds and the like.

Examples of principal parts from verbs of each conjugation:

:1st: ''ambulō, ambulāre, ambulāvī, ambulātum'' (to walk)

:2nd: ''doceō, docēre, docuī, doctum'' (to teach)

:3rd: ''mittō, mittere, mīsī, mīssum'' (to send)

:4th: ''audiō, audīre, audīvī, audītum'' (to hear)

For all regular verbs, the principal parts consist of the first person singular present active indicative, the infinitive, the first person singular perfect active indicative, and the supine (or in some texts, the perfect passive participle).

*Deponent verbs have only three principal parts:

:''patior, patī, passus sum'' (to suffer)

:''ūtor, ūtī, ūsus sum'' (to use)

*Likewise, semi-deponent verbs have only three:

:''audeō, audēre, ausus sum'' (to dare)

:''gaudeō, gaudēre, gavīsus sum'' (to rejoice)

Some verbs lack fourth principal parts (e.g., ''timeō, timēre, timuī, —''; to be afraid); others, less commonly, lack a third in addition (e.g., ''ferro, ferre, tuli, latum''; to bring/carry). Others, such as ''sum, esse, fuī, futūrus'', may use the future active participle (''futūrus'') as their fourth principal part; this indicates that the verb cannot be made passive.

[[Category:Latin]]</text>
      <sha1>p32cu5aumc7vn5zt2fns064xlwxdkds</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Ada Programming/Mathematical calculations/Trigonometry</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>3876</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1925798</id>
      <parentid>1922011</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-09-02T13:46:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>moved [[Talk:Trigonometry/Algebra Trigonometry]] to [[Talk:Ada Programming/Mathematical calculations/Trigonometry]]: No longer used by previous book; merging into remaining book using it so as to not lose content.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Can some diagrams be borrowed from wikipedia? e.g. http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trigonometry.
:[[User:219.89.185.25|219.89.185.25]] 21:34, 1 January 2006 (UTC)
----

Gee, someone needs to find some suitable diagrams. I had a tough time describing right triangles and a unit circle only in words... and I'm too lazy to find diagrams :-\. [[User:Ugen64|Ugen64]] 01:58, 16 Jan 2004 (UTC)

I'll make some in SodiPodi right now..[[User:Thunderbolt16|Thunderbolt16]] 05:15, 16 Jan 2004 (UTC)

I drew it incorrectly with not the hyp to the unit circle to the leg. I'll fix this pretty quick

Um, where are the answers?

...to the exercises


Some notation for an angle must be included in defining the trig ratios because the value of the angle measure is one of the three variables in the equation.  Math anxious students need to see as many visaul clues as possible in order for them to build an understanding of this concept.

==Elementary Trigonometric Functions==
Their teachers have taught my children the memory aid &quot;SOHCAHTOA&quot;, pronounced so-ka-toe-a.  Sin == Opposite / Hypotenuse, Cos == Adjacent / Hypotenuse. Tan == Opposite / Adjacent.  This might be considered for adding to this section. [[User:Walrii|Walrii]] 20:26, 12 May 2006 (UTC)

==Suggest delete page==

It's not clear what useful role this page plays in the book.  I think it is simply an introduction to the topic of trigonometry, which already exists in more well-developed form at the beginning of the book.  Any objections to deleting the page?  [[User:Douglas W. Mitchell|Douglas W. Mitchell]] ([[User talk:Douglas W. Mitchell|talk]]) 16:22, 26 August 2010 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>mzbhauz71ue4vpt4suhb0tun5c8kpf2</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Cprompt</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>3877</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2507273</id>
      <parentid>224129</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-30T20:21:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cprompt</username>
        <id>470</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">In [[w:DOS|DOS]], the command prompt was often referred to as the ''c: prompt'' when the current directory was set to the [[w:root directory|root directory]] of the C: [[w:Hard disk drive partitioning|hard disk partition]].

I have a somewhat more interesting [[w:User:Cprompt|user page on the English Wikipedia]]. I'm less of an editor on Wikibooks than I am on the Wikipedia. On Wikibooks, it seems I am more of a reader.

I have an account by the same name on the English Wikipedia, the Simple English Wikipedia, the Esperanto Wikipedia, and Wiktionary.</text>
      <sha1>r8zk4i5n5nlyedysvv5cuyzpp83hn1i</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Python Programming</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>3879</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2596189</id>
      <parentid>2574106</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-12-26T00:31:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>69.72.92.242</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* pdf problems */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==About==
* Started: 19 October 2003‎
* Size: 27,300 words (Oct 2013)
* {{rc}}
* {{Subpages link}}
* [[Python Programming/Print_version|Printable version]]

== Safty of user inputet data ==
Hi i didnt found anything about preventing XSS injection and SQL injections.
I think its important part of doing web apps. Chris.
: Although avoiding XSS injection and SQL injection is indeed important, I believe it is a cross-language skill that should be learned separately from the language itself (it could make a book by itself). There are however, aspects of certain language that is often an easy weak-point for malicious hackers coupled with careless programmer. In python, these weak points would be (not a complete list): input (python 2.x and below), eval, exec, popen, and subprocess, possibly open too. These weak points should be mentioned.

== Non-programmers python tutorial ==
If anyone wants to, feel free to take any material from the tutorial that I wrote for the python programming language.  [http://www.honors.montana.edu/~jjc/easytut/easytut/ Non-programmers python tutorial].  I grant permission to relicense it under the GNU Free Documentation License (though I would recommend keeping the public domain exception for the programming samples).  Josh Cogliati.  [[User:Jrincayc|Jrincayc]] 15:42, 16 Jan 2004 (UTC)

Thank you very much! I'll start to integrate it into the module ASAP [[User:Thunderbolt16|Thunderbolt16]] 22:56, 17 Jan 2004 (UTC)
:I started wikifiying it to simplify integrating it in. See my [[User:Jrincayc]] page for the contents. [[User:Jrincayc|Jrincayc]] 02:43, 1 Jun 2004 (UTC)
:More or less finished wikifying it.  See [[User:Jrincayc/Contents]] -- [[User:Jrincayc|Jrincayc]] 02:54, 2 Jun 2004 (UTC)
:::I plan on moving it from User:Jrincayc to Non-programmers Python Tutorial, if nobody objects.  I am doing this because the server honors.montana.edu is being permanently shutdown, so I wish to start changing links to it to point to wikibooks rather than honors.montana.edu.   [[User:Jrincayc|Jrincayc]] 02:44, 31 August 2006 (UTC)
::Josh's work is now avaialable at http://www.andamooka.org/reader.pl?section=easytut as his link to the website at U. Montana is broken.--[[User:DavidRoss|DavidRoss]] 06:23, 7 August 2006 (UTC)

: Thank you. That looks excellent. We now have [[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python]].
: Well, that's technically merely a redirect to the specific version of Python we recommend for new people.
: At the moment it redirects to [[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python 2.6]].
: Someday it will become a redirect to [[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python 3]] (after a few [http://wiki.python.org/moin/Python2orPython3 more issues] are resolved).
: Even further in the future I expect [[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python]] to redirect to [[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python 4]]. :-) --[[User:DavidCary|DavidCary]] ([[User talk:DavidCary|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/DavidCary|contribs]]) 19:18, 29 February 2012 (UTC)

== Explain what makes this book unique ==

People mentioned that Python is already covered in:
* the book &quot;How to think like a Computer Scientist: Learning with Python&quot;, which is already a comprehensive text about Python and covers a lot of topics on programming. Why not use that? --Offray
* [http://www.diveintopython.org Dive Into Python] by [http://www.diveintomark.org Mark Pilgrim], which is licenced under the GNU FDL--::[[User:Noldoaran|Noldoaran]] 18:14, 6 Aug 2004 (UTC)
* The official Python documentation --Beuc

Please add a note in the synopsys or introduction about what fostered the development of this wikibook :)

== September 2004 revamp ==

I am about to delve into this thing, and find it's pretty much in disarray. It appears nobody is workin on it, so I'm going to go right ahead.

I have a structure in mind. The sections of the book will go something like this:

#Introduction - What is Python; Getting Python; Editing Python programs.
#Tutorial - A series of examples and exercises.
#Language concepts - Indepth and complete treatment of Python's implementation of syntax, variables, flow control, files, classes, etc.
#Standard modules - Indepth documentation of standard modules.
#Function reference - Indepth documentation of standard functions. (Not sure about this section.)
#Appendices - List of keywords and similar stuff.

See [[User:Yath/Python]] for the full chapter outline.

[[User:Yath|Yath]] 19:24, 24 Sep 2004 (UTC)

== Web scripting ==

I'd like to read how to write a page containing a python script and how to configure apache to understand python. Thanks [[User:158.193.85.212|158.193.85.212]] 07:28, 5 May 2005 (UTC)

==Using saved programs==

Could somebody elaborate on how to get a saved python program? I entered the program in a notepad file. But when I try to get it on the python command line, it says that the : in C:\ is wrong syntax. How do I get the programs? --[[elpenmaster]]

== [[Wikibooks:Naming policy]] ==

You might want to consider the [[WB:NP]]. Your current naming convention is deprecated and has several disadvantages - e.g. it has no navigational links. Also your worthy effort is neither considered a book nor a section inside a book. See [http://en.wikipedia.org/wikistats/wikibooks/EN/Wikibooks_EN.htm wikistats] which implements an extensive book and section detector.

--[[User:Krischik|Krischik]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:Krischik|T]]&lt;/sup&gt; 07:15, 11 October 2005 (UTC)

:Adding to this, it would be a good idea in my opinion to drop the &quot;Programming&quot; pseudo-namespace. Books are starting to move out of that, notably [[Ada Programming]]. -[[User:Withinfocus|Matt]] 23:41, 17 January 2006 (UTC)

::Now what should be the new location, is it [[Python]]?. --[[User:Baijum81|Baijum81]] 04:40, 8 June 2006 (UTC)
:::One day the pages should be moved by a bot to fit the new scheme, but I'm not sure how to request that. Going to the bot maintainer's talk page will probably do it. -[[User:Withinfocus|Matt]] 14:30, 9 June 2006 (UTC)

:I'm adding the Development stages to each of the sections to it's easier to find stuff to work on at a glance.  [[Help:Development_stages]] I'm not going to 100% beside any sections (yet) as I am not a python expert, and I am reluctant to say that a section that is complete.  Once I have done this, I will work on fleshing out some of the sections that need content.

:I am new to contributing to wikibooks--well to any of the wikimedia projects--so any pointers or suggestions would be helpful. -[[User:DavidRoss|DavidRoss]] 20:00, 6 Aug 2006 (PDT)

== Unified Navigation ==

The navigation bars on this book are problematic: there doesn't seem to be any kind of general consensus on navigation bar template.  What is/should be the convention? --[[User:Quartz25|Quartz25]] 21:19, 8 March 2007 (UTC)

For reference, the convention seems to be to use the &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{Python Programming/Navigation}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; template for the top, and no template is used on the bottom. --[[User:Quartz25|Quartz25]] 23:54, 11 June 2007 (UTC)

== Changes to the Introduction section ==
The introduction, as it now appears, is convoluted, incomplete, and circular.  Thus I propose the following pages to be used in the following order:

1. Installing the python language itself
:* Broken down by platform
2. Interactive mode Python interpreter.
:*With demonstrative &quot;Hello World&quot; program (or perhaps a very simple ''print &quot;What Is Your Name?&quot;'', ''print &quot;What is your quest?&quot;'', ''print &quot;What is your favorite color?&quot;'') example.
3. Non-interactive mode python interpreter.
:*With the same demonstrative Hello program, instructing the user to use a simple text editor to save it as a text file.
4. Python Editors &amp; Addons
:(broken down by OS)
:*I'm placing this last, because this section is always going to be very much up in the air relative to a user's own tastes, but the link to the Python Editors should be maintained.
:*Furthermore, some people will be quite happy with the simple built-in text editors for quite a while, and we want to get them up to coding as quickly as possible, thus this section isn't, strictly speaking, necessary.
:*The addons come very last, because people just taking their first steps into python probably aren't looking to extend the language; again, not strictly necessary, not here anyway.
:* In fact, this last page could probably be best served as 2 separate sections of the appendix.

Once I figure out how to create subfolders and subpages in my user page, I'll start posting my reworking of the introduction there, and people can start commenting as they see fit. --[[User:MyOwnLittlWorld|MyOwnLittlWorld]] 19:24, 4 June 2007 (UTC)

The pages are up now at my [[User:MyOwnLittlWorld|user page]], please tell me what you think and whether or not the intro should be replaced.  Thanks, [[User:MyOwnLittlWorld|MyOwnLittlWorld]] 23:18, 4 June 2007 (UTC)

== Question or Suggestion on the TOC ==
When you say User Interface on the TOC to you mean a topic on UI creation or is it a section to explain the UI of Python IDLE.
And if its a UI section I will suggest some GUI Programming using the Tkinter Library if possible also support the Glade Library.
=== Few changes or Updates ===
# Help on the Python OOP page. I can use a little more help on the terms as their still too technical.
# Help with the installation of Python language (Ubuntu and Mac section)
--[[User:Dragonecc|Dragonecc]] ([[User talk:Dragonecc|talk]]) 01:34, 8 December 2007 (UTC)

== Two links to Gaming ==

There seems to be two links to the module &quot;[[Python Programming/Game Programming in Python|Game Programming in Python]]&quot; in the index.  Should one be deleted?  It is messing up the navigation on each page.  

If so, which one should go?  I was thinking about getting rid of the one under the section &quot;Learning to program in Python&quot; because the game programming is a more advanced subject.  

--[[User:Hypergeek14|hypergeek14]] ([[User talk:Hypergeek14|talk]]) 21:14, 26 July 2008 (UTC)

I have just noticed that there are also two links to the [[Python Programming/Files|Files]] module.  This time I think the link under &quot;Rocking the Python (Modules)&quot; section should go, as files are a basic concept.  

--[[User:Hypergeek14|hypergeek14]] ([[User talk:Hypergeek14|talk]]) 21:21, 26 July 2008 (UTC)

:The deed has been done.  
:
:--[[User:Hypergeek14|hypergeek14]] ([[User talk:Hypergeek14|talk]]) 21:44, 29 July 2008 (UTC)

== Examples? ==

I would like to understand the reasons for using dictionaries, tuples, lists, etc. I can't see the reasons for doing most of the things in this language. There are never an explanation of ''why'' you'd want to use certain things. [[User:Hires an editor|Hires an editor]] ([[User talk:Hires an editor|talk]]) 21:40, 18 February 2010 (UTC)

== redundancy ==

Is there a reason why most of the content is there twice? Once under &quot;Learning to program in Python&quot; and once under &quot;Python concepts&quot;. I believe we should merge those sections. Especially the following are very similar:

* Errors and Exceptions
* Flow control and Decision control
* Scoping and Namespaces

Also I dont see a reason why modules need to be treated separately but still appear many times before in the text. I would also like to fix that. Any other suggestions? Greetings --[[User:Hannes Röst|Hannes Röst]] ([[User talk:Hannes Röst|talk]]) 07:56, 20 August 2010 (UTC)
:Yes, I believe the sections were written by separate people with differing visions of the final book.  I was trying to rewrite the whole thing coherently, but moved on to other projects.  You can see my single plan [[Python_Programming/TODO|here]].  Your goals seem similar to what I was thinking.  I might return as I would like to teach Python to a friend from this. --[[User:Jesdisciple|Jesdisciple]] ([[User talk:Jesdisciple|talk]]) 12:12, 23 August 2010 (UTC)

== Which version of Python to use ==

Python 2.x or 3.x? The book in its current form contains many examples and explanation of language structures, internal functions, statements and all of that. However, there seems to be great inconsistency in the implementation of it.
The most glaring is the use of print() as a function (3.x style) or as a bare statement (2.x style).
Whichever choice is made, it needs to be clearly represented somewhere, that or all examples need a note as to the language major version they're written in, or even written in both major versions as examples should be copy/past-able.

Drivers for a decision 2 vs 3:
* How long is this book expected to be useful (3.x is going to be more useful in the longer run)
* Is third-party package support critical for people still learning the language (as most exist purely for 2.x and 2to3 is not a tool for those new to the language)
* What version is mastered by the editors here (going with 3, only to discover a wholesome three people know it, is a disappointment about to happen)


:
:Greetings while you may have a valid point on newer Python release, there are some problems.  Python 2.6 is highly use release across major Linux :releases and corporate development.  For this environment Python module are a great impact and migration to Python 3 make have costly deployment.  :Until modules are translated to Python 3 or native supported development for Python 2.6 will continue. This has being experimented with other :programming language like Cobol, Fortran and Pascal.  Also this book samples could be easily ported to Python 3 with minor changes.  Went the :development community embrace Python 3 then the book could either be ported or a new book could be written.
: Hope this help.

:~~--[[User:Dragonecc|Dragonecc]] ([[User talk:Dragonecc|talk]]) 16 January 2011(UTC)

::Question remains. Is this book based on Python 2 or 3 or is it mix of both? In any case it should be clearly stated. --[[User:Usp|Usp]] ([[User talk:Usp|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Usp|contribs]]) 18:29, 22 March 2013 (UTC)

== Python 2 Vs Python 3 ==

As there are substantial differences between Python2 and Python3, it would be better if this book clearly stated which version it does cover to avoid leading newbies onto a steep learning curve. --[[User:Mecanismo|Mecanismo]] ([[User talk:Mecanismo|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Mecanismo|contribs]]) 17:05, 26 July 2013 (UTC)
: The book mainly covers Python 2; in each location in which it covers Python 3 in addition, it should state so explicitly. An example of indicating which Python is being described is at [[Python Programming/Input and Output]]. --[[User:Dan Polansky|Dan Polansky]] ([[User talk:Dan Polansky|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Dan Polansky|contribs]]) 20:03, 13 October 2013 (UTC)

== Archive Old Discussions ==
Let's archive the old discussions.  It is pointless and confusing having them around if they are no longer relevant. [[User:Hackbinary|Hackbinary]] ([[User talk:Hackbinary|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Hackbinary|contribs]]) 21:50, 13 October 2013 (UTC)
:This is for you Dan-the-man, so could you revert the Talk page back to where I had it last night, and copy in the additions that we both have put on it?  Thanks in advance. [[User:Hackbinary|Hackbinary]] ([[User talk:Hackbinary|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Hackbinary|contribs]]) 21:51, 13 October 2013 (UTC)
* I oppose archiving the old discussions. I only support their archiving after the page becomes long, which it has not. --[[User:Dan Polansky|Dan Polansky]] ([[User talk:Dan Polansky|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Dan Polansky|contribs]]) 22:08, 13 October 2013 (UTC)

== Contents / Landing Page re-org ==
Last night I reorganised the Contents page.  Danielle Polansky was not happy with some of words that I chose for section headings.  I propose reverting back my changes, and use the following headings:
Intro --&gt; Getting Started
Basics --&gt; Fundamentals
I introduced a new section called 'Code Reuse' that moves out everything from Functions, to Classes, and namespaces.  
Modules is redundant
Standard Library Modules
Third-party modules
Writing extension modules --&gt; Extending Python
Appendices
What are your thoughts?  [[User:Hackbinary|Hackbinary]] ([[User talk:Hackbinary|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Hackbinary|contribs]]) 21:50, 13 October 2013 (UTC)
* I oppose your changes, now as before.
* Your &quot;Dan-the-man&quot;, &quot;Danielle Polansky&quot;, and &quot;Danny boy&quot;[https://en.wikibooks.org/w/index.php?diff=2566079] are not in good faith. Go away and find another playground. --[[User:Dan Polansky|Dan Polansky]] ([[User talk:Dan Polansky|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Dan Polansky|contribs]]) 22:10, 13 October 2013 (UTC)
**And you calling me a moron is in not in good faith.  You talking down to me is not good faith.  If you would like to be treated with respect and dignity Dan, then I suggest you treat others with respect and dignity.  Your treatment of me has been rather undignified, and I am glad that I illustrated that to you.[[User:Hackbinary|Hackbinary]] ([[User talk:Hackbinary|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Hackbinary|contribs]]) 22:27, 13 October 2013 (UTC)
**You conceded that chapters did not follow logically.  Here is my revision of the page for you to review again:  [https://en.wikibooks.org/w/index.php?title=Python_Programming&amp;oldid=2565977] [[User:Hackbinary|Hackbinary]] ([[User talk:Hackbinary|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Hackbinary|contribs]]) 22:27, 13 October 2013 (UTC)
**It is you that I wish could find another playground.  All I want to do is add some content, and already expressed, improve the readability, and ease of use of the book. You seem to have some idea in your head on how it should be, but you will not share it and you are unwilling to have others contribute how they think the book should work.  And you have taken a very abrasive, demeaning tone with me.  [[User:Hackbinary|Hackbinary]] ([[User talk:Hackbinary|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Hackbinary|contribs]]) 22:27, 13 October 2013 (UTC)
**I am pressing ahead with reorganising, refactoring, and rationalising the chapters and chapter order as there is a fair bit of duplicated content which needs to be sorted through.  I have organised the chapters into what I think are a coherent order.   There is currently duplication across numerous chapters, and as much as as possible, I have grouped chapters with similar content together, but their names may not be representative of their content at this time, eg text is really about strings.  [[User:Hackbinary|Hackbinary]] ([[User talk:Hackbinary|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Hackbinary|contribs]]) 16:28, 15 October 2013 (UTC)
** If you think you have a better order, or vision on how it should be, let's discuss, and get it documented [[User:Hackbinary|Hackbinary]] ([[User talk:Hackbinary|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Hackbinary|contribs]]) 16:30, 15 October 2013 (UTC)
*** I disagree with such parts of your edits as is renaming &quot;Basics&quot; to &quot;Fundamentals&quot; or even &quot;The very Language Basics&quot;[https://en.wikibooks.org/w/index.php?title=Python_Programming&amp;diff=2565869&amp;oldid=2548839]. I disagree with edits that are not constituting an objectively unquestionable improvements but rather are pushing a personal preference when these edits come from someone who is not interested in contributing ''actual content'' to the book. You are not prevented from adding ''content''; you are prevented from an ''arbitrary reorganization''. No, you should not be &quot;pressing ahead with reorganising, refactoring, and rationalising&quot; as long as your content contribution to Wikibook is nearly nonexistent and there is an opposition to that reorganizing. --[[User:Dan Polansky|Dan Polansky]] ([[User talk:Dan Polansky|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Dan Polansky|contribs]]) 08:03, 19 October 2013 (UTC)
****Sorry, you're inactivity lead the status quo being changed. While you have contributed some good content, you are not the dictator of Programming Python.  The content must be rationalised in a progressive manner, and if you are unwilling to be cooperative, I will seek assistance from others.  You have a track record of being obstinate, and forcing your views on others.   To begin with Basics is not a good section title.  The word is overly generic and does nothing to articulate that the section is about core building blocks of the language, Fundamentals on the other hand says this is core material to what will be discussed further on.  Furthermore, it makes immeasurable sense to organise related chapters that duplicate content together, before the content is merged into one chapter.  Do you not concur that the chapters Sequences, Data types, Numbers, Strings, Text, Lists, Tuples, Dictionaries, and Sets duplicates a fair amount of material?  Do not agree that this needs to merged together in a managed, organised and controlled way? If you are going to be so argumentative, and obstructive to the work that I am doing, then fine, that is your decision, but I am going to press ahead.  If you wish to discuss it, and compromise, then I am happy to do the same.  I am not willing to be in a situation where you feel that you can call the shots and that you feel that you can make arbitrary decisions yourself.  Over the past week I have been reading through chapters with greater detail, and reading through the change logs, and for example I do not approve of your revert 6 Oct, Input and Output [https://en.wikibooks.org/w/index.php?title=Python_Programming%2FInput_and_Output&amp;diff=2563925&amp;oldid=2555399] as it seems to me that using with is the better way to open a file context and read the file because 1.) you do not have to explicitly close the file once the execution path falls out of scope, and 2.) the handling of exceptions is better with the with block.  My point is that you make arbitrary changes yourself that have dubious merit.[[User:Hackbinary|Hackbinary]] ([[User talk:Hackbinary|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Hackbinary|contribs]]) 12:50, 20 October 2013 (UTC)

== pdf problems ==

In the pdf version page 94 (numbered 90) has the page number superimposed over text.
The first 2 pages aren't numbered, the next 2 are numbered III &amp; IV, &amp; the rest are numbered starting with 1. The Contents are on pages III, IV, &amp; 1 with the text starting on 3 which doesn't make sense.
At least on my system, pages 157-159 print out cropped. In the case of 157 and 159, cropping some of the blank space at the top and bottom respectively solved the problem. To fix 158 I suggest putting the entire section 36.3 on page 159.
[[Special:Contributions/69.72.92.242|69.72.92.242]] ([[User talk:69.72.92.242|discuss]]) 00:31, 26 December 2013 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>9a2qwwq8g8khfeengrzagtxdmqz8s85</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Jrincayc</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>3880</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1937772</id>
      <parentid>1754785</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-09-21T21:02:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>fixed links</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">See my [[w:en:User:Jrincayc|user page on english]]

== Wikification of [http://www.honors.montana.edu/~jjc/easytut/ non-programmers python tutorial] ==
*[[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python 2.6/Front matter]]
*[[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python 2.6/Intro]]
*[[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python 2.6/Hello, World]]
*[[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python 2.6/Who Goes There?]]
*[[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python 2.6/Count to 10]]
*[[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python 2.6/Decisions]]
*[[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python 2.6/Debugging]]
*[[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python 2.6/Defining Functions]]
*[[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python 2.6/Lists]]
*[[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python 2.6/For Loops]]
*[[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python 2.6/Boolean Expressions]]
*[[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python 2.6/Dictionaries]]
*[[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python 2.6/Using Modules]]
*[[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python 2.6/More on Lists]]
*[[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python 2.6/Revenge of the Strings]]
*[[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python 2.6/File IO]]
*[[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python 2.6/Dealing with the imperfect]]
*[[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python 2.6/The End]]
*[[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python 2.6/FAQ]]</text>
      <sha1>exkz1g2nxg00gjxiqj2ldeqsppdfzbn</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Puzzles/Decision puzzles/Weighings Once More/Solution</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>3883</id>
    <revision>
      <id>872701</id>
      <parentid>382590</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-05-20T22:52:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mattb112885</username>
        <id>33615</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[Talk:Puzzles:Decision puzzles:Weighings Once More:Solution]] moved to [[Talk:Puzzles/Decision puzzles/Weighings Once More/Solution]]: NC</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Hi, good idea to have a general proof! Here are some things I am not so happy about yet:

You say that S(n) can measure weights between 1 and |S(n)|. In standard mathematical
notation |S(n)| would be just the number of elements in S(n) which is n+1 (maybe we
should introduce another symbol like W(n) or so). Also, to be
technically precise, we should write &lt;math&gt;\lfloor 3^{(n+1)}/2 \rfloor&lt;/math&gt;  rather
than 3^(n+1)/2 for the upper bound of weights that can be measured.
[[User:ThomasStrohmann | Thomas]]

----

The answer (four weights: {1,3,9,27}) is correct as far as the question is posed. But, as the question does not require weights to be measured in a single weighing, the question and answer both miss an interesting aspect of measuring integral weights: that it is not necessary for the scale to be balanced to correctly identify an unknown weight. With four known weights, {2,6,18,54}, it's possible to measure up to 80, not just 40:

If x &lt; 2, then x = 1.

If x = 2, then x = 2.

If 2 &lt; x &lt; 6-2, then x = 3, etc.

You could repose the question with 80 instead of 40, or turn it around and ask what range of integral weights can be measured using four known weights.

[[User:Munin | Munin]]</text>
      <sha1>9nwe7vr1k70jsvmhnr4nbesrfw9px2i</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Minderaser</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>3888</id>
    <revision>
      <id>155728</id>
      <parentid>80219</parentid>
      <timestamp>2004-12-22T23:30:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Minderaser</username>
        <id>458</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">Email contact martoon42@linuxmail.org

AIM: martoon42</text>
      <sha1>5yicq9aocln4n7pzt3npms4cujcg4qa</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:Minderaser</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>3889</id>
    <revision>
      <id>155729</id>
      <parentid>134371</parentid>
      <timestamp>2005-05-31T11:23:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Geocachernemesis</username>
        <id>2477</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>rv vandalism and link spam by 202.177.170.115</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Hi,

I intend to help writing LPI certification course. Actually I already have courses for 101, 201 and 202, although there are far from ready. The courses I have are made with OpenOffice Impress (presentation). That's compressed XML. Do you how to extract the content to the wiki?

I also intend to translate them to French. [[User:Yann|Yann]] 19:29, 13 Jun 2004 (UTC)

Hi,
I got your message. Yes, I already upload 2 books and I plan to upload one more. [[User:Yann|Yann]] 14:07, 24 Dec 2004 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>9xuycz8efcvkdl1bb1z69q40rfetfty</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Vietnamese/Authors</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3890</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751224</id>
      <parentid>751223</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-02-11T08:24:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mxn</username>
        <id>167</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">The following people have started lessons as part of this textbook, or have made notable contributions to an existing lesson. They should be able to answer questions you may have about the Vietnamese language or Vietnamese culture:

&lt;!-- Note: This is not the place for self-promotion; just something so that interested readers may find out who to contact with questions. --&gt;

:'''[[User:Mxn|Minh Nguyễn]]'''
::Started the Vietnamese textbook, and at last count has started '''8''' lessons so far.
:'''[[User:Nam Đỗ|Nam Đỗ]]
::I added some parts of my book into this course.

If you feel that you have made notable contributions to this textbook, please feel free to add your name to this list.

[[Category:Vietnamese]]</text>
      <sha1>9p4m9rnrpyrcne1q6u6w2up6wliidmb</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>