<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook talk:Le Tourin</title>
    <ns>103</ns>
    <id>4948</id>
    <revision>
      <id>955546</id>
      <parentid>438253</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-09-01T00:24:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>24.60.117.236</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Edit history==
    * (cur) (last)  . . M 00:02, 29 Oct 2002 . . Olivier
    * (cur) (last) . . 13:47, 27 Sep 2002 . . Maveric149 (Wikified)
    * (cur) (last) . . 13:46, 27 Sep 2002 . . Maveric149 (moving attrib to the top of talk)
    * (cur) (last) . . 13:37, 27 Sep 2002 . . Quintessent

*Well, geez, how about telling us how much water to add?  A cup?  4 cups?  A tablespoon?  A &quot;lot&quot;?  A &quot;little&quot;?  That seems like a pretty vital ingredient to leave out of the measurements![[User:66.1.40.242|66.1.40.242]] 17:10, 29 Jun 2004 (UTC)

== VfD discussion ==

This is a worthless recipe taken from a very unreliable source, apparently almost word for word from a Net source.  The quantities are approximations added by various readers and there is no quantity for the water, the most important ingredient.  I have just consulted my magisterial 1960 edition of the Larousse Gastronomique and there is no mention of this soup amongst its hundreds of soup recipes.  It is similar to various old onion soup and garlic soup recipes, but without further info about the ingredients it should be deleted.  A web search turns up a '''real''' recipe for this soup that sounds excellent, but from a restaurant in Canada.  Here is the link to that recipe. 

http://www.gumbopages.com/food/french/garlic-soup.html

Go there, then compare that version with this weird entry here  -- which almost certainly was inserted by someone out of vanity or for testing the system.[[User:66.1.40.242|66.1.40.242]] 01:19, 14 Jul 2004 (UTC)

**Sorry, I keep forgetting that I have to log in a second time if I go to Wikibooks from WP -- it's a dumb system....[[User:Hayford Peirce|Hayford Peirce]] 01:27, 14 Jul 2004 (UTC)
**I have to disagree, I don't think this is a speedy delete candidate.  I'd like to remind our users that any module on a wiki can be edited, so if you dislike a particular incarnation of a recipe, and has find another, feel free to change the page.  Recipes are not covered by copyright; but be carefull, as any descriptive text (rather than lists of ingredients and procedural steps) is covered by copyright protection. [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] 09:40, 15 Jul 2004 (UTC) (ps: I linked to the module in question and removed descriptive narative of the location)

*Well, I could always try to fiddle the recipe to what seem to be appropriate ingredients, but I find it strange that someone would dump this useless recipe here in the first place.  And it has almost *no* history in French culinary arts that I can find.   It's really just a garlic soup recipe.  Or a quick onion soup.  Anyway, let's wait and see if there are any other comments on the situation.[[User:Hayford Peirce|Hayford Peirce]] 18:56, 15 Jul 2004 (UTC)

== 10-12 cloves of garlic ==

I changed mention of 12 cloves of garlic to 10-12 cloves of garlic. The reason I have done so is as follow. Initially, this recipe had no mention of quantities. Later, Gentgeen added them as a guess as 10 cloves. Eadmund came along and changed the quantity of garlic from 10 to 12. He/she didn't explain why the change was made. While it's possible he/she tested the recipe and found 12 was best, this seems unlikely.

The edit which changed 10 to 12 cloves was part of a series of edits to refine recipes to a style that Eadmund prefers. Some of these were useful such as fixing spelling mistakes and changing dividers like 1/2 to the integral form, some of these were okay such as changing Tablespoon to Tbsp. but quite a number of these were disruptive, removing any metric measurements (and replacing them with imperial when the recipe did not already include imperial), removing the Fahrenheit F from degrees etc. Nearly all of these have now been reverted, one of the last was in the Pavlova recipe which I carried out and which was how I came across Eadmund's edits.

Given this history, we can expect that far more likely, Eadmund has never tried this recipe and only changed the 10 cloves to 12 cloves because he/she somehow felt that 12 cloves was more imperial then 10 cloves which I guess he/she felt was too metric... I don't know but I'm guessing Eadmund is a conservative Brit. If the original author of this recipe has specified 10 cloves, I would have completely removed the 12 cloves but since it was a guess, I decided to leave Eadmund's recommendation even though the reason most likely has nothing to do with any actual experience, simply a preference for the number 12 to 10... [[User:Nil Einne|Nil Einne]] 13:24, 25 April 2006 (UTC)

== results ==

I gave this a shot, and it turned out a bland.  I found that by replacing some of the water with chicken stock, and adding more salt, it was more palatable.  But it wasn't very garlicy, and it really didn't have much flavor.  The texture and appearance was good, however.  I probably over-cooked the garlic.</text>
      <sha1>nr7xipz79vrh0l5b2ctsobbkff34yov</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Lucid Dreaming/Reality Checks/Reading</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4950</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2626118</id>
      <parentid>2490758</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-04-03T19:44:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AwesoMan3000</username>
        <id>1498566</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Examples of this reality check working */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{LDRCTOC}}

==Presentation==

With the reading reality check, you read some text, look away, and see if you can remember the text. Then, you check if it has changed when you turn back. Do this twice. You can also actively try to change the text (note that changing text in a Wikibook is not necessarily evidence you are dreaming though!).

For example, consider this paragraph. Try to remember its text. Then reload the page. If you realise that the text is now missing, you know that you are dreaming.

This reality check works because the mind has no external input to base the text upon.

Note you will usually have no problems reading text in a dream. It is remembering the text which is hard.

==Examples of this reality check working==

* I looked at some text that I found, then looked away. I couldn't remember what it said.
* I looked at some text that I found, then looked away, then looked back. The text had completely changed or is scrambled up.
* I looked at some text that I found, and it just said &quot;lucid lucid lucid...&quot;. I was surprised but understood the message.
* I dreamt I was reading a book.  I closed my eyes to sneeze, and when I looked back, the text was the same, but it was in a completely different font.
*There was a poster on a distant wall showing a spruce tree somewhere. I looked away and then back at it, where the scene changed to a small spruce tree in the middle of a city.

==Examples of this reality check failing==

* I looked at some text that I found, then looked away. I could perfectly remember what it said.
* I looked at some text that I found, then looked away, then looked back. The text stayed exactly the same.
* I read a book and then the text start to disappear and then on TV said all books that made in Japan after 2002 will have disappearing text. I didn't realize it was a dream until I wake up.
[[Category:Lucid Dreaming]]

[[es:Sueño lúcido/Test de Realidad/Lectura]]</text>
      <sha1>s7m24d004t9gun46ypms0o4zigu710f</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Dandelion</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4953</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2512920</id>
      <parentid>2512880</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-04-15T07:42:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/Kriswrite|Kriswrite]] ([[User talk:Kriswrite|talk]]) to last version by QuiteUnusual</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{ingredient}} | [[Cookbook:Vegetable|Vegetable]]

The greens of the '''dandelion''' plant are sometimes used raw in [[Cookbook:Salad|salads]],  sautéed or steamed. They taste like chicory and endive, with an intense heartiness overlying a bitter tinge. 

Dandelion leaves are best harvested in early spring, before the flowers appear. The youngest plants are best, being the least bitter. Dandelion can also be harvested again in late fall, as a frost destroys their protective bitterness. The dandelion is unusual, being one of the few non-toxic plants with milky white sap. Dandelions make a great free meal. Not only are they high in nutrition and very good for you, they also taste great!

[[Image:Loewenzahn pae.jpg|right|thumb|Dandelions]]

== Where Do I Take Them From? ==
Find some flowers in your yard or field that are not right by the road and collecting pollution from traffic. Larger varieties of dandelions and older, tougher leaves may be cooked like any greens.  They are probably closest in character to mustard greens, though bitter. Young plants are a little less bitter; the very young ones make an excellent though slightly bitter salad. 

With a knife, cut the whole plant at the top of the root so that it comes out of the ground intact. You should snap off the yellow flowers that have already opened up but be sure to leave any unopened buds - these are the tastiest part!

== Remove The Bitterness ==
Once you have given your pickings a good washing to get off all the dirt, stick them in a pot with enough water to just cover and boil until they are nice and soft. When the water turns yellow, replace it with fresh water and re-boil. This will remove the bitterness. When they are done they will have the consistency of cooked spinach. If you have very young plants you may decide to skip this step.

== Recipes ==
* Strain and dress with [[Cookbook:Butter|butter]], a squeeze of [[Cookbook:Lemon|lemon]], or [[Cookbook:Vinegar|vinegar]]. Optionally, add little pieces of fried [[Cookbook:Bacon|bacon]].
* Dandelion salad is often accompanied with [[Cookbook:Hard Boiled Eggs|hard boiled eggs]].
* Lightly [[Cookbook:Sautéing|sauté]] (or [[Cookbook:Roasting|roast]]) a clove of [[Cookbook:Garlic|garlic]], half an [[Cookbook:Onion|onion]] and a quarter teaspoon of [[Cookbook:Chili Pepper|red pepper flakes]] in a tablespoon and a half of [[Cookbook:Olive Oil|olive oil]]. Add a quart of damp greens to the sautéed vegetables, cover and steam over low heat for about thirty minutes.  Season to taste and serve.

==External Links==
*[http://www.backwoodshome.com/articles2/kallas82.html Making Dandelions Palatable by John Kallas of Wild Food Adventures]
* [http://fxcuisine.com/default.asp?Display=78 Dandelion Syrup - step-by-step illustrated recipe in English]
* [http://www.northernbushcraft.com/plants/dandelion/notes.htm Edible parts of dandelions]: Identification and edible parts of dandelions.

&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Dandelion-leaf.jpg|Dandelion leaf
Image:Taraxacum officinalis DSC02036.JPG|Dandelions
Image:Löwenzahn uhf.JPG|Dandelions
&lt;/gallery&gt;</text>
      <sha1>pt8xki7fdcl39g9tat8sr0mt6zna68p</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Paella Valenciana</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4958</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2434701</id>
      <parentid>2421473</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T01:32:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>124.158.18.230</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Ingredients */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{recipesummary
| Category = Spanish recipes
| Servings = 6
| Time = 90 minutes
| Image = [[Image:ValencianPaella.jpg|275 px]]
}}

{{recipe}} | [[Cookbook:Cuisine of Spain|Cuisine of Spain]] | [[Cookbook:Rice Recipes|Rice Recipes]]

'''''Paella Valenciana''''' and its seafood variation originated in the early 1800s in Spain's Valencian region near lake Albufera. Prior to the 19th century, the ingredients for Valencian paella varied greatly with the most unusual being marsh rat.&lt;ref&gt;Manuel Vázquez Montalbán, ''La cocina de los mediterráneos'', Ediciones B - Mexico&lt;/ref&gt;

Valencians consider Valencian paella and [[cookbook:Paella de Marisco|seafood paella]] as authentic. They view all other variations as impostors.

This recipe is based on the one that Chef Juanry Segui serves in his restaurant with plenty of detailed explanation for those attempting this for the first time.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lacocinadejuanry.es/paella-valenciana-la-cocina-de-juanry.html Valencian paella recipe by Juanry Segui]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Equipment==
*A 38-centimeter (15-inch) ''paellera''
*A 7.6-liter (two-gallon) pot
*A rice skimmer
*A sharp chopping knife for meat and vegetables
*A large serving spoon
*A clean, white towel large enough to cover the ''paellera''
*A wide heating source such as:  
:#A stove large enough to accommodate the size of the ''paellera''
:#A [http://www.deliciasdeespana.com/store1/shopexd.asp?id=313 gas burner] designed specifically for ''paelleras'' 
:#A charcoal barbecue 
:#A low, forged steel tripod to support the ''paellera'' over a wood or charcoal fire
:#Cinder blocks or heat-resistant bricks to support the ''paellera'' over a wood or charcoal fire

==Ingredients==
'''Please read ''[[cookbook:paella cooking techniques|Paella cooking techniques]]'' before attempting this recipe.'''
* 500 gr (17.5 ounces) [[Cookbook:Chicken|chicken]]
* 500 gr (17.5 ounces) [[Cookbook:Rabbit|rabbit]] (or [[Cookbook:Duck|duck]])
* 20 gr (3/4 ounce) [[Cookbook:Salt|salt]]
* 8 tablespoons [[Cookbook:Olive Oil|olive oil]]
* 250 gr (10 ounces) chopped green [[Cookbook:Bell Pepper|bell peppers]] (optional)
* 1 clove [[Cookbook:Garlic|garlic]] (optional)
* 1 tablespoon sweet [[cookbook:paprika|paprika]] 
* 500 gr (17.5 ounces) diced or grated [[cookbook:tomato|tomatoes]]
* 2 liters (2 quarts) water (preferably hard water)
* 24 boiled [[Cookbook:Snail|snails]] (optional)
* 125 gr (4.5 ounces) large haricot beans (canned or fresh)
* 100 gr (3.5 ounces) small haricot beans (canned or fresh)
* 125 gr (4.5 ounces) runner beans or [[cookbook:green beans|pole beans]] (fresh only)
* 8 to 10 threads of [[Cookbook:Saffron|saffron]] and/or 1.5 teaspoons yellow food coloring (See note below about saffron and food coloring.)
* 400 gr (14 ounces) [[cookbook:rice|short-grain, white rice]]
* 6 to 8 branches of fresh [[cookbook:rosemary|rosemary]]

==Procedure==
Clean the snails, poultry and rabbit thoroughly. Cut the poultry and rabbit into small pieces and salt them generously. Pour olive oil in a ''paellera'' and, when hot, [[Cookbook:sautéing|sauté]] the poultry and rabbit pieces until golden brown. Add green peppers and sauté for one minute. Add the garlic and sauté until brown. Be careful; garlic burns easily. Once the garlic is brown, add the paprika followed quickly by the tomatoes to prevent the paprika from burning. Sauté until the tomatoes become dark and pulpy and the mixture has reduced a bit. Add the water and bring it to a rolling boil. Then add the snails, fresh haricot beans (if canned, continue reading to see when to add these), runner beans (or green beans) and saffron (and/or food coloring). Allow the mixture to boil for 10 minutes over a high flame.

After 10 minutes have passed, you should have a flavorful broth. It's customary at this point to allow your dinner guests to taste it. The purpose is to determine if the broth needs more salt. If so, add more salt, a pinch at a time, until everybody is satisfied.
 
Add the rice and stir it using the rice skimmer. Then, once again with the skimmer, spread it over the bottom of the ''paellera''. The coating of rice should be one [[Cookbook:cm|centimeter]] thick. Let it cook over a high flame for 10 minutes. Then reduce the heat to medium and let it [[Cookbook:Simmering|simmer]] for four minutes. Add the canned haricot beans and reduce the heat again to low and let it simmer for another four minutes. Taste the rice about once every four to five minutes. You'll know it's done when it's slightly firm to the bite. Italians use a similar approach when cooking pasta. Italians call this texture ''[[Cookbook:al dente|al dente]]''.

At this point, there should be some toasted rice sticking to the bottom of the pan. This is a delicacy in Valencia called ''socarrat''. If no ''socarrat'' has developed, increase the flame to high and listen for the crackling sound of rice toasting at the bottom of the pan. Reduce the heat to low once the aroma of toasted rice wafts upwards.

Remove the pan from the heat when the rice is almost dry and place the rosemary branches on top. Cover with a clean, white towel (a white towel prevents dye from leeching onto the paella) and wait five minutes before serving to allow the rice to absorb the remaining broth.

==See also==
*[[cookbook:Mastering the art of cooking paellas|Mastering the art of cooking paellas]]
{{wikipedia|Paella}}
==External links==
*[http://www.spain-recipes.com/paellarecipes.html Paella recipes presented by Spain-recipes.com]
*[http://www.lacocinadejuanry.es/videos.html Paella recipes by Chef Juanry Segui, a prominent Valencian chef]
*[http://www.paellapans.com/recpaella.html Paella recipes from Sarah Jay]
*[http://www.foodnetwork.com/recipes/tyler-florence/paella-with-seafood-chicken-and-chorizo-recipe/index.html Mixed paella recipe presented by the Food Network]
*[http://recipes.epicurean.com/recipe/15697/traditional-paella.html Mixed paella recipe presented by Epicurean.com]

==References==
{{reflist}}
[[de:Kochbuch/ Paella Valenciana]]
[[es:Artes culinarias/Recetas/Paella tradicional]]
[[fr:Livre de cuisine/Paella]]
[[it:Libro di cucina/Ricette/Paella]]
[[ja:料理本/パエリャ]]
[[Category:Rice recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Mediterranean recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Spanish recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Chicken recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Seafood recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Featured recipes]]</text>
      <sha1>aa77jv4860svdydp4rhfupn89x2r2yp</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Cuisine of France</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4961</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2710612</id>
      <parentid>2710611</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-06T13:35:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>50.200.20.126</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Burgundy */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{cuisine|France}} | [[Cookbook:European cuisines|European cuisines]]

French cuisine is characterised by its extreme diversity. Despite France's history of political and cultural centralization around its capital Paris, each region has its own distinctive specialities: cuisine from North-West France uses [[Cookbook:Butter|butter]] and [[Cookbook:Cream|cream]]; Provençal cuisine (from the southeast) favours [[Cookbook:Olive Oil|olive oil]] and herbs; and eastern French recipes are reminiscent of [[Cookbook:Cuisine of Germany|German cuisine]], including [[Cookbook:Sausage|sausage]]s, [[Cookbook:Beer|beer]] and [[Cookbook:Sauerkraut|sauerkraut]]. [[Cookbook:Wine|Wine]] and [[Cookbook:Cheese|cheese]] are an integral part of French cuisine, both as ingredients and accompaniments.


==Related Categories==
The following related category may be of interest. 

'''L'''

[[Cookbook:Louisiana_Creole_cuisine|Louisiana_Creole_cuisine]]

==French cuisine today==
French cuisine can broadly be divided into three categories:

* ''Cuisine bourgeoise'', which includes all the classic French dishes which are not (or no longer) specifically regional, and which have been adapted over the years to suit the taste of the affluent classes. At the 'top end' of this category is what is known as ''haute cuisine'', a highly complex and refined approach to food preparation and kitchen management which developed from court cuisine.

* ''Cuisine du terroir'', which covers regional specialties with a strong focus on quality local produce and peasant tradition.

* ''Cuisine nouvelle'' or &quot;nouvelle cuisine&quot;, which developed in the 1970s as a reaction to traditional cuisine, under the influence of chefs such as Michel Guérard. This type of cooking is characterized by shorter cooking times, much lighter sauces and dressings, and smaller portions presented in a refined, decorative manner. Its modern, inventive approach sometimes includes techniques and combinations from abroad (especially Asia) and has had a profound influence on cooking styles all over the world.

Today (2004) there is a distinct focus on ''cuisine du terroir'' in France, with a return to traditional rustic cooking and the flavours of local farm produce. The ''fusion'' cuisine popular in the English-speaking world is not widespread in France, though some restaurants in the capital have a ''fusion'' theme, and many modern French chefs are influenced by a variety of international cooking styles.

Vegetarianism (''végétarisme'') is not widespread in France, and few restaurants cater for vegetarians. Veganism (''végétalisme'') is hardly known or represented at all.

For French people, cooking is an immensely important part of their culture and a way of life.

==Famous French dishes==
* [[Cookbook:Frog's Legs a'la Parisienne|Frogs' Legs à la Parisienne]] (Cuisses de grenouilles)
* [[Cookbook:Snails with Garlic Butter (Escargots à la Bourguignonne)|Escargots à la Bourguignonne (Snails with Garlic Butter)]]
* [[Cookbook:Coq au Vin|Coq au Vin]] 
* [[Cookbook:Baguette|Baguettes]]
* [[Cookbook:Cheese|Cheeses]]
* [[Cookbook:Foie Gras|Foie Gras]]
* [[Cookbook:Ratatouille|Ratatouille]]
* [[Cookbook:Pot-au-feu|Pot-au-feu]]

==Desserts==
* [[Cookbook:Crème Brûlée|Crème Brûlée]] (often mistaken to be French, this dish actually originated in England or Spain)
* [[Cookbook:Crêpe|Crêpe]]s (a speciality of Brittany) 
* [[Cookbook:Chocolate Mousse|Chocolate Mousse]] (Mousse au chocolat) 
* Pastries 
* [[Cookbook:Mille-feuille|Mille-feuille]]

==Specialities by region/city==
[[Image:FranceRegionsNumbered.png|right|thumb|Regions of France]]

===Alsace=== 
:Map (1.)
* [[Cookbook:Choucroute|Choucroute]] (sauerkraut with sausages, salt pork and potatoes) 
* [[Cookbook:Flammekueche|Flammekueche]] (or ''[[Tarte flambée]]'', like pizza, but topped with crème fraîche, onions, and bacon)
* [[Cookbook:Fleischnacka|Fleischnacka]]
* [[Cookbook:Fricassée de poulet à l’Alsacienne |''Fricassée de poulet à l’Alsacienne'']]
* [[Cookbook:Fish Stew of Alsace (Matelote de poissons d'Alsace)|''Matelote de poissons d'Alsace '']]
* [[Cookbook:Nouilles fraîches à l'Alsacienne|''Nouilles fraîches à l'Alsacienne'']]

===Alps===
:Map (22.)
* [[Cookbook:Raclette|Raclette]] (melted cheese served with potatoes, ham and often dried beef) 
* [[Cookbook:Fondue Savoyarde|Fondue Savoyarde]] (fondue made with cheese and white wine into which cubes of bread are dipped) 
* [[Cookbook:Tartiflette|Tartiflette]] (a Savoyard gratin with potatoes, Reblochon cheese, cream and pork)

===Aquitaine===
:Map (2.)

[[Crême Brûlée]]

===Auvergne===
:Map (3.)
* [[Cookbook:Tripoux|Tripoux]] (tripe 'parcels' in a savoury sauce) 
* [[Cookbook:Truffade|Truffade]] (potatoes sautéed with garlic and young &quot;tomme&quot; cheese) 
* [[Cookbook:Aligot|Aligot]] (mashed potatoes blended with young &quot;tomme&quot; cheese) 

===Basque country===
:Map
* See [[Cookbook:Basque cuisine|Basque cuisine]]

===Brittany===
:Map (6.)
* [[Cookbook:Cr%C3%AApe | Crêpes]]
* [[Cookbook:Kik ar Fars|Kik ar Fars]] (boiled pork dinner with a kind of dumpling) 
* [[Cookbook:Kouign Amann|Kouign Amann]] (a form of shortbread made with a very large proportion of butter) 

===Burgundy===
:Map (5.)

* [[Cookbook:Beurre à la bourguignonne|''Beurre à la bourguignonne'']]   &amp;ndash;   garlic and parsley butter for snails, broiled meats, fish, mussels, clams or oysters
* [[Cookbook:Snails with Garlic Butter (Escargots à la Bourguignonne)|''Escargots à la bourguignonne'']]     &amp;ndash;    snails baked in their shells with parsley butter

===Lorraine=== 
:Map (15.)
* [[Cookbook:Quiche|Quiche Lorraine]]
* [[Cookbook:Bouchée à la reine|''Bouchée à la reine'']]     &amp;ndash;     [[Cookbook:Vol-au-vent|''vol-au-vent'']] pastry shells filled with a chicken, mushroom and cream sauce [[Cookbook:Salpicon|''salpicon'']]
* [[Cookbook:Tourte à la Lorraine|''Tourte à la Lorraine'']]    &amp;ndash;   an elaborate meat pie with a [[Cookbook:Pâte brisée|''pâte brisée'']] (pie dough) base and a [[Cookbook:Puff pastry|puff pastry]] top which is baked. Ten minutes before the end of the baking period, a savoury egg-and-cream custard is poured through a hole in the pie crust and returned to the oven to set.

===Provence===
:Map (21.)
* [[Cookbook:Bouillabaisse|Bouillabaisse]] (a stew of mixed Mediterranean fish) 
* [[Cookbook:Ratatouille|Ratatouille]] 
* [[Cookbook:Pieds et Paquets|Pieds et Paquets]] (Lambs' feet and tripe 'parcels' in a savoury sauce)

===Nimes=== 
:Map (13.)
*	[[Cookbook:Cod, Olive Oil, and Cream Sauce (Brandade de Morue)|Brandade de morue de Nîmes]] - A dish of puréed salt cod, olive oil, milk or cream and garlic, served on toast as an appetizer or with potatoes as a main dish.

===Normandy===
:Map: Lower Normandy (4.)
::Upper Normandy (11.)
* [[Cookbook:Tripes à la mode de Caen|Tripes à la mode de Caen]] (tripe cooked in a highly seasoned sauce)
* [[Cookbook:Teurgoule|Teurgoule]] (cinnamon flavored rice pudding)

===Southwest=== 
:Map (2, 13, 16.)
* [[Cookbook:Cassoulet|Cassoulet]] (a dish made with beans, sausages and preserved duck or goose) 
* [[Cookbook:Foie Gras|Foie Gras]] (the liver of an overfed duck or goose) 

See also: 
* [[Cookbook:Cuisine|Cuisine]]  
* [[Cookbook:Recipes|Recipe Index]]

==Additional French recipes==
* [[Cookbook:Potatoes Anna|Potatoes Anna]]
* [[Cookbook:Le Tourin|Le Tourin]]
* [[Cookbook:Roux|Roux]]
* [[Cookbook:Béchamel Sauce|Béchamel sauce]]
* [[Cookbook:Potage Parmentier|Potage Parmentier]]

[[Category:French recipes| ]]

[[fr:Livre de cuisine/Recettes de cuisine française]]
[[nl:Kookboek/Franse keuken]]</text>
      <sha1>fuzfqjx1efd5zcaywsolsu2jcncfrqe</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Carrot</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4962</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2690387</id>
      <parentid>2287573</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-11T00:01:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Xania</username>
        <id>40302</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Carrot Recipes */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{displaytitle|tab=ingredient|title={{FULLPAGENAME}}}}
{{vegetable}}

[[Image:Daucus Carota.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Parts of a carrot]]                    

A '''carrot''' is a root [[Cookbook:Vegetable|vegetable]], typically orange
in color with a woody texture. The younger the carrot the smaller and more tender the flesh is, so 'baby carrots' are often preferred for raw use. Note that the 'baby carrots' you can buy bagged, washed and pre-peeled in US supermarkets are not actually 'babies' at all - they are larger carrots that have been mechanically shaped into stubs. True baby carrots (often known as 'Dutch carrots') are often sold by the bunch complete with tops. With a carrot that young, peeling is unnecessary - all that is needed is to scrub them under the tap to remove any dirt, and to cut off the hairy 'tail' and the leafy top. Older carrots benefit from peeling as the skin gets a lot more fibrous and hairy with age.

Carrots are often eaten raw, whole or shaved into [[Cookbook:Salad|salad]]s for color, and are often cooked in [[Cookbook:Soup|soup]]s and [[Cookbook:Stew|stew]]s. They are an essential ingredient in [[Cookbook:Carrot Cake|carrot cake]]. The greens are not generally eaten (though they have food benefit to humans, but often taste bitter), but they are technically edible.

Together with [[cookbook:Onion|onion]] and [[cookbook:Celery|celery]], carrots are one of the primary vegetables used in a ''[[Cookbook:Mirepoix|mirepoix]]'' to make various broths.

Carrots are orange because they contain large amounts of beta carotene (a precursor to Vitamin A). This gives rise to the myhth that they will improve your eyesight, by enhancing the performance of receptors on the retina in your eye. They are nevertheless good for eye health. Carrots are also rich in dietary [[Cookbook:Fiber|fiber]], [[W:Antioxidant|antioxidants]], [[w:Dietary mineral|minerals]] and are alkaline food.

[[Image:Carrots of many colors.jpg|thumb|200px|right|The variety of carrot colors]]
Carrots originally came in purple, white and yellow colours. The now standard orange carrot was developed in Holland in the 16th century. Different colored carrots are coming back in style. New yellow carrots get their color from xanthophylls, which have been linked to good eye health. Red carrots contain lycopene, also found in [[cookbook:Tomato|tomatoes]] and thought to guard against heart disease and some cancers. Purple carrots’ anthocyanins are regarded as powerful antioxidants that help protect cells from damage. White carrots lack any pigmentation, but do contain other health-promoting substances called phytochemicals, natural bioactive compounds found in plant foods that work with nutrients and dietary fibre to protect against disease.

===Carrot Recipes===
*[[Cookbook:Carrot Cake]]
*[[Cookbook:Coq au Vin]]
*[[Cookbook:Vegetable Pie]]
*[[Cookbook:Carrot and Raisin Salad]]
*[[Cookbook:Carrots cooked kinpira style]]
*[[Cookbook:Carrot and coriander soup]]
*[[Cookbook:Carrot Kugel]]

== External links ==
*[http://dmoz.org/Home/Cooking/Fruits_and_Vegetables/Carrots/ Recipes with carrots]
*[http://www.carrotmuseum.com World Carrot Museum]
*[http://www.carrotrecipes.co.uk Great Carrot Recipes]


[[Category:Featured ingredients|{{PAGENAME}}]]

[[nl:Kookboek/Wortel]]</text>
      <sha1>lyed9dfojb3uo9umdwhdsxwjia2h6h7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Shallot</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4963</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2688505</id>
      <parentid>1184575</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-04T08:05:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Shallots - sliced and whole.jpg|thumb|right|Shallots]]
{{vegetable}}
:''For the long green variety of onion, see [[Cookbook:Green onion|Green onion]].''

'''Shallots''' are a very small sweet onion like bulb that forms in clusters like garlic.Shallots have a papery skin that must be removed before they can be used. They grow in clusters, similar to [[Cookbook:Garlic|garlic]]. The taste is similar to a standard onion, but more delicate almost a blend of onion/garlic flavor. Whole immature shallots are sometimes used like [[Cookbook:Spring Onion|spring onions]]. Shallot tops are eaten much like chives, and can be dried and saved for seasoning later.

{{Wikipedia|Shallot}}</text>
      <sha1>6mqngw0lqteeobj2b0y7b02rvkzqtl5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook talk:Carrot</title>
    <ns>103</ns>
    <id>4964</id>
    <revision>
      <id>572625</id>
      <parentid>353490</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-08-31T18:31:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>66.108.36.80</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">''This module was the featured ingredient on the main [[Cookbook]] page from April 18, 2004 - April 28, 2004''

KJ - I would just remove most of the links back to Wikipedia.  Later, you may want some of those to go on to your articles in Wikibooks where they are pointing right now (although the pages do not exist).  However, if you really want to maintain the Wikipedia link for some reason, the just add Wikipedia:en: in front of the link word like this: &lt;nowiki&gt;[[Wikipedia:en:vegetable]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;. You can always change it back to a local (Wikibook) link when you get one - [[User:Marshman|Marsh]] 04:56, 24 Feb 2004 (UTC)




 Ilovebeatricealot ..lmao</text>
      <sha1>fofi9ggd8qsomksujpg2egfr9qa8n0i</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Alfalfa</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4965</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1803963</id>
      <parentid>1637103</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-05-22T22:43:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{vegetable}} | [[Cookbook:Basic foodstuffs|Basic foodstuffs]]

[[Image:alfalfa CDC.jpg|right|frame|alfalfa sprouts]]
'''Alfalfa''' sprouts are tiny alfalfa plants, usually grown directly in their container.  This should be — though famously has not always been — a sterile hydroponic environment, so there should be no need to wash the sprouts before using them.  Store the alfalfa in the refrigerator with the lid on so that it stays moist but not too wet, and do not put it in the &quot;quick chill zone&quot; or leave it out on the counter — if sprouts dry out or freeze, they become unpalatable.  If the conditions are right, the sprouts may continue to grow while being refrigerated, so the container can potentially refill itself as the shoots are used.  An orange LED in the refrigerator may help them grow.

Alfalfa can be used without any further treatment, or can have its seed casings washed away. A bit of underwater shaking will take off most of the seed casings. Most of these can then be floated away; the rest will remain in the rinse bowl after the sprouts are removed.

Add alfalfa sprouts to a [[Cookbook:Salad|salad]], or add them to a [[Cookbook:Sandwiches|sandwich]] such as a [[Cookbook:Hamburger|hamburger]] or [[Cookbook:Taco|taco]]. Alfalfa sprouts are a good source of vitamin K and chlorophyll and are said to be an extremely healthy food. Because they are more healthy than [[Cookbook:Lettuce|lettuce]], they could be used as an appropriate replacement.

Mixed sprouts have become very common. It is not unusual to see &quot;alfalfa and [[Cookbook:Radish|radish]] sprouts&quot;, &quot;alfalfa and [[Cookbook:Garlic|garlic]] sprouts&quot;, or &quot;alfalfa and [[Cookbook:Onion|onion]] sprouts&quot;. This makes for a much more spicy and pungent mix. When alfalfa sprouts are mixed with [[Cookbook:Broccoli|broccoli]] sprouts, a mild mixture, although one with a more significant texture, is produced.

==Seasonality==
{{Seasonality|Alfalfa Sprouts|3|3|3|3|3|3|3|3|3|3|3|3}}

Since seeds can easily be sprouted, regardless of season, alfalfa sprouts are available all year round. 

[[Category:Ingredients available all year|Alfalfa]]</text>
      <sha1>24kgj7xgf9ihv3ezhu5skdvkt02nlb0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Artichoke</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4967</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1707949</id>
      <parentid>1703415</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-01-29T01:21:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jua Cha</username>
        <id>317885</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>spelling</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{vegetable}} | [[Cookbook:Basic foodstuffs|Basic foodstuffs]]

[[Image:CDC_artichoke.jpg|right|artichoke]]
The '''artichoke''' is a giant thistle flower bud. It is sometimes called the '''globe artichoke''', or '''French artichoke''' to avoid confusion with the [[Cookbook:Sunchoke|sunchoke]], which is an entirely different plant that sometimes goes by the confusing name &quot;Jerusalem artichoke&quot;.

Unlike most vegetables, only a very small part of the artichoke is actually edible &amp;mdash; the very bases of the &quot;leaves&quot; and the interior heart. The heart of the flower is topped with spiky bristles or hairs that would be unpleasant to consume, and the leaves are extremely tough and fibrous.

Artichoke hearts are often sold in a [[Cookbook:Pickling|pickled]] or preserved form, and served as part of an [[Cookbook:Antipasto|antipasto]] dish at the beginning of a meal.

==Selection and Storage==
High-quality artichokes are usually compact and heavy for their size. Squeezed, a fresh artichoke will make a squeak. The thickness of each stalk should correspond to the size of the artichoke. Thin stalks signal dehydration, so look for stalks that are firm without “give.” 

Artichokes remain fairly constant in appearance for weeks, but flavor is adversely affected from the moment they are cut from the stalk. For maximum taste and tenderness, cook as soon as possible. Do not stock up on artichokes. Refrigerate unwashed, in a plastic bag, for up to 1 week.

==Cooking==
Start by cutting the thorns off with kitchen scissors or simply take a kitchen knife and cut straight across the top part off the artichoke. This will leave a flat top on the artichoke. Note that &quot;thorn-free&quot; artichokes, besides having far less of the edible part, generally do have little hidden thorns that are hard to remove.

Artichokes should be very well cooked. This is required to soften them enough to eat. Make sure to check the water level as the artichoke will absorb water as it softens. Add more water if they are still not tender and continue to cook. Unlike most vegetables, artichokes should be cooked until they are a darker color green than when they were fresh.

Artichokes may be [[Cookbook:Boiling|boiled]], [[Cookbook:Microwaving|microwaved]], [[Cookbook:Steaming|steamed]], or [[Cookbook:Pressure Cooking|pressure cooked]], although steaming is best. When steaming, spread the leaves a bit and place the artichokes stem-end-up to ensure that plenty of steam gets to the inside. Microwaving is essentially steaming; cover the artichokes and add a bit of water.

You may want to stuff the artichokes prior to cooking. They can be stuffed with ground beef, rice, or anything you prefer.

==Eating==
[[File:Cooked artichoke heart.jpg|thumb|Artichoke heart.]]
Although people from artichoke-growing regions (and many of their descendants) are very familiar with the artichoke, people from elsewhere rarely encounter this vegetable and eating one can be a trap for the inexperienced. After cooking, the large leathery &quot;leaves&quot; forming a tight rosette are pulled off one by one, and their soft, inner basal part (usually) is dipped in some kind of sauce, perhaps [[Cookbook:Mayonnaise|mayonnaise]] or [[Cookbook:Vinaigrette|vinaigrette]]. The dipped soft part is then scraped off with the teeth and all the rest of the leaf discarded &amp;mdash; absolutely ''not'' to be eaten. The fleshy, edible part is delicious, but quite sparse in proportion to that which is discarded. 

This process continues until most of the leaves have been removed and the remaining ones are too small and delicate to eat in this manner. This point is difficult to judge and the novice artichoke eater may wish to seek guidance by discreetly watching a companion.

With the softest inner leaves, there is no need to scrape away a layer using the teeth.  Pull these leaves off in bunches of perhaps 10 to 20, folding as needed to bunch up the lower edge, then dip the lower edge in the sauce and bite it off. Discard the upper portion, which may contain thorns.

Finally, an irritating fur-like layer of thistle is exposed. This layer can be pulled out, scraped out, scooped out, or cut out. It is generally best to scrape the thistle away with a sideways motion of a dull table knife (a butter knife). Some practice will be required. If this process is difficult, it is likely that the artichoke was not cooked enough.

The remaining part, minus any stem still attached, is the artichoke heart. This is often considered the best part of the artichoke. Dip it in sauce and eat it.

It will be seen that the art of eating this food is in itself a satisfying and time-consuming matter which has wider implications than mere nourishment.

==Seasonality==
{{Seasonality|Artichokes|2|2|3|3|3|2|2|2|2|2|2|2}}

Most species of artichoke have their peak season in spring, but some species produce all year round (with some having their peak in autumn), especially in locations closer to the equator. Artichokes harvested in the winter and spring will be globe-shaped, whereas artichokes harvested in the summer and fall will be more conical.

== Recipes ==
*[[Cookbook:Artichoke Hearts Attack|Artichoke Hearts Attack]]
*[[Cookbook:Steamed Artichoke|Steamed Artichoke]]
*[[Cookbook:Microwaved Artichoke|Microwaved Artichoke]]

== External Links ==
* http://oregonstate.edu/Dept/NWREC/artichgl.html
* http://www.artichokes.org/varieties.html

{{wikipedia|Globe artichoke}}


[[Category:Basic Foodstuffs|Artichoke]] 
[[Category:Featured ingredients|Artichoke]]
[[Category:Ingredients available all year|Artichoke]]
[[Category:Spring ingredients|Artichoke]]

[[cs:Wikikuchařka/Zelenina/Artyčok]]
[[nl:Kookboek/Artisjok]]</text>
      <sha1>qljr2f3b90pweg7xyjrbzz2n12b6ju8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook talk:Artichoke</title>
    <ns>103</ns>
    <id>4968</id>
    <revision>
      <id>353355</id>
      <parentid>301249</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-02-03T03:24:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Uncle G's major work 'bot</username>
        <id>10904</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[Talk:Cookbook:Artichoke]] moved to [[Cookbook talk:Artichoke]]: COOKBOT: Renaming talk page to Cookbook talk namespace</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">The 'eating' part of this article was copied from [[w:artichoke]]. The introduction was rewritten by me.

Edit History as follows:
    * (cur) (last)  . . 11:06, 10 Nov 2003 . . Michael Shields (add image)
    * (cur) (last) . . M 07:38, 7 Nov 2003 . . Muriel Gottrop (Reverted to last edit by Marshman)
    * (cur) (last) . . 07:34, 7 Nov 2003 . . 213.48.195.67
    * (cur) (last) . . 16:29, 22 Oct 2003 . . Marshman (Clrify part that is eaten; add links)
    * (cur) (last) . . 20:07, 21 Oct 2003 . . Marshman (Copy edit; correct - artichoke IS a vegetable, not a fruit)
    * (cur) (last) . . M 09:45, 20 Feb 2003 . . Nevilley (fm)
    * (cur) (last) . . M 09:39, 20 Feb 2003 . . Nevilley (minor reword)
    * (cur) (last) . . 07:53, 20 Feb 2003 . . Tarquin
    * (cur) (last) . . M 14:43, 19 Feb 2003 . . Nevilley (conclusion)
    * (cur) (last) . . M 14:42, 19 Feb 2003 . . Nevilley (Eating technique (see talk))
    * (cur) (last) . . 14:04, 19 Feb 2003 . . 65.56.77.146
    * (cur) (last) . . 14:03, 19 Feb 2003 . . 65.56.77.146


Artichokes are common in Europe and now the UK. Fresh butter is the main dip of choice. The season starts in late autumn but is quite short. A good farmers market or greengrocer is the best place to get them in Britain. LC</text>
      <sha1>na3hec3d26rz5xznpkxfrnbnhwjfzgl</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Arugula</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4969</id>
    <revision>
      <id>853983</id>
      <parentid>710330</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-05-05T15:29:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jessicapierce</username>
        <id>58196</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>copy edit</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Arugula.jpg|right|thumb|Arugula]]
{{vegetable}} | [[Cookbook:Basic foodstuffs|Basic foodstuffs]]

'''Arugula''' (also known as ''rocket'', ''rocket salad'', ''rughetta'', ''roquette'' or ''rucola''), is a leafy green vegetable with a pungent &quot;hot&quot; or &quot;stimulating&quot; flavour. It is usually eaten raw in salads but can also be steamed or cooked and served with meat or pasta. 

Arugula has been grown in the Mediterranean region since Roman times, and it was once considered to be an aphrodisiac. It was traditionally collected from the wild and not grown commercially until recent years.

==Seasonality==
{{Seasonality|Arugola|2|2|2|2|3|3|3|3|3|3|2|2}}

{{wikipedia|Arugula}}

[[Category:Basic Foodstuffs|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Ingredients available all year|{{PAGENAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>pb9hmzkr773kbrunivtqr9hbq3da8ob</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Asparagus</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4970</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1730743</id>
      <parentid>1703416</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-03-05T21:13:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Griffinofwales</username>
        <id>218858</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>spelling</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{vegetable}}
[[Image:Asparagus produce-1.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Asparagus]]

'''Asparagus''' are the growing shoots of a fern-like plant. Asparagus has a delicate flavor and diuretic properties.

One distinctive problem with asparagus is that a constituent chemical of the plant is metabolised and excreted in the urine, giving it a distinctive, mildly unpleasant odour. Apparently not everyone who eats asparagus produces the odor, but also not everyone is able to smell the odor once it is produced. [http://my.webmd.com/content/article/43/1671_51089] Many people prefer not to eat asparagus because of this effect, as it can put a damper on an otherwise romantic evening...

There are three different common 'varieties' of asparagus sold in the markets which are actually the same plant grown under different conditions. 'Green' asparagus is left exposed to the air so that it grows normally. 'White' asparagus is piled high with straw as it grows so that the shoots remain pale. The flavour is identical, but some people believe that the white asparagus is more tender and flavourful. Finally, a 'purple' asparagus is occasionally seen, which is again the same except with purple streaks on the stem.

Almost the whole shoot is edible, but the prized portion is the tender growing end. The base of the shoot can be woody and fibrous, and it is generally discarded about a third of the way up. The traditional way to prepare asparagus for cooking is to take hold of a few shoots at a time, holding an end in each hand, and firmly but gently 'snap' it. The shoots will snap at their natural break point, which should be where the woody end meets the more tender portion. Another way to prepare asparagus for cooking is to peel the bottom end with a knife or a vegetable peeler, working from the middle towards the end. This will remove the toughest fibers from the outside although some will remain and will need to be cut an inch or so from the base of the stems.

===Cooking Asparagus===

In its simplest form, the shoots are boiled or steamed until tender and served with a light sauce or melted [[Cookbook:Butter|butter]]. 

Asparagus is very long and narrow, and it is traditionally cooked in an 'asparagus steamer.' This is a very tall narrow pot with about an inch of [[Cookbook:Boiling|boiling]] water in the bottom. The asparagus is tied in a bundle and stood upright in the steamer for about five minutes so that the toughest end gets the most cooking and the tips are just barely [[Cookbook:Steaming|steamed]]. A modern alternative is to use a frypan - put boiling water in the pan and slide the asparagus gently into the water so it can lie sideways across the pan. Asparagus is cooked when it turns bright green, which only takes a few minutes regardless of the cooking method. 

Asparagus is very good in [[Cookbook:Stir-fry|stir-fries]], where it is usually cut into lengths of about an inch and added at the last minute before serving. It can also be made into [[Cookbook:Asparagus Soup|asparagus soup]], especially the older and slightly less tender shoots. 

If, as is common, the asparagus is overcooked or allowed to sit too long, [[Cookbook:Cheese|cheese]] [[Cookbook:Sauce|sauce]] is a good dip to use.

==Seasonality==
{{Seasonality|Asparagus|1|1|1|2|3|3|1|1|1|1|1|1}}

Asparagus have a very specific season that starts in May and traditionally ends on the 24th of June. Out of season asparagus are grown in regions close to the equator or in greenhouses. If fresh asparagus isn't available, canned, jarred or frozen asparagus usually are.

==&quot;False&quot; Asparagus==
The shoots of a related plant, ''Ornithogalum pyrenaicum'', called Prussian asparagus, have been used for similar purposes as genuine asparagus.

Many unrelated plants are called &quot;asparagus&quot; or &quot;used as asparagus&quot; when their shoots are used in a similar way. 

{{wikipedia|Asparagus}}


[[de:Kochbuch/ Spargel]] 
[[nl:Kookboek/Asperge]]

[[Category:Basic Foodstuffs|Asparagus]]
[[Category:Featured ingredients|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Summer ingredients|Asparagus]]</text>
      <sha1>173u1e0yhhv8o3i7fj3o35vt99k42o7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Korean/Alphabet</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4971</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2668328</id>
      <parentid>2614931</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-05-31T17:10:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>It Is Me Here</username>
        <id>83220</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Restore to older version: revert vandalism</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{:Korean/Navigation panel|ReadWrite}}
==Introduction==

The Korean alphabet, known as [[w:Hangul|''Hangeul'']] ([[wikt:한글|한글]], &quot;great script&quot;), is considered one of the most efficient and logical writing systems in the world. While most modern alphabets evolved from earlier hieroglyphics or ideographs, 한글 (''Hangeul'') was created specifically to make it easy to read and write the Korean language.

Although the characters of 한글 (''Hangeul'') may appear to be [[w:Ideogram|ideograms]] like the traditional ''Hanja'' ([[wikt:한자|한자]], [[wikt:漢字#Korean|漢字]]), they really form an alphabet. Each block character represents one syllable and is made up of individual [[w:Hangul#Jamo|''jamo'' (자모)]], much like the letters in the Latin alphabet.  한글 (''Hangeul'') is easy to learn because it has only 24 basic jamo.

:See Wikipedia's entries on [[w:Hangul|Hangul]] and [[w:Hanja|Hanja]] for more about the history and design of the Korean writing systems.

==Consonants==
[[File:Korean consonants.svg|thumb|14 Korean consonants]]
Below are the consonants ([[wikt:자음|자음]]) of the Korean alphabet. You don't need to memorize them yet because individual lessons will cover each letter in detail. For now, just be aware that the Korean alphabet has ten basic consonants and nine variations on them:

{{Korean/Consonant jamo chart}}

Notice that some consonants have two different pronunciations (e.g. ㄱ pronounced as /g/ or /k/ depending on context).  Also, some are &quot;aspirated&quot; and some are &quot;tense&quot;.  Those details and more are explained in [[../Essential Pronunciation Rules/]].

==Vowels==
[[File:Korean vowels.svg|thumb|6 Korean regular vowels: diphthongs in red]]
There are 21 letters used to represent vowels: six basic vowels, nine combinations of those six basic vowels (which originally were all pronounced as diphthongs), and six vowels with an extra short dash representing the initial ''y'' [j] sound. 
{{Korean/Vowel jamo chart}}

==End of introduction==
To learn how to read, write, and pronounce each Korean letter, proceed to [[Korean/RWP|the Read, Write, and Pronounce Korean]] course.

{{:Korean/Navigation panel|ReadWrite}}

[[Category:Korean]]
[[Category:Alphabets|korean]]</text>
      <sha1>s28x7bbamqp4bpfmnfbnfr3rpthve52</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Template:General Chemistry/Navigation</title>
    <ns>10</ns>
    <id>4973</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1925910</id>
      <parentid>1925905</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-09-02T15:45:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>fixed code</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;div class=&quot;noprint&quot;&gt;
----
&lt;span id=&quot;top-navigation&quot;&gt;&lt;!--
--&gt;{{#if:{{{prev|{{{2|}}}}}} | &amp;larr; [[General Chemistry/{{{prev|{{{2}}}}}}|{{{prev|{{{2}}}}}}]] ·}}&lt;!--
--&gt;{{#if:{{{next|{{{3|}}}}}} | [[General Chemistry/{{{next|{{{3}}}}}}|{{{next|{{{3}}}}}}]] &amp;rarr;}}
&lt;/span&gt;
{| style=&quot;background-color: transparent&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0px&quot; cellpadding=&quot;0px&quot; class=&quot;noprint&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;
 | align=&quot;left&quot; width=&quot;33%&quot; | &lt;small&gt;{{#if:{{{prev|{{{2|}}}}}}| [[General Chemistry/{{{prev|{{{2|}}}}}}|← {{{prev|{{{2|}}}}}}]] ·}}&lt;/small&gt;
 | align=&quot;center&quot; width=&quot;34%&quot; | '''[[General Chemistry]]'''
 | align=&quot;right&quot; width=&quot;33%&quot; | &lt;small&gt;{{#if:{{{next|{{{3|}}}}}} | · [[General Chemistry/{{{next|{{{3|}}}}}}|{{{next|{{{3|}}}}}} →]]}}&lt;/small&gt;
 |- style=&quot;font-size: .8em;&quot; 
 | colspan=&quot;3&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; |
[[General Chemistry/Book Cover|Book Cover]] ·
[[General Chemistry/Introduction|Introduction]] ·
{{navbar|General Chemistry/Navigation|mini=1|nodiv=1}}
 |- style=&quot;font-size: .8em;&quot;  align=&quot;center&quot; class=&quot;noprint&quot;
 | colspan=&quot;3&quot;|
'''Units''':
[[General Chemistry/Properties of Matter|Matter]] ·
[[General Chemistry/Atomic Structure|Atomic Structure]] ·
[[General Chemistry/Compounds and Bonding|Bonding]] ·
[[General Chemistry/Chemical Reactions|Reactions]] ·
[[General Chemistry/Aqueous Solutions|Solutions]] ·
[[General Chemistry/Phases of Matter|Phases of Matter]] ·
[[General Chemistry/Chemical Equilibria|Equilibria]] ·
[[General Chemistry/Chemical Kinetics|Kinetics]] ·
[[General Chemistry/Thermodynamics|Thermodynamics]] ·
[[General Chemistry/Chemistries of Various Elements|The Elements]] 
 |- style=&quot;font-size: .8em;&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; class=&quot;noprint&quot;
 | colspan=&quot;3&quot;|
'''Appendices''':
[[General Chemistry/Periodic Table|Periodic Table]] ·
[[General Chemistry/Units|Units]] ·
[[General Chemistry/Constants|Constants]] ·
[[General Chemistry/Useful Equations|Equations]] ·
[[General Chemistry/Standard Reduction Potentials|Reduction Potentials]] ·
[[General Chemistry/Table of the Chemical Elements and their Properties|Elements and their Properties]]
 |}
----
&lt;/div&gt;{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>6did0s0gk1x1mj1u0jff5ag1fwyl727</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>General Chemistry/Chemistries of Various Elements</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4974</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1925913</id>
      <parentid>1421928</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-09-02T15:47:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>formatting</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;noinclude&gt;{{General Chemistry/Navigation}}

'''Descriptive chemistry''' is the study of the physical and chemical properties of elements and substances.  As you study the elements, you will find the '''''[[General Chemistry/Periodic Table|periodic table]]''''' very helpful.

&lt;/noinclude&gt;&lt;includeonly&gt;
=== Chemistries of the Various Elements ===
&lt;/includeonly&gt;
*'''Representative Elements'''
**[[General Chemistry/Chemistries of Various Elements/Group 1|Group  1 (1A): Alkali Metals]]
**[[General Chemistry/Chemistries of Various Elements/Group 2|Group  2 (2A): Alkaline Earth Metal]]
**[[General Chemistry/Chemistries of Various Elements/Group 13|Group 13 (3A): Boron Family]]
**[[General Chemistry/Chemistries of Various Elements/Group 14|Group 14 (4A): Carbon Family]]
**[[General Chemistry/Chemistries of Various Elements/Group 15|Group 15 (5A): Nitrogen Family]]
**[[General Chemistry/Chemistries of Various Elements/Group 16|Group 16 (6A): Oxygen Family]]
**[[General Chemistry/Chemistries of Various Elements/Group 17|Group 17 (7A): Halogens]]
**[[General Chemistry/Chemistries of Various Elements/Group 18|Group 18 (8A): Noble Gases]]
*[[General Chemistry/Chemistries of Various Elements/Hydrogen|'''Hydrogen''']]
*[[General Chemistry/Chemistries of Various Elements/Transition Metals|'''Transition Metals''']]
**[[General Chemistry/Chemistries of Various Elements/Transition Metals#Coinage Metals|Group 11 (1B): Coinage Metals]]
**[[General Chemistry/Chemistries of Various Elements/Transition Metals#Zinc Family|Group 12 (2B): Zinc Family]]
**[[General Chemistry/Chemistries of Various Elements/Transition Metals#Platinum Family|Group 8/9/10 (8B): Platinum Family]]
*[[General Chemistry/Chemistries of Various Elements/Inner Transition Metals|'''Inner Transition Metals''']]
**[[General Chemistry/Chemistries of Various Elements/Inner Transition Metals#Lanthanoids|Lanthanoids]]
**[[General Chemistry/Chemistries of Various Elements/Inner Transition Metals#Actinoids|Actinoids]] (including [[General Chemistry/Chemistries of Various Elements/Inner Transition Metals#Nuclear Chemistry|Nuclear Chemistry]])
*[[General Chemistry/Chemistries of Various Elements/Synthetic Elements|Synthetic Elements]]</text>
      <sha1>r4yp5379meb23xl56mb88r6tj2kwrn7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>General Chemistry/Compounds and Bonding</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4975</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2255630</id>
      <parentid>2255604</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-01-22T22:52:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Addihockey10 (automated)</username>
        <id>502783</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Compounds and Bonding */Replaceing raster images with vector equivalents, replaced: 50%.png → 50%.svg (2) using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;noinclude&gt;{{General Chemistry/Navigation}}

&lt;/noinclude&gt;&lt;includeonly&gt;
== Compounds and Bonding ==
&lt;/includeonly&gt;
#[[General Chemistry/Overview of bonding|Overview of bonding]] [[Image:75%.svg]]
#[[General Chemistry/Electronegativity|Electronegativity]] [[Image:75%.svg]]
#[[General Chemistry/Ionic bonds|Ionic bonds]] [[Image:75%.svg]]
#[[General Chemistry/Covalent bonds|Covalent bonds]] [[Image:75%.svg]]
#[[General Chemistry/Metallic bonds|Metallic bonds]] [[Image:50%.svg]]
#[[General Chemistry/Molecular Shape|Molecular Shape]] [[Image:75%.svg]]
#[[General Chemistry/Intermolecular bonds|Intermolecular bonds]] [[Image:50%.svg]]</text>
      <sha1>7pu0keof4ldw2acz2nqqbbm8q91tena</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:How to Cook Oysters</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4976</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2686721</id>
      <parentid>1502850</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-07-31T19:57:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Koavf</username>
        <id>16549</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Koavf moved page [[Cookbook:How to cook oysters]] to [[Cookbook:How to Cook Oysters]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{cookwork}}

{{recipe}}

Cooking '''oysters''' - from the 1881 ''Household Cyclopedia''



=== Stewed Oysters ===
''Recipe moved to [[Cookbook:Stewed Oysters]]''

=== Oysters Roasted ===
''Recipe moved to  [[Cookbook:Roasted Oysters with Madeira]]''

=== Another Mode ===
''Recipe moved to [[Cookbook:Simple Roasted Oysters]]'' 

=== Scalloped Oysters ===

One hundred oysters, a baker's loaf crumbed, four eggs boiled hard; salt and cayenne pepper to taste. Chop the eggs very fine and mix with the crumbs, which season highly with cayenne and salt. Cover the bottom of a deep pie-dish with the eggs and crumbs; then with a fork, place layer of oysters with two or three small pieces of butter, and so continue until all are in, reserving sufficient crumbs for the cover For those who like it, a little mace may be added. Bake in a quick oven three-quarters of an hour. Serve hot. 

=== Fried Oysters ===
''Recipe moved to [[Cookbook:Breaded Fried Oysters]]'' 

=== Panned Oysters ===

Take fifty large oysters, remove every particle of shell which may adhere to them, put them in to a colander and pour over a little water to rinse them. After letting them drain, put them into a stewpan with a quarter of a pound of butter, salt' black and red pepper to taste. Put them over a clear fire, and stir while cooking. As soon as they commence to shrink remove them from the fire, and send to table hot in a well (covered) heated dish. 

=== To Pickle Oysters ===

Drain off the liquor from one hundred oysters, wash them and put to them a table-spoonful of salt and a tea-cup of vinegar; let them simmer over the fire about ten minutes, taking off the scum as it rises; then take out the oysters and put to their own liquor a tablespoonful of whole black pepper and a teaspoonful of mace and cloves; let it boil five minutes, skim and pour it over the oysters in a jar. 

=== To Spice Oysters ===

One hundred oysters, one dozen cloves, two dozen allspice, mace, cayenne pepper, and salt to taste. 

Strain the liquor through a sieve, put it in a saucepan, and add the oysters, spice, pepper, salt, and half a pint of cider vinegar. Place them over a slow fire, and as soon as they boil take them off. Pour them into a large bowl and set them away to cool. When cold cover them close.

=== Oysters Kilpatrick ===
Oysters Kilpatrick can be made in one of 2 ways. To begin you need to make the Kilpatrick sauce which is 1 part Tomato Sauce to 1 part Worcestershire Sauce which is thoroughly mixed together. The next step is to finely dice bacon into small pieces which is then placed over the raw oysters. Once the bacon pieces are placed over the oysters quite generously, then pour the Kilpatrick sauce over the top of the oysters and bacon. Now the oysters can be placed in a oven proof frying pan with a stable base for the oysters and baked at a moderate temperate (180 degrees Celsius) until the oysters are firm to the touch and bacon is crispy. The oysters can also be placed in a tray under a grill with a high heat until firm and bacon is crispy. Serve the Kilpatrick oysters with either lemon wedges or additional Kilpatrick sauce.
{{Household Cyclopedia}}
[[Category:Oyster recipes|How to cook oysters]]
Placing the oysters on a generous amount of rock salt will help stand them upright, keeping the bacon and the sauce where it needs to be.</text>
      <sha1>70goyfaf3pmpav98qqqiv0jreuz3op0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:How to Cook Pasta</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4977</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2686725</id>
      <parentid>1267448</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-07-31T19:58:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Koavf</username>
        <id>16549</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Koavf moved page [[Cookbook:How to cook pasta]] to [[Cookbook:How to Cook Pasta]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{cookwork}}

{{recipe}}

This is how to cook [[Cookbook:Pasta|pasta]], the Italian way.

Depending on your recipe, you might have to start preparing sauces or other additions before making the actual pasta. The general rule is that the sauce should wait for the pasta, not the other way around.

This method of boiling applies to most types of pasta.  On average, for every 200 grams of pasta you need 4 liters of water.
When the water boils, put in the salt; you will need about one tablespoon of salt for every two quarts of water. 
You can also put the salt when the water is cold, but the salt will take longer to dissolve, and can stain or corrode the bottom of stainless steel pots. 
Once the salt has dissolved and the water has returned to a boil, throw in your pasta and start measuring the time. 
 
The length of time differs for each kind of pasta (generally, the box suggests a boiling time), and goes from 5 minutes for thin spaghettini to 12 and up minutes for some thicker kinds. A bit less time than suggested will produce a firmer pasta (al dente - heavy to digest, however) while a bit more time causes pasta to be more flexible. It is a good idea to follow the suggestions on the box until you are sufficiently experienced in making pasta. Fresh, egg-based pasta (''pasta all'uovo'') takes very little time to cook. Fresh [[Cookbook:Noodle|noodles]] hardly need a minute after the water has returned to the boil; filled pasta like [[Cookboook:tortellini|tortellini]] need only a few minutes to cook through. Many experienced cooks like to sample a piece of the pasta while boiling it (''spizzicatura'' - they &quot;fish&quot; it out with a slotted spoon) to stop cooking just at their desired consistency. When boiling time is completed, separate pasta from water with a strainer, put in a wide dish and add everything else. A suggestion: a simple combination of butter and Parmigiano Reggiano, or some oil, parsley or basil and fresh garlic, will be as tasty as more sophisticated preparations. Serve the pasta hot, immediately, unless the recipe says differently.

[[Category:Pasta recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>8hxa0bg90z699hug5tovkn0uwz7w4og</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Davodd</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>4978</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1943514</id>
      <parentid>156637</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-10-05T19:48:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Davodd</username>
        <id>648</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Please leave comments on my [[User_talk:Davodd|Talk]] page.


----

==About==
*Name: David Speakman
*Born: Fort Wayne, Indiana
**Western astrology sun sign: Aquarius
**Chinese zodiac sign: Monkey
*Current city: Mountain View, Santa Clara County, California
*College: Ball State University; Lincoln Law School
*Web page: http://www.davodd.com</text>
      <sha1>h3cwpnugus2uig1fouuzkoj3bas1ib1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>