<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>Spanish/Infinitive</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>590</id>
    <revision>
      <id>532423</id>
      <parentid>472788</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-07-22T07:41:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">The '''infinitive''' is the simple, unconjugated form of a verb. It does not indicate who is doing the action or any time reference. &quot;To be&quot; is a verb in the English infinitive form. &quot;Ser&quot; is a verb in the Spanish infinitive form. When you look up a verb in the dictionary it is found in the infinitive form.

In Spanish the infinitive forms always end with &quot;ar&quot;, &quot;er&quot; or &quot;ir&quot;. Examples: &quot;amar&quot; (to love), &quot;temer&quot; (to fear), &quot;partir&quot; (to leave).

The infinitive can be used for a lot of things in Spanish grammar.  It functions as a gerund in Spanish.  In the following examples, I will use &quot;nadar&quot; (to swim):
*Yo quiero &quot;nadar&quot;.--- I want to swim.
*Yo pensaba que &quot;nadar&quot; era divertido---I used to think that swimming was fun

[[Category:Spanish]]</text>
      <sha1>tvs2xis7kf9ii2aghw5x1rmv6c54b8v</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Wintermute/drafts</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>591</id>
    <revision>
      <id>616026</id>
      <parentid>152731</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-10-18T04:12:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Guanabot</username>
        <id>5478</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>User-controlled Bot: table syntax updated</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[User:Wintermute|Wintermute]] 19:11, 12 Aug 2003 (UTC)
draft:
-----

Grammar.
Gender of nouns in Spanish.

In Spanish all the nouns are masculine or feminine.

For nouns that express entities with gender (people, animals..) there is both a feminine form and a masculine form (example: profesor (m), profesora (f))

The nouns that express entities without gender (objects, abstract concepts) have only one form. This form can be masculine or feminine.

Normally, the feminine words finalize with the letter 'a' and the masculine words end with the letter 'o'.

Examples:

Masculine words:
     caballo         horse
     perro           dog
     libro           book
     amor            love

Femenine words:     
     paloma          dove
     hierba          grass
     casa            house
     libertad        freedom

-----
Grammar.
The definite article:

As you know, in Spanish, the nouns can be feminine or masculine.

In English the definite article is always “the”.

In Spanish, the definite article is different - depending on the noun being feminine, masculine, singular or plural.




{|  border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
| || 
Article
|
Example
|-
|
feminine, singular
|
la
|
la mujer (the woman)
|-
|
masculine, singular
|
el
|
el hombre (the man)
|-
|
feminine, plural
|
las
|
las mujeres (the women)
|-
|
masculine, plural
|
los
|
los hombres (the men)
|}

-----

Grammar.
The indefinite article:

In English de indefinite articles are &quot;a&quot; and &quot;an&quot; (singular) or &quot;some&quot; (plural).

In Spanish there are different forms for feminine, masculine, singular or plural.



{|  border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
| || 
Article
|
Example
|-
|
feminine, singular
|
la
|
una mujer (a woman)
|-
|
masculine, singular
|
el
|
un hombre (a man)
|-
|
feminine, plural
|
las
|
unas mujeres (some women)
|-
|
masculine, plural
|
los
|
unos hombres (some men)
|}

Hi Wintermute, this looks really nice! Great work! I have restructured Lesson 2 a little bit so that you can put your grammar section right in the beginning (the gender of nouns should definitely go before doing 'matching adjectives' - my fault, I didn't think of that before...) [[User:ThomasStrohmann|Thomas]] &lt;br&gt;
P.S. your English is very good, I just made some minor changes.
--------------------------------------------

Pronombres personales.
''(Personal pronouns.)''


Ejercicio 1.
Rellena los espacios en blanco con los pronombres personales correctos en Español.
''Exercise 1.''
''Fill the blank spaces with the correct Spanish personal pronous.''



{|  border=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot;
|-
|  
Inglés:                      
|
Español
|-
|
''English:''
|
''Spanish:''
|-
| -- || --
|-
|
'''I'''     am        
|
'''Yo'''         soy 
|-
|
'''You'''   are           
|
______     eres
|-
|
'''He'''    is
|  
______     es
|-
|
'''She'''   is
|  
______     es
|-
|
'''We'''    are
|  
______     somos
|-
|
'''You'''   are
|  
______     sois
|-
|
'''They'''  are
|  
______     son
|}


Ejercicio 2.
Rellena los espacios en blanco con los pronombres personales correctos en español.
''Exercise 2.''
''Fill the blank spaces with the correct Spanish personal pronouns.''




{|  border=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot;
|-
|  
Inglés:                      
|
Español
|-
|
''English:''
|
''Spanish:''
|-
| -- || --
|-
|
'''You'''  are                   
|
'''Vosotros'''    estáis
|-
|
'''He'''   is                   
|
______      está
|-
|
'''You'''  are                   
|  
______      estás
|-
|
'''I'''    am 	           
|  
______      estoy
|-
|
'''They''' are                   
|  
______      están
|-
|
'''We'''   are                   
|  
______      estamos
|-
|
'''She'''  is                    
|  
______      está
|}

----
This looks great. I have put in a link to ''Spanish Exercises Personal Pronouns'' in Lesson 1. You can just go and fill the link with your exercises as content! -- [[User:ThomasStrohmann | Thomas]]
--------
Llena los espacios en blanco con la forma verbal correcta del verbo &quot;ser&quot;.
''Fill the blank spaces with the correct form of the ver &quot;ser&quot; (to be).''




{|  border=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot;
|-
|  
Inglés:                      
|
Español
|-
|
''English:''
|
''Spanish:''
|-
| -- || --
|-
|
I '''am''' your brother.
|
Yo '''soy''' tu hermano.
|-
|
I '''am''' your sister.
|
Yo ____ tu hermana.
|-
|
You '''are''' my friend.
|
Tu ____ mi amigo.
|-
|
He '''is''' a good man.
|
El ____ un buen hombre.
|-
|
She '''is''' a traveller.
|
Ella ____ una viajera.
|-
|
We '''are''' studendts.
|
Nosotros ____ estudiantes.
|-
|
You '''are''' dangerous.
|
Vosotros ____ peligrosos.
|-
|
They '''are''' persons.
|
Ellos ____ personas.
|}



Llena los espacios en blanco con la forma verbal correcta del verbo &quot;estar&quot;.
''Fill the blank spaces with the correct form of the ver &quot;estar&quot; (to be).''





{|  border=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot;
|-
|  
Inglés:                      
|
Español
|-
|
''English:''
|
''Spanish:''
|-
| -- || --
|-
|
I '''am''' in my house.
|
Yo _____ en mi casa.
|-
|
You '''are''' in the correct place.
|
Tu _____ en el sitio correcto.
|-
|
He '''is''' in Europe.
|
El _____ en Europa.
|-
|
We '''are''' in America.
|
Nosotros _____ en America.
|-
|
You '''are''' in África.
|
Vosotros _____ en África.
|-
|
They '''are''' ill.
|
Ellos _____ enfermos.
|-
|
You '''are''' angry.
|
Tu _____ enfadado.
|}
----------------------------


Llena los espacios en blanco con la forma verbal correcta del verbo &quot;ser&quot; o &quot;estar&quot;.
''Fill the blank spaces with the correct form of the ver &quot;ser&quot; or &quot;estar&quot; (to be).''


{|  border=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot;
|-
|  
Inglés:                      
|
Español
|-
|
''English:''
|
''Spanish:''
|-
| -- || --
|-
|
I '''am''' in Xine.
|
Yo '''estoy''' en China.''(soy/estoy)''
|-
|
You '''are''' my friend.
|
Tu _____ mi amigo.''(eres/estás)''
|-
|
You '''are''' there.
|
Tu _____ allí. ''(eres/estás)''
|-
|
She '''is''' my sister.
|
Ella _____ mi hermana. ''(es/está)''
|-
|
He '''is''' ill.
|
El _____ enfermo. ''(es/está)''
|-
|
We '''are''' ready.
|
Nosotros _____ preparados. ''(somos/estamos)''
|-
|
We '''are''' intelligent.
|
Nosotros _____ inteligentes. ''(somos/estamos)''
|-
|
You '''are''' in Europe.
|
Vosotros _____ en Europa. ''(sois/estáis)''
|-
|
You '''are''' sad.
|
Vosotros _____ tristes. ''(sois/estáis)''
|-
|
They '''are''' sympathetic.
|
Ellos ____ comprensivos. ''(son/están)''
|-
|
They '''are''' interesting people.
|
Ellos ____ gente interesante. ''(son/están)''
|}</text>
      <sha1>li1jhuho1brmotfco7h1z9w61252ndc</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:Wintermute</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>592</id>
    <revision>
      <id>152732</id>
      <parentid>27159</parentid>
      <timestamp>2004-04-23T23:21:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Get-back-world-respect</username>
        <id>1073</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Hey Wintermute, thanks for your work on the [[Spanish]] textbook. You said that English is not your first language ... what is ? -- [[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
----
A poco hablas el espanol ... yo estuve viviendo en Mexico por unos anos, en DF .. me encanto, todavia estaria alla si huberia encontrado otro trabajo. Me encantan las chicas latinas y en general toda la cultura latina. De donde eres ? Latinoamerica o Espana o otro lugar ? 

Entonces vas a poder corregir el mal espanol que ponemos en el libro de [[Spanish]] (por favor !)

--[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]


==Vocabulary Project==
Hi there,
I saw you contributed to the Spanish wikibook, so I thought it might be of interest to you that I have written a [http://amor.rz.hu-berlin.de/~h0444e1w/vokeng.htm program for learning vocabulary]. I think for this purpose a program is more useful than a website, although maybe one day we can make this a java project. 
It is based on the belief that it is best to learn foreign words by learning typical sentences. The program can also be used for learning other stuff that works with the question/answer scheme, e.g. the theory for the driving licence or anatomy. Unfortunately I wrote it in qbasic, which can be downloaded [http://www.microsoft.com/windows/download/olddos.exe here]. It also uses images and sound files for alternation and in order to work on the pronunciation. Let me know what you think about it. I currently have files in English, French (with sound), and Spanish. Catalan and Portuguese are in the planning. Corrections or additions are very welcome. The easiest thing to start with for improvements would be adding new vocabulary, sound files or images. A guide to the program will follow soon, although I think it is rather self-explanatory. In the long run the program should be rewritten in a better language like Visual Basic. Afterwards it should be possible to switch languages within the program. Up to now there is a different version of the program for each language. [[User:Get-back-world-respect|Get-back-world-respect]] 23:21, 23 Apr 2004 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>sjgytu0jbunvs29t8uk5fia07puepxl</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Organic Chemistry/Introduction to reactions/Redox reactions</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>593</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1475501</id>
      <parentid>1475447</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-04-20T13:43:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jomegat</username>
        <id>12605</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/62.150.124.27|62.150.124.27]] ([[User talk:62.150.124.27|Talk]]) to last version by [[User:Whiteknight|Whiteknight]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;noinclude&gt;
[[Organic Chemistry/Introduction to reactions/Polar and radical reactions|&lt;&lt; Polar and radical reactions]] | [[Organic Chemistry/Introduction to reactions/Functional groups in reactions|Functional groups in reactions &gt;&gt;]]
----
&lt;/noinclude&gt;
===Oxidation and reduction===
Two important types of reactions in organic chemistry are '''oxidation''' and '''reduction'''.

In '''oxidation reactions,''' the oxidized species ''loses electron density.''

In '''reduction reactions,''' the reduced species ''gains electron density.''

Of course, these two actions happen in unison as one species is reduced and the other is oxidized. The term '''redox''' was coined from the fragments ''red'' (reduction) and ''ox'' (oxidation).

===Oxidation===
'''Oxidation''' was first observed when oxygen drew electrons off of metals, which were then referred to as &quot;oxidized&quot;. (Oxygen is more elecronegative than most other elements.) The term was then applied later to the part of any reaction where electrons are drawn off. Other elements that commonly oxidize in organic reactions include halogens like chlorine and bromine.

===Reduction===
'''Reduction''' of a chemical species results in the gain of electrons for that species. This does not necessarily include any change in charge; any time an atom increases its electron density even a little bit it is said to be reduced. For example, if an oxygen is removed from a carbon and replaced by a hydrogen (assume the oxygen is also bonded to another atom), the formal charge of the carbon does not change. However, the carbon &quot;sees&quot; a greater share of the electrons from the single bond to hydrogen than it did for the single bond to oxygen. That is because hydrogen is less electronegative than oxygen and gives up its electrons a bit more easily than oxygen does. So a carbon bonded to hydrogen can take up more of its electron density than the same carbon bonded to oxygen.
&lt;noinclude&gt;
----
[[Organic Chemistry/Alkanes|&lt;&lt; Alkanes]] | [[Organic Chemistry/Introduction to reactions/Polar and radical reactions|&lt;&lt; Polar and radical reactions]] | Redox reactions | [[Organic Chemistry/Introduction to reactions/Functional groups in reactions|Functional groups in reactions &gt;&gt;]] | [[Organic Chemistry/Introduction to functional groups|Introduction to functional groups &gt;&gt;]]
&lt;/noinclude&gt;
{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>p6hhlet247uhglz3200nsuyunkwuy0u</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Imran/tempusenet</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>594</id>
    <revision>
      <id>152734</id>
      <timestamp>2003-08-12T22:49:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Imran</username>
        <id>31</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">What is Usenet ?

If your familiar with mailing lists or web-based forum, then the general principle of Usenet is simple so you may just want to skim over this first section.

To explain what Usenet is, I'll try and make analogies with real-life that most people are familiar with. Imagine Usenet as a pin-up board, where anyone can come along and stick a message up, people can then come by read the original message and attach a reply to the board, and then someone els can come along and look at the messages written, and if they want add their own message.

In a basic view that's all that Usenet is, an exchange point for messages.

Now imagine that about 25 million people were reading and writing messages for this pin-board, with one pin-board it would get overcrowded very quickly, the obvious solution is to have more pin-boards, say one for every topic

The technically correct name for Usenet's pin-boards is &quot;newsgroups&quot;, currently there are approximately 25,000 active(active meaning in-use) newsgroups, with overall somewhere between 150,000 and 250,000 that currently are dead (dead meaning they are not in use currently).

Returning to our pin-board analogy, it would be very busy if all 25 million users were in the same area, so instead we have replicas created, meaning there are copies of these pin-boards all over the world.

(From now on I'll be calling the pin-boards &quot;newsgroups&quot; as that's the most commonly used term)

I'll introduce some more terminology here, as it makes the explaination go easier later.

News server = These are the places where copies of the newsgroups are held, there is no central news server from where all copies are held, but rather</text>
      <sha1>g2dftuqzoanb754ikmrdzae0b5gvde1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Organic Chemistry/Introduction to reactions/Functional groups in reactions</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>595</id>
    <revision>
      <id>961192</id>
      <parentid>654347</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-09-07T18:35:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>removing all sub-pages from [[Category:Chemistry]], reformatting book main pages to use {{Subject}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;noinclude&gt;
[[Organic Chemistry/Introduction to reactions/Redox reactions|&lt;&lt; Redox reactions]] | [[Organic Chemistry/Introduction to reactions/Drawing reactions|Drawing reactions &gt;&gt;]] 
----
&lt;/noinclude&gt;
[[Organic_Chemistry/Introduction_to_functional_groups|'''Functional groups''']] in reactions make your life easier as an organic chemist because they draw your attention right to where the action is. Any time a reaction is going to occur, you can be almost certain that it is going to take place at a functional group.

There are many functional groups of interest to organic chemists. Here are a few:

1. Halides

These groups are all made up of a single atom in Group 17 of the Periodic Table, which is known as the halogen group, bonded to a carbon atom. They include fluorine, chlorine, bromine, and iodine. Astatine is also a halogen, but it is rarely discussed because it is not readily found in nature and is radioactive. Their electronegativities vary from fluorine with 4.0 to iodine with 2.5, which is approximately the same value that carbon has. Each of these atoms are able to form a single bond with a carbon atom, replacing hydrogen in alkanes and adding across multiple bonds in alkenes and alkyne. Of the four, fluorine is the most reactive and iodine is the least. Because of their intermediate reactivity, chlorine and bromine are often more useful in many reactions.

2. Carbonyl

This group consists of an oxygen atom doubly bonded to a carbon atom. Carbonyl groups are important because the oxygen atom, with an electronegativity of 3.5, shifts electron density away from the rest of the molecule and towards itself. Carbonyls are a key ingredient in aldehydes, ketones, carboxylic acids, esters, and amides.

3. Hydroxyl

This group consists of a hydrogen atom singly bonded to an oxygen atom. The electronegativity difference between hydrogen, which has an electronegatity of 2.1, and oxygen, 3.5, pulls electrons away from the hydrogen and makes it somewhat acidic. This acidic character varies depending on the composition of the rest of the molecule.  Hydroxyl groups are found in alcohols, phenols, enols, and carboxylic acids.

&lt;noinclude&gt;
----
[[Organic Chemistry/Introduction to reactions/Redox reactions|&lt;&lt; Redox reactions]] | Functional groups in reactions | [[Organic Chemistry/Introduction to reactions/Drawing reactions|Drawing reactions &gt;&gt;]]
&lt;/noinclude&gt;

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>5o1kq3sn0fxb4oia3h1vkfw681wbrr1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Organic Chemistry/Introduction to reactions/Drawing reactions</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>596</id>
    <revision>
      <id>961198</id>
      <parentid>688422</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-09-07T18:35:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>removing all sub-pages from [[Category:Chemistry]], reformatting book main pages to use {{Subject}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;noinclude&gt;
[[Organic Chemistry/Introduction to reactions/Functional groups in reactions|&lt;&lt; Functional groups in reactions]] | [[Organic Chemistry/Introduction to reactions/Rates and equilibria|Rates and equilibria &gt;&gt;]]
----
&lt;/noinclude&gt;
==Drawing reactions==
There are various techniques you will run across for notation of organic reactions.

==Arrows==
'''Curved arrows''' are used to show '''movement of electrons'''. They are not used to show where atoms, ions, or molecules move, just electrons.  A curved arrow with two &quot;hooks&quot; on the end indicated movement of a pair of electrons.  A curved arrow with one &quot;hook&quot; indicated movement of one electron.

[[Image:Curvedarrow.png|center|Two &quot;hooks&quot; represents movement of two electrons.]] [[Image:half-arrow.png|center|One &quot;hook&quot; represents movement of one electron.]]

'''Double-headed arrows''' are used to represent equivalence between resonance structures.

[[Image:Arrows2.png]]

'''Two-way double half arrows''' are represent a reaction that can go forward or reverse. If one of the half arrows is longer than the other it means that the reaction pathway favors that direction with the longer arrow.

[[Image:Arrows.png]]

&lt;noinclude&gt;
----
[[Organic Chemistry/Alkanes|&lt;&lt; Alkanes]] | [[Organic Chemistry/Introduction to reactions/Functional groups in reactions|&lt;&lt; Functional groups in reactions]] | Drawing reactions | [[Organic Chemistry/Introduction to reactions/Rates and equilibria|Rates and equilibria &gt;&gt;]] | [[Organic Chemistry/Introduction to functional groups|Introduction to functional groups &gt;&gt;]]
&lt;/noinclude&gt;

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>kx2bys5g4oyf10qcrjv9r1lsyyicgr2</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>General Chemistry/Chemical Reactions</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>602</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2255629</id>
      <parentid>2255603</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-01-22T22:52:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Addihockey10 (automated)</username>
        <id>502783</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Replaceing raster images with vector equivalents, replaced: 50%.png → 50%.svg (3) using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;noinclude&gt;{{General Chemistry/Navigation}}

&lt;/noinclude&gt;&lt;includeonly&gt;
== Chemical Reactions ==
&lt;/includeonly&gt;
#[[General Chemistry/Naming Substances|Naming Substances]] [[Image:75%.svg]]
#[[General Chemistry/Formulas and Numbers|Formulas and Numbers]] [[Image:50%.svg]]
#[[General Chemistry/Stoichiometry|Stoichiometry]] [[File:100%.svg]]
#[[General Chemistry/Chemical equations|Chemical equations]] [[File:100%.svg]]
#[[General Chemistry/Balancing Equations|Balancing Equations]] [[Image:75%.svg]]
#[[General Chemistry/Limiting Reactants and Percent Yield|Limiting Reactants and Percent Yield]] [[Image:50%.svg]]
#[[General Chemistry/Types of chemical reactions|Types of chemical reactions]] [[File:100%.svg]]
#[[General Chemistry/Energy changes in chemical reactions|Energy changes in chemical reactions]] [[Image:75%.svg]]
#[[General Chemistry/Predicting Chemical Reactions|Predicting Chemical Reactions]] [[Image:50%.svg]]

=== Redox Reactions ===
#[[General Chemistry/Redox Reactions/Oxidation and Reduction equations|Redox reactions]] [[Image:75%.svg]]
#[[General Chemistry/Redox Reactions/Oxidation state|Oxidation states]] [[Image:75%.svg]]
#[[General Chemistry/Redox Reactions/Electrochemistry|Electrochemistry]] [[Image:25%.svg]]</text>
      <sha1>jvl8vkf59dkue7800fq0zrp7pom4gri</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Discrete Mathematics/Set theory</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>604</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2214309</id>
      <parentid>1578474</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-11-19T19:55:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TricksterWolf</username>
        <id>499642</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Euler diagrams */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">== elements and members ==
Should the discussion under notation refer to the example number as '''an '''element''' of the set of a member''' of the set? ... [[User:LouI|LouI]]

: I assume you mean to say that 3 is an element of the set ''or'' a member of the set? Yes, either terminology is acceptable...thank you for jogging my memory :) 
: If that's ''not'' what you meant, please clarify, as I don't think I understand you correctly. [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 22:46, 13 Aug 2003 (UTC)

== page moved ==

I have moved Set theory back to where it was before. [[Discrete mathematics/Set theory|Set theory]] is intended as a purely introductory text, and putting further higher level article links with Set theory disturbs the gradual nature of increase of difficulty as the articles will follow...
I hope this is okay with everyone :) [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 10:27, 14 Aug 2003 (UTC)

== questions / answers numbering ==

The numbering of the questions (section 2.6) doesn't make sense, and some of the answers don't seem to match the questions.

There was a stupid error (probably of mine :) that inserted a carriage return which mucked up the ordering of the numbers. It should be better now. [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 09:30, 8 Nov 2003 (UTC)

==Venn diagrams==
Shall I draw some ? If yes what would you like ? [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 14:42, 2 Feb 2004 (UTC)

Don't ask it, do it. And put them here, too. The one you are asking if she/he would like you drawing pictures to may not look at this section never again. You cannot know. So go and do it (supposing that you know about what you are doing).

--[[User:80.220.156.128|80.220.156.128]] 21:20, 9 September 2005 (UTC)

== ambiguity in section 2.4 ==

I think that section 2.4 is a little unclear

the line reading 

Now, B contains some elements of A, but not necessarily all.

could be interpreted to mean that B contains some elements of A in addition to some other elements
(not belonging to A) 

I suggest

Now, B is made up of elements of A, but not necessarily all

: I've reworded it in a different way, so it's a bit more clear. [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 09:02, 19 Oct 2004 (UTC)

How about we say that B is a subset of A if every element of B is also an element of A? Or, equivalently, B doesn't have any elements that aren't also elements of A? (The formation with the double negative makes it clearer that the empty set is a subset of all sets.)

== overstatement ==

&quot;Note that :
: &lt;math&gt;\{x \in \mathbb{N}|\, ax^2+bx+c = 0\}&lt;/math&gt;
is a completely different set!&quot;

Is a bit of an overstatement...it's actually a subset, not a completeley different set.

: That is nitpicking a bit. The idea is still there. Though a different example might be called for. [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 09:15, 29 Jan 2005 (UTC)

== problem set: proper subset ==

I changed the &lt;math&gt;\subset&lt;/math&gt; signs in problems 3 and 4 to &lt;math&gt;\subseteq&lt;/math&gt; signs. You can show that A &lt;math&gt;\subset&lt;/math&gt; B is false by showing that A = B in addition to showing that there is an element of A that is not in B.

problem set: no pun intended?


== pointing ==

In the first paragraph, I changed &quot;your pointing is called a set&quot; to &quot;what you are pointing to is called a set&quot;.  A set consists of its members.  A pointing consists of a (possibly metaphorical) extension of the index finger.  Actually, there is a lot of pointing talk in this module that strikes me as a little troubling.  Perhaps this should be changed.


(I also added titles to the first two comments of this talk page so the contents box would appear in the right place.)

== set comprehension, problem 3 ==

I'm kind of a newbie, so maybe I'm missing something obvious, but in number 3 the first set would start with 2, whereas the second set would start with 1 as the minimum value. Why are they equal?

Never mind, I got it. Duh.


== Definitions of Union, Intersection and Difference ==


I have simplified the definitions of union and intersection, making them more consistent with the notation used in logic, and clarified the example of difference, where the definition referred to B - A, but the example showed A - B. [[User:Nigeltn35|Nigeltn35]] ([[User talk:Nigeltn35|talk]]) 20:56, 8 November 2008 (UTC)

PS I'm new to using LaTeX.  There must be an easier way of writing ''A'' - ''B'' to get the font and size right![[User:Nigeltn35|Nigeltn35]] ([[User talk:Nigeltn35|talk]]) 07:28, 9 November 2008 (UTC)


== Introductory Section and Notation ==
I've attempted a simple introduction, defining a set in terms of 'things' and 'rules'.  Have included in the Notations section &amp;isin; and &amp;notin;, and used simple text rather than LaTeX where possible.  (IMHO LaTeX looks a bit naff in the default font size!) --[[User:Nigeltn35|Nigeltn35]] ([[User talk:Nigeltn35|talk]]) 17:28, 9 November 2008 (UTC)
== Special Sets ==
Introduce these special sets before introducing relations between sets and operations on sets, so that an exercise can follow to allow consolidation of basic ideas.  [[User:Nigeltn35|Nigeltn35]] ([[User talk:Nigeltn35|talk]]) 20:17, 9 November 2008 (UTC)

== Russell's Paradox ==

As I understand it, this page is intended as introductory teaching material on Set Theory as part of a Discrete Maths book. Introducing Russell's paradox may be interesting as a bit of background material for Set Theory in general, but I don't really think that it belongs in this text at all. Is there anyone who would vote to keep it in?  If not, I propose to remove it. (If anyone wants to keep it, I think it needs re-writing...) [[User:Nigeltn35|Nigeltn35]] ([[User talk:Nigeltn35|talk]]) 12:01, 21 November 2008 (UTC)

== I've finished editing for the time being ==

I seem to have pretty well completely re-written this stuff on Set Theory. No-one seems to have objected so far.  As far as I'm concerned, it's fairly complete.  At any rate it will provide a way in to Relations and Functions, Logic, etc.  Does anyone else think there's more to do at this stage?  If not, what happens to it now? [[User:Nigeltn35|Nigeltn35]] ([[User talk:Nigeltn35|talk]]) 12:34, 21 November 2008 (UTC)

== Page now split into Four Sections ==

Following a warning message about the size of the file exceeding 32KB, I have split the text up into four sections: the original Set Theory page containing the first half of the teaching material, Page 2 (the remaining teaching material), Exercises and Answers.  [[User:Nigeltn35|Nigeltn35]] ([[User talk:Nigeltn35|talk]]) 12:06, 25 November 2008 (UTC)

== Euler diagrams ==

Venn diagrams are a special case of Euler diagrams, and half of the diagrams in the Venn diagrams section are not Venn diagrams.  Some of the instruction also shows how to convert a Venn diagram to a simpler Euler diagram, though it does not use this terminology.

For those who don't know the difference, an Euler diagram may or may not show intersections between sets which are empty, and if an region of exclusivity or intersection between sets is not shown then this is an assertion that the region is empty.  For example, if set A is circumscribed by set B, this indicates that all members of A are also members of B.  In some cases, Euler diagrams assert that regions which are shown must be non-empty, or at least it is not yet known whether the region is empty.

A Venn diagram is a special case of an Euler diagram that must show all possible intersections and exclusions.  So there is only one Venn diagram for three sets (a token of this diagram is shown in Figure 4), but there are many possible Euler diagrams for three sets (in general, 2^2^(n-1) for n sets). [[User:TricksterWolf|TricksterWolf]] ([[User talk:TricksterWolf|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/TricksterWolf|contribs]]) 19:55, 19 November 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>sihtfgcsebydfjhs38q8h4yji0mibew</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>CACS/Preface</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>606</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2657841</id>
      <parentid>2063601</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-05-19T13:34:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Authors */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">The Wikibook Introduction to computers and communications technology.

==Scope and Audience==
This textbook is intended to provide a comprehensive overview of the field, useful to those who will practice in it, and those who need to deal with it peripherally.
While it is not a technical work it does deal with technology and describes its structure, background, content, and business in some detail.
This means that it while it can be a general survey, it cannot be necessarily simple.
Every attempt is made to add no more complex details than are necessary to place a part of the field in context.
But context here also means having a general understanding of the internals of an area, and so some complexity is unavoidable.

Thus there are three goals established:
#To be comprehensive and complete in terms of the areas covered.
#To provide enough detail for each area so that the reader can understand what work is accomplished by its practitioners and how that area relates to the rest of the field.
#To avoid enough technical detail so that a reader who isn't involved in an area does not get trapped in it.

These goals may at first seem contradictions, but they are not mutually exclusive.
Instead they serve as boundaries to identify the material included for each topic.
Another limit is imposed with respect to large or ''mainframe'' computers. The mainframe environment and history are briefly discussed in the introducyion to each part, but most material is based on the now ubiquitous personal or desktop computer  environment.

===Professional Readers===
Those who actively work in computers and communications tend to increase the depth of their knowledge and skills within a limited domain.
As they accumulate greater experience and skill, their viewpoint tends to become increasingly that of a single role or area within the discipline.
While this text can serve them for an initial survey of the field, its greatest value will be as a continued reference and context to provide a higher level view of those areas outside of their specialty.

An online, collaborative text may be particularly valuable in this second role.
All of the areas, disciplines, roles, and uses of this technology are changing.
Indeed, the rate of change seems to increase geometrically, while the number of areas or specialties increases exponentially.
Unlike a paper text, an online one can be maintained rapidly and constantly.
Once the reader is familiar with the format and content of the work, future reference is easier.
So when presented with a new feature, function, or technology there is an updated textbook that's just like the one they used before.
While some may prefer a paper copy for initial use, an updated copy may be continually available.
===Non-Professional Readers===
Very few professions today escape being affected by the application of computers and the related communication technology.
For those who work in other disciplines an up to date survey and reference may also be valuable when they must deal with the impact of the technology within their own field.
When forced to interact with the high priests of technology, they need not compete to get their viewpoint recognized while ignorant of the goals, practices, and terminology of the ordained.
When a piece of these technologies interacts with your own business, this will not replace a user manual, or even the level of the ''Topic X for Dummies''.
What it does is to provide the background and context that make those materials more useful.
==Terminology==

There are four words used in this work that require some explanation.
The words ''platform, entity, element,'' and ''component'' are used loosely, but with some intent.
Generally the term '''''entity''''' is used to describe the thing being considered or addressed by a topic,
'''''element''''' is used to describe a feature or function of the entity being discussed,
and '''''component''''' is used to describe a unit that is considered as a whole, and stands alone for some functions,
while '''''platform''''' refers to the group of components that are prerequisite to the entity under discussion.
Each term frequently represents the specific being discussed and its peers or similar units that operate at the same level.

A specific area or topic may be treated at all four levels.
Consider a single Web Page as an example.
When describing the Client–Server model of the Internet, it is a ''component''.
When considering HTML it is a part of the ''platform''.
In a part of the discussion of Web Site Construction it is first an ''element'' of the site, and then an ''entity'' since there are several topics that directly discuss Web Pages.

==Structure==

The question of how to organize a comprehensive technology overview is both fundamental and complex.
You can probably think of ways to improve the organization chosen (I know I do every time I look at it).
This section outlines of the survey's major organization into parts and breiefly identifies the main subject for each part.

The overview is organized into a decomposition hierarchy.
The hierarchy is presented two layers at a time.
Subject definitions are always presented twice, once with their parent subject and again in their own introduction.

''For full detail, see the:'' [[CACS:Contents]]

Subject areas and major parts are listed below:
*Hardware – The machines that are computers and their supporting attachments.
**Computing Machines – The fundamental engines of the revolution.
**Peripherals – The things that tie the computers to worthwhile work.
**Architectures – The structure that ties things together.
**Communications – The hardware that couples computers and components.

*Software – The program components that make the computer world accessible.
**Platforms – Operating Systems and basic Tool Suites.
**Middleware – The attachment layer.
**Construction Tools – Languages, Environments, and builders of all kinds.
**Applications – Tool sets that are used to do real work.
**Architecture – Structures for coupling components.

*Communications – Things that let computers and people connect to each other.
**Architecture – In communications, the Structure comes first.
**Networks – Computers and users coupled to gain processing power and leverage.
**Internet – The virtual structure that ties networks together.
**Content – The information that makes the structure worth having. 

*Applications – Applying the computer world to get things done.
**Desktop – Direct support of human efforts.
**Departmental – Those applications that support a single function or functional area.
**Process – Applications that support a broader work effort.
**Platforms – Generic applications, structures, and architectures for all kinds of work. 
**Vertical – Organizing applications by Industry Group.

*Services – How work gets done.
**Skills, specialties, and expertise.
**Methods and Life Cycles.
**Analysis and Programming – Specialties, Languages.
**Education and training, certification.
**Related functions: project management, business planning, consulting.

*Business – How computers, software, and applications are bought and sold.
**Manufacturers –
**Software Vendors –
**Support Structures –
**Service Providers –
**Newly Enabled Functions – Call centers, knowledge base, Supplier-company-customer integration.
**Packaging – Retailing, OEM, Integrators, Alliances.

Some things fell off this hierarchy, and are contained in other areas of topics. These are:
*History –
*Miscellaneous Topics – Stray interesting topics that affect multiple areas.
*Lists –
**Glossary – An industry full of buzzwords, a consolidated glossary.
**Reference Data –
**Companies –
**Organizations –
**Index –

==Authors==

Any work with the broad and inclusive scope proposed cannot succeed without the contributions of many individuals, both experts and generalists.
If this text is to be useful to the general audience, it also needs a lot of amateurs to insure that it stays readable.
Thanks in advance to all contributors.

As in any good Wiki, details of contribution will be kept for each subject on the page history.
Major contributors who wish to be identified will be acknowledged on the [[CACS/Authors]] page.

There is to be a separate page about writing sections of this book, and it is kept on the [[CACS/Author Guidelines]] page.
To comment on direction or structure please use the Talk page of the part, chapter, section or topic.

[[Category:{{FULLBOOKNAME}}|{{FULLCHAPTERNAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>le87syjo2cmn00lrlmuga642sx6qnwz</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>CACS/Authors</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>607</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1493464</id>
      <parentid>1493391</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-05-07T18:07:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Darklama</username>
        <id>7662</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>recat</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">This Wikibook is a the result of a collaborative effort by a number or contributors.
All of them are gratefully acknowledged, and thanked for their good work.

The only ones identified here are those who have chosen to share the blame for its shortcomings.
You can contact any of them through their Wikibook user talk page or by eMail.
---
Contributors in alphabetic order are:
*[[User:LouI|LouI]] - just a start up of the work. (instigator, nag, and critic).

{{subject|computing|technology}}</text>
      <sha1>pe6lr91v3dfg9io5n91q2wd4eylhaqa</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>CACS</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>609</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1912522</id>
      <parentid>1912521</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-08-16T20:24:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>noeditsection; remove the obvious</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{book title|Introduction to Computers and Communications Technology|&amp;nbsp;}}

==Table of Contents==
:[[/Preface/]]
:[[/Authors/]]

=== Hardware ===
:[[/Hardware Introduction/]]
:[[/Computers/]]
:[[/Peripherals/]]
:[[/Hardware Architecture/]]
:[[/Communications Hardware/]]

=== Software ===
:[[/Software Introduction/]]
:[[/Software Platforms/]]
:[[/Software Middleware/]]
:[[/Software Toolboxes/]]
:[[/Software Applications/]]
:[[/Software Architecture/]]

=== Communications ===
:[[/Communications Introduction/]]
:[[/Communications Architecture/]]
:[[/Communications Networks/]]
:[[/Internet and Web/]]
:[[/Internet Content/]]

=== Applications ===
:[[/Applications Introduction/]]
:[[/Desktop Applications/]]
:[[/Departmental Applications/]]
:[[/Application Processing/]]
:[[/Application Platforms/]]
:[[/Vertical Applications/]]

=== Services ===
:[[/Skills and Specialties/]]
:[[/Methods/]]
:[[/Analysis/]]
:[[/Programming/]]
:[[/Education/]]
:[[/Project Management/]]
:[[/Business Planning/]]
:[[/Consulting/]]

=== The Computer Business ===
:[[/Business Introduction/]]
:[[/Manufacturers/]]
:[[/Software Vendors/]]
:[[/Support Structures/]]
:[[/Service Providers/]]
:[[/New Business Functions/]]
:[[/New Delivery Models/]]

=== Miscellaneous Topics ===
:[[/User Conundrum/]] - ''An essay''.
:[[/Trouble with Models/]] - ''A view of models and their uses''.

=== Appendices ===
:[[/Glossary/]]
:[[/Index/]]
__NOTOC__ __NOEDITSECTION__
{{subjects|Computing|Communication}}
{{alphabetical|C}}
{{status|0%}}</text>
      <sha1>nat5mjrk7td8i82xhiwsadp6qf6m2w0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>CACS/Glossary</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>610</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1493465</id>
      <parentid>1493400</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-05-07T18:07:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Darklama</username>
        <id>7662</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>recat</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Glossary of Computer and Communications Terms'''

For each term in the Glossary, there is a single data page. When a term is usually known by its acronym, it is defined on a page with that title.
When needed, redirect pages will be used to get to that data page from any other frequently used names.

Many terms contained here have more information than is displayed in a simple definition.
When a word or phrase within a definition is shown in ''italics'', that word or phrase is also expected to appear in the glossary.
A list of All terms is contained at the bottom of this page.

Terms in the Glossary include: processes, languages, terms of art, acronyms, hardware devices, software package names, companies and organizations.
Every effort is made to note those that are trademarks or proprietary names.
All such use is intended to be made under ''fair use'' conditions and should not reduce the owner's rights or the terms of the GNU/GFDL license applied to this work as a whole.
The full text of the free use license that applies here is located at [http://www.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia%3AText_of_the_GNU_Free_Documentation_License Wikipedia License].
----
''The following is '''Subject to Change'''. Currently each term is being set up on a subpage of the Glossary. This is mandated by their intended use in pop-up windows when reading the book.''
----
{{compactTOC}}
==List of Terms==
===A===
[[CACS:Glossary/ASP|Active Server Page]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/ACWP|Actual Cost of Work Performed]] - 
[[CACS:Glossary/ACWP|ACWP]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/Adobe|Adobe]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/ADP|ADP]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/Aldus|Aldus]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/ANI|ANI]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/ANI|Animated Cursor]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/Apache|Apache]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/ASF|Apache Software Foundation]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/ASP|ASP]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/Application|Application]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/ASProvider|Application Service Provider]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/Assembler|Assembler]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/Assembly|Assembly]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/ASML|Assembly Language]]

===B===
[[CACS:Glossary/Basic|Basic]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/Binary|Binary]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/Borland|Borland]]
===C===
[[CACS:Glossary/Computer|Computer]] - [[/CSS/]]

===G===
[[CACS:Glossary/GRE|General Routing Encapsulation]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/GRE|GRE]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/HTML|HTML]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/HTML|Hypertext Markup Language]]
===I===
[[CACS:Glossary/ISOC|ISOC]]
===M===
[[CACS:Glossary/MPLS|MPLS]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/MPLS|Multiprotocol Label Switching]]
===P===
[[CACS:Glossary/PKI|PKI]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/PKI|Public Key Infrastruture]]
===T===
[[CACS:Glossary/Tunneling|Tunneling]]
===U===
[[CACS:Glossary/Unary|Unary Operator]] -
[[CACS:Glosary/Unicode|Unicode]] - 
[[CACS:Glossary/URI|Uniform Resource Identifier]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/URL|Uniform Resource Locator]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/URN|Uniform Resource Name]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/URI|URI]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/URL|URL]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/URN|URN]]
===V===
[[CACS:Glossary/VPN|Virtual Private Network]] -
[[CACS:Glossary/VPN|VPN]]

{{subjects|computing|technology}}</text>
      <sha1>0n278svx7ahdtqrm8f4hiyiy6vnhtv6</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>CACS/Glossary/HTML</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>611</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1508363</id>
      <parentid>1493440</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-05-25T23:54:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>recat</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Hypertext Markup Language (HTML)''' &lt;small&gt;(Internet)&lt;/small&gt; A document publishing language that mixes content, formatting rules, and processing ''scripts'' to create ''Web Pages''.
The HTML source is interpreted and displayed by a ''browser'' on the end user's computer.
HTML is an open specification maintained through a consortium of major vendors and corporations known as the ''W3C''.
The most recent, full version of the ''language specification'' is HTML 4.01 and dates from December 1999. It can be downloaded from the [http://www.w3.org/TR/html401/ W3C Web Site].

HTML (or .htm) is also used as a file extension for a stored web page that uses the language.

[[Category:{{FULLBOOKNAME}}|{{FULLCHAPTERNAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>74egw67cfenz1ayt6kbtcqvmdxnyzae</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Discrete Mathematics/Naive set theory</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>612</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2065176</id>
      <parentid>1578517</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-03-06T01:37:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Avicennasis</username>
        <id>314063</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WP:AWB/T|Typo fixing]], typos fixed: seperated → separated, unwieldly → unwieldy using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">When we talk of '''set theory''', we generally talk about ''collections'' of certain mathematical objects. In this sense, a ''set'' can be likened to a bag, holding a finite (or conceivably infinite) amount of things. Sets can be sets of sets as well (bags with bags in them). However, a set cannot contain duplicates -- a set can contain only one copy of a particular item.

When we look at sets of certain types of numbers, for example, the natural numbers, or the rational numbers, for instance, we may want to speak only of these sets. These collections of numbers are, of course, very important, so we write special symbols to signify them.

We write sets in curly brackets -- { and }. We write all of the ''elements'', or what the set contains, in the brackets, separated by commas. We generally denote sets using capital letters.

For example, we write the set containing the number 0 and the number 1 as {0,1}. If we wish to give it a name, we can say B={0,1}. 

== Special sets ==
The aforementioned collections of numbers, the naturals, rationals, etc. are notated as the following:
* the ''natural'' numbers are written &lt;math&gt;\mathbb{N}&lt;/math&gt;
: {0,1,2,...}
* the ''integers'' are written &lt;math&gt;\mathbb{Z}&lt;/math&gt;
: {0,1,-1,2,-2,...}
* the ''rational'' numbers are written &lt;math&gt;\mathbb{Q}&lt;/math&gt;
: {0,1,1/2,1/3,...,2,2/3,2/4,...}
* the ''real'' numbers are written &lt;math&gt;\mathbb{R}&lt;/math&gt;
: {0,&lt;math&gt;-\sqrt{2}&lt;/math&gt;,&lt;math&gt;\sqrt{2}&lt;/math&gt;,&lt;math&gt;\pi&lt;/math&gt;,...}

Here we will generally write these in standard face bold instead of the doublestruck bold you see above. So we write here '''N''' instead of &lt;math&gt;\mathbb{N}&lt;/math&gt; (NB following Wikipedia conventions).

== Notations ==
We can write some special relations involving sets using some symbols.

=== Containment relations ===
To say that an element is in a set, for example, 3 is in the set {1,2,3}, we write:
:&lt;math&gt;3\in\{1,2,3\}&lt;/math&gt;

We can also express this relationship in another way: we say that 3 is a ''member'' of the set {1,2,3}. Also, we can say the set {1,2,3} ''contains'' 3, but this usage is not recommended as it is also used to refer to subsets (see following).

We can say that two sets are equal if they contain exactly the same elements. For example, the sets {2,3,1} and {3,1,2} both contain the numbers 1, 2 and 3.
We write:
:&lt;math&gt;\{2,3,1\}=\{3,1,2\}&lt;/math&gt;

We write the set with ''no'' elements as &lt;math&gt;\empty&lt;/math&gt;, or {}. Here, we use the notation {} for the ''empty set'' (NB following Wikipedia conventions).

=== The concept of the subset ===
A very important concept in set theory and other mathematical areas is the concept of the '''subset'''. 

Say we have two sets A={0,1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9}, and B={0,1,2,3,4,5}. 
Now, B ''contains some elements'' of A, but not all. We express this relationship between the sets A and B by saying B is a ''subset'' of A.  
We write this
:&lt;math&gt;B\subseteq A&lt;/math&gt;

If B is a subset of A, but A is not a subset of B, B is said to be a ''proper subset'' of A.
We write this
:&lt;math&gt;B\subset A&lt;/math&gt;

Note that if &lt;math&gt;B\subset A&lt;/math&gt;, then &lt;math&gt;B\subseteq A&lt;/math&gt;

=== Intersections and unions ===
There are two notable and fundamental special operations on sets, the ''intersection'' and the ''union''. These are somewhat analogous to multiplication and addition.

==== Intersection ====
The intersection of two sets A and B are the elements ''common'' to both sets.
For example, if A={1,3,5,7,9} and B={0,1,3}, their intersection, written &lt;math&gt;A\cap B&lt;/math&gt; is the set {1,3}. 

If the intersection of any two sets are empty, we say these sets are ''disjoint''. 

==== Unions ====
The union of two sets A and B are the ''all'' elements in ''both'' sets. For example if A={1,3,5,7,9} and B={0,2,4,6,8}. We say the union, written &lt;math&gt;A\cup B&lt;/math&gt; is the set {0,1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9}.

=== Set comprehensions ===
When we write a set, we can do so by writing all the elements in that set as above. However if we wish to write an ''infinite'' set, then writing out the elements can be too unwieldy. We can solve this problem by writing sets in ''set comprehension'' notation. We do this by writing these sets including a ''rule'' and by a relationship to an ''index set'', say I. That is;
: &lt;math&gt;S=\{x \in I | rule\}&lt;/math&gt;
where rule can be something like ''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, or ''x''=3''x''.

For example, this set forms the set of all even numbers:
: &lt;math&gt;\{x \in \mathbb{N}| x \mod 2 = 0\}&lt;/math&gt;

This set forms the set of all solutions to the general quadratic:
: &lt;math&gt;\{x \in \mathbb{C}| ax^2+bx+c = 0\}&lt;/math&gt;

=== Universal sets and complements ===
==== Universal sets ====
When we do work with sets, it is useful to think of a larger set in which to work with. For example, if we are talking about sets {-1,0,1} and {-3,-1,1,3}, we may want to work in '''Z''' in this circumstance. When we talk about working in such a larger set, such as '''Z''' in that instance, we say that '''Z''' is a ''universal set'', and we take all sets to be subsets of this universal set. 

We write the universal set to be &lt;math&gt;\mathcal{E}&lt;/math&gt;, however it may be simpler to denote this as '''E'''. 

==== Complements ====
Given a set A in a larger universal set '''E''', we define the complement of A to be all elements in E that are not in A, that is the complement of A is:
:&lt;math&gt;\{x\in \mathcal{E}|x\not\in A\}&lt;/math&gt;
We write the complement as A' or A&lt;sup&gt;c&lt;/sup&gt;. In this document we will use A'.

=== Problem set ===
Based on the above information, write the answers to the following questions
(Answers follow to even numbered questions)
# Is &lt;math&gt;3/4\in\mathbb{Q}&lt;/math&gt;?
# Is &lt;math&gt;\sqrt{2}\in\mathbb{Q}&lt;/math&gt;? &lt;!--2 --&gt;
# Is &lt;math&gt;\{x\in\mathbb{N}|2x\}=\{x\in\mathbb{N}|{x \over 2}\in \mathbb{N}\}&lt;/math&gt;?
# True or false? If false, give an example of an element in the first set which is not in the second. &lt;!--4 --&gt;
## &lt;math&gt;\mathbb{N} \subset \mathbb{Z}&lt;/math&gt;
## &lt;math&gt;\mathbb{Q} \subset \mathbb{Z}&lt;/math&gt;
# True or false? If false, give an example of an element in the first set which is not in the second.
## &lt;math&gt;\mathbb{R} \subset \mathbb{Q}&lt;/math&gt;
## &lt;math&gt;\mathbb{Z} \subset \mathbb{R}&lt;/math&gt;
# Is &lt;math&gt;\{1,2,3\} \subset \{1,2,3,4\}&lt;/math&gt;? &lt;!--6 --&gt;
# Is &lt;math&gt;\{1,2,3,5\} \subseteq \{1,2,3,4\}&lt;/math&gt;?
# Write the 5 elements of&lt;br&gt;&lt;math&gt;\{x\in\mathbb{Z}|x-3 \mod 2 = 0\}&lt;/math&gt;&lt;!--8 --&gt;
# Write the elements of&lt;br&gt;&lt;math&gt;\{x\in\mathbb{C}|x^2+4x-3=0\}&lt;/math&gt;
# Find a universal set such that these sets are subsets thereof: &lt;math&gt;\{x \in \mathbb{Z^+}|a=x^2 and\ \sqrt{a}\in\mathbb{N}\},\{x \in \mathbb{N}|x/3\} &lt;/math&gt; &lt;!-- 10 --&gt;
# Given &lt;math&gt;\mathcal{E}=\{0,1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9\}&lt;/math&gt;, find A' given &lt;math&gt;A={1,4,7,9}&lt;/math&gt;

==== Answers ====
2. No, the square root of 2 is ''irrational'', not a rational number&lt;br&gt;
4.1. Yes &lt;br&gt;
4.2. No&lt;br&gt;
6. Yes.&lt;br&gt;
8. 5 elements could be {3,5,7,9,11}.&lt;br&gt;
10. &lt;math&gt;\mathcal{E}=\mathbb{Q}&lt;/math&gt;&lt;br&gt;

== Further ideas ==
These mentioned concepts are not the only ones we can give to set theory. Key ideas that are not necessarily given much detail in this elementary course in set theory but later in abstract algebra and other fields, so it is important to take a grasp on these ideas now.

These may be skipped.

=== Power set ===
The ''power set'', denoted P(S), is the set of ''all'' subsets of S. 
'''''NB''''': The empty set is a subset of '''all''' sets.

For example, P({0,1})={{},{0},{1},{0,1}}

=== Cardinality ===
The ''cardinality'' of a set, denoted |S| is the amount of elements a set has. So |{a,b,c,d}|=4, and so on. The cardinality of a set need not be finite: some sets have infinite cardinality.

==== The cardinality of the power set ====
If P(S)=T, then |T|=2&lt;sup&gt;|S|&lt;/sup&gt;.

==== Problem set ====
Based on the above information, write the answers to the following questions. (Answers follow to even numbered questions)
# |{1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,0}|
# |P({1,2,3})|
# P({0,1,2})
# P({1})

==== Answers ====
2. 2&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;=8&lt;br&gt;
4. {{},{1}}

== Set identities ==
When we spoke of the two fundamental operators on sets before, that of the ''union'' and the ''intersection'', we have a set of rules which we can use to simplify expressions involving sets. For example, given:
:&lt;math&gt;(A\cup B)'\cap B'\cap A&lt;/math&gt;
how can we simplify this?

Several of the following set identities are similar to those in standard mathematics

'''''This is incomplete and a draft, additional information is to be added'''''

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>ohvwn1xckuat6t1u1mri7i57bn5p9ne</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Tomos</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>615</id>
    <revision>
      <id>152754</id>
      <parentid>74236</parentid>
      <timestamp>2004-12-03T07:46:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tomos</username>
        <id>71</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* notes */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[w:en:User:Tomos]]
[[w:ja:利用者:Tomos]]
[[meta:User:Tomos]]

==notes==
1464, 578, 233, 10041, 1861, 71, [[User:Tomos|Tomos]] 02:55, 14 Aug 2003 (UTC)

*Kana sound files
**Recording...done
**Converting into .ogg... done 
**Quality check...sort of done -&gt; antimobius will help us
**Commenting/Licensing... done anyway (probably not copyrightable)
**(Re)naming... done - ja_[hepburn].ogg -&gt; to be renamed by antimobius
**Uploading... done to yahoogroup

Software tools used:

*Recording: Opcode direct2disk (OpD2d) (URL lost, version unkown)
*Encoding &amp; Commenting: [http://winvorbis.stationplaylist.com/ WinVorbis] (v.1.56)
*Renaming: [http://www.albert.nu/default.asp?sub=programs/default.asp?sub=renamer/main.htm Renamer] (v.4.0)</text>
      <sha1>kp315fpbr4qoxbusx95b9iackuj1cdx</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>CACS/Index</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>616</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1508371</id>
      <parentid>1493456</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-05-25T23:57:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Fixed category, typos, removed {{alphabetical}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">''This page is not yet a normal '''Index'''.''
''The capabilities of search engines now satisfy some of the needs formerly addressed by a paper index.''
''That means that as this volume nears completion, the content or use of this page may need redesign.''

''Currently the page is more of a notepad or guide for an author than it is an aid to the ultimate reader.''
''For any index entry, there is simply a list of those pages, by full name, that have some bearing on the subject.''
''Having this cross reference will aid in updating topics that involve several pages as well as reviewing them to ensure consistency.''

''Please Direct comments and suggestions for the format and content of this page to its Talk Page.''
----
==Index Subjects==
&lt;!-- Wikibook Editors - please maintain the Definition list formatting --&gt;
;component
:(as used in the book) [[CACS/Preface#Terminology]]
;HTML:[[CACS/Glossary/HTML]]
;Hypertext Markup Language:[[CACS/Glossary/HTML]]

[[Category:{{FULLBOOKNAME}}|{{FULLCHAPTERNAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>32d1zuxmr16fuf78oq2d9u1njqdhoag</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:CACS/Index</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>617</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1493458</id>
      <parentid>152756</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-05-07T18:02:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Darklama</username>
        <id>7662</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>moved [[Talk:CACS:Index]] to [[Talk:CACS/Index]]:&amp;#32;per [[WB:NP]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">I'm not sure if this is a good idea for building a Wikibook or not. For a while I'll be using it to sort of mirror a technique I used when building very large word documents. During construction we used the expanded index as a tool to aid internal consistancy for the document as a whole. But part of that utility came from the ability to pop open an insert box for a new entry while editing any page.

Wiki page editing has the advantage of being text only, but page separation makes maintaining this list cumbersome at best. If it proves too difficult, I'll find another solution. Of course, suggestions are welcome! ..[[User:LouI|LouI]] 06:00, 14 Aug 2003 (UTC)
----</text>
      <sha1>3c46sgcb4axdr3brjamlhpk7g707u36</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Polish</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>620</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2670045</id>
      <parentid>2525503</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-06-05T12:30:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>84.22.40.121</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Flag of Poland.svg|thumb|200px|Flag of Poland]]
{{Category 2}}
The '''Polish language''' is a member of the '''Western Slavic''' group of the [[w:Indo-European|Indo-European]] family of languages. It is easiest to learn if one already knows some other related language.

The most closely related are other Western [[w:Slavic languages|Slavic languages]]: [[w:Czech language|Czech]], [[w:Slovak language|Slovak]], [[w:Silesian language|Silesian]], [[w:Kashubian language|Kashubian]] and [[w:Sorbian languages|Sorbian]]. More distant are the Southern and Eastern Slavic languages like [[w:Russian language|Russian]], [[w:Ukrainian language|Ukrainian]], [[w:Belorusian language|Belorusian]], [[w:Bulgarian language|Bulgarian]], [[w:Macedonian language|Macedonian]], [[w:Serbo-Croatian language|Serbo-Croatian]], and [[w:Slovenian language|Slovenian]]. 

Polish is spoken by a total of approximately 40 million people, making it the second most widely spoken Slavic language in the world, next to Russian. Speakers of related languages can pick it up with not much effort. 

Someone who doesn't speak any Slavic language, but speaks some other Indo-European language, may still find many similarities between Polish grammar and the grammar of that language, as well as many similar words. 

This Wikibook is designed for anyone who wants to learn the basics of the Polish language.  It is suitable for beginners and those who've been learning the language for a few years. 

==Table of contents==
[[Image:Krakow rynek 01.jpg|thumb|350px|right|Market square of [[w:Kraków|Kraków]] ]]

===Lesson 1===
# [[/Polish pronunciation/]]
# [[/Basic grammar/]]
#* [[/Exercises - Introductory conjugation/]]
#* [[/Exercises - Introductory declension/]]
# [[/Some useful expressions/]]
#* [[/Exercises - Useful expressions/]]
# [[/Introductions/]] 
#* [[/Exercises - Introducing yourself, simple questions/]]
# [[/List of words/]] (Lista słów)

===Lesson 2===
# [[/More on nouns - genders/]]
# [[/Order of words in a sentence/]]
# [[/Plural/]]
# [[/Noun cases/]] (declensions)
#* [[/Hard and soft consonants/]]
#* [[/Feminine noun declension/]]
#* [[/Masculine noun declension/]]
#* [[/Neuter noun declension/]]
#* [[/Prepositions as hints to declensions/]]
#[[/Cześć! Jak się masz?/]]

===Lesson 3===
# [[/Conjugations of common verbs/]]
#* [[/Exercises - Conjugations of common verbs/]]
# [[/Adjectives/]]
#* [[/More on adjectives/]]
#* [[/Comparative and Superlative/]]
#* [[/Possessive Adjectives/]]

===Lesson 4===
# [[/Grouping expressions/]]
# [[/Questions/]]
# [[/Verbs/]]
#* [[/Usage of the infinitive/]]
# [[/Na kursie/]]

===Lesson 5===
# [[/Conversation in Polish/]]
# [[/Vocabulary/]]

===Lesson 6===
# [[/Declension/]]
#* [[/Nominative case/]] (mianownik)
#* [[/Genitive case/]] (dopełniacz)
#* [[/Dative case/]] (celownik)
#* [[/Accusative case/]] (biernik)
#* [[/Instrumental case/]] (narzędnik)
#* [[/Locative case/]] (miejscownik)
#* [[/Vocative case/]] (wołacz)

===Grammar===
# [[/Present tense/]] (czas teraźniejszy)
# [[/Past tense/]] (czas przeszły)
# [[/Future tense/]] (czas przyszły)
# [[/Conditional mood/]] (tryb przypuszczający)
# [[/Imperative mood/]] (tryb rozkazujący)

===Grammar 2===
# [[/Nouns - Gender/]] (''Rzeczowniki - Rodzaj'')
# [[/Nouns - Number/]] (''Rzeczowniki - Liczba'')
# [[/Pronouns/]] (''Zaimki'')
# [[/Possessive pronouns/]] (''Zaimki dzierżawcze'')
# [[/Nouns - Gender II/]] (''Rzeczowniki - Rodzaj II'')
# [[/Adjectives/]] (''Przymiotniki'')
# [[/Nouns - Number II/]] (''Rzeczowniki - Liczba II'')
# [[/Verbs/]] (''Czasowniki'')


==Copyright==
This document was originally copyright 2002 Tomasz Węgrzanowski &amp; Anna (grammar) &amp;lt;taw&amp;#64;users&amp;#46;sf&amp;#46;net&amp;gt;
It may be distributed under terms of GNU Free Documentation Licence. Since its original writing, it has been edited and redistributed on Wiktionary and, currently, Wikibooks.

==See also==
* [http://www.polish-translators.com/grammar.html Polish Pronunciation Audio and Grammar Charts]
* [[wikt:Category:Polish language|Polish language in English Wiktionary]] and [[wikt:pl:Strona główna|Polish Wiktionary]]
* [[voy:Polish_phrasebook|Polish phrasebook]] (WikiVoyage)
* [[w:Polish language|Wikipedia: Polish language]]
* [[w:pl:Strona główna|Polish Wikipedia]]
* [[commons:Category:Polish pronunciation|Polish pronunciation records]] on Wikimedia Commons
* [[False Friends of the Slavist]]

==External links==
* [http://www.polish-translators.com/grammar.html Polish Pronunciation Audio and Grammar Charts]
* [http://www.learnpolish-online.com/Pages/polish_grammar.aspx/grammar.html Free Polish Grammar]

==Further reading==
* {{cite book| last=Sadowska| first=Iwona| title= Polish: A Comprehensive Grammar| year=2012| publisher=[[Routledge]]| location=[[Oxford]]; [[New York]]| isbn=978-0-415-47541-9}}

{{Subjects|Languages of Europe}}
{{alphabetical|P}}
{{status|25%}}
__NOTOC__ __NOEDITSECTION__

[[cs:Polština]]
[[de:Polnisch]]
[[fr:Polonais]]
[[he:פולנית]]
[[nl:Pools]]
[[ja:ポーランド語]]
[[pt:Polonês]]
[[ru:Польский язык]]</text>
      <sha1>tpcko9v1a979rwv0tc9z1uljjygl532</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:128.175.112.225</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>623</id>
    <revision>
      <id>152762</id>
      <parentid>4475</parentid>
      <timestamp>2003-10-10T08:16:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dysprosia</username>
        <id>32</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>suggestion</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Hello :) Please ''use'' the Move Page feature in future...
Not doing so makes things messier and doesn't allow to save edit history.

However I've moved some things around, if you are interested... please see [[Talk:Discrete mathematics:Set theory]] for the rationale
Thanks [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 10:02, 14 Aug 2003 (UTC)

----
Hey again :) I really appreciate the edits to the Group theory article, however could you be a little more &quot;instructional&quot; in the way you write? We need to explicate the ideas for group theory in an extensive way. 

Thanks, and keep contributing! [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 08:16, 10 Oct 2003 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>hbrgrj6c4srqyj6gsil7333vwomcizx</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>