<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>How to Write an Essay/AP/Introduction</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3962</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1624490</id>
      <parentid>1495529</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-09-04T18:20:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>moved [[How to write an essay/AP/Introduction]] to [[How to Write an Essay/AP/Introduction]]: Title casing.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Content needed==
* Explanation of the AP program
AP (Advanced Placement) courses allow high school students to take and get credit for college-level classes. To get credit for a course, a student must pass the AP test. Unfortunately, not all colleges and universities in the US accept AP tests, and some may have their own independent exams. The AP is prepared by Collegeboard and their buddies at ETS (I think), also the writers of such tests as the SAT and PSAT. Courses cover a wide range of subjects, including Spanish, Calculus, English, Chemistry, and History.


* Types of essays

1. Agree or Disagree&lt;br&gt;
2. Author's attitude, tone, or point of view&lt;br&gt;
3. Analyze effect&lt;br&gt;
4. Author's purpose&lt;br&gt;
5. General statement about society or human nature&lt;br&gt;
6. Comparison/Contrast&lt;br&gt;

==Sources to use==
* [http://apcentral.collegeboard.com/ AP Central]

[[Category:{{FULLBOOKNAME}}|{{FULLCHAPTERNAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>0iysj2qzs9ggi7wvbq6589ts2ro9d7h</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Botany/Mycology</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3967</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2294398</id>
      <parentid>624877</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-03-30T07:29:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>75.172.102.102</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Added &quot;mycorrhizal&quot; as the third type of mushroom (with regards to classification by how they get their nutrients)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;small&gt;&lt;&lt; [[Botany#Contents|Contents Page]] | [[Botany/Phycology|Chapter 9]] | &lt;/small&gt;Chapter 10&lt;small&gt; |   [[Botany/Bryology|Chapter 11]] &gt;&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 
----
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;big&gt;&lt;big&gt;Chapter 10. Mycology ~ The Fungi&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/big&gt;  
&lt;/center&gt;

== Introduction ==
[[Image:Fungi_bracket.jpg|thumb|right|(''Pycnoporus sanguineus'')&lt;br&gt;Fruiting bodies of a bracket fungus on a Christmasberry log'']]

The '''Fungi''' (singular is ''fungus'') are a large group of organisms treated within the science of Botany, but not really &quot;plants&quot; in the usual sense of the term. The Fungi are ranked as a kingdom within the Domain [[Wikipedia:en:Eukaryote|Eukaryota]]. That is, they have eukaryotic cells with distinct nuclei, although in some species divisions between nucleated &quot;cells&quot; are sparse.  However, they all lack chlorophyll, and the species are saprophytic, parasitic or mycorrhizal. Included within the Fungi are the well known mushrooms, but the group also includes many microscopic forms, and fungi inhabit every environment on earth, perhaps second only to the bacteria (Chapter 7) in distribution.

== Structure ==
(...)

*Read [[Wikipedia:en:Mycology|Mycology]] (&lt;small&gt;Follow all links)&lt;/small&gt;
*Read [[Wikipedia:en:Fungi|Fungi]] (&lt;small&gt;The following links are included:&lt;/small&gt;)
** [[Wikipedia:en:Mushroom|Mushroom]]
::Be sure to read about and understand each of the following terms: '''basidium''', '''hyphae''', '''mycorrhizae''', '''psilocybin'''

----
&lt;center&gt;
{{BotanyTOC2}}
&lt;/center&gt;

[[Category:Botany]]</text>
      <sha1>1x5yodqy1abw1rgwvfjo12ahtd9zt72</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Fungi bracket.jpg</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>3968</id>
    <revision>
      <id>904325</id>
      <parentid>900051</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-06-20T07:57:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Webaware</username>
        <id>27565</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>licensing</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Bracket fungus (?''Pycnoporus sanguineus'') photographed in Hawai'i by Eric Guinther and released under the GNU Free Documentation License.

==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>nwdy9agi7431f3k9cumxj464itz7qvd</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Ensjo</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>3976</id>
    <revision>
      <id>155802</id>
      <timestamp>2004-01-21T13:05:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>161.148.99.130</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Vide: http://ia.wikipedia.org/wiki/Usator:Ensjo</text>
      <sha1>5nvkdxq1pk1jhpqsh120pj7kllxo7xg</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Geometric series representation.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>3978</id>
    <revision>
      <id>636421</id>
      <parentid>155804</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-11-04T10:59:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Theresa knott</username>
        <id>93</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">diagram drawn by theresa knott

{{GFDL}}
{{Cc-by-sa-2.5}}</text>
      <sha1>mk3caygslsqud0ic4yru2b41aylabxv</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Lucid Dreaming/Induction Techniques</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3985</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2697684</id>
      <parentid>2697606</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-09-05T08:32:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Panic2k4</username>
        <id>2865</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{LDTOC}}

This page describes a number of lucid dream induction techniques. It is recommended that you be able to [[Lucid Dreaming/Dream Recall|recall]] ''at least'' one dream per night in order to maximize the effectiveness of these methods.

==Preliminary Knowledge==
Certain elements are common to many of the lucidity-inducing techniques discussed later in this chapter.  To better understand these techniques, these common components will be discussed first.

===Sleep Interruption===
An element shared by many of the techniques is sleep interruption. Sleep interruption is the process of purposefully awakening during your normal sleep period and falling asleep a short time later (10&amp;ndash;60 minutes).  This can be easily done by using a relatively quiet alarm clock to bring you to consciousness without fully waking you. If you find yourself resetting the clock in your sleep, it can be placed on the other side of the room, forcing you to get out of bed to turn it off. Other biorhythm-based options involve drinking lots of fluid (particularly water or tea, a known [[w:Diuretic|diuretic]]) prior to sleep, forcing one to get up to urinate. 

Sleep interruption is a natural part of the MILD technique (described below) which trains you to arise immediately after your dreams end.

=== Sleep Continuity ===
If you have trouble initially falling asleep, avoid drinking water for about an hour before going to bed. Otherwise, you may find yourself running to the bathroom, disrupting any attempts at lucidity.  Also, try to avoid caffeine and sugar before bed. However, depending on your sensitivity, caffeine may only stimulate your mind as opposed to your body. This extra grip on consciousness could be helpful in inducing lucid dreams. Exercising during the day is an excellent way of preparing your body for sleep. However, be sure to not exercise inside the three hours before bedtime, as your body will be stimulated for a short time afterwards. The morning or afternoon is the best time for this.

If you still have difficulty getting to sleep, try reading about lucid dreaming just before going to sleep. Your subconscious will likely absorb this information, increasing your chances of experiencing a lucid dream. If you ''do'' decide to read before going to sleep, keep a lamp next to your bed as physically getting up to turn off the lights may reawaken your body.

===Reality checks===
A reality check is a test you can perform to see if you're dreaming or awake. It might seem odd to test reality when you are sure that you're awake, but making a habit out of one or more of these reality checks will hugely increase your chances of having a lucid dream. If, say, you hold your nose and try to breathe in through it several times throughout the day then you're very likely to dream about doing it. And when you dream about performing a reality check, then of course the results should come out differently, in this case you'll find that you are somehow breathing in through your closed nostrils. You'll know that you're dreaming, and be able to take lucid control!

So here are some reality checks. You should be familiar with the entire list even if you only use a few.

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;
|-
!class=&quot;unsortable&quot; width=&quot;10%&quot;|
!class=&quot;unsortable&quot;|
!width=&quot;5%&quot;|Reliability
!width=&quot;5%&quot;|Speed
!width=&quot;5%&quot;|Discreetness
!width=&quot;5%&quot;|Overall
!width=&quot;5%&quot;|False positives
!width=&quot;5%&quot;|False negatives
|-
| '''[[Lucid Dreaming/Reality Checks/Breathing|Breathing]]'''
| Can you breathe with your fingers tightly sealing your nose and your mouth shut?
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|'''5'''
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|'''5'''
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|3
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|4.33
|style=&quot;text-aligh: center&quot;|-
|style=&quot;text-aligh: center&quot;|Very Rare
|-
| '''[[Lucid Dreaming/Reality Checks/Jumping|Jumping]]'''
| When you jump, do you float back down?
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|'''5'''
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|'''5'''
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|1
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|3.67
|style=&quot;text-aligh: center&quot;|-
|style=&quot;text-aligh: center&quot;|Rare
|-
| '''[[Lucid Dreaming/Reality Checks/Reading|Reading]]'''
| Do sentences change when you read them? Read, turn away and repeat it to yourself, and then turn back and read it again. Do this twice.
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|'''5'''
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|4
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|4
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|4.33
|style=&quot;text-aligh: center&quot;|-
|style=&quot;text-aligh: center&quot;|Rare
|-
| '''[[Lucid Dreaming/Reality Checks/Vision|Vision]]'''
| Do you have perfect vision? This only works for people who have at least slightly blurry vision in the waking world. Alternatively, if you have ''perfect'' vision in the waking world, you may have blurred vision in the dream world.
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|4
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|'''5'''
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|'''5'''
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|4.67
|style=&quot;text-aligh: center&quot;|-
|style=&quot;text-aligh: center&quot;|Common
|-
| '''[[Lucid Dreaming/Reality Checks/Hands|Hands]]'''
| Do your hands have a strange color, too many fingers (sometimes they disappear and reappear when you try to count them!) or other abnormalities? Can you push your finger through your other hand?
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|4
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|'''5'''
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|'''5'''
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|4.67
|style=&quot;text-aligh: center&quot;|-
|style=&quot;text-aligh: center&quot;|Occasional
|-
| '''[[Lucid Dreaming/Reality Checks/Time|Time]]'''
| Does your watch or clock tell a reasonable time? Are you even able to read the time off it? Sometimes clocks have the wrong number of hands or have strange symbols. Try reading the time twice, like the Reading check above. Note: Digital clocks often work better for this reality check.
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|4
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|'''5'''
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|4
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|4.33
|style=&quot;text-aligh: center&quot;|-
|style=&quot;text-aligh: center&quot;|Occasional
|-
| '''[[Lucid Dreaming/Reality Checks/Powers|Powers]]'''
| Are you able to fly (just visualize it), unlock doors, or use other magical powers? Try to change the shape of your body, or walk through a wall, window, or mirror.
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|4
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|'''5'''
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|3
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|4
|style=&quot;text-aligh: center&quot;|-
|style=&quot;text-aligh: center&quot;|Common
|-
| '''[[Lucid Dreaming/Reality Checks/Light switches|Light switches]]'''
| Does a light switch work?
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|4
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|3
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|1
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|2.67
|style=&quot;text-aligh: center&quot;|Occasional
|style=&quot;text-aligh: center&quot;|Occasional
|-
| '''[[Lucid Dreaming/Reality Checks/Mirrors|Mirrors]]'''
| Do you look normal in a mirror?
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|3
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|3
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|3
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|3
|style=&quot;text-aligh: center&quot;|-
|style=&quot;text-aligh: center&quot;|Occasional
|-
| '''[[Lucid Dreaming/Reality Checks/Nose|Nose]]'''
| Can you see your nose with one eye closed?
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|2
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|'''5'''
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|'''5'''
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|4
|style=&quot;text-aligh: center&quot;|-
|style=&quot;text-aligh: center&quot;|Rare
|-
| '''[[Lucid Dreaming/Reality Checks/Memory|Memory]]'''
| Are you able to remember how you got here, why you are here and what happened an hour ago?
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|2
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|3
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|'''5'''
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|3.33
|style=&quot;text-aligh: center&quot;|Rare
|style=&quot;text-aligh: center&quot;|Common
|-
| '''[[Lucid Dreaming/Reality Checks/Identity|Identity]]'''
| Do you have the same gender, age, job, relationships and responsibilities as usual?   
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|2
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|3
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|'''5'''
|style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;|3.33
|style=&quot;text-aligh: center&quot;|-
|style=&quot;text-aligh: center&quot;|Occasional
|}

Choose a few reality checks which you will do regularly. Take them seriously, do not assume you are awake (even when you know you are). If you practice performing these checks very thoroughly while awake, then you're more likely to perform them thoroughly while dreaming. You should '''always''' carry out more than one reality check. If you find that it is not a dream, look around you and think of what would be different if it were a dream. If you do this it will make it more likely that you will do a reality check in a dream.

Apart from doing reality checks throughout the day, you also need to do a reality check immediately after you wake up. This helps you become lucid in false awakenings, when you dream that you have woken up but in fact are still dozing. Using a digital alarm clock or mobile phone display to do a Reading check, every single time you wake up, is a quick and reliable way to catch false awakenings.

If you have trouble bringing reality checks into your dreams then before going to bed imagine yourself in a dream, noticing odd details and doing a reality check. Then do a reality check in real life. If you do this a few times before bed you will find that you will do it more often in dreams.

If you are in a situation where you cannot do a reality check, such as at a public speaking, try to do one as soon as possible. You can do some reality checks very discreetly, such as looking at some text on a sign. If you start to say “well, I can't do a reality check now” you should not be surprised when you make this mistake in a dream!

'''Which reality checks are best?'''

When selecting reality checks, the most important properties of a reality check are ''reliability'', ''speed'', and ''discreetness''.

* The '''reliability''' of each reality check is how likely you are to recognize the dream-sign's results as showing that you are dreaming '''once you do them in a dream'''. It changes for each person but some reality checks are overall more accurate than others. The figures in the table above are ''rough only'' and differ for each person.
* It is important for a reality check to be '''fast'''. It wastes dream time if you have to search around for a book or (perhaps worse) a mirror. Plus, it could also give your subconsciousness more time to produce real-life results, especially if you believe that the check will give real-life results.
* Third, a reality check should be '''discreet'''; that is, it should not draw too much attention to you when you do it in the waking world. Suddenly jumping in the air or trying to walk through a wall as a reality check could cause much embarrassment!
* Fourth, a reality check should not have &quot;false positives&quot;. These occur when the reality check shows you are dreaming in real life. When you get a dream result, do another reality check to be sure!
* A final important note is whether or not a reality check should have &quot;false negatives&quot;. These occur when a reality check shows you are in real life when you are actually dreaming. If you think you may be dreaming, keep doing tests until you prove yourself right!
 
On the table above, these are scored '''out of 5'''.

'''I have trouble remembering to do reality checks throughout the day. What reminders can I use?'''

You are lucky to have an interesting day and forget about lucid dreaming! You can tag your mind to remember dreaming when you think of certain things, like your friend or your homework. It isn't advisable to explicitly write “reality check” or “lucid” on your hand, as this could create an over dependence on this reminder, which may not exist in a dream. However, you might want to just draw a dot or small circle on your hand. This should be enough to remind you to do a reality check.

Try putting a little label on your clock, mobile phone, or watch, reminding yourself to do a reality check. (Some weird colors will make it more noticeable and it will take longer for you to get used to it and ignore it.) If you check these regularly during the course of your waking day, you will be doing lots of reality checks.

A simple coffee mug with a reminder such as &quot;Are you dreaming?&quot; printed on it or random alarms can also serve well, but try not to become too dependent on them. You can find examples of these at [http://bytered.com/gallery-purchase.html Byte Red] and [http://ld4all.com/ LD4All]. 

Another technique is to write down three things you do regularly in a day. Examples include hearing your name, going through a doorway, turning on a TV, beginning to read a book, or seeing a stranger. In the morning, choose three such events and intend to do a reality check whenever they happen in the following day.

'''I did a reality check in a dream but it said that I was not dreaming. What went wrong?'''

Some reality checks work perfectly for some people and awfully for others. These are mostly the light switches one and the hands one. If you find that the light switch works or that your hands are perfectly normal, you need to change to a different technique.

'''I did a reality check in a dream but I did not quite realize I was dreaming. What went wrong?'''

An example of this is looking into a mirror and seeing some huge boils or a gray mist on your reflection and not realizing that you are dreaming. This is rare if you actually intended to look into the mirror as a reality check. You need to be more careful when doing your reality checks in real life or pick more reliable reality checks which show more obviously that you are dreaming. Also try to pick reality checks that are easy to do. For example, don't rely the Time Reality Check if you never wear a watch, and don't pick the Mirror Reality Check if you rarely look in the mirror during the day or you know that you won't find a mirror in your dream.

Another good remedy for this problem (and a good practice in general) is to perform two or three reality checks at a time. The Time Reality Check, for example, can be easily combined with attempting to push one hand through another. Or, for those with glasses, testing your ability to read text fits naturally with checking for &quot;perfect eyesight w/o glasses&quot;.

&lt;div width=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: solid 1px #fea; padding: 2px 5px 2px 5px;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;
Threads about reality checks on [http://ld4all.com ld4all.com]: The BIG Reality Check topic [http://web.archive.org/web/20060507033358/http://www.ld4all.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=540 I] [http://ld4all.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=2929 II] |
[http://ld4all.com/archive0205/viewtopic.php?t=5217 RCs that prove you are awake while dreaming] | 
[http://ld4all.com/archive0205/viewtopic.php?t=5627 New RC?] |  [http://web.archive.org/web/20051130083341/http://ld4all.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=5636 Today's Lucid Tip: Dream Characters Suck] | 
[http://web.archive.org/web/20051128133216/http://ld4all.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=5708 The RC List!] | 
[http://web.archive.org/web/20051123120245/http://ld4all.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=5778 Failed Reality Checks] | [http://web.archive.org/web/20051130083317/http://ld4all.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=5846 Funny dream cue / RC experience] | [http://web.archive.org/web/20051130084618/http://ld4all.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=5890 The Automatization Technique] | 
[http://web.archive.org/web/20051130091058/http://ld4all.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=5903 Reality Check Failure] | [http://web.archive.org/web/20051123023652/http://ld4all.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=6002 Need a better reality check for Christ's sake!!!!!!] | [http://web.archive.org/web/20051123115829/http://ld4all.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=6256 WHY?!?!?! Failed Reality Check!]&lt;br/&gt;
Threads about reality checks at [http://lucidity.com The Lucidity Institute]: Reality Testing [http://www.novadreamer.com/discus/messages/41/465.html September 2000] [http://www.novadreamer.com/discus/messages/41/511.html June 2001] [http://www.novadreamer.com/discus/messages/41/1587.html August 2001] [http://www.novadreamer.com/discus/messages/41/2014.html December 2001] [http://www.novadreamer.com/discus/messages/41/52.html Latest]
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: right; font-size: small&quot;&gt;[[#top|top]]&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br&gt;

==Techniques==
When you read through these techniques, remember that different techniques work for different people. There is no “best technique” and most techniques could be used to have 2&amp;ndash;5 lucid dreams every night! You could have several lucid dreams in a night, but you will not know it unless you remember them!

However, you will probably want some advice as to which technique you should try first. Consider whether you want to use a method which starts from a dream or a method which starts from being awake.&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt; If you master a technique which starts from being awake, you will eventually be able to have lucid dreams on demand when you sleep. For other techniques, you have to rely on your luck to give you lucid dreams after you have done your technique. Here are some advantages and disadvantages for specific techniques:

(Remember, it is ''essential'' to be able to recall at least one dream per night before attempting these techniques)

{| cellpadding=&quot;4&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot;
!width=&quot;10%&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #efe; border: 1px solid #bfb; text-align: center;&quot;|Technique
!width=&quot;20%&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #efe; border: 1px solid #bfb; text-align: center;&quot;|Summary
!width=&quot;20%&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #efe; border: 1px solid #bfb; text-align: center;&quot;|Advantages
!width=&quot;20%&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #efe; border: 1px solid #bfb; text-align: center;&quot;|Disadvantages
!width=&quot;20%&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #efe; border: 1px solid #bfb; text-align: center;&quot;|Best for...
!width=&quot;5%&quot;  style=&quot;background-color: #efe; border: 1px solid #bfb; text-align: center;&quot;|Rating
|-
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea; text-align: center;&quot;|
[[Lucid Dreaming/Induction Techniques#WBTB|WBTB]]&lt;br/&gt;(Wake-Back-To-Bed)
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
Wake after some sleep and then return to bed.
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
* Simple
* Can be very reliable, especially when used with other techniques
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
* Disrupts sleep cycle
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
People who want to strengthen other techniques, or who wake up in the middle of the night anyway.
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
Green
|-
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea; text-align: center;&quot;|
[[Lucid Dreaming/Induction Techniques#Auto-suggestion|Auto-suggestion]]
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
Let yourself genuinely believe that you'll become lucid&amp;mdash;without ''intending'' to become lucid&amp;mdash;so that you really will.
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
* Simple
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
* Less effective than some other techniques (such as MILD)
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
People who are susceptible to [[Hypnosis|hypnosis]] or practice meditation.
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
Green
|-
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea; text-align: center;&quot;|
[[Lucid Dreaming/Induction Techniques#MILD|MILD]]&lt;br/&gt;(Mnemonic Induction of Lucid Dreams)
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
Fall asleep while focused on your intention to ''remember'' that you are dreaming.
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
* Simple
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
* Can be boring
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
People with a good prospective memory (remembrance of future intentions).
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
Green
|-
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea; text-align: center;&quot;|
[[Lucid Dreaming/Induction Techniques#WILD|WILD]]&lt;br/&gt;(Wake-Initiation of Lucid Dreams)
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
Keep your consciousness while falling asleep and go straight into a dream.
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
* Lets you truly induce lucid dreams at will
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
* Can cause frightening experiences
* Can take long to master
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
People who want to reliably have lucid dreams.
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
Green
|-
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea; text-align: center;&quot;|
[[Lucid Dreaming/Induction Techniques#VILD|VILD]]&lt;br/&gt;(Visual Induction of Lucid Dreams)
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
By repetitive visualisation, incubate a dream in which you do a reality check.
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
* Also lets you induce lucid dreams at will
* Works ''extremely'' well for some people...
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
* ...but not very well for others
* Visualizing can keep you awake
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
People who have good visualization skills.
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
Green/ yellow
|-
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea; text-align: center;&quot;|
[[Lucid Dreaming/Induction Techniques#CAT|CAT]]&lt;br/&gt;(Cycle Adjustment Technique)
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
Adjust your sleep cycle to encourage awareness during the latter part of your sleep.
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
* Requires relatively little effort other than adjusting your sleep cycle
* Is very effective
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
* Requires you to wake up early on some days
* You are only likely to get a lucid dream on every other day (though this could easily be more frequently than with other techniques)
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
People who have a very regular sleep cycle.
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: 1px solid #fea;&quot;|
Green/ yellow
|}

&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt; The usual acronyms in forums for this are DILD (Dream-Initiated Lucid Dream) and WILD (Wake-Initiated Lucid Dream). All the techniques that induce WILDs are described under [[Lucid Dreaming/Induction Techniques#WILD|WILD]] on this page.&lt;/small&gt;

===WBTB===
{| width=&quot;100%&quot;
|style=&quot;background-color: #efffef; border: 1px solid #bafaba;&quot;|Rated green. This technique has been successful in scientific research and/or is part of a commercial book about lucid dreaming.
|}

WBTB stands for “Wake-Back-To-Bed”.

Wake yourself up after 4 to 6 hours of sleep, get out of bed and stay up for anywhere between a few minutes to an hour before going back to bed. It is preferable that you do something related to lucid dreaming during this time (such as reading about lucid dreaming), but it is not required. This is best combined with other techniques; many people have amazing results with a MILD/WBTB combination. The WBTB technique significantly increases your chances of a lucid dream, and using MILD (see below) in conjunction increases your success rate if you are planning to sleep an hour or more after your WBTB session. However, you might need plenty of sleep time and therefore you may only be able to use it on weekends.

If you are sleeping too deeply to become lucid, then you can modify this technique. Try returning to sleep somewhere different than where you usually sleep, e.g. on a couch, a different bed, or even on the floor. If you are unable to do this, try changing the way you sleep, e.g. try sleeping with a lighter blanket or reversing the orientation of your body while in the bed (that is, swapping head and feet). Do this in order to teach your body that these different surroundings mean you want to have a more conscious sleep rather than a deeper sleep. In the beginning, different surroundings will also make you more alert, which can heighten your level of consciousness during sleep.

'''I am sometimes awake for very short times, but cannot pull myself together enough to get up and out of bed. What can I do?'''

Put a bright piece of paper on the wall or ceiling so that you will see it when you wake up. Other stimuli could be a hot water bottle, a light turned on under your bed, or an alarm clock. A good technique is to place an alarm clock out of arm's reach so that you are compelled to physically get up from bed and turn it off. If this is still insufficient to restore consciousness, try making a note of your intentions to remain awake and place the note on your alarm clock. After you get a lucid dream with this method, you'll find it easier and easier to get out of bed because you'll have more motivation.

&lt;div width=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: solid 1px #fea; padding: 2px 5px 2px 5px;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;
Threads about the WBTB technique at [http://ld4all.com ld4all.com]: [http://web.archive.org/web/20060502063146/http://ld4all.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=4361 The BIG WBTB topic]
&lt;/div&gt;

===Auto-suggestion===
{| width=&quot;100%&quot;
|style=&quot;background-color: #efffef; border: 1px solid #bafaba;&quot;|Rated green. This technique has been successful in scientific research and/or is part of a commercial book about lucid dreaming.
|}

This technique describes how to use [[w:Autosuggestion|auto-suggestion]] to have lucid dreams. It can be especially effective for people who are highly susceptible to [[Hypnosis|hypnosis]] or understand meditation, but for most people, MILD will probably be more effective.

As you are falling asleep, suggest to yourself that you will have a lucid dream either that night or in the near future. You can use a mantra (such as “I will recognize that I'm dreaming”) if you want, but make sure you don't try too hard to get a lucid dream. Instead of putting intentional effort into the suggestion, try to genuinely expect to have a lucid dream. Let yourself think expectantly about the lucid dream you are about to have, but be patient if you don't get one right away.

You may also use auto-suggestion to improve dream recall. Just use the technique as described above, but instead of suggesting that you'll have a lucid dream, suggest that you'll remember your dreams when you wake up. You could also use a mantra with this, such as “When I wake up, I will remember what I dreamt”. Just be careful not to put too much intentional effort into the mantra &amp;mdash; try to genuinely expect to remember your dreams instead.

===MILD===
{| width=&quot;100%&quot;
|style=&quot;background-color: #efffef; border: 1px solid #bafaba&quot;|Rated green. This technique has been detailed in ''Exploring the World of Lucid Dreaming'' by Stephen LaBerge.
|}

MILD stands for “Mnemonic Induction of Lucid Dreams&quot;, or sometimes, “Mnemonically Induced Lucid Dream&quot;. The MILD technique was developed by Stephen LaBerge, and is described fully in his book ''Exploring the World of Lucid Dreaming''.

With the MILD technique, as you are falling asleep, you concentrate on your intention to ''remember'' to recognize that you are dreaming. Repeat a short mantra in your head, such as “Next time I'm dreaming, I will remember I'm dreaming”. Think about what this means (i.e., that you want to remember that you are dreaming&amp;mdash;in the same way you might go to a grocery store and suddenly remember that you need bread), and imagine that you are back in a dream you've had recently, but this time you recognize that you are dreaming. For example, if you recently dreamed of flying, imagine realizing that it is a dream because you are flying. Keep repeating and visualizing the mantra until you are sure that your intention is set in your mind or you fall asleep. If you stop repeating and visualizing the mantra, then still try to make sure the last thing in your mind before falling asleep is your intention to remember to recognize that you are dreaming.

In general, the MILD technique can be practiced when you first go to bed at night, or after you have awakened from a dream during the night. If you practice the MILD technique after you have awakened from a dream, you should first run through the dream to ensure that you remember it. Some people find it helpful to jot down a few notes about their dream in their dream journal.

Once you have committed the dream to memory, go back to sleep and follow the steps above. But this time, visualize the dream you just had. Move through the dream in your mind until you encounter a dream-sign you originally missed.  Now, instead of missing the dream-sign, imagine yourself recognizing it and becoming “lucid”.

Repeat this until you have fallen asleep. You ''will'' re-enter the dream, and you ''will'' recognize the dream-sign and finally, become lucid.

&lt;div width=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: solid 1px #fea; padding: 2px 5px 2px 5px;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;
Threads about the MILD technique at [http://ld4all.com ld4all.com]: The BIG MILD topic [http://www.ld4all.com/archive0205/viewtopic.php?t=623 I] [http://ld4all.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=4870 II] | [http://www.ld4all.com/archive0205/viewtopic.php?topic=5326 MILD at Midnight?] | [http://ld4all.com/archive0205/viewtopic.php?t=5485 MILD Mantras]&lt;br /&gt;
archive.org threads about the MILD technique from www.dreamviews.com (offline): [http://web.archive.org/web/20080302015405/http://www.dreamviews.com/community/showthread.php?t=1885 Mnemonic Induction of Lucid Dreams (MILD)] | [http://web.archive.org/web/20080302223741/http://www.dreamviews.com/community/showthread.php?t=5679 Getting more help with MILD from your subconscious]
&lt;/div&gt;

===WILD===
{| width=&quot;100%&quot;
|style=&quot;background-color: #efffef; border: 1px solid #bafaba;&quot;|Rated green. This technique has been successful in scientific research and/or is part of a commercial book about lucid dreaming.
|}

WILD stands for “Wake-Initiated Lucid Dream”, or “Wake-Initiation of Lucid Dreams” to refer to any technique that involves falling asleep consciously. These techniques are similar to self-hypnosis. Some people believe that WILDs are not actual dreams, but are instead [[w:astral projection|astral projection]]. Various detailed resources are available under that moniker. 

For most people, they are far easier to induce in the early morning after waking up or in afternoon naps, as the sleep cycle will continue with a REM period. Once you are experienced with inducing WILDs, you can try to induce them at other times.

For WILDs to occur, it is best for your body to be completely relaxed. When you go back to bed, lie down comfortably. Now tense and relax your body, starting from your shoulders and working downwards, then back up to the face. This (or similar relaxation, meditation, or trance techniques) should make your body feel slightly heavy and relaxed. 

There are many different ways to induce WILDs, but they all involve simultaneously attempting to keep the mind aware while attempting to have the body fall asleep. A few techniques are detailed below.

If you pay attention to your physical body while using these techniques, then you will likely enter sleep paralysis (which usually happens after you are already asleep) without losing conscious awareness of your body. You will get a tingling and buzzing sensation (this might be unpleasant). These sensations might be so strong that you feel that you will die (e.g., you might feel a choking sensation), but don't worry, this is perfectly safe! In fact, this process happens to you every time you sleep, you are just not conscious during it. Sometimes you can simply wait until you fall asleep straight into a lucid dream. However, if you do not fall asleep, and you become completely paralyzed (with the exception of your eyes), do not try to move. Imagine your dream hand (or spirit hand if you prefer) going up and leaving your physical hand behind. Now you should have two separate bodies, a dream one and a real one. Control your dream body only &amp;mdash; if you control your real one, you will wake up. Now you can try to roll out of bed into your dream world (alternatively, you can get up and walk through a mirror, or sink into your bed). There is a possibility that after waking up from a dream that you initiated using this technique, you may still be paralyzed. If this phenomenon occurs, it may be accompanied by hallucinations. For example, you may wake up from a lucid dream that you started using one of the WILD techniques, and you will still be paralyzed, this is a state of [[w:Sleep paralysis|Sleep paralysis]].

If you have the experience then you have been given an example of what your mind can do, even without your direction. Before the phenomena was understood, as Sleep paralysis also occurs outside of Lucid Dream experiments it had been given a general negative outlook, while the experience is truly unique (partial awareness, unable to move, and multi-sense hallucinations) it is often linked to cultural fears, nightmares and other night terrors, Americans call it Old Hag Japanese people call it kanashibari, Korean people call it kawi nullida (being pressed by a pair of scissors), Turkish people call it ''karabasan'' and in old French it was called ''Cauquemare'', which was later transformed into the term ''cauchemar''. In any case as soon as you rationalize what is happening you should lose any fear by the temporary loss of muscular control and contextualize any hallucination.

====Chakra Technique====

{| width=&quot;100%&quot;
|style=&quot;background-color: #fffaef; border: 1px solid #fada9a&quot;|Rated green/yellow. There have been anecdotes from a few people of this working on the [http://web.archive.org/web/20090406111627/http://www.dreamviews.com/community/showthread.php?t=71387 DreamViews forums].
|}

Using Chakra (&quot;third eye&quot;) meditation is one way to achieve WILDs. Basically, one has to focus solely on his third eye and breathing to achieve a lucid dream. This is a technique over 5000 years old, taught to Parvati by Shiva.&lt;ref name=&quot;shiva&quot;&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20080104094658/www.totallyok.com/secret/007m.htm 112 Meditations from Shiva to Parvati]. ''Internet Archive.'' Accessed on 2009-09-18.&lt;/ref&gt; He is quoted as saying:&lt;blockquote&gt;With intangible breath in center of forehead, as this reaches heart at the moment of sleep, have direction over dreams and over death itself.&lt;ref name=&quot;shiva&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

====Eyelid Patterns====
{| width=100%
|style=&quot;background-color: #faffef; border: 1px solid #dafa9a;&quot;|Rated yellow. There have been some anecdotes from at least one person of this technique working, although there is no scientific research proving it.
|}

This has been found to be very effective in many cases. However, it may lead to strange after effects, such as up to 15 dreams in one night, but otherwise, nothing harmful. This technique is as follows: When you go to sleep, ensure the room is completely dark. Then, with eyes closed, try to focus on the little dots that should appear to be moving on your eyelids. You will find that you can change their color at will. Continue focusing on these dots; make them dance around and form patterns and change colors, and eventually you should enter a Lucid Dream. This may take a little practice, but is usually very effective for summoning Lucid Dreams at will. Works better in conjunction with WBTB and other techniques mentioned above, but is still extraordinarily effective on its own.

====Hypnagogic Imagery====
{| width=&quot;100%&quot;
|style=&quot;background-color: #efffef; border: 1px solid #bafaba;&quot;|Rated green. This technique has been successful with a large amount of people, in scientific research, and/or is part of a commercial book about lucid dreaming.
|}
Stimulate your thinking patterns by constantly switching your attention. After doing this long enough, the images and sounds should begin to take a momentum on their own (this is called hypnagogic imagery), and may they get very strange and illogical. You should enter a dream at this point and quickly become lucid. Otherwise, you will eventually realize you have entered sleep paralysis consciously (see above).    
Because hypnagogic sleep paralysis involves full consciousness, dreaming can sometimes be frighteningly real. There is often a feeling of being flipped upside down, spun, or being tugged upon by an outside force. Hypnagogic hallucinations may also include strange auditory hallucinations, dark beings and flying. 
It is possible to observe waking reality while in a hypnagogic state, but this is limited to the sensations of your physical body.  Most hypnagogic sleep paralysis states occur when sleeping face up.  There is evidence that the tendency toward experiencing Hypnagogic sleep paralysis may be hereditary.

====Counting====
{| width=&quot;100%&quot;
|style=&quot;background-color: #efffef; border: 1px solid #bafaba;&quot;|Rated green. This technique has been successful with a large amount of people, in scientific research, and/or is part of a commercial book about lucid dreaming.
|}

Another technique is to count up to 100 in your head, optionally adding (for example) an “I'm dreaming” between each number. Alternatively, you can imagine stepping down stairs and reading each floor number, from 100 to 0. Try to make this image as vivid as possible &amp;mdash; include not only what you see, but also what you hear, feel (touch the banister), and smell. At some point this image should continue into a dream or you will begin to get sleep paralysis as described above. It is easy to lose count, especially with counting up to 100 with an 'I'm dreaming' with each number. But stay focused: you are not going to sleep; your body is, and you must concentrate fully.

====Sound Technique====
{| width=100%
|style=&quot;background-color: #faffef; border: 1px solid #dafa9a;&quot;|Rated yellow. There have been some anecdotes from at least one person of this technique working, although there is no scientific research proving it. [Important advice regarding this, may be unsafe, just do one of the other methods instead. See discussion page under [[Lucid Dreaming/Induction Techniques|Facts to know about Tinnitus]]]
|}

This method is for people, who can hear the &quot;tinnitus&quot;. The idea is pretty much the same as the other WILD methods, which is to remain conscious while entering the dream state. In order to use this method, you must sleep in a perfectly quiet place. You need to hear the inner buzzing sound inside your ears. Lay your body down and relax as much as possible while trying to hear the sound. If you are too tired, you will fall asleep too fast and it will be difficult to remain conscious - it this case you should combine it with WBTB. By time you realize that the buzzing sound will increase in intensity. This might frighten newcomers, but be assured - nothing bad is going to happen. No, you will not be deaf when you wake up, it’s perfectly safe! *It is just an effect caused by your brain is trying to change mode, from listening to the ambient sound, to listening to the sound of dreamland, which is not real sound but just electrical charge inputed to the part of the brain to create a sensation of hearing. By that time, you will enter the hypnagogic state. All you need to do is concentrate, do not be afraid or think of anything, just be still, and in time your dream body will float, separating from your physical body, and there you go, you arrive in the dreamworld.

Note: These sounds can be heard when you concentrate, even throughout the day - when you pay attention to them, but they shouldn't be heard much aloud if you are not in silence and concentrating on it - *as author said. The formula to hear it is quite simple:
come into complete silence close your eyes and listen: is there only absolute silence or is there - something else? some...? 
do not create some sound just concentrate - :-) The best thing on this tech is - you can do it when you want.

====Facts to know about Tinnitus====

Tinnitus is a condition termed for a hissing and whistling sound that one hears in his/her ears. It's a medical term for ringing in the ears. Several reasons lead to this irritating condition and the most common cause is the damage to the nerves located inside the ear. However, there are some other factors as well such as earwax buildup, exposure to loud noises, ear infections and certain medications. Remember, the first step in finding a natural care is to determine the actual cause of tinnitus.
Some Facts about Tinnitus.

The foremost thing to remember is that ringing in the ears is a symptom and not a disease. It's normal to a certain extent, however, the condition could be an indicator of a more serious condition. It's often related with hearing loss that is caused by aging. It can be a major nuisance when the ringing becomes very loud. The condition cannot be cured permanently but certainly can be eased.

'''Some Causes of Tinnitus'''

As mentioned above, ringing in the ear has some related causes and the most common out of them are damage of the cochlea due to aging (known as presbycusis), infection of the ear, exposure to loud noises and eardrum rupture. Amazingly, it has also been observed that excess ear wax buildup can also lead to this condition. Also, then there's the overuse of aspirin. Though, it's a very efficient pain reliever, its ototoxic properties (resulting into the damage to the ear) can result in tinnitus and worsen the condition in those that already have this ailment. 

Tinnitus can also be developed by the usage of antibiotics, particularly amino glycoside antibiotics (a powerful form of infection fighting drug) and quinine. Also, many studies have proven the relationship between tinnitus and stress. When the brain is under stress, it has a tendency to read ordinary as well as daily sounds as fearful. After this, the tinnitus develops or becomes worse. Thus, it's very important and critical to manage stress. And if that's not enough, there are other causes for tinnitus that are not that common but are 
quite serious: Some of them are:
* A jaw misalignment disorder known as Temporo-Mandibular Joint (TMJ) Syndrome
* Meniere's disorder which is a disorder with recurring episodes of vertigo
* Head and neck injuries (resulting in tinnitus in one ear)
* A benign tumor known as acoustic neuroma which develops on the cranial nerve that runs from the brain to the inner ear 

'''Treating Tinnitus'''

Putting in some hours with a therapist can really be beneficial and in several situations it's necessary to mental success even after the condition is alleviated. It's not easy to deal with anxiety and depression and knowing how to ignore the problem appropriately rather than indulging in it can be the best solution. It's also suggested to see a psychiatrist or psychologist who are experts with the patient suffering from the condition. This can be one of the [http://tinnituscureone.com/ cures for tinnitus relief] and getting control over your mind can build up tolerance towards this condition which can also benefit you in dealing with other problems as well.

Masking the noise in your head can also provide you with a solution when you're trying to sleep or get rid of heavy waves of noise being produced. As tinnitus can appear loud in a silent room, leaving it on radio static can let you proper sleep. Remember, alleviating your tinnitus is only the cure for ringing in the ear as the condition can only be minimized and not completely cured.

====Slight Physical Discomfort====
{| width=100%
|style=&quot;background-color: #faffef; border: 1px solid #dafa9a;&quot;|Rated yellow. There have been some anecdotes from at least one person of this technique working, although there is no scientific research proving it.
|}

For the purpose of helping to retain your conscious awareness, slight physical discomfort is useful while performing any WILD technique. This prevents you from just drifting off to sleep. If you are lying down on your bed to do WILD and you are totally comfortable then your chances of going to sleep instead of remaining conscious are very high. The WILD technique relies on a form of deep trance induction, and many people who induce trances for other reasons rely on slight physical discomfort — for example the lotus position, or sitting in a hard-backed chair. Depending on your own preferences and your requirements of discomfort for success, you could choose from the following methods, arranged in ascending order of discomfort:
# Stacking pillows so that you can sit up in bed — the discomfort is caused by not being in a normal sleeping position.
# Lying down on a hard floor.
# Lifting your forearm vertically upwards, with the rest of your arm resting on the bed.
# Sitting in a hard chair.

&lt;div width=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: solid 1px #fea; padding: 2px 5px 2px 5px;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;
Threads about the WILD technique at [http://ld4all.com ld4all.com]: The BIG WILD topic [http://www.ld4all.com/archive0205/viewtopic.php?t=311 I] [http://ld4all.com/archive0205/viewtopic.php?t=665 II] [http://ld4all.com/archive0205/viewtopic.php?t=1075 III] [http://ld4all.com/archive0205/viewtopic.php?t=1582 IV] [http://ld4all.com/archive0205/viewtopic.php?t=2372 V] [http://ld4all.com/archive0205/viewtopic.php?t=2975 VI] [http://ld4all.com/archive0205/viewtopic.php?t=3645 VII] [http://ld4all.com/archive0205/viewtopic.php?t=4109 VIII] [http://ld4all.com/archive0205/viewtopic.php?t=4458 IX] [http://ld4all.com/archive0205/viewtopic.php?t=5254 X] [http://ld4all.com/archive0205/viewtopic.php?t=6254 XI] [http://ld4all.com/archive0205/viewtopic.php?t=7727 XII] [http://www.ld4all.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=11180 XIII] [http://www.ld4all.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=13858 XIV]|   [http://ld4all.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=5341 Strange colored dots?!? ULTIMATE WILD method]  |  
Threads about the WILD technique at [http://dreamviews.com dreamviews.com]: [http://www.dreamviews.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=2048 Wake-Initiated Lucid Dream (WILD)] | [http://www.dreamviews.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=12621 Five Stages of WILD] | [http://www.dreamviews.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=9026 WILD induction. help, only 3 hours til sleep time] | [http://www.dreamviews.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=8645 Lotus-Flame WILD technique]
&lt;/div&gt;

===Incubating Dreams===
{| width=100%
|style=&quot;background-color: #efffef; border: 1px solid #bafaba&quot;|Rated green. This technique has been successful in scientific research and/or is part of a commercial book about dreaming.
|}

To incubate a dream about a specific topic, you should first think of a phrase that summarizes that topic (e.g., “I want to go to Atlantis.”). It may help to write the phrase down. If there is something you want to do in the dream, think of a phrase to summarize that too (e.g., “I want to watch Atlantis sink into the ocean.”). If you want to become lucid in the dream, then you should probably write something like “When I dream of [the topic], I will remember that I'm dreaming.” beneath your topic phrase. Immediately go to sleep and focus on your topic phrase. Visualize yourself dreaming about the topic and (if you want to become lucid) realizing that you are dreaming. If there is something specific you want to do in the dream, visualize yourself doing it once you become lucid (not very likely to work if you don't become lucid in the dream). Think about your phrase and topic (and intention to become lucid) as you fall asleep. Make sure that the last thing in your mind before falling asleep is your intention to (lucidly) dream about the topic you want to dream about. You might want to wake yourself up when the dream starts to fade so that you remember more of the dream; you can do this by ignoring your perception of the dream environment &amp;mdash; the opposite of dream stabilization techniques (just make sure you do a reality check when you wake up to make sure you are really awake).

====Chaining Dreams====
{| width=100%
|style=&quot;background-color: #efffef; border: 1px solid #bafaba&quot;|Rated green. This technique has been successful in scientific research and/or is part of a commercial book about dreaming.
|}

Dream-chaining or “chaining dreams” is a method to re-enter your dream ''after you've woken up''. It can work for lucid and non-lucid dreams, but you will probably want to enter your dream lucidly.

Once you wake up from a dream (if you don't think you were dreaming before you woke up, it may not work well) you should stay still and keep your eyes closed. Small movements are okay, but the less movement, sensory stimulation, and less time awake, the better. Ideally, it should feel less like you've woken up, and more like you've taken a 30 second break from dreaming. Once you are prepared to go back to sleep, close your eyes and either visualize yourself back in your dream, or use the “spinning technique” given in the next chapter to imagine yourself spinning back “into” your dream. Spinning is a little faster than visualization. Be sure to maintain the fact that you are dreaming (unless you don't want to be lucid), or you may lose your lucidity while falling asleep. Once in the dream, stimulate your senses as early as possible (see the next chapter).

====VILD====
{| width=&quot;100%&quot;
|style=&quot;background-color: #fffaef; border: 1px solid #fada9a&quot;|Rated green/yellow. There have been anecdotes from several people of this working on the [http://ld4all.com ld4all.com] forums.
|}

VILD stands for “Visual Induction of Lucid Dreams”, or sometimes, “Visually Incubated Lucid Dream”. This technique has been perfected by Peter Harrison, known as Pedro on the [http://ld4all.com/forum/ forums at ld4all.com]. You may wish to read [http://ld4all.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=4789 the main thread about the technique]. The version described here has been adapted slightly.

First, make sure you are relaxed. You can use the relaxing technique mentioned in the description of the WILD technique. You can also imagine your brain emptying out and becoming sleepier. If you have a hard time falling asleep quickly, it should help to read a book (preferably about lucid dreaming) for a while before you go to sleep, until you feel very sleepy.

Now, you need to visualize a dream which you had prepared earlier. Here is an example of a prepared dream:
: I am in a red room with one door. A friend next to me asks me to show them what a reality check is. I do my reality checks (which show that I am dreaming), tell them that I am dreaming, and head towards the door.
Make sure you know exactly what the dream would be like, such as which friend, the exact words they say, and which reality checks you do. Reality checks that require no props, such as books or clocks, are recommended. Visualize this dream slowly three times, to make sure that you know every detail. Then, start going full-on and visualize the dream over and over. You should visualize the dream as though you are looking through your own eyes, not from a third-person perspective. If you find your thoughts drifting, ignore them and continue to visualize the dream continuously. You will need patience for this &amp;mdash; don't just give up if you think it won't work.

When you actually dream this, you will not notice the difference &amp;mdash; until you do your reality checks! Continue with the dream as you incubated it (e.g., remember to thank your friend!) before continuing through the door.

'''I tried to visualize the dream until I fell asleep, but I just stayed awake. What went wrong?'''

If visualizing keeps you awake, the VILD technique is not the technique for you! You should use a different technique.

&lt;div width=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: solid 1px #fea; padding: 2px 5px 2px 5px;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;
Threads about VILD at [http://ld4all.com ld4all.com]: I can LD at will!!!! [http://ld4all.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=4774 I] [http://ld4all.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=4844 II] [http://ld4all.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=5194 III] | [http://ld4all.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=4789 VILD...Visually Incubated Lucid Dream]&lt;br/&gt;
Topics about VILD at [http://lucidity.com The Lucidity Institute]: [http://www.novadreamer.com/discus/messages/41/2021.html The VILD Technique]&lt;br/&gt;
There is an [[Lucid Dreaming/Appendices/VILD|appendix on VILD]].
&lt;/div&gt;

====LILD====
{| width=&quot;100%&quot;
|style=&quot;background-color: #fffaef; border: 1px solid #fada9a&quot;|Rated yellow. There have been some anecdotes from at least one person of this technique working, although there is no scientific research proving it.
|}

LILD stands for “Lucid Induction of Lucid Dreams”, or sometimes, “Lucidly Induced Lucid Dream”.

To use this technique, you need to have a lucid dream in the first place, but it can help you to get more later. The idea is to do something in your dream that will help you to become lucid the next time you are dreaming. For example, you could ask a dream character for help &amp;mdash; ask them to meet you the next night and tell you that you are dreaming. If it works out the way it should, then the next time you are dreaming, the dream character will walk up to you and tell you that you are dreaming, and so you'll (hopefully) become lucid. There are many variations on this technique; you could set up signs in your dreamworld that remind you to do a reality check or eat lucid pills instead! This technique is not likely to be very effective, but it ''can'' work; it relies on the chance that you'll subconsciously induce the reminder (i.e., the dream character or sign or whatever you used) during some later dream, and become lucid because of it.

Note that LILD is best used in conjunction with dream-signs and auto-suggested non-lucid dreams.  The basic idea as explained above is to have something in your dream that triggers the transition from normal dream state to lucid dreaming.  To simply tell a character to tell you that you are dreaming the next time you fall asleep is usually not enough.  There is no guarantee that you will dream about that character and there is no guarantee that your subconscious will believe the character enough to make you snap into lucidity (make you realize that you are in fact dreaming).  

Now as this technique suggests, you must have some previous alternate means of having a lucid dream.  Whatever technique you employ to get into this initial lucid dream state is not really important, but you should try to remember to use this technique (LILD) once you do get into a lucid dream state.  Thinking of this before falling asleep (MILD) sometimes helps and usually takes many lucid dreams before finally remembering.  Once you are in a lucid dream, make up a dream-sign.  It can be anything.  It can be an object.  It can be food or a drink (that doesn't taste like anything).  It is usually best to pick something that isn't quite right.  Something that on the surface would appear normal in the real world, but that upon closer inspection is not quite right.  Food or drinks are good as they can have no taste or not be refreshing in a dream.  But try and pick something that you dream about a lot so that there is a better chance of you dreaming about this dream-sign later on.  Now pick something else that only appears or happens in your lucid dream.  It can be anything.  If there is nothing in your current lucid dream, create something really strange.  Something that could never be confused with the real world.  Now mentally associate the dream-sign (food) with this unusual item or event that could never happen in the real world.  But at the same time, this unusual item or event should equate to &quot;lucid dreaming&quot;.  When you see the unusual item, it should only make you think of when you have a lucid dream as this should be the only time you encountered it.  So we have a 3 item associative link.  Do all of the above while in a lucid dream.

The next time you dream about your dream-sign, your subconscious will think of the unusual item or event.  The unusual item or event will make you think of lucid dreaming.  The two combined impossibilities (1. dream-sign that cannot exist in the real world  2. item or event that only appears in lucid dreams) will make your unconscious try to make a decision on all this.  This will make your conscious mind come to the surface and hopefully you will come to the conclusion that you are dreaming.  Many times, you will not want to deal with it because you are too tired (that is why you are sleeping, no?) and fall back into a normal dream state.  This is why it can take a few tries.  Eventually, your subconscious will start putting clear signs in your dreams like billboards that spell out &quot;YOU ARE DREAMING&quot;.  But once it triggers, it is quite the realization that an instant before, you had no real control over your actions and now you can do whatever you want.  Another note... if it failed, you will usually know why.  So next time, you can choose another dream-sign or slightly different technique or something more shocking.  Once you get this working once, it is relatively easy to use over and over as the hard part just described is over with.  Sometimes disassociative techniques are needed if used too much.

To sum up, this technique is a way to force a reality check while in a normal dream state where your subconscious has no choice but to come to the conclusion that you are in fact dreaming.  Once your mind knows that you are dreaming, there will be no other conclusion than your conscious mind taking over.  And this is what lucid dreaming is all about.

===CAT===
{| width=100%
|style=&quot;background-color: #faffef; border: 1px solid #dafa9a;&quot;|Rated green/yellow. There have been anecdotes from many different people of this technique working.
|}

# For one week, go to bed at the same time each night and get up 90 minutes earlier than you usually do. Spend those 90 minutes doing reality checks every 2&amp;ndash;5 minutes.
# Thereafter, on alternate days: follow the routine from step one, and set the intention to do your reality check routine at its regular time, while getting a full night sleep. This will cause the reality check conditioning to kick in during REM prime-time.

For detailed information on the Cycle Adjustment Technique, see the [[Lucid Dreaming/Appendices/CAT|appendix on CAT]].

&lt;div width=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #ffe; border: solid 1px #fea; padding: 2px 5px 2px 5px;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;&gt;
Topics about CAT at [http://lucidity.com The Lucidity Institute]: [http://www.novadreamer.com/discus/messages/441/2024.html?1090227250 **CAT method** New Lucid dream induction technique]&lt;br/&gt;
There is an [[Lucid Dreaming/Appendices/CAT|appendix on CAT]].
&lt;/div&gt;

===Tibetan methods===
Tibetan Buddhists practice what is known as Tibetan dream yoga. Probably the most time consuming way of inducing lucid dreams, it is also, according to the practitioners, the most rewarding. The basic practice is ''awareness''. Awareness should be practiced while sleeping just as well as while being awake. Meditating on the question “who is aware?” might catapult you into a higher degree of awareness according to Buddhist beliefs. Keeping this level of awareness is another matter. The Tibetans have developed many yogic exercises and disciplines to be practiced. Maybe the most interesting difference between Tibetan dream yoga and modern western methods of lucid dream induction is the Tibetan claim of the possibility to be aware during deep sleep, not only in the REM periods of sleep. For the reader who is interested in these methods a good start is to begin to regard all experience as a dream. After all, from the countless multitude of matter and radiation reaching our senses the nervous system tunes in only to a small fraction of this chaos. For members of the phalanx that believes we, more or less, create our own reality in the above sense this practice should feel natural. In general though, it is recommended to gain instruction from a teacher in the flesh rather than from books (like this one!).

The Tibetan Methods are not &quot;time consuming&quot; if the goal is to go into deeper than Lucid states. From a Raja Yoga stand point, from a Daoist standpoint, and from a Tibetan Yoga standpoint the goal is not to &quot;play&quot; in Lucid Dreams, but to dispel the delusional nature of what we call &quot;reality.&quot; Also, to heal and to develop super-learning. Now &quot;super-learning&quot; is a relative term, it depends on your culture, modernity (in terms of entrepreneurialism - in 3rd world, 2nd world, 1st world sense; &quot;are you developing a better rickshaw or are you developing an engine that runs off of water, what is relevant?&quot;), and on the &quot;energy&quot; you find most attractive: innovative, creative, joyous, blissful, love, power, wisdom, mirth. Are you Ambitious-Worldly or Ambitious-Spiritual? All these factors play into it.

These techniques are very easy to learn and are rooted in a deeper science than the WILD, VILD, LILD -- one that does not use auto-suggestion or forced recall. In conclusion, the Tibetan methods are advanced yogic techniques that only an accomplished practitioner can fully teach. If one does not have access to a Tibetan dream yogi, one should probably concentrate on techniques that are more mundane from a Western point of view.

===Other techniques===
{| width=&quot;100%&quot;
|style=&quot;background-color: #ffefef; border: 1px solid #fababa&quot;|Rated red. There have been no anecdotes found of these techniques working.
|}

Many of these are combinations of other techniques with some addition or modification.

* '''Inducing dream-signs''' - You can become lucid by trying to induce specific dream-signs to watch for during your dream. You can use auto-suggestion (see above) to associate a specific dream-sign with doing a reality check, or you can just get used to doing a reality check whenever you encounter the dream-sign while awake. Some dream-signs you can use:
** '''Thirst''' - Avoid drinking for very long. Wake up later in the night and put salt on your tongue or eat chili to make you even thirstier. Fill a glass of fresh cold water and take it with you back to bed. Hopefully, you'll dream of getting something to drink. Don't use this technique if you have trouble falling asleep while thirsty.
** '''False Awakening''' - Set your intention as you fall asleep to wake up in the middle of the night. If you are a heavy sleeper, you'll hopefully dream of waking up in the middle of the night. If you are a light sleeper, you are probably more likely to really wake up.
** '''Bladder''' - Drink large amounts of water before going to sleep. You should dream of having to go to the bathroom. You may wet your bed! This technique should be used carefully, to avoid the possibility of [[w:Water_intoxication|water intoxication]].
* '''Conditioning''' - Strictly punish or reward yourself after a dream where you failed to realize you were dreaming or when you do have a lucid dream. This could increase motivation but not necessarily cause lucid dreams in itself. Cognitive psychology, however, states that this punishment/reward system is very counterproductive, because it ties our self-esteem to the outcome of the endeavor. The opposite of this system would be to see each attempt, including those that fail, as another step towards success.
* '''Muscle Exhaustion''' - Lift slight weights with one's arms and legs for about fifteen minutes before one begins to fall asleep.  One should not, however, lift anything that strains the muscles too much, for that stimulates the sympathetic nervous system and excites the body.  The method should cause a release of tension in the muscles and tire them out.  This combined with relaxation techniques and any of the -ILD's should produce a positive result.

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: right; font-size: small&quot;&gt;[[#top|top]]&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br&gt;

==Other methods==
===Food and drink===
There are various foods and drinks that you can consume which seem to have some effect on sleeping and dreaming. Note that for most of these there is no explanation or scientific study of how they work, and some may simply be placebos.

Don't go overboard with the consumption of any of these, as overdosing could have nasty effects (well, milk should be safe unless you are allergic). '''Don't experiment without accumulating enough knowledge first.''' The authors in no way encourage the use of legal or illegal drugs.

* The amino acid tryptophan, which can be found in warm milk amongst other sources, is a precursor for the hormone serotonin, and has been proven to help you fall asleep.
* Vitamin B6 and others of the B group are important for neuronal functions.
* [[w:Melatonin|Melatonin]] is a hormone with neuronal effects. It is produced by the pineal gland in darkness and is suppressed by blue light. Wearing blue-blocking sunglasses or avoiding bright light in general the hours before bedtime maximizes night-time melatonin secretion.
* [[w:5-HTP|5-HTP]] or [[w:L-5-HTP|L-5-HTP]] is a supplement that is related to serotonin, which some claim has induced lucid dreaming on approximately half the nights it is taken.
* [[w:Caffeine|Caffeine]] is useful in WILD techniques, as it helps the mind stay focused and think vividly. Please notice that caffeine is an addictive substance and may have negative effects on your health.
* An [[w:Amino Acid|Amino Acid]] Blend made up of 2000mg L-aspartic acid, 4000mg L-glutamine, and 300mg [[w:Theanine|L-theanine]] can substantially increase your odds of having a Lucid Dream.
* [[w:Galantamine | Galantamine]] - acetylcholinesterase inhibitors extract from plants such as ''Lycoris radiata'' (Red Spider Lily) or from chemical synthesis. Works best when taken together with choline and/or alpha-GPC.
Some people who practice Lucid dream (LD) or  Out of body experience (OBE) use Galantamine to increase their odds to achieve LD or OBE. By taking small amount of Galantamine (around 4 to 8 mg) after 5 to 6 hours of deep sleep and practice the induction technique such as [[Happiness/Meditation|meditation]], MILD or WILD many people report more success with Galantamine.

There also report that taking Galantamine without proper induction technique will not lead to LD or OBE but will result in only a vivid dream instead. It should also be noted that due to a long half life Galantamine will stay in the body for a period of up to and over 48 hours, as such it is advisable to space out the use of Galantamine over a period of three days so that the body does not build a resistance to the drug ruining its effectiveness.

Some people report mixing Galantamine with other Nootropic can enhance the degree of lucidity but this is still controversial since some mixtures may work for some people, but lead to failure for others. 

Plants:
* [[w:Artemisia vulgaris|Artemisia vulgaris]]
* [[w:St John's wort|Hypericum perforatum]]
* [[w:Ginseng|Korean Ginseng]]
* [[w:Valerian (plant)|Valeriana officinalis]]
* [[w:Calea zacatechichi|Calea zacatechichi]]
* [[w:Ginkgo Biloba|Ginkgo biloba]]
* [[w:Nutmeg|Nutmeg]] - contains [[w:myristicin|myristicin]] a [[w:deliriant|deliriant]].

For an in-depth guide to using supplements for lucid dreaming, see the book &lt;i&gt;Advanced Lucid Dreaming - The Power of Supplements&lt;/i&gt;.

===Drugs===
Dissociatives and hallucinogens can be used to create a (more or less) lucid dream-like state, though whether or not these help with lucid dreaming is debatable. '''The authors do not recommend use of these substances for induction of lucid dreams, nor do they urge the breaking of any applicable laws.'''

Some dissociatives and hallucinogens are:
* [[w:Amanita muscaria|Amanita muscaria]]
* [[w:Banisteriopsis caapi|Ayahuasca]]
* [[w:Dimethyltryptamine|DMT]] - Common in the shamanic method of drinking Ayahuasca, to the result of entering the spirit realm. The herbal brew contains the psychedelic DMT, a drug is actually synthesized in minute quantities by the metabolism. It may be produced during dreams, adding to the enhanced experience.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20090406111627/http://www.dreamviews.com/community/showthread.php?t=71387 5000 year old WILD technique. Very easy, and very effective.] ''DreamViews forums.'' Accessed 2009-09-18.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[w:Dextromethorphan|DXM]]
* [[w:Ketamine|Ketamine]]
* [[w:LSD|LSD]]
* [[w:Mescaline|Mescaline]]
* [[w:Morning glory|Morning glory]] seeds
* [[w:Phencyclidine|PCP]]
* [[w:Psilocybe|Psilocybe mushrooms]]
* [[w:Salvia divinorum|Salvia divinorum]]
For more info, see [http://www.erowid.org/psychoactives/psychoactives.shtml Erowid Vaults]

===Gadgets===
There are various gadgets you can use to become lucid easily. They generally detect when you are in the REM state and then provide a light and/or sound signal. This signal is supposed to be adjusted so that it doesn't wake you up but does enter your dream. The signal is then recognized as showing that you are dreaming, and you become lucid.

The most well-known device is the NovaDreamer from the Lucidity Institute. However, this product is no longer produced. Be sure to check for recommendations for devices from lucid dreaming forums.

A similar device is the [http://www.wellnesstools.com/dreammaker_quickinfo.htm DreamMaker].  The DreamMaker works very similarly to the NovaDreamer but without the Dream Alarm feature, which worked to wake the dreamer in the middle of the REM state.  This device comes with a mask, a circuit board with adjustable controls, the batteries needed to operate it, a short owner's manual, a lucid dreaming workbook, and the [[w:Stephen LaBerge|Stephen LaBerge]] book ''Exploring the World of Lucid Dreaming''.  The circuit board is supplied completely ready to use, but you have to insert the batteries and put the circuit board into the mask yourself.

An alternative is the [http://brindefalk.solarbotics.net/kvasar/kvasar.html Kvasar]. The Kvasar costs about $20 in raw materials, but needs to be constructed by somebody skilled in electronics as it is not sold commercially. It can also be hard to operate.

Another do-it-yourself alternative to commercial dreaming masks is Nate True's [http://cre.ations.net/creation/face-mounted-lucid-dreaming-mask Lucid Dream Mask], which does not bother with difficult-to-calibrate sensors and just uses a timer for flashing lights, and has (ostensibly) competitive results with all of the former gadgets.

The owners of Wellness Tools, who makes the DreamMaker, and Kvasar have not had friendly relations; see [http://web.archive.org/web/20080504084354/http://www.dreamviews.com/community/showthread.php?t=11228 DreamViews.com].

===Software===
There are many programs for your computer that can assist with lucid dreaming. These can give out verbal cues while you sleep, or assist in doing your reality checks:
* [https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/ilucid-dream/id668103961?ls=1&amp;mt=8 iLucid Dream] for the iPhone. Dream journal, reality checks, induction techniques, binaural beats for deep sleep and much more!
* [http://lucidcode.com/LightenedDream/ Lightened Dream] is available for Windows as freeware. It can be used as a dream journal and a dream-sign list. One of its more notable features is that you can have it play a voice or song each time you enter a REM sleep period.
* [http://www.dreamdoze.com DreamDoze] A web application for Social Dream interpretation and dreams journal management
* [http://gnaural.sourceforge.net/ Gnaural] is a multi-platform programmable binaural-beat generator. Gnaural is released as free software under the GNU General Public License. (For a browser based demo, see [http://pantheon.yale.edu/%7Ebbl2/GnauralJavaApplet_signed.html Gnaural Java)])
* [http://www.bwgen.com Brainwave Generator] is available for Windows. It works by playing binaural beats into your ears, changing your brainstate.
* [http://bytered.com/software-realitycheck.html Reality Check] is available for Windows. It works by appearing on your computer screen at random times to remind you to do a reality check.
* [http://uazu.net/sbagen SBaGen] is available for Windows, MacOS X, and Linux. It works by playing binaural beats into your ears, changing your brainstate.
* [http://www.transparentcorp.com Neuro-Programmer] is available for Windows. This is powerful software that creates binaural beats and can work in conjunction with special goggles to induce certain mental states.
* [http://www.lucidweaver.com/ LucidWeaver] is available for mobile phones and PDA that support Java (J2ME). It includes a Dream alarm with sound cue which can be adjusted to a personal REM-sleep cycle for improving dream recall and lucidity training. Randomized reality tests can be set and it can be used as regular alarm clock.
* [http://mythwell.com/lucille/index.html Lucille 2.0] is an application to assist with doing reality checks.
* [http://www.sadglad.com/yad/yad.html You Are Dreaming]
* [http://www.sadglad.com/daldom/readme.html Daldom] a cross platform audio lucid dream induction software.
* [http://www.dreaminglife.org/downloads/lucid_dreaming_assistant.exe Lucid Dreaming Assistant] DOS software (no home page) 
* [http://www.world-of-lucid-dreaming.com/lucid-dreaming-mp3.html Unexplainable Store] Lucid Dreaming Brainwave Entrainment MP3 
* [http://www.androlib.com/android.application.com-ropez-android-sleepcheckreminder-qDwmw.aspx Sleep Check Reminder] for Android. 
* [https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/ilucid/id591703883?mt=8 iLucid] for iOS (iPod, iPhone, iPad).
* [https://sites.google.com/site/sleepasandroid/ Sleep As Android] is an Android sleep tracking app. It has a feature where it can play a sound file (by default, a soft voice that says &quot;You're dreaming...&quot; and echoes out) when it detects that the user is in a deep sleep.

There is also a list of programs available at [http://www.ld4all.com LD4all.com], under the “How” section.

====Hypnosis====
The techniques commonly referred to as hypnosis is based in a set of hypnotic suggestions are commonly composed of a series of instructions and ideas that may be delivered by a hypnotist in the presence of the subject, or they may be self-administered (&quot;self-suggestion&quot; or &quot;autosuggestion&quot;), even in a conscious state.

Hypnosis is not a science. In fact, it has in almost every aspect eluded scientific analysis, as it is extremely hard to generalize (each individual responds differently and at different levels) and the methodology is so diverse and based on yet to be completely understood mental/biological phenomena, most related with faith or the placebo effect. For the phenomena to work, whom in aggregate we define as hypnosis, the mind has to be able to turn the suggestions into reality. All hypnosis is ultimately self hypnosis. If you, for instance, take into consideration the problems that faith beliefs have caused to the human race, or even the problems in the field of psychology, you can appreciate the problem of scientifically studying hypnotic phenomena, as they are extremely open to individual interpretation and to one's ability to be open to suggestibility (self-induced or otherwise).

The Wikibook's work on [[Hypnosis]] will covers the subject in greater detail. It will also offer support material, or reference it, such as methods to induce, or reinforce specific mental states (or states of mind) and any attitudes and beliefs that impact the phenomena. Including information on techniques or procedures for hypnotic induction and hypnotic suggestion.

====Forums====
* [http://www.world-of-lucid-dreaming.com/forum/ The World of Lucid Dreaming Forum] is a good place to ask questions and receive feedback on how accurately you are performing these techniques.

== References ==
&lt;references/&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: right; font-size: small&quot;&gt;[[#top|top]]&lt;/div&gt;
{{LDTOC}}

[[es:Sueño lúcido/Técnicas de Inducción]]
[[it:Sogno lucido/Tecniche di Induzione]]</text>
      <sha1>2ammodubol90xzs85c3i6q3ayscp06h</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Bicycles/Maintenance and Repair/Tools and Supplies/Cable Cutter</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3990</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2412842</id>
      <parentid>2412841</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-28T22:18:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Armchair</username>
        <id>77084</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Intro */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[image:Cable cutters.jpg|right|thumb|350px|Cable cutters.   These are used also to cut cable housings, (Bowden cables), that are reinforced with several steel wires.]]
Brake and derailleur cables are extremely difficult to cut with a standard pair of wire cutters (sometimes called side or diagonal cutters); when it is finally accomplished, this process usually leaves a frayed mess of the inner cable, which is impossible to slip through the cable housing or the hole in a fastening bolt. In addition, the jaws of these cutters are made for cutting copper electrical wire, and will become notched when cutting steel bicycle cables.

'''Cable cutters''' specifically designed for steel cable, on bicycles or elsewhere, are available at prices low enough to eliminate this nuisance. They are generally similar to regular cutters or scissors, but have extra-hard jaws, each of which carries a v-shaped notch. When cutting a cable, the notches overlap, trapping the cable in a diamond shaped hole with sharp edges, which becomes smaller as the handle is compressed, thereby cutting the cable easily without fraying and with no damage to the tool. They are also useful for cutting the cable housing, although they often close the inner sleeve, and it needs to be re-opened with a piece of cable or other means.   Sometimes their use leaves a small burr on the housing which may need to be filed off.

[[Category:{{FULLBOOKNAME}}|{{FULLCHAPTERNAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>df07e2jz9ufwca119yu1anipvq3apc1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Brown Rice with Ground Turkey</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>3992</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2682714</id>
      <parentid>2679503</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-07-19T16:33:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Austncorp</username>
        <id>1540792</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Distinguishing the various types of frying cats.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{recipesummary|Turkey recipes|4|30 minutes|3||280 Cal}}

{{recipe}} | [[Cookbook:Meat|Meat]] | [[Cookbook:California cuisine|California cuisine]]

==Ingredients==
* 2 cups cooked [[Cookbook:Rice|brown rice]] (300 Calories, 66&amp;nbsp;g Carbs, 8&amp;nbsp; Protein)
* 20 ounces of extra lean ground [[Cookbook:Turkey|turkey]] breast (600 calories, 130&amp;nbsp;g protein, cholesterol 225&amp;nbsp;mg)
* 1 12 oz can diced [[Cookbook:Tomato|tomato]]es with [[Cookbook:Chili Pepper|green chili]]es (90 calories, 18&amp;nbsp;g Carbs, 3&amp;nbsp;g protein, 3&amp;nbsp;g dietary fiber)
* 1 ounce [[Cookbook:Vegetable Oil|vegetable oil]] (120 calories)
* 1 tablespoon [[Cookbook:Teriyaki Sauce|Teriyaki Sauce]] (10 calories, 2&amp;nbsp;g carbs, 1&amp;nbsp;g sugar)
* Seasonings to taste: e.g., garlic powder, lemon pepper, All Spice, etc.

Makes 4 servings.

==Procedure==
# Put rice and water in pan or [[Cookbook:Rice Cooker|rice cooker]] to cook, I used the 10-minute variety.
# Spray [[cookbook:skillet|skillet]] with cooking spray, sprinkle in garlic powder and other seasonings. Put in turkey and crumble it as it cooks. Add can of tomatoes (a whole can is actually too much for us but it still tasted good.) Mix with turkey till turkey is cooked.
# Rice will be done before ground turkey. Use a [[Cookbook:Wok|wok]] or deep [[Cookbook:Skillet|skillet]], add cooking oil add 1-teaspoon All Spice and/or other seasonings. As pan heats slowly add cooked rice (watch for splattering of hot oil). When rice is heated evenly add Teriyaki Sauce and mix it evenly.
# When ground turkey is done cooking add it to rice in wok, mix it thoroughly and serve.

==Nutritional information==

*Total calories of meal 1120 divided by 4 servings = 280 calories
*Total carbs 86&amp;nbsp;g divided by 4 servings = 21.5&amp;nbsp;g carbs
**Total sugar 10&amp;nbsp;g divided by 4 servings = 2.5&amp;nbsp;g sugars
*Total protein 141&amp;nbsp;g divided by 4 servings = 35.25&amp;nbsp;g protein
*Total cholesterol 225&amp;nbsp;mg divided by 4 serving = 56.25&amp;nbsp;mg. cholesterol

[[Category:Californian recipes]]
[[Category:Rice recipes]]
[[Category:Turkey recipes]]
[[Category:Boiled recipes]]
[[Category:Pan fried recipes]]
[[Category:Main course recipes]]</text>
      <sha1>o7c0y8t9b3epqj05hyk0wgtacbgvl8s</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook talk:Brown Rice with Ground Turkey</title>
    <ns>103</ns>
    <id>3993</id>
    <revision>
      <id>353458</id>
      <parentid>155815</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-02-03T03:40:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Uncle G's major work 'bot</username>
        <id>10904</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[Talk:Cookbook:Brown Rice with Ground Turkey]] moved to [[Cookbook talk:Brown Rice with Ground Turkey]]: COOKBOT: Renaming talk page to Cookbook talk namespace</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Page histroy from [[en:Brown rice with ground turkey]]

Brown rice with ground turkey

Revision history

View (previous 50) (next 50) (20 | 50 | 100 | 250 | 500).

Legend: (cur) = difference with current version, (last) = difference with preceding version, M = minor edit

    * (cur) (last) . . 10:28, 18 Jan 2003 . . 68.3.146.254
    * (cur) (last) . . 20:38, 17 Jan 2003 . . Maveric149 (reinstated article - by-line ; contributor who posted this has indicated authorship of external version)
    * (cur) (last) . . 19:31, 17 Jan 2003 . . Maveric149 (Removed possible copyright infringement. )
    * (cur) (last) . . 19:21, 17 Jan 2003 . . 68.3.146.254
    * (cur) (last) . . 19:20, 17 Jan 2003 . . 68.3.146.254



==Talk from en:==

This recipe sounds delicious. I must try it.

Ok. I bite. Where can I get some of this Mrs. Dash stuff?

It should be available at any supermarket. They have different varieties, even. no salt.

:This calls for an awful lot of name brand ingredients. Are you sure it's not taken from a product label or something? -- [[User:Wapcaplet|Wapcaplet]]

Oerr new recipe coming up... I'll beat him to it [[User:Mintguy|Mintguy]]

The recipe sounded really good. Perhaps, instead of Mrs. Dash, add &quot;salt-free spice&quot; or something to that effect?

What about '''Jennie-O''' turkey and '''Del Monte''' diced tomatoes. lol, are you for real?
:Sounds copyrighted.  Don't forget the Pam (TM) cooking spray.  [[User:Koyaanis Qatsi|Koyaanis Qatsi]]

- just change the brand names to generic terms, and it should be okay. &quot;canned diced tomatoes&quot;, &quot;ground turkey&quot;, &quot;cooking spray&quot;.

I'm not sure I trust the idea of recipes on Wiki. It's too easy for someone to come along and change the ingredients and muck it up. LOL. ~~

::? People can do that with ''any'' fact in Wikipedia. --[[User:Maveric149|mav]]

:::Of course they can. But if I take a recipe from here and it says use 3 gallons of Chicken stock and half a cupfull of rice, instead of a pint of stock and two cups of rice, my guests will be sorely disappointed. Certainly a lot more disappointed than if I relate the story I read on Wikipedia about Adolf Hitler's early life in Liverpool painting ceilings! [[User:Mintguy|Mintguy]]

::::I would be equally disappointed if I memorized a fact gleamed from Wikipedia only to fail an exam. --mav

:::::Well Ok. I could easily poison someone if a recipe read to cook something for 20 minutes when it should be cooked for 2 hours. Now I suppose you'll tell me that if I used Wikipedia to help me study my anatomy exam I could accidentally cut the wrong artery or something. LOL [[User:Mintguy|Mintguy]]

- good point. I hadn't thought of that.

true! but the recipe sounds too yummy not trying it. Some wikipedians can try it using brand ingredients of their choices and tell us how it tastes.

----
It reminds me to eat my chicken diner now. Hey some articles help people not be Wikipediholic even though they are gonna be. [[kt2]]

Wikipedios Anonymous. It's a 12-wik program &lt;rimshot.wav&gt;.

I am the recipe creator although I posted it somewhere else first I did create it. The reason I mentioned the products so much is 1. allows user an idea of who/what 2. Recently started lifestyle change that makes you a little more responsible with what you put in to your system =*)
Bodyforlife.com is the plan, I have lost 20 pounds in 3 months and feel better than I have in a long time. Enough commercials. Oh by the way it was Kroger brand Butter flavored cooking spray. Mike Feddersen

:That's good enough for me. Please do indicate this in the edit summary next time so that you are not wrongly accused of copyright infringement in the future. --mav

Well, it sounds like a good recipe. I am going to find it, and print it. Is the bodyforlife system based on a lowfat philosophy?

----</text>
      <sha1>d3wagrd2w35eldrf8xvgxvoanq04dsa</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Recipes</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>3995</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2704592</id>
      <parentid>2698113</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-09-27T14:40:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Austncorp</username>
        <id>1540792</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* B */ Corrected link to Bobó de Camarao</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{recipe|*}}

'''Wikimedia Cookbook Alphabetical Index of Recipes'''

You will find a more complete listing of recipes in the cookbook in [[:Category:Recipes]].

Please only add links to recipes that exist or that you are about to immediately add to the Cookbook.  To request that a recipe be added, please see [[Cookbook:Requested Recipes]].

'''Pictures:''' If you have a digital camera please include a pictorial illustrating the different steps. Please mark the name of the recipe with a '''(p)''' in parenthesis to indicate that your recipe contains pictures, or '''(pt)''' to indicate that it contains a whole pictorial.

__NOTOC__
[[#0-9|0-9]] [[#A|A]] [[#B|B]] [[#C|C]] [[#D|D]] [[#E|E]] [[#F|F]] [[#G|G]] [[#H|H]] [[#I|I]] [[#J|J]] [[#K|K]] [[#L|L]] [[#M|M]] [[#N|N]] [[#O|O]] [[#P|P]] [[#Q|Q]] [[#R|R]] [[#S|S]] [[#T|T]] [[#U|U]] [[#V|V]] [[#W|W]] [[#X|X]] [[#Y|Y]] [[#Z|Z]]

==0-9==
*[[Cookbook:1-2-3-4 Cake|1-2-3-4 Cake]] (pt)

==A==
*[[Cookbook:Aam panna|Aam panna]] (raw mango drink, India)
*[[Cookbook:Acorn Squash with Orange Marmalade|Acorn Squash with Orange Marmalade]]
*[[Cookbook:Shrimp Fritters (Accra)|Accra]] (Shrimp Fritters, Trinidad and Tobago)
*[[Cookbook:Adobo|Adobo]] (Philippines)
*[[Cookbook:Agedashi tofu|Agedashi tofu]]
*[[Cookbook:Alfredo Sauce|Alfredo Sauce]]
*[[Cookbook:Aloo gobi|Aloo gobi]] (Indian; Pakistani; Vegetarian)
*[[Cookbook:Potato Samosas (Aloo Pies)|Aloo Pies]] (Trinidad and Tobago)
*[[Cookbook:Aloo masala|Aloo Masala]] (Indian; Vegan)
*[[Cookbook:Angels On Horseback|Angels On Horseback]]
*[[Cookbook:A Nice Cup of Tea|A Nice Cup of Tea]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Ambrosia Fruit Salad|Ambrosia Fruit Salad]]
*[[Cookbook:Red Bean Paste (Anko)|Anko]] (Japan)
*[[Cookbook:Anzac Biscuits|Anzac Biscuits]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Appam|Appam]] (Indian; Vegan)
*[[Cookbook:Apple Bundt Cake|Apple Bundt Cake]]
*[[Cookbook:Apple Crisp|Apple Crisp]]
*[[Cookbook:Apple Pie|Apple Pie]]
**[[Cookbook:Apple Pie I|Apple Pie I]] '''(p)'''
**[[Cookbook:Apple Pie II|Apple Pie II]]
*[[Cookbook:Apple raisin oat muffins|Apple raisin oat muffins]]
*[[Cookbook:Apple Tapioca|Apple Tapioca]]
*[[Cookbook:Arroz con pollo|Arroz con Pollo]] (Peruvian)
*[[Cookbook:Arroz negro|Arroz negro]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Rice - Molded (Arroz Tapado)|Arroz Tapado]]
*[[Cookbook:Artichoke Hearts Attack|Artichoke Hearts Attack]]
*[[Cookbook:Asparagus soup|Asparagus soup]]
*[[Cookbook:Atkins-friendly Tira Misu|Atkins-friendly Tira Misu]]
*[[Cookbook:Azteca|Azteca]]

==B==
*[[Cookbook:Hard Tack of India (Baati)|Baati]] (Indian Hard Tack)
*[[Cookbook:Baba ganoush|Baba ganoush]]
*[[Cookbook:Salt Cod and Potato Casserole (Bacalhau à Gomes de Sá)|Bacalhau à Gomes de Sá]] (Portuguese Cod Casserole)
*[[Cookbook:Bacon Cheese Omelet|Bacon Cheese Omelet]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Baingan Bartha (Southern)|Baingan Bartha (Southern)]] (Indian)
*[[Cookbook:Baked Lamb and Yogurt|Baked Lamb and Yogurt]]
*[[Cookbook:Baked Oatmeal|Baked Oatmeal]]
*[[Cookbook:Baked Pork Chops|Baked Pork Chops]]
*[[Cookbook:Banana bread|Banana Bread]]
*[[Cookbook:Banana nut muffin|Banana Nut Muffins]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Banana Chocolate Bread Pudding|Banana Chocolate Bread Pudding]]
*[[Cookbook:Banana Cream Pie|Banana Cream Pie]]
*[[Cookbook:Banana Cream Pie II|Banana Cream Pie II]]
*[[Cookbook:Pancake|Banana-Spirulina Pancakes]]
*[[Cookbook:B%C3%A1nh_M%C3%AC|Banh Mi]]
*[[Cookbook:Barbecued Spare Ribs|Barbecued Spare Ribs]]
*[[Cookbook:Barbecue Sauce|Barbecue Sauce]] '''(p)''' (simple everyday sauce for leftovers) 
*[[Cookbook:Barbecue Sauce - Kansas City style|Barbecue Sauce - Kansas City style]]
*[[Cookbook:Basic Indian Tomato Gravy|Basic Indian Tomato Gravy]] (Indian; Vegan)
*[[Cookbook:Bean Jahni soup|Bean Jahni soup]] (Albanian)
*[[Cookbook:Béchamel Sauce|Béchamel sauce]]
*[[Cookbook:Beef and Barley Stew|Beef and Barley Stew]]
*[[Cookbook:Beef Gravy Soup|Beef Gravy Soup]]
*[[Cookbook:Bengal Potatoes|Bengal Potatoes]]
*[[Cookbook:Biscuit|Biscuit]]
*[[Cookbook:Biscuits|Biscuits]]
*[[Cookbook:Biscuits and Gravy|Biscuits and Gravy]]
*[[Cookbook:Bison Loaf|Bison Loaf]]
*[[Cookbook:Black-Eyed Peas and Kale|Black-Eyed Peas and Kale]]
*[[Cookbook:Bliny|Bliny]] (Russian)
*[[Cookbook:Blondies|Blondies]]
*[[Cookbook:BLT Sandwich|BLT Sandwich]]
*[[Cookbook:Blueberry muffin|Blueberry muffin]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Shrimp and Cassava Sauce of Brazil (Bobó de Camarao)|Bobó de Camarao]] (Brazilian)
*[[Cookbook:Boerewors|Boerewors]] (South Africa)
*[[Cookbook:Boiled pasta|Boiled pasta]]
*[[Cookbook:Boliche|Boliche]]
*[[Cookbook:Börek|Börek]] (Middle Eastern cuisine)
*[[Cookbook:Bouballe|Bouballe]]
*[[Cookbook:Bouillabaisse|Bouillabaisse]]
*[[Cookbook:Bread|Bread]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Breaded Fried Oysters|Breaded Fried Oysters]]
*[[Cookbook:Breakfast Waffles (Gluten-Free)|Breakfast Waffles (Gluten-Free)]]
*[[Cookbook:Brigadeiro|Brigadeiro]] (Brazilian chocolate confection)
*[[Cookbook:British Lemon Meringue Pie|British Lemon Meringue Pie]]
*[[Cookbook:Broccoli Stir Fry|Broccoli Stir Fry]]
*[[Cookbook:Brown Gravy|Brown Gravy]]
*[[Cookbook:Brown Rice with Ground Turkey|Brown Rice with Ground Turkey]]
*[[Cookbook:Brownie|Brownies]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Bruschetta|Bruschetta]] (Italian, Appetizer)
*[[Cookbook:Bubble and Squeak|Bubble and Squeak]]
*[[Cookbook:Bubble Tea|Bubble Tea]]
*[[Cookbook:Bulgur Bread|Bulgur Bread]]
*[[Cookbook:Bulgher Burger|Bulgher Burger]]
*[[Cookbook:Bulgogi|Bulgogi]] (Korean beef recipe)
*[[Cookbook:Burrito|Burrito]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Butter tart|Butter Tart]] (Canadian)
*[[Cookbook:Buuz|Buuz]] (Mongolian)

==C==
*[[Cookbook:Cabbage and Bacon|Cabbage and Bacon]]
*[[Cookbook:Caesar Salad|Caesar Salad]]
*[[Cookbook:California Curry Chicken|California Curry Chicken]]
*[[Cookbook:California Fusion Peach Salsa|California Fusion Peach Salsa]]
*[[Cookbook:Campfire Trout|Campfire Trout]]
*[[Cookbook:Candied yams|Candied yams]]
*[[Cookbook:Diana's Candied Sweet Potatoes|Candied Sweet Potatoes (Diana's)]] (Southern United States)
*[[Cookbook:Caramel|Caramel]]
*[[Cookbook:Cardamom Bread|Cardamom Bread]]
*[[Cookbook:Carpetbag Steak|Carpetbag Steak]]
*[[Cookbook:Cashew Chicken|Cashew Chicken]]
*[[Cookbook:Cebiche de pescado|Cebiche de pescado]] (Peruvian)
*[[Cookbook:Century egg|Century egg]]
*[[Cookbook:Ceviche of Shrimp and Sea Bass|Ceviche of Shrimp and Sea Bass]]
*[[Cookbook:Chai Tea|Chai Tea]] (Pakistani/Indian)
*[[Cookbook:Chapati|Chapati]] (Indian)
*[[Cookbook:Cheescake cups|Cheescake cups]]
*[[Cookbook:Chewy Ginger Cookies|Chewy Ginger Cookies]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Chicken Broccoli|Chicken Broccoli]]
*[[Cookbook:Chicken Parmesan|Chicken Parmesan]] (Italian)
*[[Cookbook:Chicken Pot Pie|Chicken Pot Pie]]
**[[Cookbook:Chicken Pot Pie I|Chicken Pot Pie I]]
**[[Cookbook:Chicken Pot Pie II|Chicken Pot Pie II]]
*[[Cookbook:Chicken Soup|Chicken Soup]]
*[[Cookbook:Chicken Stir-Fry|Chicken Stir-Fry]]
*[[Cookbook:Turkey Soup|Chicken Soup (variation of Turkey Soup)]]
*[[Cookbook:Midwestern Chicken Wings|Chicken Wings, Midwestern style]] (US)
*[[Cookbook:Chili|Chili]]
*[[Cookbook:Chili (Vegan)|Chili (Vegan)]]
*[[Cookbook:Chili con carne|Chili con carne]]
*[[Cookbook:Chip|Chip]]
**[[Cookbook:Potato Chip|Potato Chip]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Chocolate Cake|Chocolate Cake]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Chocolate Chip Cookies|Chocolate Chip Cookies]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Chocolate Chip Cookies (Gluten-Free)|Chocolate Chip Cookies (Gluten-Free)]]
*[[Cookbook:Chocolate Fudge|Chocolate fudge]]
*[[Cookbook:Chocolate Mousse|Chocolate Mousse]]
*[[Cookbook:Chocolate Pear Bake|Chocolate Pear Bake]]
*[[Cookbook:Chocolate Sour-Cream Icing|Chocolate Sour-Cream Icing]] '''(pt)'''
*[[Cookbook:Chowder|Chowder]]
*[[Cookbook:Christmas ham|Christmas ham]]
*[[Cookbook:Chuu Chee Fish|Chuu Chee Fish]] (Thai)
*[[Cookbook:Nick's Cinnamon Chicken|Nick's Cinnamon Chicken]]
*[[Cookbook:Clam Chowder|Clam Chowder]]
*[[Cookbook:Coconut Chutney|Coconut Chutney]] (Indian)
*[[Cookbook:Cola Cake|Cola Cake]]
*[[Cookbook:Boiled Collard Green|Collard Greens]] (Southern United States) '''(pt)'''
*[[Cookbook:Coq au Vin|Coq au Vin]]
*[[Cookbook:Corn Bread|Corn Bread]]
*[[Cookbook:Corn Bread 2|Corn Bread 2]]
*[[Cookbook:Sweet Cornbread|Cornbread (Sweet)]]
*[[Cookbook:Cottage Cheese Eggs|Cottage Cheese Eggs]]
*[[Cookbook:Crab Cakes|Crab Cakes]]
*[[Cookbook:Crab Quesadillas with Mango Salsa|Crab Quesadillas with Mango Salsa]]
*[[Cookbook:Cream Cheese Wontons|Cream Cheese Wontons]]
*[[Cookbook:Creamed Spinach|Creamed Spinach]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Creamy BLT Pasta|Creamy BLT Pasta]]
*[[Cookbook:Creme Anglaise|Creme Anglaise]]
*[[Cookbook:Crème Brûlée|Crème Brûlée (Creme Brulee)]]
*[[Cookbook:Crêpe|Crêpe (Crepe)]]
*[[Cookbook:Crispy Gingerbread Cookies|Crispy Gingerbread Cookies]]
*[[Cookbook:Cucumber and Buttermilk Soup|Cucumber and Buttermilk Soup]]
*[[Cookbook:Cucumber Sprout Sandwich|Cucumber Sprout Sandwich]]
*[[Cookbook:Cupcakes|Cupcakes]] '''(pt)'''
*[[Cookbook:Curried Rice|Curried Rice]] (Vegetarian)
*[[Cookbook:Curry Chicken|Curry Chicken]]
*[[Cookbook:Curry Fried Rice|Curry fried rice]] (Indian fried rice)
*[[Cookbook:Custard Pie|Custard Pie]]

==D==
*[[Cookbook:Date Bar|Date Bar]] (US)
*[[Cookbook:Deep Fried Mars Bar|Deep Fried Mars Bar]] (Scottish Chip Shop delicacy and a classic at American fairs)
*[[Cookbook:Denver Crunch|Denver Crunch]] (US)
*[[Cookbook:Dill Cucumber Salad|Dill Cucumber Salad]]
*[[Cookbook:Doc'Roberts Grilled Vegetable Sandwich|Doc'Roberts Grilled Vegetable Sandwich]] (Vegan)
*[[Cookbook:Dosa|Dosa]] (Indian)
*[[Cookbook:Duck Confit|Duck confit]]
*[[Cookbook:Döner kebab|Döner kebab]] (kebab meat recipe, and some European kebab dishes, pictures planned to be added soon)

==E==
*[[Cookbook:Easy Maklubi|Easy Maklubi]] (Palestine)
*[[Cookbook:Easy pasta sauce|Easy pasta sauce]] (Vegetarian)
*[[Cookbook:Easy Scrambled Eggs|Easy Scrambled Eggs]] (International)
*[[Cookbook:Eel alla Milanese|Eel alla Milanese]]
*[[Cookbook:Egg Casserole|Egg Casserole]] (US)
*[[Cookbook:Egg Butter|Egg Butter]] (Estonia, Vegetarian)
*[[Cookbook:Egg noodles|Egg noodles]] (Vegetarian)
*[[Cookbook:Egg Rice|Egg Rice]] (Indian)
*[[Cookbook:Egg Roll|Egg Roll]] (can be made Vegetarian)
*[[Cookbook:Eggs Connaught|Eggs Connaught]] (Eggs Starter)
*[[Cookbook:Eggplant and Chickpea Skillet|Eggplant and Chickpea Skillet]] (Vegan)
*[[Cookbook:Eggplant Pasta|Eggplant Pasta]] (Vegan)
*[[Cookbook:Empanada|Empanada]]
*[[Cookbook:Eggnog|Eggnog]]
*[[Cookbook:English Field Bean Pate|English Field Bean Pate]] (Vegan)

==F==
*[[Cookbook:Fairy Cakes|Fairy Cakes]]
*[[Cookbook:Fast cooking recipes|Fast cooking recipes]]
*[[Cookbook:Favorite Beans and Rice|Favorite Beans and Rice]]
*[[Cookbook:Fesenjān|Fesenjān]]
*[[Cookbook:Fiddlehead-Portobello_Linguine|Fiddlehead-Portobello Linguine]]
*[[Cookbook:Field of Dreams Guacamole|'Field of Dreams' Guacamole]]
*[[Cookbook:Figgie 'obbin|Figgie 'obbin]] 
*[[Cookbook:Clam Chowder|Fish Chowder]] (Clam Chowder variation)
*[[Cookbook:Spanish Flan|Spanish Flan]] 
*[[Cookbook:Focaccia Bread|Focaccia Bread]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Fool's Gold Loaf|Fool's Gold Loaf]]
*[[Cookbook:Frappé Coffee|Frappe Coffee]]
*[[Cookbook:French Dip Sandwiches|French Dip Sandwiches]]
*[[Cookbook:French Dressing|French Dressing]]
*[[Cookbook:French Fries|French Fries]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:French Toast|French Toast]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Fresh Broadbeans Salad|Fresh Broadbeans Salad]]
*[[Cookbook:Fresh Mozzarella Bruschetta|Fresh Mozzarella Bruschetta]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Fried Cheese Balls with Sausage|Fried Cheese Balls with Sausage]]
*[[Cookbook:Fried Eggs|Fried Eggs]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Fried Fish|Fried Fish]] 
*[[Cookbook:Fried Meatballs|Fried Meatballs]]
*[[Cookbook:Fried Okra|Fried Okra]]
*[[Cookbook:Fried Rice|Fried Rice]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Frikadeller|Frikadeller (Danish)]]
*[[Cookbook:Frog's Legs à la Parisienne|Frog's Legs à la Parisienne]]
*[[Cookbook:Fruit Whip|Fruit Whip]]
*[[Cookbook:Fry Bread|Fry Bread]]

==G==
*[[Cookbook:Gado-gado|Gado-Gado]] (Indonesian)
*[[Cookbook:Galaktoboureko|Galaktoboureko]]
*[[Cookbook:Garlic bread|Garlic bread]]
*[[Cookbook:Garlic croutons|Garlic Croutons]] (Vegan)
*[[Cookbook:Garlic Lemon Chicken|Garlic Lemon Chicken]] (Lebanese)
*[[Cookbook:Garlic Parmesan Pasta|Garlic Parmesan Pasta]]
*[[Cookbook:Garlic, Tomato and Cheddar Sandwich|Garlic, Tomato and Cheddar Sandwich]]
*[[Cookbook:Gazpacho|Gazpacho]]
*[[Cookbook:Giblet Soup|Giblet Soup]]
*[[Cookbook:Gingerbread|Gingerbread]]
*[[Cookbook:Ginny's Toll House Cookies|Ginny's Toll House Cookies]]
*[[Cookbook:Glazed Sweet Potatoes|Glazed Sweet Potatoes]] (or yams)
*[[Cookbook:Goulash|Goulash]] (Hungarian)
*[[Cookbook:Goulash Soup|Goulash Soup]] (Austrian)
*[[Cookbook:Grand Union Bacon|Grand Union Bacon]]
*[[Cookbook:Granola|Granola]]
*[[Cookbook:Hominy Grits|Grits]]
*[[Cookbook:Grilled Cheese Sandwich|Grilled Cheese Sandwich]]
*[[Cookbook:Grilled Peanut Butter Sandwiches|Grilled Peanut Butter Sandwiches]]
*[[Cookbook:Grilled Portobello Mushrooms|Grilled Portobello Mushrooms]]
*[[Cookbook:Grotten Hans|Grotten Hans]]
*[[Cookbook:Guacamole|Guacamole]]
*[[Cookbook:Guacamole Dip|Guacamole Dip]]
*[[Cookbook:Gyoza|Gyoza]] (Japanese, also known as Pan-Fried Dumplings or Potstickers) (p)

==H==
*[[Cookbook:Hard Tack|Hard Tack]]
*[[Cookbook:Herb Bubble Bread|Herb Bubble Bread]]
*[[Cookbook:Hermits|Hermits]] (Chewy molasses-spice cookies)
*[[Cookbook:Herring soup|Herring soup]]
*[[Cookbook:Holland Tea Cakes|Holland Tea Cakes]]
*[[Cookbook:Pizza Vanegas|Home Made Pizza]]
*[[Cookbook:Hominy recipe|Hominy]]
*[[Cookbook:Hominy Grits|Hominy Grits]]
*[[Cookbook:Honey Mustard Salmon|Honey Mustard Salmon]]
*[[Cookbook:Honey Taffy|Honey Taffy]]
*[[Cookbook:Hot and Sour Soup|Hot and Sour Soup]]
*[[Cookbook:Hot and Spicy Dip|Hot and Spicy Dip]] (Vegetarian)
*[[Cookbook:Hot milk cake|Hot Milk Cake]]
*[[Cookbook:Hot Sauce|Hot Sauce]]
*[[Cookbook:Huevos divorciados|Huevos divorciados]] (divorced eggs)
*[[Cookbook:Huevos Rancheros|Huevos Rancheros]] (ranch-style eggs) '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Hummus|Hummus]]

==I==
*[[Cookbook:Italian risotto|Italian risotto]]

==J==
*[[Cookbook:Jamaican Jerk Chicken|Jamaican Jerk Chicken]]
*[[Cookbook:Jamaican Jerk Spice|Jamaican Jerk Spice]]
*[[Cookbook:Jalebi|Jalebi]] (Indian)
*[[Cookbook:Jambalaya|Jambalaya]] (southern USA)
*[[Cookbook:Rainbow Jell-O|Jello, Rainbow]]

==K==
*[[Cookbook:Kal kals|Kal Kals]] (Indian)
*[[Cookbook:Kashmiri Pulao|Kashmiri Pulao]] (Indian)
*[[Cookbook:Keralan vegetable stew|Keralan Vegetable Stew]] (Indian; Vegan)
*[[Cookbook:Khara pongal|Khara Pongal]] (Indian; Vegan)
*[[Cookbook:Kimchi|Kimchi]]
*[[Cookbook:Kiwi and Asian Pear in Lemon Sauce|Kiwi and Asian Pear in Lemon Sauce]]
*[[Cookbook:Koeksisters|Koeksisters]] (South African)
*[[Cookbook:Kovaim|Kovaim]] (Hungarian)
*[[Cookbook:Kroppkakor|Kroppkakor]]
*[[Cookbook:Kung Pao Chicken|Kung Pao Chicken]]

==L==
*[[Cookbook:Lancashire Hotpot|Lancashire Hotpot]]
*[[Cookbook:Lasagne with bean sauce|Lasagne with bean sauce]] (Vegetarian)
*[[Cookbook:Latkes|Latkes]]
*[[Cookbook:Le Tourin|Le Tourin]]
*[[Cookbook:Lemonade|Lemonade]]
*[[Cookbook:Lemon Meringue Pie|Lemon Meringue Pie]]
*[[Cookbook:Lentil soup|Lentil Soup]]
*[[Cookbook:Lettuce Soup|Lettuce soup]]
*[[Cookbook:Limoncello|Limoncello]] (Italian)
*[[Cookbook:Lomo saltado|Lomo saltado]] (Peruvian)
*[[Cookbook:Luciabullar|Luciabullar]]
*[[Cookbook:Louis Dressing|Louis Dressing]]
*[[Cookbook:Loukoumas|Loukoumas]]
*[[Cookbook:Low Country Shrimp and Grits|Low Country Shrimp and Grits]]
*[[Cookbook:Lynn's Veggie Salad|Lynn's Veggie Salad]]

==M==
*[[Cookbook:Macaroni &amp; Nutritional Yeast|Macaroni &amp; Nutritional Yeast]] (Vegan, like Macaroni &amp; Cheese)
*[[Cookbook:Macaroni and Cheese|Macaroni and Cheese]]
*[[Cookbook:Macaroni Salad|Macaroni salad]]
*[[Cookbook:Macho Nachos|Macho Nachos]]
*[[Cookbook:Madeira Honey Cake|Madeira Honey Cake]]
*[[Cookbook:Manhattan Clam Chowder|Manhattan Clam Chowder]] (USA)
*[[Cookbook:Marinara Sauce|Marinara]]
*[[Cookbook:Masala Chai|Masala Chai]] (Indian)
*[[Cookbook:Masaledaar chole|Masaledaar chole]]
*[[Cookbook:Mead|Mead]]
*[[Cookbook:Meatballs|Meatballs]]
**[[Cookbook:Fried Meatballs|Fried]]
**[[Cookbook:Swedish Meatballs|Swedish]]
*[[Cookbook:Meatloaf|Meatloaf]]
*[[Cookbook:Menudo|Menudo]]
*[[Cookbook:Meringata|Meringata]] (Italian)
*[[Cookbook:Mjeddrah|Mjeddrah]] (Lebanese; Vegan), see also: [[Cookbook:Mejadra|Mejadra]]
*[[Cookbook:Microwave Chocolate Pudding|Microwave Chocolate Pudding]]
*[[Cookbook:Microwave Quesdilla|Microwave Quesdilla]]
*[[Cookbook:Microwave Risotto|Microwave Risotto]]
*[[Cookbook:Microwaved Artichoke|Microwaved Artichoke]]
*[[Cookbook:Midwestern Chicken Wings| Midwestern Chicken Wings]] (US)
*[[Cookbook:Milkshake|Milkshake]]
*[[Cookbook:Milk toast|Milk toast]]
*[[Cookbook:Mille Crêpe|Mille Crêpe]]
*[[Cookbook:Mincemeat Tart|Mincemeat Tart]]
*[[Cookbook:Minestrone alla Capucina|Minestrone alla Capucina]]
*[[Cookbook:Minestrone of Rice and Turnips|Minestrone of Rice and Turnips]]
*[[Cookbook:Veal with lima beans|Veal with lima beans]] (Albanian)
*[[Cookbook:Miso Soup|Miso Soup]] (Japanese)
*[[Cookbook:Mocha icing|Mocha Icing]]
*[[Cookbook:Modak|Modak]] (Indian)
*[[Cookbook:Molasses Cookies|Molasses Cookies]]
*[[Cookbook:Molasses Taffy|Molasses Taffy]]
*[[Cookbook:Moqueca de Peixe|Moqueca de Peixe]] (Brazilian)
*[[Cookbook:Moules Mariniere|Moules Mariniere]]
*[[Cookbook:MPT|MPT]]
*[[Cookbook:Müsli|Müsli]]
*[[Cookbook:Mudde|Mudde]] (Indian; Vegan)
*[[Cookbook:Mung Beans and Brown Rice|Mung Beans and Brown Rice]] (Vegan)
*[[Cookbook:Mussels with Potatoes|Mussels with Potatoes]]

==N==
*[[Cookbook:Neapolitan sauce|Neapolitan sauce]]
*[[Cookbook:Neapolitan soup|Neapolitan soup]]
*[[Cookbook:Nachos|Nachos]]
*[[Cookbook:New Mexico Pork Tamales|New Mexico Pork Tamales]]
*[[Cookbook:No-Bake Chocolate Chip Cookie Pie|No-Bake Chocolate Chip Cookie Pie]]
*[[Cookbook:No-Bake Cookies|No-Bake Cookies]]
*[[Cookbook:Not Quite Eggs Benedict|Not Quite Eggs Benedict]]
*[[Cookbook:Nut Roll|Nut Roll]]

==O==
*[[Cookbook:Oatcake|Oatcake]]
*[[Cookbook:Oatmeal Banana Waffle|Oatmeal Banana Waffle]]
*[[Cookbook:Oatmeal Raisin Cookies|Oatmeal Raisin Cookies]]
*[[Cookbook:Raisin Oatmeal Muffins|Oatmeal Raisin Muffins]]
*[[Cookbook:Olive Oil Bread|Olive Oil Bread]]
*[[Cookbook:Øllebrød|Øllebrød]]
*[[Cookbook:Omelet Recipes|Omelet recipes]]
*[[Cookbook:One-Hour Thanksgiving Dinner|One-Hour Thanksgiving Dinner]]
*[[Cookbook:Onion Chutney|Onion Chutney]]
*[[Cookbook:Onion Dip|Onion Dip]]
*[[Cookbook:Onion Soup|Onion Soup]] (French, can be vegetarian)
*[[Cookbook:Orange Hot Chocolate|Orange Hot Chocolate]] (Beverage)
*[[Cookbook:Orange Julius|Orange Julius]]
*[[Cookbook:Orange Sherbet Smoothie|Orange Sherbet Smoothie]] (Beverage)
*[[Cookbook:'Out of Salad Dressing' Salad Dressing|'Out of Salad Dressing' Salad Dressing]] 
*[[Cookbook:Ossobuco Alla Milanese|Ossobuco Alla Milanese]]
*[[Cookbook:How to cook oysters|Oysters]]

==P==
*[[Cookbook:Pad Thai|Pad Thai]] (Thai)
*[[Cookbook:Valencian paella|Paella, Valencian]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Pancake|Pancakes]]
*[[Cookbook:Pancakes (Vegan)|Pancakes]] (vegan)
*[[Cookbook:Panch Puran|Panch Puran]] (Indian spice mixture)
*[[Cookbook:Brown Rice with Other Starches and Vegetables (Pandora's Feast)|Pandora's Feast]]
*[[Cookbook:Papas a la Huancaína|Papas a la Huancaína]] (Peruvian)
*[[Cookbook:Paprika Chicken|Paprika Chicken]] (Hungarian)
*[[Cookbook:Pasta Marinata|Pasta Marinata]]
*[[Cookbook:Pasta Romanov|Pasta Romanov]]
*[[Cookbook:How to cook pasta|Pasta the Italian way]]
*[[Cookbook:Pate Chinois|Pate Chinois]] (Canadian)
*[[Cookbook:Pavlova|Pavlova]] (AUS, NZ)
*[[Cookbook:Peach Cobbler|Peach Cobbler]] (US)
*[[Cookbook:Peanut Brittle|Peanut Brittle]]
*[[Cookbook:Peanut Sauce|Peanut Sauce]] (Thai, Vegetarian)
*[[Cookbook:Pear Pie|Pear Pie]]
*[[Cookbook:Anise Bread (Penia)|Penia Bread]] (Italian)
*[[Cookbook:Penne Pasta With Sausage|Penne Pasta With Sausage]]
*[[Cookbook:Pesto|Pesto]] (Italian, Vegetarian, can be modified to Vegan)
*[[Cookbook:Pickert|Pickert]]
*[[Cookbook:Pico de Gallo|Pico de Gallo]]
*[[Cookbook:Pierogi|Pierogi]]
*[[Cookbook:Pineapple Tarts|Pineapple Tarts]]
*[[Cookbook:Pineapple Teriyaki|Pineapple Teriyaki]]
*[[Cookbook:Pineapple upside-down cake|Pineapple upside-down cake]]
**[[Cookbook:Original Pineapple Upside-Down Cake|Original Pineapple Upside-Down Cake]] (from Dole)
**[[Cookbook:Pineapple Upside-Down Cake in a Skillet|Pineapple Upside-Down Cake in a Skillet]]
**[[Cookbook:Quick and Delicious Pineapple Upside-Down Cake|Quick and Delicious Pineapple Upside-Down Cake]]
*[[Cookbook:Piñon (Spanish Stovetop Pot Pie)|Piñon (Spanish Stovetop Pot Pie)]]
*[[Cookbook:Pizza|Pizza]]
*[[Cookbook:Pizza Sauce|Pizza Sauce]]
*[[Cookbook:Pezzetti di Cavallo|Pezzetti di Cavallo]]
*[[Cookbook:Plank-Grilled Salmon|Plank-Grilled Salmon]]
*[[Cookbook:Po' Boy|Po' Boy Sandwich]]
*[[Cookbook:Polenta|Polenta]]
*[[Cookbook:Pork Pot Pie|Pork Pot Pie]]
*[[Cookbook:Potage Parmentier|Potage Parmentier]]
*[[Cookbook:Potato-Chickpea Curry|Potato-Chickpea Curry]]
*[[Cookbook:Potato recipes|Potato recipes]]
*[[Cookbook:Potato Skins|Potato Skins]]
*[[Cookbook:Potatoes on the Half-Shell|Potatoes on the Half-Shell]]
*[[Cookbook:Pound Cake|Pound Cake]]
*[[Cookbook:Poutine|Poutine]]
*[[Cookbook:Prekmurska gibanica|Prekmurska gibanica]]
*[[Cookbook:Preserved Lemon|Preserved Lemon]]
*[[Cookbook:Pretzel|Pretzel]]
*[[Cookbook:Puliyodarai Quick|Puliyodarai (Quick)]] (Indian; Vegan)
*[[Cookbook:Pulse Chutney|Pulse Chutney]] (Indian; Vegan)
*[[Cookbook:Pumpkin Pie|Pumpkin Pie]] (American, Vegetarian)
*[[Cookbook:Pumpkin Scones|Pumpkin Scones]]
*[[Cookbook:Pupusa|Pupusa]] (Salvadoran)
*[[Cookbook:Purée Mongole|Purée Mongole]]

==Q==
*[[Cookbook:Quesadilla|Quesadilla]]
*[[Cookbook:Queso|Queso]]
*[[Cookbook:Quiche|Quiche]]
*[[Cookbook:Quick Marshmallow Rice Squares|Quick Marshmallow Rice Squares]]

==R==
*[[Cookbook:Potato Casserole (Rakott Krumpli)|Rakott Krumpli]] (Hungarian Potato Casserole)
*[[Cookbook:Rainbow Jell-O|Rainbow Jello]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Raisin Oatmeal Muffins|Raisin Oatmeal Muffins]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Raita|Raita]] (Indian; Side dish or salad) 
*[[Cookbook:Ranch Dressing|Ranch Dressing]]
*[[Cookbook:Ratatouille|Ratatouille]]
*[[Cookbook:Red Chile Sauce|Red Chile Sauce]]
*[[Cookbook:Red Cross Fudge|Red Cross Fudge]]
*[[Cookbook:Red Devils|Red Devils]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Refried Beans|Refried Beans]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Reuben Sandwich|Reuben Sandwich]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Rhubarb Cake|Rhubarb Cake]]
*[[Cookbook:Rhubarb crumble|Rhubarb crumble]]
*[[Cookbook:Rice an' Peas|Rice an' Peas]]
*[[Cookbook:Rice and Beef Soup|Rice and Beef Soup]]
*[[Cookbook:Rice Bubble cake|Rice Bubble cake]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Rice in Fish Broth-Sayyadieh|Rice in Fish Broth-Sayyadieh]] (Lebanese)
*[[Cookbook:Rice Pilaf|Rice Pilaf]]
*[[Cookbook:Rice Pudding|Rice Pudding]]
*[[Cookbook:Ricotta Lasagne|Ricotta Lasagne]]
*[[Cookbook:Rigatoni pasta with Ricotta in Tomato Cream Sauce|Rigatoni pasta with Ricotta in Tomato Cream Sauce]]
*[[Cookbook:Risotto|Risotto]]
*[[Cookbook:Rissoles|Rissoles]]
*[[Cookbook:Roast Chicken on Salt|Roast Chicken on Salt]]
*[[Cookbook:Roasted Brined Turkey|Roasted Brined Turkey]]
*[[Cookbook:Roasted Oysters with Madeira|Roasted Oysters with Madeira]]
*[[Cookbook:Roasted Vegetable Pasta|Roasted Vegetable Pasta]]
*[[Cookbook:Rolls|Rolls]]
*[[Cookbook:Rosemary Bread|Rosemary Bread]]
*[[Cookbook:Rosemary Garlic Baked Potatoes|Rosemary Garlic Baked Potatoes]]
*[[Cookbook:Rosół|Rosół]] (Polish)
*[[Cookbook:Roti|Roti]] (Redirects to [[Cookbook:Chapati|Chapati]]; Indian - '''(p)''')
*[[Cookbook:Roux|Basic Roux]] ([[Cookbook:Cuisine of France|French]], Sauce)
*[[Cookbook:Rhubarb Fool|Rhubarb fool]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Borscht|Russian Cabbage Borscht]] '''(p)'''

==S==
*[[Cookbook:S'more|S'more]]
*[[Cookbook:Saffron Rice|Saffron Rice]] (Indian; Vegan)
*[[Cookbook:Salsa|Salsa]]
*[[Cookbook:Samosa|Samosa]] (Indian; Vegan)
*[[Cookbook:San Francisco style Scallop Ceviche|San Francisco style Scallop Ceviche]]
*[[Cookbook:Saucepan Fudge Crackle Cookies|Saucepan Fudge Crackle Cookies]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Scrambled Eggs|Scrambled Eggs]]
*[[Cookbook:German Style Sweet Mustard (Senf)|Senf]] - German Style Sweet Mustard
*[[Cookbook:Seafood Kebabs with Zhoug Sauce|Seafood Kebabs with Zhoug Sauce]] (Israeli-Yemeni)
*[[Cookbook:Sesame Shrimp Toast|Sesame Shrimp Toast]]
*[[Cookbook:Shakshuka|Shakshuka]]
*[[Cookbook:Sheer khurma|Sheer Khurma]] (Indian)
*[[Cookbook:Shepherd's Pie|Shepherd's Pie]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Silvash Gombotz|Silvash Gombotz]] (Hungarian)
*[[Cookbook:Simple Nachos|Simple Nachos]]
*[[Cookbook:Simple Roasted Oysters|Simple Roasted Oysters]]
*[[Cookbook:Sirniki|Sirniki]] (Russian)
*[[Cookbook:Six Layer Casserole|Six Layer Casserole]]
*[[Cookbook:S'more|S'more]] (US)
*[[Cookbook:Sockerdricka|Sockerdricka]]
*[[Cookbook:Soda Bread|Soda Bread]] (or Irish Brown Bread{?})
*[[Cookbook:Pretzel|Soft Pretzel]]
*[[Cookbook:Sour Cream Dip|Sour Cream Dip]]
*[[Cookbook:Southwest Pasta|Southwest Pasta]]
*[[Cookbook:Southwestern Scramble|Southwestern Scramble]]
*[[Cookbook:Soup with Supplì|Soup with Supplì]]
*[[Cookbook:Soy Protein Bread|Soy Protein Bread]]
*[[Cookbook:Space Cake|Space Cake]]
*[[Cookbook:Spaghetti alla Carbonara|Spaghetti alla Carbonara]]
*[[Cookbook:Spanish Omelet|Spanish Omelet]]
*[[Cookbook:Spiced Pumpkin Soup|Spiced Pumpkin Soup]]
*[[Cookbook:Spicy Chicken Casserole|Spicy Chicken Casserole]]
*[[Cookbook:Spicy feta burger|Spicy feta burger]]
*[[Cookbook:Sprout Salad|Sprout Salad]]
*[[Cookbook:Sponge Cake|Sponge Cake]]
*[[Cookbook:Stargazy Pie|Stargazy Pie]]
*[[Cookbook:Steak tartare|Steak tartare]]
*[[Cookbook:Steamed Artichoke|Steamed Artichoke]]
*[[Cookbook:Steamed Buns with BBQ Pork|Steamed Buns with BBQ Pork]] (China)
*[[Cookbook:Steamed Rice|Steamed rice]]
*[[Cookbook:Stewed dry figs dessert|Stewed dry figs dessert]] (Albanian)
*[[Cookbook:Stewed Oysters|Stewed Oysters]]
*[[Cookbook:Strudel|Strudel]]
*[[Cookbook:Broccoli Stir Fry|Stir Fry, Broccoli]]
*[[Cookbook:Stuffed Mushrooms with Crabmeat|Stuffed Mushrooms with Crabmeat]]  
*[[Cookbook:Stuffed Portabella Mushrooms|Stuffed Portabella Mushrooms]]
*[[Cookbook:Succotash|Succotash]] (US)
*[[Cookbook:Grannie Gilbert's Sugar Cookies|Sugar Cookies, Grannie Gilbert's]]
*[[Cookbook:Sunglow Motel-Cafe Pickle Pie|Sunglow Motel-Cafe Pickle Pie]] (US dessert)
*[[Cookbook:Sunshine Cake|Sunshine Cake]]
*[[Cookbook:Sushi|Sushi]] '''(p)''' (Japan)
*[[Cookbook:Sweet and Sour|Sweet and Sour]]
*[[Cookbook:Sweet Cornbread|Sweet Cornbread]]
*[[Cookbook:Sweet pongal|Sweet Pongal]] (Indian)
*[[Cookbook:Swedish Meatballs|Swedish Meatballs]]
*[[Cookbook:Swiss pudding|Swiss pudding]]

==T==
*[[Cookbook:Tabouli|Tabouli]] (Lebanese; Vegan), see also: [[Cookbook:Tabula|Tabula]]
*[[Cookbook:Tadka dhal|Tadka Dhal]] (Indian; Vegan)
*[[Cookbook:Tahini Goddess Dressing|Tahini Goddess Dressing]] (Vegan)
*[[Cookbook:Tandoori masala|Tandoori Chicken]] 
*[[Cookbook:Tangerine Jelly|Tangerine Jelly]]
*[[Cookbook:Tarbes Salad|Tarbes Salad]]
*[[Cookbook:Tartiflette|Tartiflette]] '''(p)''' (French)
*[[Cookbook:Tater Tot Casserole|Tater Tot Casserole]]
*[[Cookbook:Tea Eggs|Tea Eggs]]
*[[Cookbook:Tempura|Tempura]]
*[[Cookbook:Teriyaki|Teriyaki]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Texas Easy Chili|Texas Easy Chili]]
*[[Cookbook:The Concoction|The Concoction]]
*[[Cookbook:Thousand Island Dressing|Thousand Island Dressing]]
*[[Cookbook:Three Ginger Soup|Three Ginger Soup]]
*[[Cookbook:Tiramisu|Tiramisu]]
*[[Cookbook:Toasted Cheese Sandwich|Toasted Cheese Sandwich]]
*[[Cookbook:Toasted Ravioli|Toasted Ravioli]]
*[[Cookbook:Tofu|Tofu]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Tofu Pancake|Tofu Pancake]]
*[[Cookbook:Tomato Curry|Tomato Curry]]
*[[Cookbook:Tomato Coulis|Tomato Coulis]]
*[[Cookbook:Tomato Pasta|Tomato Pasta]] (Italian; Vegetarian)
*[[Cookbook:Tomato Sauce Piquante|Tomato Sauce Piquante]]
*[[Cookbook:Tomatoes with Cheese Stuffing|Tomato with Cheese Stuffing]]
*[[Cookbook:Tuna Curry|Tuna Curry]]
*[[Cookbook:Tuna Salad|Tuna Salad]]
*[[Cookbook:Turkey Biscuit|Turkey Biscuit]]
*[[Cookbook:Turkey Soup|Turkey Soup]]
*[[Cookbook:Turkey Wrap|Turkey Wrap]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Tomato and Onion Salad|Tomato and Onion Salad]]
*[[Cookbook:Tomato Salad|Tomato Salad]] (Vegetarian; Feel free to change the name)
*[[Cookbook:Tri-colored Autumn Rice Balls|Tri-colored Autumn Rice Balls]]
*[[Cookbook:Turkey and Bacon Salad|Turkey and Bacon Salad]]

==U==
*[[Cookbook:Ukrainian Cornmeal Stuffing (Nachynka)|Ukrainian Cornmeal Stuffing (Nachynka)]]
*[[Cookbook:Ukrainian Cabbage Soup (Kapusniak)|Ukrainian Cabbage Soup (Kapusniak)]]
*[[Cookbook:Umeboshi|Umeboshi (Pickled Japanese plum)]]
*[[Cookbook:Ume-shu|Ume-shu (Japanese plum juice and plum liquor)]]
*[[Cookbook:Upeseru|Upeseru]] (Indian; Vegan)

==V==
*[[Cookbook:Chocolate chip cookies|Valerie's chocolate chip cookies]]
*[[Cookbook:Chili (Vegan)|Chili (Vegan)]]
*[[Cookbook:Vegetable Pie|Vegetable Pie]] 
**[[Cookbook:Ale, Mustard and Winter Vegetable Pie|Ale, Mustard and Winter Vegetable Pie]] (Vegan)
**[[Cookbook:Aubergine and Onion Vegetable Pie|Aubergine and Onion Vegetable Pie]]
*[[Cookbook:Vegetable Stew and Dumplings|Vegetable Stew and Dumplings]] (Vegan)
*[[Cookbook:Vegetarian Gravy|Vegetarian &quot;Bacon&quot; Gravy over Biscuits]] (Vegetarian)
*[[Cookbook:Vegetarian Soft Tacos|Vegetarian Soft Tacos]] (Vegetarian)

==W==
*[[Cookbook:Waldorf Salad|Waldorf Salad]]
*[[Cookbook:Wheat grass juice|Wheat grass juice]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Whipped cream|Whipped cream]]
*[[Cookbook:White Bread|White Bread]]
*[[Cookbook:White Sauce|White Sauce]]
*[[Cookbook:Wiejska|Wiejska]] (Polish pork and veal sausage)
*[[Cookbook:Wild Spinach and Lemon Salad|Wild Spinach and Lemon Salad]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Windsor pudding|Windsor pudding]]
*[[Cookbook:Wonton Soup|Wonton Soup]] '''(p)'''
*[[Cookbook:Wonton Wrapper|Wonton Wrappers]]

==X==

==Y==

*[[Cookbook:Yam casserole|Yam casserole]]
*[[Cookbook:Yorkshire Pudding|Yorkshire Pudding]]
*[[Cookbook:Yorkshire Pudding (Vegan)|Yorkshire Pudding (Vegan)]]
*[[Cookbook:Yogurt Dip|Yogurt Dip]]
*[[Cookbook:Yurvarlak|Yurvarlak]]

==Z==
*[[Cookbook:Zupa Ogórkowa|Zupa Ogórkowa]]
*[[Cookbook:Zuppa Toscana|Zuppa Toscana]]

[[Category:Recipes|*]]

[[it:Libro di cucina/Ricette]]
[[he:ספר מתכונים/מתכונים]]
[[nl:Kookboek/Recepten]]</text>
      <sha1>70q1sncpihx1mnrpqvwikjhm5sxi4m8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Cottage Cheese Eggs</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>3996</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2716823</id>
      <parentid>2716776</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-23T07:11:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/76.22.60.80|76.22.60.80]] ([[User talk:76.22.60.80|talk]]) to last version by QuiteUnusual</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{recipe}} | [[Cookbook:Breakfast|Breakfast]]

==Ingredients==
*2 [[Cookbook:Egg|eggs]]
*2 tablespoons [[Cookbook:Cottage cheese|cottage cheese]] (small curd 4% milkfat)
*1 teaspoon [[Cookbook:Mexican Seasoning|Mexican seasoning]] or [[Cookbook:Chili powder|chili powder]])

==Procedure==

#Preheat a large metal or non-stick [[Cookbook:Skillet|skillet]] to medium heat.
#[[Cookbook:Whisk|Whisk]] eggs and cottage cheese together in a small bowl; place in skillet.
#Sprinkle Mexican seasoning on eggs (to taste).
#As eggs begin to cook, start folding them together, turning as needed, until done cooking.

Serve with or on wheat toast.

[[Category:Breakfast recipes|Cottage Cheese Eggs]]
[[Category:Egg recipes|Cottage Cheese Eggs]]
[[Category:Cheese recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[category:Gluten-free recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>404v7mebdrgcon9shcaq395fygphep1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook talk:Cottage Cheese Eggs</title>
    <ns>103</ns>
    <id>3997</id>
    <revision>
      <id>711672</id>
      <parentid>353570</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-01-08T16:05:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kellen</username>
        <id>4014</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>unlink WP cookbook</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Revision history from [[en:Cottage Cheese Eggs]]

View (previous 50) (next 50) (20 | 50 | 100 | 250 | 500).

Legend: (cur) = difference with current version, (last) = difference with preceding version, M = minor edit

    * (cur) (last) . . M 09:06, 22 Nov 2003 . . Wik
    * (cur) (last) . . 10:28, 15 Nov 2003 . . The Grimm Ripper (Formatting, clarification and an explanation of the term 'Mexican Seasoning')
    * (cur) (last) . . M 02:54, 18 Jan 2003 . . Mintguy
    * (cur) (last) . . M 02:54, 18 Jan 2003 . . Mintguy (de-branding)
    * (cur) (last) . . 02:50, 18 Jan 2003 . . Tarquin (See also the Wikipedia Cookbook.)
    * (cur) (last) . . M 19:36, 17 Jan 2003 . . Maveric149 (- crap)
    * (cur) (last) . . M 19:35, 17 Jan 2003 . . Maveric149 (removed by-line; that is what the page history is for)
    * (cur) (last) . . 19:08, 17 Jan 2003 . . 68.3.146.254
    * (cur) (last) . . 19:08, 17 Jan 2003 . . 68.3.146.254
    * (cur) (last) . . 19:05, 17 Jan 2003 . . 68.3.146.254

View (previous 50) (next 50) (20 | 50 | 100 | 250 | 500).

----
Discussion from [[en:Talk:Cottage Cheese Eggs]]

WTF is this? Sounds revolting, please take out accreditations about your wife and whatnot. Is this copyright somewhere?

:Is there maybe a '''Wikipedia is not a Cookbook'''? -- [[User:Wapcaplet|Wapcaplet]]

:: oddly enough, we have a Wikipedia Cookbook... -- [[User:Tarquin|Tarquin]] 10:51 Jan 18, 2003 (UTC)

:Actually, it's even more revolting than it sounds. [[User:213.107.49.131|213.107.49.131]] 14:35, 11 November 2005 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>95t7g7lphrv1nd71a1g04ub18rhm0tq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Cream Cheese Wontons</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>3998</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2683021</id>
      <parentid>2682017</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-07-21T00:48:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Austncorp</username>
        <id>1540792</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Distinguishing the various types of frying cats.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{recipe}} | [[Cookbook:Appetizers|Appetizers]]

''Makes 16 wontons or 24 small wontons''

==Ingredients==

*1 cup [[Cookbook:Cream Cheese|cream cheese]]
*16 [[Cookbook:Wonton Wrapper|wonton wrapper]]s or 24 egg roll wrappers
*[[Cookbook:Oil|oil]] (for frying)
* [[cookbook:Sweet and Sour|sweet and sour sauce]]

==Procedure==
#Heat oil in a [[cookbook:Deep Fat Frying|deep-fat fryer]] or pour into a deep [[cookbook:skillet|skillet]] on high temperature. [[cookbook:Vegetable Oil|Vegetable oil]] or [[cookbook:Peanut Oil|peanut oil]] works best.
#While oil is heating, lay out as many wrappers as you plan to use. Have a small bowl of water nearby to wet your fingers. Put a small dab of cream cheese in one corner of each wrapper, about 1/2” from the edges. Use about 2 tsp. for egg roll wrappers or 1 tsp. for wonton wrappers. Using your fingers, wet the two edges nearest the cream cheese, then fold the other half down and seal the edges, making a triangle shape. Seal the edges tightly, but try to leave small gaps at the corners so the triangles will not expand so much that they burst.
#Drop several wontons into oil at a time. Turn over when the edges start to brown and cook for another minute or two. Set on paper towels to drain, then serve hot with sweet-and-sour sauce.

[[Category:Appetizer recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:East Asian recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Cream cheese recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Deep fried recipes]]</text>
      <sha1>072pvor4s8eigwmdth2nvdbtc0jvxu0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook talk:Cream Cheese Wontons</title>
    <ns>103</ns>
    <id>3999</id>
    <revision>
      <id>353574</id>
      <parentid>155821</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-02-03T03:57:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Uncle G's major work 'bot</username>
        <id>10904</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[Talk:Cookbook:Cream Cheese Wontons]] moved to [[Cookbook talk:Cream Cheese Wontons]]: COOKBOT: Renaming talk page to Cookbook talk namespace</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Revision history from [[en:Cream Cheese Wontons]]

View (previous 50) (next 50) (20 | 50 | 100 | 250 | 500).

Legend: (cur) = difference with current version, (last) = difference with preceding version, M = minor edit

    * (cur) (last) . . 17:19, 23 Jun 2003 . . Pookel (added recipe)

View (previous 50) (next 50) (20 | 50 | 100 | 250 | 500).

----
Contents of [[en:Talk:Cream Cheese Wontons]]

Recipes?  What's that about? [[User:Nricardo|Brooklyn Nellie]] 17:14, 1 Nov 2003 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>dy3dev420uy7y0yng0zid6g79h8il1u</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Au Jus Sandwich</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4002</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2692239</id>
      <parentid>2678519</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-16T23:16:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Austncorp</username>
        <id>1540792</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Added to featured recipe cat.  This is currently on the list</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{recipe}} | [[Cookbook:Cuisine of the United States]] | [[Cookbook:Cuisine of California|Cuisine of California]]
{{recipesummary
 | category   = Sandwich recipes
 | servings   = 4
 | time       = 6 hours
 | difficulty = 2
 | image      = [[File:French-dip-sandwich.png|250px]]
}}
The '''Au Jus Sandwich''' is also known as '''Roast Beef Au Jus''', and is better known in America as the '''French Dip Sandwich'''. It traces its origins to downtown Los Angeles in either 1908 or 1918, when a local restaurant owner was making a sandwich for a police officer and accidentally dropped a French roll into a pan containing beef drippings. The officer liked the sandwich so much that he brought some friends in the next day for the new invention. From that point on, the Au Jus sandwich went on to become internationally known. Two Los Angeles restaurants claim to have created the sandwich: Philippe The Original and Cole's Pacific Electric (P.E.) Buffet. Both have been in operation since 1908. For more information on the history of the sandwich, see the [[w:French Dip Sandwich|Wikipedia article]].

== Ingredients ==

* 1 tablespoon flour
* 2-3 [[Cookbook:Pound|pounds]] roast or other cut of [[Cookbook:Beef|beef]] 
* 1 beef bullion cube
* 1 can beef [[w:Consommé|consommé]] (~2 cups/10.5 oz), bullion cube equivalent, or additional roast beef
* 1 can [[Cookbook:Onion Soup|French onion soup]] (~2 cups)
* 4 French/sandwich/hoagie rolls
* 1 cup of butter
* 1 can of [[Cookbook:Beer|beer]] (optional)
* spices (e.g., salt, pepper) (optional)

== Procedure ==

# Combine all the ingredients except the rolls in a [[Cookbook:Slow Cooker|slow cooker or crock pot]]. Let the mixture [[Cookbook:Simmer|simmer]] for at least six hours. This step is critical because it makes the meat tender.
# You can either pre-dip the sandwich, or serve with a bowl of meat drippings. Serve beef on split hoagie rolls or miniature French bread loaves. When serving the drippings separately, remove the beef shreds from the juices and serve with a small bowl of meat drippings on the side. Dip the sandwiches in the drippings as you eat.

== Notes, tips, and variations ==

* Bread can be toasted and buttered before adding beef.
* In the original sandwich, the bread was dipped in the juice prior to adding the meat, rather than dipped at the table.
* Other meats can be substituted, including [[Cookbook:Lamb|lamb]], [[Cookbook:Pork|pork]], and [[Cookbook:Turkey|turkey]].
* Try adding [[Cookbook:Cheese|cheese]], [[Cookbook:Horseradish|horseradish]], or [[Cookbook:Mustard|mustard]] to the sandwich.

== Warnings ==

{{Wikipedia|French Dip Sandwich}}
* Always follow the instructions for your [[Cookbook:Slow Cooker|slow cooker or crock pot]].

[[Category:American recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Californian recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Beef recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Sandwich recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Slow cooker recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Featured recipes]]</text>
      <sha1>3d7r9hbl5a6kizvh28p31si0uslzl7j</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook talk:Au Jus Sandwich</title>
    <ns>103</ns>
    <id>4003</id>
    <revision>
      <id>353361</id>
      <parentid>249854</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-02-03T03:25:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Uncle G's major work 'bot</username>
        <id>10904</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[Talk:Cookbook:Au Jus Sandwich]] moved to [[Cookbook talk:Au Jus Sandwich]]: COOKBOT: Renaming talk page to Cookbook talk namespace</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Revision history from [[w:French Dip Sandwiches]]

View (previous 50) (next 50) (20 | 50 | 100 | 250 | 500).

Legend: (cur) = difference with current version, (last) = difference with preceding version, M = minor edit

    * (cur) (last) . . 18:44, 23 Jun 2003 . . Pookel (added recipe)

View (previous 50) (next 50) (20 | 50 | 100 | 250 | 500).
----
This module was the [[Template:Featured recipe|featured recipe]] on the main [[Cookbook]] page from July 10, 2004 - July 27, 2004.


== Move ==

I think this recipe should be moved to something like [[Cookbook:Au Jus Sandwich]], since this has nothing to do with the French and have the French Dip Sandwich part be the secondary name.  Could just be me though.  [[User:Nmontague|Nmontague]] 20:22, 28 August 2005 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>qm4zcune3pheas9zvk57iw1bg631y4d</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:81.101.8.93</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>4015</id>
    <revision>
      <id>155833</id>
      <parentid>13739</parentid>
      <timestamp>2004-02-04T15:38:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>81.101.8.5</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" />
      <sha1>phoiac9h4m842xq45sp7s6u21eteeq1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Reytan</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>4016</id>
    <revision>
      <id>368349</id>
      <parentid>155834</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-02-17T18:33:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Reytan</username>
        <id>493</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">My name is Szymon. I'm a student. I live in [[Wikipedia:pl:Częstochowa|Częstochowa]].&lt;br&gt;
[[pl:Wikipedysta:Reytan]] [[en:User:Reytan]]</text>
      <sha1>krouyzf0lznpyhop3zusc57uqcxtfih</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Empanada</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4021</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2710540</id>
      <parentid>2710151</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-06T09:46:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/208.54.5.152|208.54.5.152]] ([[User talk:208.54.5.152|talk]]) to last version by Austncorp</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{recipe}} | [[Cookbook:South American cuisines|South American cuisines]] | [[Cookbook:Tex-Mex cuisine|Tex-Mex cuisine]]
[[Image:Empanadas.JPG|300px|right|thumb|Peruvian empanadas]]
In Spain, Latin America, and the Philippines, an [[wikipedia:empanada|empanada]] is essentially a stuffed pastry.

The filling usually consists primarily of [[Cookbook:Beef|beef]]. It may also contain [[Cookbook:Ham|ham]] and [[Cookbook:Cheese|cheese]], ''humita'' corn with [[Cookbook:Béchamel Sauce|Béchamel sauce]], or [[Cookbook:Spinach|spinach]]. Fruit is used to create a [[Cookbook:Dessert|dessert]] empanada. Dessert empandas are usually baked, but may be fried. In some [[Cookbook:Cuisine of Argentina|Argentinean]] provinces, empanadas can be spiced with peppers, more akin to those of the rest of South America.

[[Cookbook:Cuisine of Chile|Chilean]] empanadas also use a wheat flour-based dough, but the meat filling is slightly different and often contains more onion. Chileans consider the Argentine filling ''seco'', or dry. Fried empanadas of shrimp/prawns and cheese are a favourite dish of the coastal areas, like Viña del Mar.

In [[Cookbook:Cuisine of Colombia|Colombia]], common empanadas are filled with chopped meat, pieces of potato, and yellow rice, and are eaten with a spicy sauce made of cilantro and ají pepper, stuffed in a corn-based pastry and fried.

It is likely that empanadas are originally from Galicia, [[Cookbook:Cuisine of Spain|Spain]], where they were prepared rather like Cornish pasties as a portable and hearty meal for working people and often filled with leftovers or staple ingredients. Tuna and chicken are varieties still seen in Galicia.

==Wheat Dough Recipe==

===Ingredients===
*1 [[Cookbook:kg|kg]] [[Cookbook:Flour|flour]], approx. 8 cups
*2 [[Cookbook:Egg|egg]]s
*200 [[Cookbook:g|g]] [[Cookbook:Butter|butter]] (or [[Cookbook:Margarine|margarine]]), approx. 1 cup
*1 [[Cookbook:Teaspoon|tsp.]] [[Cookbook:Salt|salt]]
*2-3 [[Cookbook:Cup|cups]] cold water
*[[Cookbook:Olive Oil|olive oil]]
*[[Cookbook:Cornstarch|cornstarch]]

===Procedure===
#Dissolve salt in water.  
#Mix eggs, flour, butter and 1 cup of water to form a dough.  While kneading the dough, gradually add in more water until the dough is soft and stretchy.  If the dough becomes sticky, add more flour.  
#Once the dough is the desired consistency, allow to rest for a couple minutes, then roll it out to a thickness of ~2-3 [[Cookbook:mm|mm]] (1/10 inch).  
#Cut the dough into discs roughly 10-15 [[Cookbook:cm|cm]] (4 to 6 inches) in diameter.

For a flakier crust, before cutting it into discs, lightly coat the dough with olive oil and dust with cornstarch.  Fold the dough in half (with the cornstarch on the inside) and again coat with oil and cornstarch. Fold again and roll out to a thickness of ~2-3 mm (1/10 inch).

==Filling (''Relleno'')==

Every household in Argentina has its own special recipe for empanada filling.  The fillings vary from region to region, with some being sweet and others spicy.  The following is a recipe for a sweet empanada filling typical of those found in the province of Santa Fe.

===Ingredients===
*1 [[Cookbook:kg|kg]] ground [[Cookbook:Beef|beef]]
*1 large [[Cookbook:Onion|onion]]
*2 [[Cookbook:Tablespoon|tblsp]] [[Cookbook:Vegetable Oil|vegetable oil]]
*2 tblsp [[Cookbook:Sugar|sugar]]
*1 1/2 [[Cookbook:Teaspoon|tsp]] [[Cookbook:Pepper|black pepper]]
*1 1/2 tsp [[Cookbook:Paprika|paprika]]
*1 tsp [[Cookbook:Salt|salt]]
*1/2 tsp ground [[Cookbook:Cumin|cumin]] (''comino''), optional. Cumin is very invasive and gives the filling a whole different flavor.
*1/2 tsp ground [[Cookbook:Cinnamon|cinnamon]]
*1/4 tsp [[Cookbook:Nutmeg|nutmeg]]
*1/4 tsp [[Cookbook:Clove|clove]]s
*1/2 [[Cookbook:Cup|cup]] [[Cookbook:Raisin|raisins]]
*[[Cookbook:Green Olives|green olives]] (optional)
*[[Cookbook:Dice|dice]]d hardboiled [[Cookbook:Egg|egg]] (optional)
*diced boiled [[Cookbook:Potato|potato]]es (optional)

===Procedure===
#Dice onion into small pieces and [[Cookbook:Sautéing|sauté]] in vegetable oil in a large [[Cookbook:Frying Pan|frying pan]]. Add and [[Cookbook:Brown|brown]] ground beef.  
#While beef is browning, mix in salt, sugar and spices. 
#Once meat has finished cooking, remove from heat and add raisins.  
#If desired add sliced olives, egg or potatoes.

==Filling (''Pino'')==

&quot;Pino&quot; is the name of the filling used in Chilean empanadas. Much like filling for Argentine empanadas, each Chilean household has their own pino. The one below is like the Argentine but includes more onions and does not have the cinnamon, nutmeg, or cloves, and uses less sugar.

===Ingredients===
*1 [[Cookbook:kg|kg]] ground [[Cookbook:Beef|beef]]
*2 cloves [[Cookbook:Garlic|garlic]]
*3 large [[Cookbook:Onion|onion]]
*2 [[Cookbook:Tablespoon|tblsp]] [[Cookbook:Olive Oil|olive oil]]
*1 tblsp [[Cookbook:Sugar|sugar]]
*1 1/2 [[Cookbook:Teaspoon|tsp]] [[Cookbook:Black Pepper|black pepper]]
*1 1/2 tsp [[Cookbook:Paprika|paprika]]
*1 tsp [[Cookbook:Salt|salt]]
*1/2 tsp ground [[Cookbook:Cumin|cumin]] (''comino'')
*1 [[Cookbook:Bay Leaf|bay leaf]]
*1/2 [[Cookbook:Cup|cup]] [[Cookbook:Raisin|raisins]]
*[[Cookbook:Black Olive|black olives]]
*[[Cookbook:Dice|dice]]d hardboiled [[Cookbook:Egg|egg]]

===Procedure===
#Dice onion into small pieces and [[Cookbook:Sautéing|sauté]] in olive oil in a large [[Cookbook:Frying Pan|frying pan]]. Mince garlic and add to the onions. Add and [[Cookbook:Brown|brown]] ground beef.  
#While beef is browning, mix in salt, sugar, spices and bay leaf. 
#Allow to [[Cookbook:Simmering|simmer]] for about 20 mins for flavours to blend.
#Remove bay leaf, and add olives and raisins.

==Empanada preparation==

#Place 1-2 tablespoons of empanada filling into the center of one of the dough discs (''[[Cookbook:Tapas|tapas]]'').
#If Chilean empanadas are being made add one piece of the diced hardboiled egg next to the filling.
#Wet the outer edge of the tapa with cold water and fold the tapa in half to encase the filling, ensuring there is no air left inside (the wet portion will help the dough stick together, air will burst out when cooked).  
#Holding the empanada in the palm of one hand, with the round edge pointing outwards, pinch and twist over a small (finger-sized) portion of the dough at the top.  Continue pinching and twisting around the outer edge until you reach the bottom of the empanada, so that the open edge is sealed shut.  (you can also use a fork to smash together the lips of the outer edge, but it is not the traditional way and the filling can burst through).  
#Repeat for the remaining filling and dough.
#To cook the empanadas, [[Cookbook:Deep fry|deep fry]] in vegetable oil on medium heat until golden brown.  Alternatively, you can glaze them with butter and cook on a cookie sheet in the oven at [[Cookbook:Oven Temperatures|400 °F]] for 8-10 minutes or until light brown. 
#Allow empanadas to cool and then eat.     

Empanadas are usually eaten with your hands (like a [[Cookbook:Taco|taco]] or [[Cookbook:Burrito|burrito]]).

[[Category:Argentine recipes|Empanada]]
[[Category:Ground beef recipes]]
[[Category:Chilean recipes|Empanada]]
[[Category:Colombian recipes|Empanada]]
[[Category:Tex-Mex recipes]]
[[Category:Pastry recipes|Empanada]]
[[Category:Deep fried recipes]]
[[Category:Main course recipes]]
[[Category:Recipes_with_metric_units|{{PAGENAME}}]]

==Related Recipes==
*[http://www.sooogood.org/recipes/sambusac.html Iraqi empanada recipe and Video Tutorial]
*[http://www.herbivoracious.com/2007/08/block-party-emp.html Cheese-filled appetizer empanadas with Chimichurri sauce]</text>
      <sha1>bk8xxcxfc1c8hw928j4dfjn8av1twum</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Meat Recipes</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4022</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2672574</id>
      <parentid>2672573</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-06-11T23:49:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Austncorp</username>
        <id>1540792</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Minor tweak.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{cooknav}}

[[Image:NCI_meatpile.jpg|right|thumb|320px]]

[[Cookbook:Meat and poultry|Meat and poultry]] recipes in the Cookbook.

In addition to this page, you may also be interested in:

* [[:Cookbook:Meat and poultry|Meat and poultry]], a list of descriptions of types of meat and poultry

* [[:Cookbook:Meat - 1881|Meat - 1881]], meat recipes from the &lt;i&gt;1881 Household Cyclopedia&lt;/i&gt;

* [[:Category:Meat recipes|Meat recipes]], an automatically generated listing of all recipes which, on their individual pages, have been categorized as being meat recipes (excludes poultry)

* [[:Category:Poultry recipes|Poultry recipes]], an automatically generated listing of all recipes which, on their individual pages, have been categorized as being poultry recipes


Also, below, is a list of selected meat and poultry recipes on the Cookbook which contributors have manually added to this page.
__NOTOC__
==[[Cookbook:Bacon|Bacon]]==
*[[Cookbook:Bacon And Egg Pie|Bacon And Egg Pie]]
*[[Cookbook:Bacon and Egg Stuffed Tomatoes|Bacon and Egg Stuffed Tomatoes]]
*[[Cookbook:Bacon Cheese Omelet|Bacon Cheese Omelet]]
*[[Cookbook:Bacon-Wrapped Scallops|Bacon-Wrapped Scallops]]
*[[Cookbook:BLT Sandwich|BLT Sandwich]]

==[[Cookbook:Beef|Beef]]==
*[[Cookbook:Au Jus Sandwich|Au Jus Sandwiches]]
*[[Cookbook:Beef Curry|Beef Curry]]
*[[Cookbook:Beef Jerky|Beef Jerky]]
*[[Cookbook:Beef Stroganoff|Beef Stroganoff]]
*[[Cookbook:Carpetbag Steak|Carpetbag Steak]]
*[[Cookbook:Chicago Sirloin with Cabernet Balsamic Reduction|Chicago Sirloin with Cabernet Balsamic Reduction]]
*[[Cookbook:Corned Beef|Corned Beef]]
*[[Cookbook:Empanada|Empanada]]
*[[Cookbook:Hamburger|Hamburger]]
*[[Cookbook:Meatloaf|Meatloaf]]
*[[Cookbook:Ropa Vieja|Ropa Vieja]]
*[[Cookbook:Steak tartare|Steak tartare]]
*[[Cookbook:Sweet Beef|Sweet beef]]
*[[Cookbook:Taco Meat|Taco Meat]]
*[[Cookbook:Texas Easy Chili|Texas Easy Chili]]
*[[Cookbook:Braised Beef Short Ribs|Braised Beef Short Ribs]]

==[[Cookbook:Chicken|Chicken]]==
*[[Cookbook:California Curry Chicken|California Curry Chicken]]
*[[Cookbook:Chicken Marsala|Chicken Marsala]]
*[[Cookbook:Chicken Pot Pie|Chicken Pot Pie]]
*[[Cookbook:Chicken_Tikka|Chicken Tikka]]
*[[Cookbook:Chicken_Tikka Masala|Chicken Tikka Masala]]
*[[Cookbook:Coq au Vin|Coq au Vin]]
*[[Cookbook:Crispy Chicken|Crispy Chicken]]
*[[Cookbook:Curry Chicken|Curry Chicken]]
*[[Cookbook:Jamaican Chicken Fingers with Honey-Mustard Sauce|Jamaican Chicken Fingers with Honey-Mustard Sauce]]
*[[Cookbook:Jamaican Jerk Chicken|Jamaican Jerk Chicken]]
*[[Cookbook:Kung Pao Chicken|Kung Pao Chicken]]
*[[Cookbook:Marsala Chicken Scallopini|Marsala Chicken Scallopini]]
*[[Cookbook:Midwestern Chicken Wings|Midwestern Chicken Wings]] 
*[[Cookbook:Spicy Chicken Casserole|Spicy Chicken Casserole]]

==[[Cookbook:Lamb|Lamb]]==
*[[Cookbook:Baked Lamb and Yogurt|Baked Lamb and Yogurt]]
*[[Cookbook:Lancashire Hotpot|Lancashire Hotpot]]
*[[Cookbook:Shepherd's Pie|Shepherd's Pie]]

==[[Cookbook:Pork|Pork]]==
*[[Cookbook:Barbecued Spare Ribs|Barbecued Spare Ribs]]
*[[Cookbook:Hongshao Rou|Hongshao Rou]]
*[[Cookbook:Pork Pot Pie|Pork Pot Pie]]
*[[Cookbook:New Mexico Pork Tamales|New Mexico Pork Tamales]] 
*[[Cookbook:Pork Tenderloin with Asparagus and Prosciutto|Pork Tenderloin with Asparagus and Prosciutto]]

==[[Cookbook:Sausage|Sausage]]==
*[[Cookbook:Boerewors|Boerewors]]
*[[Cookbook:Wiejska|Wiejska]]

==[[Cookbook:Turkey|Turkey]]==
*[[Cookbook:Brown Rice with Ground Turkey|Brown Rice with Ground Turkey]]
*[[Cookbook:Jambalaya|Jambalaya]]
*[[Cookbook:One-Hour Thanksgiving Dinner|One-Hour Thanksgiving Dinner]]
*[[Cookbook:Roasted Brined Turkey|Roasted Brined Turkey]]
*[[Cookbook:Turkey Biscuit|Turkey Biscuit]]


[[Category:Cookbook pages with recipe lists]]

[[ja:料理本:肉料理]]</text>
      <sha1>pt5j0quvrj92fh6pjn0uqj1yr402ile</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>