<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Chapters 6-10</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3195</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2063126</id>
      <parentid>1898784</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-03-04T17:17:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Avicennasis</username>
        <id>314063</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WP:AWB/T|Typo fixing]], typos fixed: forbiding → forbidding, omniously → ominously, someting → something using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis}}

=[[Atlas Shrugged]], Part 1, Chapters 6-10=

==CHAPTER SIX: THE NON-COMMERCIAL==

===Section 161: Part 1, Chapter 6, Section 1===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**At the expense of postponing the myriad commercial tasks that must still be done, Hank Rearden reluctantly attends a party thrown by his wife on their wedding anniversary.  Lillian Rearden has invited her circle of friends, which includes the &quot;heart of the country's culture&quot;, the so-called intellectual elite whose opinions are shaping the times.  This is a bit of an insult, though, as the whole country is falling apart.  As these friends speak, we are introduced to the ideas that are causing the collapse of society:
***Dr. Simon Pritchett, the nation's leading philosopher, declares that man is a miserable bit of protoplasm, there are no standards, reason is a superstition, the purpose of philosophy is to prove we can know nothing and that there is no meaning to be found in life, and that when people realize this they will be more &quot;tractable.&quot;
***Balph Eubank is the literary leader of the age (albeit, his books do not sell), declares that suffering is the essence of life, and that free will, achievement, and happiness are laughable concepts of old literature. Plot, he says, is a primitive vulgarity in literature.  Moreover, life is about suffering and frustration, that the only thing to live for is brotherlove.  He later says, that the machine age has destroyed man's humanity, observing that Dagny Taggett runs a railroad rather than practicing the beautiful art of the handloom and bearing children.
***Bertram Scudder, the editor, declares that property rights are a superstition. Moreover, even though he has written an editorial filled with groundless insults against Rearden, he is present at Rearden's party.   
***Claude Slagenhop, president of [[Characters in Atlas_Shrugged|Friends of Global Progress]], declares that need is the only consideration, that an empty belly is a fact, and that this consideration justifies anything, that ideas are just hot air - that right is whatever is good for society, and that the people have the right to seize what they need.
***All of them are introduced in the context of their pro-Equalization of Opportunity Bill views.
**Rearden is shocked by the arrival of Dagny Taggart.  When they talk he is formal and distant, quite unlike the easy manner that characterized their business dealings.  Dagny is taken aback by his manner and is puzzled when he gives her the cold shoulder throughout the evening.  
**Rearden argues with Lillian after he discovers she has invited Bertram Scudder to the party.  Scudder had trashed Rearden in an article.  He cannot understand why she would invite a man who is so hostile to him, and why Lillian seems to enjoy his anger.  He thinks there is some riddle to her character that he should try to understand, but he cannot accept the insanity that would make it possible for her to take pleasure in his fury.  
**Just then, Francisco d'Anconia enters, who will in due time provide Rearden with the answer to this riddle.  A self-made man, Rearden despises Francisco as a worthless profligate who does not know how to deserve the great gift of inherited wealth.  He tells Lillian to &quot;keep that man away from me.&quot;  But Francisco has come for the specific purpose of meeting Rearden, and it is only a matter of time until he corners him.  
**First, though, Francisco circulates, and as Lillian's friends spout out their inanities, he glibly refutes them. When James Taggart confronts him about the failure of the [[Things in Atlas Shrugged|San Sebastian Mines]], Francisco justifies his actions as being in accords with the &quot;virtue&quot; of the times. 
*** Francisco tells a disbelieving and frustrated Taggart that the San Sebastian Mines is the &quot;practical realization of the highest moral order.&quot; Frisco has taken no personal interest, is completely selfless in it; he has eliminated the useless presence of the exploiter-owner. He has hired based on need, rather than ability. Focusing on the livelihood on the employees, he has constructed a settlement for his employees regardless of the place's potential for copper. He has not profited, but has loss - as human beings should, according to the morality of the times, for privation and imperfection are man.
**When Francisco does meet Rearden, their talk is prolific.  Francisco asks why Rearden is willing to support those who are helpless, who never show their gratitude towards him, and who, in fact, openly denounce him as an evil exploiter.  He leaves this an open question.  Rearden at this point of the story is aware that there is something wrong with the world, but does not know what, while Francisco does know.  In this, their first meeting, Francisco tries to place in Rearden's mind the seeds of understanding.  The reader is in the same position as Rearden, and the scene is meant to do the same for the reader, preparing us for the explicit revelation of Galt's Speech.  Francisco leaves Rearden with two ambiguous facts: 
*** They have a terrible weapon against Rearden, and the evidence for this is his unhappiness. 
*** He warns Rearden about the sin of forgiveness. He also asserts that everything Rearden had said to him is true, except his belief that the commercial is evil.  As Francisco leaves him, Rearden is filled with a feeling of wishing him to stay, for, unbeknownst to him, Francisco has given him the beginnings of a moral sanction. 
**Dagny approaches Rearden, attempting to make smalltalk with him by commenting on the debasing nature of his guests, casually stating her belief that celebration should only be done by those who mean it, implying that the drudgery of the milieu is due to their attempt to be more senseless and meaningless than usual. When Rearden denies that they're missing something, a frustrated and confused Dagny leaves, wandering into a group of &quot;respectable women.&quot; She hears a fable of John Galt, as the millionaire who had found Atlantis and lost it all in the process. Francisco is nearby, and he asserts his belief of her story, although Dagny finds it another ludicrous myth.
**As the scene reaches a climax, Halley's music, as remixed into cacaphony by an inept Mort Liddy, permeates the room. Dagny is leaving the party before she loses her composure.  What she has slowly come to realize is that she came to the party hoping to make Rearden aware of her as a woman, not just a business partner.  She was distraught when Rearden responds to her with indifference, and upset when Francisco is the only one who sees her as an object of sexual desire--she is also angered that Francisco would call her appearance a waste, that the heroes would have to succumb to wasting their time in miasmaic milieus such as this party of aimless people.  She has also been pushed to the edge by the inane ramblings of Lillian's guests.  As she walks out, she is pushed over the edge when she hears Mort Liddy's bastardized treatment of her favorite song, [[Things in Atlas Shrugged|Halley's Fourth Concerto]].  At that moment, Dagny hears Lillian denigrating the [[Things in Atlas_Shrugged|bracelet]] of [[Technology in Atlas_Shrugged|Rearden Metal]] that she has been wearing all night as a joke, carefully pronouncing its oddity in the midst of an extravagant display of excessive jewelry.  Lillian jokes that it is supposed to be priceless because it is the first thing ever made from Rearden Metal, but she would gladly exchange it for a common diamond bracelet any time.  In an act of supreme audacity, Dagny removes her diamond bracelet and offers it in exchange, saying that if Lillian is not a coward she would take the offer.  Lillian is taken aback but accepts the trade, not realizing that this act would ultimately undermine her secret weapon against Rearden.  Hank Rearden is furious at Dagny's gall, for the trade symbolizes Lillian's passing her status of &quot;wife&quot; to Dagny.  Rearden's guilt manifests in his acting like the ideal husband throughout the rest of the evening.  (This scene symbolizes Rand's [[Concepts in Atlas_Shrugged|theory of sex]] that will be elucidated in the next section.)

*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Rearden's home in [[Places in Atlas_Shrugged|Philadelphia]].

*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Balph Eubank
**Bertram Scudder
**Betty Pope
**Businessman 1
**Young Woman who blushes when she admits she cannot understand how life is to be lived with nothing but frustraction and suffering
**Claude Slagenhop
**Dagny Taggart
**Gwen Ives
**Hank Rearden
**Hugh Akston
**James Taggart
**John Galt - legend mentioned
**Lillian Rearden
**Mort Liddy
**Mrs. Whitcomb
**Newspaperman 1
**Philip Rearden
**Ragnar Danneskjold
**Simon Pritchett
**Spinster
**Wesley Mouch - mentioned
**Francisco d'Anconia
**Richard Halley - mentioned

*The following bills appear in this section
**Equalization of Opportunity Bill - first mentioned

*The following groups appear in this section
**Friends of Global Progress

*'''Quotations:'''
**&quot;I am in favor of a free economy. A free economy cannot exist without competition. Therefore, men must be forced to compete. Therefore, we must control men in order to force them to be free.&quot; - Dr. Pritchett (127)
**&quot;Plot is a primitive vulgarity in literature&quot; - Balph Eubank
***&quot;Quite so. Just as logic is a primitive vulgarity in philosophy.&quot; - Dr. Pritchett
***&quot;Just as melody is a primitive vulgarity in music.&quot; - Mort Liddy (129)
**&quot;Need is the only consideration. If people are in need, we've got to seize things first and talk about it afterwards.&quot; - Claude Slagenhop (130)
**&quot;But surely you wouldn't want me to do anything about it. My mines and your railroad were seized by the will of the people. You wouldn't want me to oppose the will of the people, would you?&quot; - Francisco d'Anconia to James Taggart (137)
**&quot;Isn't it generally conceded that when you hire a man for a job, it is his need that counts, not his ability? Doesn't everyone believe that in order to get the goods, all you have to do is need them? I have carried out every moral precept of our age, I expected gratitude and a citation of honor. I do not understand why I am being damned.&quot; - Francisco d'Anconia (138)
**&quot;To me, there's only one form of human depravity - the man without a purpose.&quot; - Hank Rearden (142)
***&quot;If one's actions are honest, one does not need the predated confidence of others, only their rational perception. The person who craves a moral blank check of that [the confidence] kind has dishonest intentions.&quot;

----

===Section 162: Part 1, Chapter 6, Section 2===

*'''Plot summary'''
**After the anniversary party, late in the evening, Hank Rearden enters his wife's bedroom with the pretext of having sex with her.  Yet, he is disgusted by Lillian, not caring to admit his defeat by leaving.  Lillian accedes perfunctorily, and starts talking about the party, because talking is what people are supposed to do before making love.  As she jabbers, Rearden wonders why she married him, and recalls the details of their courtship and early marriage.  He thinks about what a torture it has become, pretending that he and Lillian still find their marriage and their sex life rewarding.  By the time she is done talking, Rearden has lost his desire and returns to his own room.  It is his first glimpse of the premise, from Rand's [[Concepts in Atlas Shrugged|sexual theory]], that one's sexual desires are an expression of one's values.

*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Lillian Rearden's bedroom.

*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Hank Rearden
**Lillian Rearden
**Balph Eubank - mentioned
**Bertram Scudder - mentioned
**Dagny Taggart - mentioned
**Francisco d'Anconia - mentioned
**Mrs. Weston - mentioned
**Simon Pritchett - mentioned
**Simons - mentioned

----
----

==CHAPTER SEVEN: THE EXPLOITERS AND THE EXPLOITED==

===Section 171: Part 1, Chapter 7, Section 1===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dagny Taggart visits the construction site of the [[Things in Atlas_Shrugged|Rio Norte Line]] near the [[Things in Atlas_Shrugged|Wyatt oil fields]].  Construction is being supervised by Ben Nealy, who is incompetent but the best contractor Dagny could find.  She meets Ellis Wyatt who indicates he now knows what she is, and that he respects her.  Hank Rearden is also on hand, designing a [[Technology in Atlas_Shrugged|Rearden Metal]] bridge to show off his new metal.  The two get along as they always had, as if the party had never happened.
**Rearden mentions he is flying back east, and Dagny asks if she can go back with him.  He tells her no, because he is flying to Minnesota before heading to New York.  Later at the airfield, Dagny discovers Rearden was lying -- that he did fly straight to New York.  Dagny has no clue why Rearden would flat out lie to her.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Laying of the new [[Things in Atlas_Shrugged|Rio Norte Line]] track near the [[Things in Atlas_Shrugged|Wyatt oil fields]] in [[Places in Atlas_Shrugged|Colorado]].
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Airport attendant 1
**Ben Nealy
**Chief Engineer 2
**Dagny Taggart
**Ellis Wyatt
**Hank Rearden
**Francisco d'Anconia - mentioned
**Dick McNamara - mentioned.
**Mr. Coleman - mentioned.
**Mr. Mowen
**Nat Taggart's son - mentioned.
**Orren Boyle - mentioned
*'''Mysteries'''
**Why Rearden lies to Dagny about his flying directly to New York.  

*'''Quotations:'''
**&quot;muscles - that's all it takes to build anything in the world&quot; - Ben Nealy (154)
**&quot;I never believed that story. I thought by the time the sun was exhausted, men would find a substitute&quot; - Hank Rearden (162)

----

===Section 172: Part 1, Chapter 7, Section 2===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Jim tries to trap Dagny into appearing on a radio program to debate Bertram Scudder by promising she'd be there.  When she discovers that the topic is 'Is Rearden Metal a lethal product of greed?' she bails out of the car, considering such a ridiculous question to be non-debatable.  
**She visits a diner in a slum area and hears more myths about John Galt, including one that he found the [[Fountain of Youth]], but never came back because he couldn't bring it back.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**[[Places in Atlas Shrugged|New York]] City streets 
**A Diner in a run-down section of [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|New York]] City.
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Bertram Scudder - mentioned
**Dagny Taggart
**Jim Taggart
**Various people in the diner
**John Galt - legend mentioned
*'''Quotations:'''
**&quot;You go through life looking for beauty, for greatness, for some sublime achievement, and what do you find? A lof of trick machinery for making upholstered cars - or inner-spring mattresses&quot; - Bum in diner (168)
**&quot;What is morality?&quot; she asked.
&quot;Judgement to determine right and wrong, vision to see the truth, courage to act upon it, dedication to that which is good, integrity to stand by the good at any price.&quot;
----

===Section 173: Part 1, Chapter 7, Section 3===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dr. Potter tries to convince Rearden to take his metal off the market, because it will make the [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|State Science Institute]], a government research facility, look bad for its failure to produce any serious new developments in metallurgy over the past few years.  Rearden refuses, even after Dr. Potter tries to bribe him into selling all rights to the metal to the government.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**[[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Rearden's Office]] at Rearden Steel in Pennsylvania.
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dr. Potter
**Hank Rearden
----

===Section 174: Part 1, Chapter 7, Section 4===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Eddie Willers informs Dagny that the [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|State Science Institute]] has released a sham condemnation of Rearden Metal that has no actual facts as to any problems with the metal, but essentially an innuendo of doubt as to whether it is safe or not.  
**Dagny visits the Institute to try to find out why the statement was made.  The Director of the Institute, Dr. Robert Stadler, refuses to denounce the statement, which was made without his knowledge or consent, even though he knows it to be untrue, because to denounce the statement would destroy the institute, which is all he cares about.  
**Dr. Stadler doesn't really have any concern as to how people are going to think about the false statement his institute has made, because he has essentially lost faith in humanity.  He notes when he was at the [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Patrick Henry University]] he had three star pupils: Francisco d'Anconia who become a worthless playboy; Ragnar Danneskjöld who become a pirate; and a third very promising student who went nowhere.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**[[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Dagny's Office]] at Taggart Transcontinental in [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|New York]] City
**[[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Dr. Stadler's Office]] at the [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|State Science Institute]] in [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|New Hampshire]].
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggart
**Eddie Willers
**Dr. Robert Stadler
**Francisco d'Anconia - mentioned
**Ragnar Danneskjöld - mentioned
*'''Quotations:'''
**&quot;What is happening to people? ...how could they accept it? Didn't they read it? Didn't they see? Don't they think?&quot; - Eddie Willers (175)
**&quot;Men are not open to truth or reason. They cannot be reached by a rational argument. The mind is powerless against them. Yet we have to deal with them. If we want to accomplish anything, we have to deceive them into letting us accomplish it. Or force them. They understand nothing else.&quot; - Dr. Stadler (180)
----

===Section 175: Part 1, Chapter 7, Section 5===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**When Conway refuses to sell to Taggart Transcontinental the rails of his Phoenix-Durango Line and Taggart Transcontinental becomes unable to finish the construction of the [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Rio Norte line]], but is also in the precarious position if they don't finish it the railroad will collapse, Jim Taggart develops a strange case of flu and runs off to the mansion on the old [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Taggart Estate]].  Dagny delivers an ultimatum: she will finish the Rio Norte Line herself, on her own terms, disassociating herself and the publically notorious project from Taggart Transcontinental.  She also demands Eddie Willers be appointed Vice President of Operations in her absence (but it will actually still be her running the company, just nobody will admit it.)  In deciding what to call the new railroad she will operate, when suggesting her own name, Jim feels that her using her own name will suggest there is a connection between the two companies (which everyone will know but nobody will admit).  Flippantly, she suggests calling the line The John Galt line, and decides to use that name.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**[[Places in Atlas Shrugged|The Taggart Estate]] on the [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Hudson River]].
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggart
**Jim Taggart
**Eddie Willers - mentioned
----

===Section 176: Part 1, Chapter 7, Section 6===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dagny spends time selling bonds to finance the construction of the John Galt Line.  Through a desperate display of emotional turmoil, Francisco d'Anconia struggles in his refusal to purchase the bonds for reasons he cannot say.  Dagny reduces herself to begging, hoping that Francisco will have pity for her cause -- he has already thrown away many more millions of dollars in his depraved endeavors.  Tortured that he cannot tell Dagny the full truth behind his refusal, he gives her one crucial hint -- &quot;that contradictions do not exist, whenever you believe you've found one, check your premises.&quot;   He is shocked when he finds out the name of the railroad, because she did it for the effect, that it represents &quot;the hopeless&quot; and suggests that if it is that way, let John Galt come and claim his line.  Francisco's response is, &quot;He will.&quot;
**Dagny visits Rearden to place the &quot;first official order&quot; for Rearden Metal rails for the John Galt Line.  Dagny shows Rearden a list of the Line's bondholders upon request.  The bondholders are the remaining great businesses from [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Colorado]] and other places have put up their own money to have the line built. In contrast to Francisco's tortured refusal to Dagny's begging, Hank Rearden makes an unsolicited offer to buy the largest block of bonds, not because he's offering her charity, but because he knows he will make a big profit off her work. (In their conversation, it is revealed that the bonds are convertible and high-yield.)
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**The [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|John Galt Line]] office in [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|New York]] City.
**[[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Rearden's Office]] at [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Rearden Steel]] in [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Pennsylvania]].
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggart
**Francisco d'Anconia
**Hank Rearden
*'''Quotations:'''
**&quot;Contradictions do not exist. Whenever you think that you are facing a contradiction, check your premises. You will find that one of them is wrong.&quot; - Francisco d'Anconia (188)
----

===Section 177: Part 1, Chapter 7, Section 7===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Rearden's mother - against Rearden's wishes that his family does not visit the mills without asking him first - comes to see him. She wants Rearden to give his skillless brother Philip a job in the steel mill.  Rearden refuses because Philip can't do the work.  His mother tries to manipulate Rearden by saying he only thinks of justice and has no love.  To the astonishment of is mother, Rearden responds saying, &quot;Mother, I'm running a steel plant--not a whorehouse.&quot; His mother retaliates by saying, &quot;What are... your mills--a holy temple of some kind?&quot; Despite her tone, Rearden finds himself agreeing in the sacredness of his mills. His mother attempts to broach up morality, &quot;Don't you ever think of people and of your moral duties?&quot; Rearden says that if he ever gives a job to Philip, he wouldn't be able to face any competent man who needs work and deserves it. His mother then attempts to warp morality with the statement that, &quot;Virtue is the giving of the undeserved.&quot; Rearden ends the meeting with finality, &quot;You don't know what you're saying. I'm not able ever to despise you enough to believe that you mean it.&quot;
**Rearden next has a meeting with Mr. Ward, the honest owner of a family-owned plant that makes harvest equipment. Ward has spent months trying to get a meeting with Rearden -- his goal being to explain the full truth of his situation, that just a little bit of Rearden steel would keep his company running, and he would be ever so grateful. Although his plant is already running at maximum, Rearden agrees to help. Ward's appearance and manner of speech is a stark contrast to Rearden's mother; Ward is fully conscious of his position, that though he owns a successful plant, he is in a position of a beggar, while Rearden's mother, who is the real beggar, acts as if Rearden owes her his success. 
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**The mill floor at [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Rearden Steel]] in [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Pennsylvania]].
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Phillip Rearden - Mentioned
**Rearden's Mother
**Hank Rearden
*'''Quotations:'''
**&quot;That's why I can't talk to you - because you're not human. You have no pity, no feeling for your brother, no compassion for his feelings&quot; - Rearden's Mother (196)
**&quot;If you loved your brother, you'd give him a job he didn't deserve, precisely because he didn't deserve it - that would be true love and kindness and brotherhood. Else what's love for? If a man ''deserves'' a job, there's no virtue in giving it to him. Virtue is the giving of the undeserved.&quot; - Rearden's Mother (197)
----

===Section 178: Part 1, Chapter 7, Section 8===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**The Legislature passes the Equalization of Opportunity bill, which will make Rearden unable to operate the other businesses he has as part of his operation.  Privately, he feels as if a part of his body has been cut out from under him. In thinking about this he realizes a revelation about a new type of bridge development; he calls Dagny to tell her about it.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**[[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Rearden's Office]] at the steel mill in [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Pennsylvania]].
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggart
**Hank Rearden
**Mr. Ward
**Rearden's Secretary Gwen
**Wesley Mouch - Mentioned
*'''Quotations:'''
**&quot;I don't like people who talk too much about how everything they do is just for the sake of others. It's not true, and I don't think it would be right if it were true.&quot; - Mr. Ward (199)
----
----

==CHAPTER EIGHT:THE JOHN GALT LINE==
===Section 181: Part 1, Chapter 8, Section 1===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Eddie is ashamed to see The Worker whom he's known for years, because for the moment, Eddie is Vice President of Operations of Taggart Transcontinental while Dagny has been disentitled of her position, and while it would be an honor for him to be a stooge for her, in some undefined way he feels he is a (greasy) stooge for Jim Taggart.  
**Eddie tells The Worker how Dwight Sanders has taken over the bankrupt United Locomotive Works so they should soon be receiving new Diesel locomotives. He also mentions that Sanders is now crucially important to Taggart Transcontinental -- the new line will need diesels from him.
**While updating The Worker on the strategic needs of the company, Eddie broaches up the truth of the matter: that, all around, the great men are forced to relinquish their status, while lesser men become their stooges. 
**Eddie ends the conversation with the naming of the line -- the John Galt Line. Eddie doesn't like the name, but The Worker does. 
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Employee Cafeteria of Taggart Transcontinental in [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|New York]] City
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Eddie Willers
**The Worker
**Dwight Sanders - mentioned
----

===Section 182: Part 1, Chapter 8, Section 2===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dagny, dead tired after an endless workday at John Galt, Inc., slumps her head down in need of a hero's viaticum: someone she could love, a strong man who would bring out the best in her. As she raises her head, she sees a shadow indicating some person is thinking of walking into her office. The man who is about to enter the office stops at the door, then changes his mind and walks away.  Instead of feeling the fear of a potential intruder, Dagny runs out but finds no one out there; all she can see is the empty street and the entrance to the Taggart Transcontinental Building's train tunnels.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Offices of The [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|John Galt Line]] in [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|New York]] City.
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggart
**Shadow Man 
----

===Section 183: Part 1, Chapter 8, Section 3===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Rearden, required to do so because of the Equalization of Opportunity Law, sells his iron ore mines to a friend of his family, Paul Larkin, and hates having to do so because he sees Larkin as unworthy. When Larkin says that he will always consider the mines to belong to Rearden, that this ownership business is a mere legal triviliaty, Rearden declares one of his foundational principles: &quot;Either I own a property or I don't (208).&quot; The truth of the matter is that, now that he has the official rights, Larkin can do whatever he wants against Rearden. Rearden does not want to be at anyone's mercy. Moreover, unlike Dagny, he will not allow anyone -- least of all Larkin -- to be his stooge. 
**When Rearden sells his coal mines to Ken Dannager, it's almost painless, because he respects Dannager. But, when Dannager offers to sell Rearden coal at cost, Rearden refuses and even offers to pay more for the coal. Rearden wants the small triumph of having defeated the irascible incumbents by paying a worthwhile man the money he's worth -- and since he's paying all the incompetent men the market value, he'd have to hike up the price to meet Dannager's worth.
**Summoned by Rearden for a last-minute business venture, Eddie Willers eats breakfast at Rearden's suite at the Wayne-Falkland Hotel in New York.  Rearden recognizes that Taggart Transcontinental is in financial trouble and cannot pay its first payment coming up in a week for Rearden Metal. On account of his metal, he proposes to give the railroad a six month delay in paying its bills.  Eddie thanks him profusely, but Rearden makes it clear to him that this is not an act of charity -- Rearden has received a lot of money, which he cannot use, from the purchases of his mines and ores from the looters, and giving Taggart Transcontinental a break is a sort of fuel in his fight against the looters.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**[[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Rearden's Office]] at [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Rearden Steel]] in [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Pennsylvania]]
**[[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Ken Dannager's Office]] at [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Dannager Coal Company]] in [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Pennsylvania]]
**Rearden's hotel room in the [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Wayne-Falkland Hotel]] in [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|New York]] City.
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Hank Rearden
**Paul Larkin
**Ken Dannager
**Eddie Willers
**Jim Taggart - mentioned
*'''Quotations:'''
**And the government, he [Rearden] thought suddenly, the money now given to him as payment for his property, where had that come from? Whose work had provided it? (209)
----

===Section 184: Part 1, Chapter 8, Section 4===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Public Opinion - without any evidence or proof - is that the Rearden Metal rail of the John Galt line will break or fail, and that the Rearden Metal bridge will collapse. Jim Taggart informs Dagny he's afraid of public opinion.  Dagny tells him how their ancestor, Nat Taggart, only envied one of his competitors, who said, &quot;The public be damned!&quot; because he wished he had said it.
**A delegate of the Union of Railroad Engineers tries to blackmail Dagny by saying they won't allow her to run trains on the [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|John Galt Line]], whereupon she orders him out of her office.  He changes his tone when she refuses to acceed to his blackmail.  She states she won't make anyone work on the train, she will ask for volunteers.
**In putting out a request for volunteers, Eddie Willers informs Dagny that with the exception of three men who are unreachable, every single engineer on Taggart Transcontinental volunteered to drive the first train on the [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|John Galt Line]].
**Dagny announces casually to a packed audience of railroad engineers that she will also be aboard that first train, but her casual attitude fools no one, they all expected her to go.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**[[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Jim Taggart's Office]] at Taggart Transcontinental in [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|New York]] City
**Offices of the [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|John Galt Line]] in [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|New York]] City
**[[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Eddie Willer's Office]] at Taggart Transcontinental in [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|New York]] City
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggart
**James Taggart
**Eddie Willers
**Union Shop Steward
**Room full of train engineers
----

===Section 185: Part 1, Chapter 8, Section 5===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dagny Holds a press conference to announce the opening of the John Galt Line and welcomes the press to be in [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Cheyenne, Wyoming]] for the first train, which will not be a passenger special with celebrities and politicians, but a freight express, running at an average speed of 100MPH. She also announces she will be aboard the train.
**Hank Rearden is present at the press conference, and announces that he, too, will ride the first train of The John Galt Line.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Offices of the [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|John Galt Line]] in [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|New York]] City
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggart
**Several Reporters
**Hank Rearden
----
===Section 186: Part 1, Chapter 8, Section 6===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dagny and Hank arrive at the station in Cheyenne on July 22nd where the first trip on the John Galt line will begin. Eddie Willers is representing Taggart Transcontinental because Dagny has forbidden Jim to come stating, &quot;If you come, Jim, I'll have you thrown out of your own station. This is one event you're not going to see&quot;
**Many reporters are at the scene. The ebulliance of the moment has torn away their usual disinterested pessimism. Laughingly, in defiance of the doom the media's groundlessly predicted, one photographer exclaims, &quot;Can't you people look doomed, please? I know that's what the editor wants.&quot; One cynical reporter who's had years of success writing the kind of dribble expected and wanted by the media proclaims, &quot;I know what I'd like to be: I wish I could be a man who covers ''news.'' (223)&quot;  Finally, before they take off the pressing question &quot;Who is John Galt?&quot; is asked by a reporter. Dagny turns to him and proclaims &quot;We are!&quot;
**Though the press wants multiple shots to choose from, Eddie Willers refuses to cut the ribbon multiple times for photo opportunities to avoid being a &quot;phony.&quot; In one fell swoop, he cuts the ribbon and orders the driver Pat Logan to &quot;Open her up!&quot; Thus, begins the first ride on the John Galt Line.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**The [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Taggart Station]] in [[Places in Atlas Shrugged|Cheyenne]], Wyoming
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggart
**Hank Rearden
**Pat Logan
**Eddie Willers
**Various reporters
----

===Section 187: Part 1, Chapter 8, Section 7===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dagny and Hank ride the first train on the John Galt line with Pat Logan driving the train at an unprecedented 100 mph. Taggart workers and local townspeople line the sides of the track along the way to celebrate -- and to act as guards of honor. In the blink of an eye, they cross the bridge made of Rearden Metal without any trouble and arrive at Wyatt Junction. Wyatt and other industrialists greet and congratulate Hank and Dagny.
**Hank, Dagny, and Wyatt have dinner together at Wyatt's mansion out in the woods. Wyatt has provided them a sanctuary away from the mindless media that will, doubtlessly, be bandwagoning on the heroes' success they had denied as impossible, just a few hours ago. This is the first time Rearden has seen Wyatt in person -- and Wyatt appears as his true happy self, unmarred by his usual mask of anger. The success of the John Galt Line has made Wyatt boundlessly happy, but his happiness quickly diminishes when his old pessimistic bitterness returns -- that this will not last. 
**Wyatt shows Hank and Dagny to where they will be staying and Hank and Dagny consummate their love for each other. See [[Ayn Rand's Theory of Sex]]
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**The first train of the John Galt Line
**Wyatt Junction
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny
**Hank Rearden
**Pat Logan
**Ellis Wyatt
**Various industrialists
----

==CHAPTER NINE:THE SACRED AND THE PROFANE==
===Section 191: Part 1, Chapter 9, Section 1===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Rearden and Dagny put into words the differing yet similar nature of their &quot;love&quot; for each other. Rearden views the act of sex that he has succumbed to as depraved, yet he needs her, wants it, while Dagny views it as the joy to look forward to, the goal of arduous work. Each of them finds in the other a worthwhile mate to render mutual pleasures to.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Dagny's apartment
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Hank Rearden
**Dagny Taggart
**James Taggart
**Board of Taggart Transcontinental (mentioned)
**Dr. Simon Pritchett (mentioned)
*'''The following quotations appear in this section:'''
**&quot;Nothing's important&quot; - James Taggart (242)
**&quot;I saw pictures of New York and I thought, somebody built those buildings - he didn't just sit and whine that the kitchen was filthy and the roof leaking and the plumbing clogged and it's a goddamn world and ... we were stinking poor and not giving a damn about it. That's what I couldn't take - that they didn't give a damn.&quot; - Cherryl Brooks (245)
**&quot;He didn't do it for any noble purpose, he did it just for his own profit. He's never done anything for any other reason.&quot; - Jim to Cherryl
***&quot;What's wrong with that, Mr. Taggart?&quot; - Cherryl to Jim (246)
**&quot;There are no absolutes - as Dr. Pritchett has proved irrefutably.&quot; - James Taggart (248)
**&quot;Unhappiness is the hallmark of virtue, If a man is unhappy, really, truly unhappy, it means that he is a superior sort of person&quot; - James Taggart (248)
**&quot;The worst thing about people is not the insults they hand out, but the compliments&quot; - Hank Rearden (259)

===Section 192: Part 1, Chapter 9, Section 2===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**James Taggart finds himself wandering down a slum street plagued with a discontent he cannot pinpoint, succumbing to feelings of contempt and disgust in lieu of cogent thoughts. The setting is dark, the weather damp; Taggart has a cold, and he can't find his handkerchief. With the task of purchasing paper tissues and the malice of hoping the store will be out of business soon, he walks into a dime store in the district, the only spot of light in the dark decay of the slum neighborhood. The contrast between the dark decay of the slums that Taggart walks into and the brightness of the dime store sharpens the difference between Brooks and Taggart. Brooks, an innocent salesgirl at the dime store, is naive enough to see in Taggart a genuine hero. Taggart is amused by her ignorance and also drawn to her by it. Moreover, she does not regard him with the secret contempt of fellow looters, who know that Taggart's so-called &quot;greatness&quot; is gained in underhand tricks, rather than genuinely. Having been askew by the media's muckracking of Taggart as one of the supporters of the John Galt Line, she views him as one of the truly heroic. Taggart's true motive, however, is not to deceive himself that he is great. Although a part of him seems to want greatness, as if jealous of Rearden's ability to invent that metal, he wouldn't be happy if he receives that greatness because it's unearned--but he does not know this, as he lets feelings bypass thoughts. Taggart's true motive is feeling the superiority that he has something over her--that he's deceived her. To him, she is a girl with the same spirit of the heroes he despises, and deceiving her, to him, is like putting something over the heroes. When he brings her back home, having resisted the &quot;customary action&quot; of taking advantage of her sexually, she praises him, saying that anyone else would have. Taggart smugly asks if she would have, and Brooks runs away, abashed and ashamed. Taggart is satisfied that he has rendered the feelings of the profane into the sacred spirit Brooks represents.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Dime store in the slums
**James Taggart's living room
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**James Taggart
**Cherryl Brooks (first appearance) 
**Ragnar Danneskjold (mentioned)
**Orren Boyle (mentioned)
**Dr. Floyd Harris (mentioned)
**Dr. Simon Pritchett (mentioned)
*'''The following pieces of [[Literature in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**The Metaphysical Contradictions of the Universe by Dr. Simon Pritchett

===Section 193: Part 1, Chapter 9, Section 3===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**As Dagny and Rearden talk about the aftermath of the success of the John Galt Line, they realize that their love for each other is based on a mutual capitalistic gauge of each other's worth. This scene is in stark juxtaposition to the one before, as unlike Taggart/Brooks, Dagny/Rearden worship each other in a worthwhile pride of mutual strength, while Taggart toys with Brooks' ignorance, letting a faked sense of pride win over his feelings. 
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Philadelphia
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Hank Rearden
**Dagny Taggart
**Francisco D'Anconia (elliptical reference as Dagny's former lover)

===Section 194: Part 1, Chapter 9, Section 4===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**[[Places in Atlas Shrugged|The Quinn Ball Bearing Company]] is yet another company leaving their homestate to join the incipient wealth in Colorado. Mowen complains about how everyone is leaving for Colorado. The low-labor worker explains that it's due to the [[Things in Atlas Shrugged|Equalization of Opportunity Bill]] forbidding others from owning more than one business. Mowen whines about how someone should do something about the world. He likes the worker, as the worker makes him feel safe. The worker states that Mowen wouldn't care what happens to the world. The worker turns out to be Owen Kellogg. 
***Mowen mentions that Wesley Mouch, the man whom James Taggart liked for being reticent, becomes Top-Coordinator of the Bureau of Economic Planning and National Resources.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Quinn Ball Bearing Company of Connecticut
**Amalgamated Switch and Signal Company (mentioned)
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Mr. Mowen
**Owen Kellogg
**Dan Conway (mentioned)
**Orren Boyle (mentioned)
**Wesley Mouch (mentioned)

===Section 195: Part 1, Chapter 9, Section 5===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**The shackles of orthodox depravity that restrain Rearden from his full happiness are beginning to crack, as he lets his love for Dagny push aside the burden of public scandal. He wants Dagny to wear the bracelet of Rearden Metal in public. He also wants to take her on a vacation. This will be their only break, as there is a plethora of business jam-packed into the next three years. 
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Dagny's apartment
**John Galt. Inc. building (briefly)
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggart
**Hank Rearden
**Francisco D'Anconia (mentioned)

===Section 196: Part 1, Chapter 9, Section 6===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**After spending an aimless week of wandering, Rearden confronts Dagny with the characteristic restlessness of the heroes, &quot;Does relaxing have to be purposeless?&quot; In reply, Dagny asks him which factory he wants to visit. They start visiting abandoned factories and ore mines. They come across the Twentieth Century Motor Company. But, the rampant decay around the factory is depressing; moreover, it foreshadows the emotional context in which the world's greatest material treasure is to be found. Dagny finds in the company the broken remnants of a motor that would run on static electricity. While all other valuables have been looted from the factory, the significance of the motor has been heartfallingly disregarded, the re-usable parts of the motor having been torn off. Rearden states the good the motor could have done, implying that all the loot taken away from the company wouldn't have been worth the potential of the motor. Those who had run the company to its ends were not capable of realizing the worth of the motor; their lack of judgment parallels that of the incomptency of the incumbents who now hold power over the world. 
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
** Abandoned ore pit in Michigan
** Anonymous motels in Wisconsin and Michigan
** The Twentieth Century Motor Company
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Hank Rearden
**Dagny Taggart
**Ted Nielsen (mentioned)
**Dwight Sanders (mentioned)
*'''The following pieces of [[Literature in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''


----
----

==CHAPTER TEN:WYATT'S TORCH==
===Section 197: Part 1, Chapter 10, Section 1===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**The clerk of the Hall of Records explains that the Twentieth Century Motor Company had been sold out twice, at the same time. Mark Yonts had used the company as collateral for a loan from an Illinois bank and he had sold it to some South Dakotans. The clerk describes Yonts as not the kind of person who operates things, that he &quot;doesn't want to ''make'' money, only to ''get'' it.&quot; The clerk tells them that Yonts had sold the parts of the factory piece-meal after he bought it and that scavengers from Starnesville probably took everything else to use as kindling. He admits that Yonts bought it from a Mayor Bascom of Rome. When the clerk asks Rearden and Dagny what they're looking for, Rearden replies saying that it is a friend they've lost, a friend who used to work at the factory. 

*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Hall of Records
**Starnesville (mentioned)
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**People's Mortage Company (mentioned)
**Twentieth Century Motor Company (mentioned)
**Mark Yonts (mentioned)
**Dagny Taggart
**Hank Rearden
**Clerk of Hall of Records
**Mayor Bascom of Rome, Wisconsin (mentioned)
*'''The following Quotations appear in this section:'''
**&quot;So it seems like everybody owns the place--and nobody&quot; (Clerk describes state of 20th century motor company)
**&quot;He didn't want to ''make'' money, only to ''get'' it&quot; (Clerk describes Mark Yonts)(273)
----

===Section 198: Part 1, Chapter 10, Section 2===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dagny and Rearden visit Bascom in Rome. Bascom is the type of man who believes that one can only become rich by &quot;cutting corners&quot; and bending laws, and he's open about this, &quot;as if a fellow cheat displaying his shrewdness to his partners in guilt.&quot; Bascom rambles on about how he can't stand a man with principles, and Rearden is forced to have to clue him in with questions. Bascom mentions that he managed to take a few items before he sold it to Mark Yonts--Jed Starnes' mahogany desk and a mermaid shower stall. When Rearden figures out to ask him which bankruptcy sale he bought it from, Bascom finally tells that it was from the Community National Bank, run by Eugene Lawson, the banker with a heart. Bascom implies in passing that much of the poverty is because of the crash of the bank. Rearden again tells him that they are looking for a friend. Bascom replies that it must be a good friend if they would go through all this trouble to find him, &quot;you and the charming lady who is not your wife.&quot;
**Rearden is enraged. But, when Dagny asks Bascom why he thinks so, Bascom tells them that married couples don't look as if they have a bedroom on their minds because &quot;in this world, either you're virtuous or you enjoy yourself. Not both.&quot; 
**When they leave Bascom, Rearden apologizes to Dagny. Dagny, however, tells him to think through the man's explanation, revealing that Dagny knows the fetters that Hank's family has around him. 
**Rearden gets paranoid about sending their engineers down to sift through the remains of the factory for more details of the motor, fearing that others would find out about their furtive romance. Dagny effortlessly bypasses his pessimism saying she'd call her engineers down here to search the factory, saying that she was on vacation. 
**Dagny reaches a long distance phone to call Eddie. Eddie is panicked, his words foreboding, &quot;I think they're planning to kill Colorado.&quot; 

*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Mayor Bascom's office in Rome, Wisconsin
**Long-distance telephone station
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggart
**Hank Rearden
**Mayon Bascom
**Mark Yonts (mentioned)
**Jed Starnes (mentioned)
**Community National Bank (mentioned)
**Eugene Lawson (mentioned)
**Eddie Willers
*'''The following quotations appear in this section:'''
**&quot;No principle ever filled anybody's milk bottle&quot; - Mayor Bascom (275)
**&quot;Don't ever get mad at a man for stating the truth&quot; - Dagny (277)
----

===Section 199: Part 1, Chapter 10, Section 3===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dagny returns to New York. She hides the motor in a vault in an abandoned Taggart tunnel that used to hold an emergency electric generator. This is symbolic of the motor's role in the state of things--it has the potential to power the world in this emergency state.
**The media has muckraked the following: 
***Union of Locomotive Engineers demanding the maximum speed of trains be set at 60 mph. 
***Union of Railway Constructors and Brakemen demand that the trains be reduced to 60 cars. (James Taggart would later argue that because of the massive unemployment, having less cars per train would divide up the work.) 
***The neighboring states of Wyoming, New Mexico, Utah, Arizona demand that the number of trains running in Colorado not to exceed the number of trains run in each of neighboring states. (Parallel: Brother's keeper become State's keeper.)
***Orren Boyle vies for the Preservation of Livelihood Law limiting the production of Rearden Metal to that of the output of other steel mills of equal plant capacity. 
***Mowens demands a Fair Share Law so that every customer of Rearden Metal gets an equal share of it. (Ironically, just a few months ago, he had refused to make switches out of Rearden Metal.)
***Scudder demands for the Public Stability Law forbidding Eastern businesses from moving out of states.
***Wesley Mouch, the Top Co-ordinator of the Bureau for Economic Planning and National Resources makes a bunch of ambiguous statements repeating the phrases &quot;emergency powers&quot; and &quot;unbalanced economy.&quot;
**Dagny reminisces about Eddie's despair and James Taggart's response. Taggart had argued for each of the demands above, albeit each one has the potential to destroy Taggart Transcontinental. When confronted with this, Taggart adamantly states that he &quot;fully intends to protect the interests of Taggart Transcontinental.&quot; Dagny points out that it is impossible if he intends to kill Colorado. Taggart claims there is no need for panic, that Dagny had predicted disaster for the Anti-dog-eat-dog-rule, but it's yet to come. Dagny points out that that was because she saved them! She ominously points out that if she doesn't save them, who will? 
**All this does not seem real to her while underground. Dagny realizes that finding the man who created the motor is more important than anything, albeit the impending legislature may easily stifle her business. 
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Taggart Tunnels
*'''The following pieces of [[Things in Atlas Shrugged|legislature]] are used in this section:'''
** Preservation of Livelihood Law (mentioned)
** Fair Share Law (mentioned)
** Public Stability Law
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Union of Locomotive Engineers (mentioned)
**Union of Railway Constructors and Brakemen (mentioned)
**Wesley Mouch
**Bertram Scudder
**Orren Boyle
**Mr. Mowen
**James Taggart
**Dagny Taggart
**Hank Rearden (mentioned)
**Eddie Willers
*'''The following quotations appear in this section:'''
**&quot;If one of my blast furnaces goes down, will I be able to keep it going by feeding your intention into it?&quot; - Hank Rearden to Paul Larkin (281)
**&quot;The same kind of brain can't do both. Either you're good at running the mills or you're good at running to Washington&quot; The Purchasing Manager to Rearden (283)
**&quot;Lillian, what purpose do you live for?&quot; - Hank
***&quot;What a crude question! No enlightened person would ever ask it.&quot; - Lillian
***&quot;Well, what is it that enlightened people do with thier lives?&quot; - Hank
***&quot;Perhaps they do not attempt to do anything. That is their enlightenment&quot; - Lillian (287)
----

===Section 200: Part 1, Chapter 10, Section 4===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**The section begins with Rearden realizing that he cannot fight both battles: the fight against the incumbent gangs vying for the restrictive laws and the fight against the traditional gangs of ruffians for ore to run his mines. Rearden's purchasing manager would later tell him that he's not the type of man who would win the fight in Washington, that either he's good at running the mills or running to Washington. 
**Larkin, who had bought Rearden's mines c/o The Equalization of Opportunity Bill, has shipped the ore to Boyle instead of Rearden. Moreover, he's using railway transportation instead of lake shipping in order to keep his friendship with Taggart. 
**Rearden has been reduced to furtive bargains with ungainly sources, such as ruffian gangs, to obtain his ore. Rearden finds himself unable to see his own cause as right because he feels guilt for his secret relationship with Dagny. He does not believe in degrees of evil, thus seeing himself as one of the evil ones, he finds himself unable to fully condemn the looters. He would fight as one guilty wretch against the others. But, he finds that it is all worth it because of Dagny. 
**Rearden returns home late. Lillian offers him the duty of a wife, but Rearden, who is now in love with Dagny, is disgusted. Lillian hints at her motive in wanting him--not in the gutter sense. She, like his family, would hold onto him by his sense of duty and guilt, and this is how they are ''having him.'' 
**When Lillian finally leaves, Rearden falls asleep consoled by sexy thoughts of Dagny.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Rearden's Office
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Paul Larkin
**Hank Rearden
**Rearden's Purchasing Manager
----

===Section 201: Part 1, Chapter 10, Section 5===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dagny meets with Eugene Lawson, who is now a member of the Bureau of Economic Planning and National Resources, one of the controllers of the world. Lawson, thinking she's here to leech dirty news from him, states he is not ashamed of his past presidentship of the Community National Bank of Madison.
**Dagny inquires about the Twentieth Century Motor Company, but Lawson claims that whatever or whomever she's searching for would be of less importance than a friendship with Wesley Mouch, which he can obtain for her. Dagny believes that he's wrong, that the man she is looking for is more important than anything. 
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Lawson's office in Bureau
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggart
**Eugene Lawson
**Lee Hunsacker (mentioned)
**Wesley Mouch (mentioned)
*'''The following quotations appear in this section:'''
**&quot;My objective was social progress, human brotherhood and love. Love, Ms. Taggart. That is the key to everything. If men learned to love one another, it would solve all their problems&quot; - Eugene Lawson (290)
**&quot;I can proudly say that in all of my life I have never made a profit!&quot; - Eugene Lawson
***&quot;Mr. Lawson, I think I should let you know that of all the statements a man can make, that is the one I consider most despicable.&quot; - Dagny (292)
----

===Section 202: Part 1, Chapter 10, Section 6===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Hunsacker's tag line is &quot;I never had a chance.&quot; He tells of a life where, from his perspective, he has been massively cheated on all levels--the wealth ''entitled to him'' made impossible because of averse circumstances that seem to reoccur. Hunsacker claims he is the only man who has beaten Midas Mulligan. Upon Mulligan's rejection of a loan to him, Hunsacker had brought his case to court. Hunsacker had appealed to a higher court, when Judge Narrangansett rejected his suit against Mulligan. The higher court reversed Narrangensett's decision. 
**Dagny recalls her memory of Midas Mulligan, a famous banker. He had disappeared, suddenly, without a trace. His company had also liquidated itself suddenly -- every single penny of it liquidated, the company completely wiped out. Narrangansett had disappeared shortly after.
**Dagny recalls Judge Narrangetsett, the ideally impartial judge who is likened to the blind-folded statue of justice. 
**Dagny manages to get the locations of the Starnes heirs from Hunsacker. 
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Hunsacker's squalid home
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Lee Hunsacker
**Dagny Taggart
**Starnes Heirs (mentioned)
**Midas Mulligan (mentioned)
**Judge Narrangetsett (mentioned)
*'''The following Quotations appear in this section:'''
**&quot;Why yes I can,&quot; said Midas Mulligan, when he was asked whether he could name a person more evil than the man with a heart closed to pity. &quot;The man who uses another's pity for him as a weapon.&quot; (294)
**&quot;I didn't have much money to spend on such things as laboratories . . . I had to have a brighter color scheme in my office, and a decent modern bathroom with a stall shower. Furthermore, I spent a lot of money on a new cafeteria and a playroom and rest room for the workers. We had to have morale didn't we?&quot; - Lee Hunsacker (298)
----

===Section 203: Part 1, Chapter 10, Section 7===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Each Starnes heir is akin to a demon of greater evil in hell. They are archetypes of the evil people in the world.
***Eric would kill himself just to hurt others.
***Gerald claims that the factory crashed because it was bad. He represents a man who has reversed the proper metaphysics that it is the men who have brought the factory to its current decrepit state that are bad. 
***Ivy installed the creed of communism as the new company plan. She is the epitome of pure evil, from Dagny's perspective. 
****&quot;From each according to his ability, to each according to his need...&quot;
*****&quot;Rewards were based on need; and the penalties on ability... Those who had not produced as much as the vote said they could were fined... It required men to be motivated, not by personal gain, but by a love for their brothers...&quot;
**Dagny almost murders Ivy, but Ivy gives her a shred of information--of a William Hastings, who had been the chief engineer. 
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Flophouse where Gerald crashes in
**Ivy's stinky bungalow
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Eric Starnes (mentioned)
**Gerald Starnes
**Ivy Starnes
**Dagny Taggart
**Jed Starnes (mentioned)
**William Hastings (mentioned)
----

===Section 204: Part 1, Chapter 10, Section 8===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dagny visits the Hastings' home. Mrs. Hastings answers the door. William had died five years ago. Dagny is crestfallen, but she soon finds that the man who had made the motor still exists somewhere. Mrs. Hastings does not know much of her husband's affairs, except once when she was picking him up she saw him with two other men. One a young man, whom William claimed would upturn the world, and the other a veneraable old man. It is almost a dead end for Dagny, but Mrs. Hastings remembers that she has seen the man at a diner near the Lennox Foundry. 
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**the Hasting's modest home in suburbia
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Lennox Foundry (mentioned)
**William Hastings (mentioned)
**Mrs. Hastings
**Dagny Taggart
----

===Section 205: Part 1, Chapter 10, Section 9===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dagny eats the best burger she's ever had at the diner near Lennox Foundry. She finds from the owner and cook that it'll close in a week, after the foundry closes.
**The owner turns out to be Hugh Akston. He warns her to stop searching for the man who made the motor, that it would be a dead end alley. 
**Dagny leaves, stating that she would still search for him.
**As she boards the train back to civilization, she hears news of the new directives enacted for emergency measures. 
**As the train speeds by Colorado, Dagny screams, seeing that Wyatt's oil fields are ablaze with fire. 
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**diner near Lennox Foundry
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Francisco d'Anconia (mentioned) 
**Ragnar Danneskjold (mentioned) 
**Dagny Taggart
**Hugh Akston
**Dr. Stadler (mentioned)
*'''The following quotations appear in this section:'''
**&quot;If you find it inconceivable that an invention of genius should be abandoned among ruins and that a philosopher should wish to work as a cook in a diner - check your premises. You will find that one of them is wrong.&quot; - Hugh Akston to Dagny (308)
**&quot;I am leaving it as I found it. Take over. It's yours.&quot; - Note left by Ellis Wyatt at the foot of the burning hill of Wyatt Oil.

----

{{Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis}}</text>
      <sha1>tnjqi4qv3mevxd502l29fh9a3u4l6bm</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Section 2</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3196</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2709263</id>
      <parentid>2709257</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-02T00:32:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>108.212.198.13</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Section 253: Part 2, Chapter 5, Section 3 */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis}}

=[[Atlas Shrugged]], Part 2, Chapters 1-5=

==CHAPTER ONE: The Man Who Belonged on Earth==

===Section 211: Part 2, Chapter 1, Section 1===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**While waiting for Dr. Ferris to arrive, Dr. Stadler paces in his office and thinks about the outrageous weather and the Ferris' outrageous book. Stadler is worried about how the book will be received. Although it was not written by him, it was published by the State Science Institute, and whatever notoriety it acquires will inevitably be attributed to him, since his name helps affirm the SSI. He is worried about the philosophy in the book which begins &quot;Thought is a primitive suspicion. Reason is an irrational idea.&quot; After some time Dr. Stadler screams to himself that &quot;I had nothing to do with it!&quot;
**Dr. Ferris arrives one hour late because his car broke down and he &quot;had a hell of a time trying to find someone to fix it.&quot; They briefly talk of the trouble with reclaiming the Wyatt oil fields - the scientists cannot discover the special method Wyatt used. Dr. Ferris had yet to reclaim one drop but has received many large grants from the government. Moreover, he gauges the project's success based on approval from certain incumbents, rather than actual results. Dr. Stadler attempts to ask for actual results, but Ferris tells him he's not interested in practical technological endeavors. Stadler then complains of the lack of heating due to the oil shortage.  Dr. Stadler then asks about Project Xylophone or Project X. Ferris informs him that it is a top secret project that has to do with sound. Stadler then presses Ferris on the book. Ferris is flustered and asks &quot;did you find the text confusing?&quot; Stadler warns of the dangerous message of the book and Ferris shrugs it off. Ferris claims the audience is one that does not want to think and thus will not be troubled by the content. He believes the audience will embrace the books for giving them justification for not thinking.
**Dr. Stadler lets Ferris leave without saying he will denounce the book in public. He fears this threat would not faze Ferris. He begins to feel that his word no longer had any power. 
**His secretary informs him that Dagny is on the line. She asks him to meet with her in New York, and although he does not have an engagement there, he lies so that he can meet her today. He leaves as soon as he can, desperate for another mind of like competence.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Dr. Stadler's office
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dr. Robert Stadler
**Dr. Ferris
**Ellis Wyatt (mentioned)
**Dagny
*'''The following quotations appear in this section:'''
**Excerpts from Why Do You Think You Think by Dr. Floyd Ferris
***&quot;Thought is a primitive suspicion. Reason is an irrational idea.&quot; (316)
***&quot;The more we know, the more we learn that we know nothing&quot; (316)
***&quot;Do not expect consistancy. Everything is a contradiction of everything else. Nothing exists but contradictions.&quot; (317)
***&quot;You cannot be sure of anything&quot; (317)
**&quot;You see, Dr. Stadler, people don't want to think. And the deeper they get into trouble, the less they want to think. But by some sort of instinct, they feel that they ought to and it makes them feel guilty. So they'll bless and follow anyone who gives them justification for not thinking. Anyone who makes a virtue - out of what they know to be sin, their weakness and their guilt.&quot; - Dr. Ferris to Dr. Stadler (322)
*'''The following pieces of [[Literature in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Why Do You Think You Think by Dr. Floyd Ferris
----

===Section 212: Part 2, Chapter 1, Section 2===

*'''Plot summary'''
** While at work, Dagny reminisces the recent events -- the dying companies, and Jim's triumph. Hammonds and Stockton have disappeared, and Dagny has no longer become astonished at this steady disappearance of the producers. Through his friends in Washington, Jim has managed to make all the restrictive legislatures favor Taggart Transcontinental, in some way, usually through forced elimination of competition. Jim has thus grafted large sums of money, &quot;Listed as profit, on the glossy pages of his report to the stockholders, was the money he had not earned--the subsidies for empty trains; and the money he did not own--the sum that should have gone to pay the interest and the retirement of Taggart bonds, the debt which, by the will of Wesley Mouch, he had been permitted not to pay. (327)&quot; He proclaims to Dagny, &quot;'You have always considered money-making as such an important virtue... well, it seems to me that I'm better at it than you are (327).&quot;
** In her conversation with Stadler, Dagny almost finds herself sympathizing with Stadler when he offers a potential scientist to take on the quest of reconstructing the motor. This type, as Stadler admits himself, is the type who would refuse to work for the State Science Institute. The small talk of incompetent railway workers broaches up the rhetorical question, &quot;Who is John Galt?&quot; Stadler mentions that he knew of a John Galt once, &quot;He had such a mind that, had he lived, the whole world would have been talking of him by now (334).&quot; Ominously, Stadler declares that this John Galt must be dead, he ''has to'' -- even though he appears to be lonely for a like mind. 
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Taggart Tunnel
**Dagny's office
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Stadler
**James Taggart
**Dagny Taggart
**John Galt (mentioned)
**incompetent railway workers
**Hammond
**Stockton's sister
----

===Section 213: Part 2, Chapter 1, Section 3===

*'''Plot summary'''
**Rearden receives a mysterious order from the State Science Institute demanding that he sell 10,000 tons of Rearden Metal for a certain Project X. Recent legislation has required that he limit sales to any one customer only 500 tons -- which is clearly an arbitrary sum set by some clueless incumbent, since it's barely enough to lay 3 miles of Taggart rail. Rearden refuses to sell to the State Science Institute. 
** The Wet Nurse, a representative from Washington hired to monitor Rearden's progress, advises Rearden to reconsider, because the source is the government, and that there will be trouble if he rejects it. 
** When a representative of the State Science Institute comes to discuss the issue with Rearden, Rearden states that because it's his creation, he has a moral right to know what use is made of his metal -- regardless of the fact that just a short while ago, the State Science Institute had issued libel against Rearden Metal. The spokesman invokes a bunch of words, stating that it's a great project of great social value, but does not actually state what Project X is. Rearden then gives him the ultimatum -- if you want the metal, just go out and take it like any looter. He can't shoot him, but he will not help make this extortion look moral and legal. The spokesman leaves, ominously stating that he will regret his action. Rearden, however, feels elated. His reaction is a step closer to understanding of his role in the Sanction of the Victim.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Rearden's office
**Rearden Metal
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Rearden
**Rearden's Superintendent
**Miss Ives
**The Wet Nurse
----

===Section 214: Part 2, Chapter 1, Section 4===

*'''Plot summary'''
**Rearden buys Dagny a bunch of expensive luxury items, some of which he can't afford, in hopes of turning her into his own luxury item. Dagny claims the ownership is righteous because he has bought her long ago through his ability and achievement. (This ritual of courtship through merit is typical in Ayn Rand's romances.) Hank admits that he'd never had a reason for spending the money he'd earned -- he'd always envisioned that he'd buy treasures for a woman, but has not found her until now. 
**Dagny tells Rearden of Quentin Daniels and the possibility of finding a mind to revive the motor. She mentions Stadler, and Rearden tells her that Stadler wanted from Dagny a recognition that he's still great, &quot;to juggle reality for him, so that his greatness would remain. (350)&quot;
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Dagny's apartment
**d'Anconia Copper (mentioned)
**Elegant and hidden Inn situated in a knoll in the woods
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Hank Rearden
**Dagny Taggart
**Dr. Stadler (mentioned)
----
----

==CHAPTER TWO: The Aristocracy of Pull==

===Section 221: Part 2, Chapter 2, Section 1===

*'''Plot summary:'''
** Within view of the giant citywide calendar across the street, Dagny reminisces recent events in her office in New York. The giant calendar is a looming presence that haunts her with the thought that her days are limited, and that she's working towards an end it knows, but she does not know. 
** She remembers her meeting with Quintin Daniels, the scientist Stadler suggested to her who might remake the motor. Daniels had refused to work at the State Science Institute on the basis that &quot;Governmental scientific inquiry&quot; is a contradiction in terms. Instead, Daniels works as a night watchman at the Utah Institute of Technology. The low pay is sufficient to pay for his meals, and he has full access to the labs; cut off from the world, he is doing research for his own personal enjoyment. He had refused Dagny's high monthy pay, stating that he would gamble with his own mind and not with her money, uncertain about whether he will succeed in reconstructing the motor. However, when and if he succeeds, he will demand a high percentage of the profits. Daniels' method of payment is both ideally [[w:Objectivism|Objective]] and a tribute to the meaning and worth of money, which is clarified later in this chapter by Francisco's speech at Taggart's wedding. 
** As Dagny leaves the building, the cigarette-collecting old man at the cigar stand stops her, telling her that he'd looked everywhere to try to find the manufacturer of the cigarette with the sign of the dollar she had given him -- though the cigarette is definitely machine made, to the best of his knowledge, &quot;that cigarette was not made anywhere on earth.&quot;

*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Giant citywide calendar &quot;Calendar in the sky beyond the windows of her office (352)&quot;
**Dagny's office
**Corner cigar stand
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Quentin Daniels
**Dagny Taggart
**Dr. Stadler (mentioned)
**Ted Neilsen
**Roger Marsh (mentioned)
**Old man at the cigar stand

===Section 222: Part 2, Chapter 2, Section 2===

*'''Plot summary:'''
** Rearden sits in his room in the Wayne-Falkland Hotel reminiscing his secret meeting with Dannager. He had arranged to give Dannagar enough Rearden Metal to reinforce the roofing of Dannagar's mines from caving in. Dannager is one of the only competent men remaining, and Rearden feels this underhand action is a blow against the looters. Yet, he feels contempt for himself that he is reduced to having to pull a secret meeting for an honest trade.
** After the waiter has cleared away the in-room dinner cart, Lillian bursts into the room. Rearden is surprised at her appearance. Though he does not want to attend the party, Lillian convinces Rearden to attend Taggart's wedding. The fact that she has convinced him to go to the party means that she still holds him as a [[w:Atlas_Shrugged#Sanction_of_the_Victim|victim]]. 
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Wayne-Falkland Hotel
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Lillian Rearden
**Ken Dannager
**Hank Rearden
----

===Section 223: Part 2, Chapter 2, Section 3===

*'''Plot summary:'''
** Cherryl reminisces while she dresses for her wedding under the supervision of a sob sister who had taken Brooks under her protection. Masses of reporters have tailed after Brooks, shooting pictures of her in her slum neighborhood, making Brooks something of a sensation, though to her chagrin. Brooks senses something wrong in the sort of publicity she's receiving -- indeed, Taggart had not only not offered her money to escape the reporters, he had also not hired her an escort to take her to the wedding. The sobsister would be the one to drive Brooks to her wedding.
** Cherryl also recounts her &quot;romance&quot; with Taggart. She had been surprised that Taggart had dropped by her slum room one day, out of the blue. Taggart seems to find in her an unlikely confidante; he spills out his animosity towards his contemporaries, both heroes and looters, while Brooks, understanding little of what he rambles about, innocently assumes the burden of listening to his words. Taggart is drawn to Brooks by her innocence, her hero-worshipping ideals; he feels like he's winning  by making Brooks believe that he is the hero, and Dagny and Rearden the villains.
** The sob sister warns her that &quot;there are people who'll try to hurt you through the good they see in you--knowing that it's the good, needing it and punishing you for it. Don't let it break you when you discover that. (364)&quot; Rather than taking heed from the sobsister's words, Brooks is optimistic that she'd soon be Mrs. James Taggart. 
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
** Cherryl Brooks' Apartment
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
** Cherryl Brooks
** Sob Sister
----

===Section 224: Part 2, Chapter 2, Section 4===

*'''Plot summary:'''
** The section on Cherryl and Jim Taggart's wedding. Jim has received media attention for his democratic wedding--that his bride is one of the poor.
** Bertran Scudder states that &quot;Money is the root of all evil&quot;. To which d'Anconia gives a lengthy rebuttal. 
** Lillian asks Dagny for the bracelet back, but Dagny refuses to return it. Lillian attempts to get Dagny to admit that she's having an affair with Rearden, yet when Dagny gets to the point, Lillian realizes how ludicrous the speculation is. Taking Dagny's side, Rearden asks Lillian to apologize to Dagny.
** In Francisco's speech, he asserts that &quot;money is the root of all good.&quot; Those who believe it is evil have let money be its own value, when the value of money is dependent on its creator and trader. This value can be deprecated into something evil if money is abused through fraudulent trade.
** The party ends when Francisco states to Rearden that he has instigated the crash of D'Anconia Copper Stock, and the party guest leave in a hurry to try and talk to their respective stockbrokers. 
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Wayne-Falkland Hotel
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Cherryl Brooks
**James Taggart
**Dagny Taggart
**Lillian Rearden
**Hank Rearden
**Francisco d'Anconia
**Orren Boyle
**Bertran Scudder
**Paul Larkin
**Eugene Lawson
**Balph Eubank
**Wesley Mouch (mentioned)
**Several unnamed party guests
----


----
----

==CHAPTER THREE: White Blackmail==

===Section 231: Part 2, Chapter 3, Section 1===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Rearden returns to his hotel room in the Wayne-Falkland Hotel after Taggart's party. Lillian announces that she's going to take a train home and complains that she hates d'Anconia, that he could have kept his mouth shut until tomorrow morning, that &quot;he owed a certain duty to his stockholders, didn't he? (392)&quot; The tension in her voice is revealed in a later section.
**Rearden escorts Lillian by taxi to the train station, still dressed in his evening clothes.
**Rearden gives the taxi driver the address of Dagny's apartment, and he goes there immediately after dropping Lillian off.
**At Dagny's apartment, Dagny explains the nature of their love for one another--that it is like a mutual trade. In accords with [[w:Atlas_Shrugged#Theory_of_sex|Ayn Rand's Theory of Sex]], Dagny tells Rearden that that her &quot;way of trading is to know that the joy [he] gives [her] is paid for by the joy [he] gets from [her]--not by [his] suffering or [hers]. (394)&quot; She won't accept sacrifices, and if he asks her to give up her railroad, she'd leave him. She tells him that if the pleasure of one is bought by the pain of the other, then the trade is a fraud. She warns him that, &quot;You don't do it in business, Hank. Don't do it in your own life. (394)&quot; Dagny's words remind Rearden of how different she and Lillian are. 
**Rearden asks Dagny who had been her first lover. Dagny refuses to answer, in part because of Rearden's motive in asking, and instead prompts Rearden to understand his error in envy over her first man, &quot;Do you know your only real guilt? With the greatest capacity for it, you've never learned to enjoy yourself. You've always rejected your own pleasure too easily. You've been willing to bear too much. (395)&quot; Ironically, Rearden mentions that that's exactly what Francisco told him at the party. Dagny asks Rearden what he thinks of Francisco, and Rearden admits that he's the one man to whom he'd entrust his life.
**Rearden apologizes for the insults he threw at Dagny, the morning after at Wyatt's house. 
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Wayne-Falkland Hotel
**Taggart Terminals
**Dagny's apartment
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Lillian Rearden
**Hank Rearden
**Francisco d'Anconia (mentioned)
**taxi driver
**Dagny Taggart
**Ellis Wyatt (mentioned)
----

===Section 232: Part 2, Chapter 3, Section 2===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**The radio announces the stock-market crash of d'Anconia Copper.
**Lillian returned to the Wayne-Falkland hotel earlier the previous evening, and is waiting when he returns in the morning, to discover's Hank's unfaithfulness.  She wants him to move out but will not allow a divorce and loss of her social status.  He refuses to tell her with whom he has been having an affair.
**Dr. Ferris wants Rearden to sell the State Science Institute some Rearden Metal for use in Project X.  He threatens Rearden with the possibility of ten years jail time for illegally selling Rearden Metal to Ken Dannager.  Rearden has Dr. Ferris thrown out of his office.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Wayne-Falkland Hotel, New York City
**Rearden's office at Rearden Steel, Pennsylvania
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Hank Rearden
**Lillian Rearden
**Gwen Ives
**Dr. Ferris
----

===Section 233: Part 2, Chapter 3, Section 3===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Eddie Willers is talking to the Worker in the employee cafeteria of Taggart Transcontinental.  He mentions how Rearden and Ken Dannager were both indicted for the illegal sale of Rearden Metal.  He fears what will happen if Ken Dannager quits and abandones his business, because while Rearden can take it, Dannager is barely hanging by a thread; Dagny has recognized that he is &quot;ready for the destroyer&quot; and a small push might set him off and make him quit.  He also mentions that Dagny wishes she knew who the destroyer was, so that she could kill him, even if it meant she had to die in the process.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Cafeteria of the Taggart Transcontental Building
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Eddie Willers
**The Worker 
----

===Section 234: Part 2, Chapter 3, Section 4===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dagny goes to Pittsburgh to try to see Ken Dannager and prevent him from quitting.  
**There is an unannounced visitor already in the office with Mr. Dannager, who is causing his appointment with her to run late.  This is extremely unusual for Dannager, who is as punctual as a train schedule.
**Dagny is admitted to Dannager's office, only to find that the visitor ahead of her was The Destroyer, who has convinced Dannager to quit.  Dagny tries to beg Dannager not to quit, but is unsuccessful, and he will be leaving that day.  Dannager asks Dagny to tell Hank Rearden that he is probably &quot;the only man I ever loved,&quot; indicating how much he cared about Rearden.
**Dannager tells her not to worry, as she'll be seeing him again soon.  &quot;Oh?  Are you going to return?&quot;  &quot;No.  You're going to join me.&quot;
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Dannager's office at Dannager Coal Company in Pittsburgh.
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggart
**Ken Dannager's Secretary
**Ken Dannager
**Unnamed visitor (The Destroyer, actually turning out to be John Galt).
----

===Section 235: Part 2, Chapter 3, Section 5===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Rearden is sitting in his office thinking about how badly he feels that his friend Ken Dannager has quit.  Dagny's mention to him of Dannager's admission of how much of a friend Rearden was to him has made him realize how much he will miss Dannager. 
**As Rearden prepares to leave the office, he discovers Francisco d'Anconia waiting outside.  Francisco talks to him about whether his actions in making metal or running his business have given him any benefits, or is he simply being punished for his good qualities, and whether any one should continue under the circumstances.  &quot;Mr. Rearden, if you saw Atlas, the giant who holds the world on his shoulders, if you saw that he stood, blood running down his chest, his knees buckling, his arms trembling but still trying to hold the world aloft with the last of his strength, and the greater his effort the heavier the world bore down upon his shoulders&amp;mdash;what would you tell him to do?&quot;  &quot;I... don't know.  What... could he do?  what would ''you'' tell him?&quot; &quot;To shrug.&quot;
**As Francisco tries to speak to Rearden about the nature of his burdens and ask him a question, an alarm sounds as a break-out has occurred at one of the furnaces.  Rearden and Francisco both run out to the furnace, and both begin acting to stop the furnace from overflowing.
**While responding to the break-out, Rearden saves Francisco's life as he almost slips and falls into a pool of molten metal.
**After the crisis is over, Rearden suggests Francisco come work for him in order to appreciate the business he has inherited.  Francisco admits he wishes he could, but he can't.  Rearden asks him to tell him the question he was going to ask.  Francisco admits that it's pointless to ask the question, he already knows the answer.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Rearden's office at the mill
**Mill floor in front of a furnace
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Hank Rearden
**Francisco d'Anconia
**Various mill workers
----

----
----

==CHAPTER FOUR: The Sanction of the Victim==

===Section 241: Part 2, Chapter 4, Section 1===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Rearden's family prepares to celebrate Thanksgiving, but are unhappy that he might end up going to jail over the illegal sale of metal that he and Ken Dannager were indicted over, instead of cooperating with the government.
**Rearden listens to Lillian's condemnation of him, and realizes what she is stating represents a monstrous system where one's own goodwill is used for one's very destruction.
**Lillian says they know what he is thinking, and that's why they are cracking down on him.  He says they don't, and he's going to tell them at his trial.  Phillip criticises Rearden's attitude, saying he thinks he's guilty as hell and finds it contemptible.  Rearden tells him if he talks that way to him again in his house he will throw Phillip out on the street.
**Rearden, disgusted with his family, walks out to go to New York.
**Rearden remembers how the Wet Nurse knew about his deal with Dannager, but never told anyone about it.  
**Rearden goes to Dagny's Apartment in New York, but discovers she's at her office. Rearden goes there and meets Eddie, who tells Rearden that his trial is something he doesn't believe in and even if it's done in the name of the people, he's not one of the people that is represented.  Dagny tells Rearden that if he's sent to jail she'll quit, without any destroyer coming to see her.  Rearden does not think that will happen, and informs Dagny that for the sixty thousand tons of steel they ordered, he is actually going to deliver eighty thousand tons of Rearden Metal, and if anyone finds out, he will make it look like he is the only one to blame, and he doesn't want her to ever admit she knows about it.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Rearden's home
**Rearden's office
**Dagny's apartment
**Dagny's office
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Hank Rearden
**Lillian Rearden
**Phillip Rearden
**Rearden's Mother
**The Wet Nurse
**Eddie Willers
**Dagny Taggart
----

===Section 242: Part 2, Chapter 4, Section 2===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Hank Rearden appears for his trial for illegally selling Rearden Metal.  He is asked to enter a plea in his own defense.  He admits he has no defense because he does not recognize the court's right to try him, as he is not before a tribunal of justice, but, in effect, a kangaroo court, and will not allow them to disguise what they are.  They can rule in whatever fashion they please, since he has no rights and no ability to defend himself, but he will not co-operate in their actions.  If they want him to go to jail, they will have to send armed men to carry him; if they want to impose fines upon him, they will have to seize his property themselves, he will not pay it.  He has done nothing but act honorably in his business, and he will neither accept sacrifices from others nor be sacrificed for others, or be a victim.  &quot;If it is now the belief of my fellow men, who call themselves the public, that their good requires victims, then I say: The public good be damned, I will have no part of it!&quot;  The audience in the courtroom cheers.
**The judges are overwhelmed by Rearden's stand, and choose to fine him $5,000 and suspend sentence.  The audience in the courtroom laughs at them.  
**Rearden tries to understand why people had allowed themselves to accept the doctrines of self-destruction such as what the court had effectively been a part of, and that is the real sentence imposed upon him, to learn why.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Courtroom in Philadelphia
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Hank Rearden
**Dagny Taggart
**Eddie Willers
**Mr. Mowen
**Paul Larkin
**Bertram Scudder
**Lillian Rearden
**Three judges
**Members of the courtroom audience
----

===Section 243: Part 2, Chapter 4, Section 3===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dagny admits to Rearden as a result of the decision in his trial that she will never doubt that right wins in the end.  Lillian chides Rearden over his stand in the trial.
**The Wet nurse asks Rearden a question about his speech: &quot;What's a moral premise?&quot;  &quot;Something you're going to have a lot of trouble with.&quot;  Rearden discovers that his fellow businessmen are unwilling to refuse to be victims, or to stand up for themselves, despite the results that occurred in his own case.  
**Rearden sits in his hotel room, wanting to see Francisco, then realizes he could simply go see him in his suite in the same hotel.  Rearden does so, and discovered Francisco had been listening to Rearden's trial over the radio.  Rearden admits he does not understand why someone with the intelligence and the ability of Francisco has chosen to live as a womanizing wastrel playboy.
**Francisco introduces Rearden to the value theory of sex, that only a neurotic man chases worthless women, and since he isn't a neurotic, it's another reason: to camouflage his actions for a secret purpose of his own.
**Rearden admits that since Francisco has told him a secret, he will tell him one: Rearden has secretly ordered copper from d'Anconia copper in order to fill the order for Taggart Transcontinental's rail, an order that is ten times the size of the one he was indicted for.
**Francisco is furious, reminding Rearden that he had told him never to deal with d'Anconia Copper.  Francisco reaches to use a telephone, but stops himself.  Rearden realizes there is something Francisco has the power to prevent, but it is a power he will not use.  Pained, Francisco swears to Rearden that despite what he is going to find out, he is still Rearden's friend.
**Rearden is informed he will not be receiving the copper, because Ragnar Danneskjold has sunk the d'Anconia ore freighters.
**Rearden later realizes he must stay away from Francisco, lest he kill him on sight.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Rearden's Office
**Rearden's suite at the Wayne-Falkland hotel
**Francisco's suite at the Wayne-Falkland hotel
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Hank Rearden
**Lillian Rearden
**Various businessmen
**Francisco d'Anconia
**Dagny Taggart
**The Wet Nurse
----
----

==CHAPTER FIVE: Account Overdrawn==

===Section 251: Part 2, Chapter 5, Section 1===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Various businesses are closing, affecting other business and often causing them to close in turn.
**The Atlantic Southern bridge over the Mississippi River collapses. After investigation, two other bridges are condemned, leaving the Taggert Bridge as the only train bridge crossing the Mississippi.
**Dagny is at a Taggert Board Meeting. A Mr. Weatherby from the government is there, although his role is unclear. Taggert Transcontinental is becoming a financial disaster. One reason of many is that there are less goods to ship on any given line due to closed businesses, there is no longer an economy of scale. Mr. Weatherby wants a raise in wages and a drop in rates. Dagny responds that she can't make the company profitable any longer.  The Board must close one of the lines in order to use track from one to repair another. They decide to close the John Galt Line for political reasons as opposed to financial ones.
**Leaving, Dagny sees Francisco waiting for her. He knew what would happen and came to help her get past it. They talk about how the world is being run these days, the injustice of it.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
** Taggert Transcontinental
** A diner 

*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
** Dagny Taggert
** Jim Taggert
** Clem Weatherby 
** Francisco d'Anconia
** Danagger's Cousin
** Mr. Quinn (mentioned)
** Lawrence Hammond (mentioned)
** Dwight Sanders (mentioned)
** Ragnar Danneskjöld (mentioned)
** Wesley Mouch (mentioned)
** Bertram Scudder (mentioned)
** Simon Pritchett (mentioned)
** Oren Boyle (mentioned)
** Nathaniel Taggart (mentioned)
** Buzzy Watts (mentioned)
** Chick Morrison (mentioned)
** Tinky Holloway (mentioned)
** Joe Dunphy (mentioned)
** Bud Hazelton (mentioned)
** Kip Chalmers (mentioned)
** Ellis Wyatt (mentioned)
** Andrew Stockton (mentioned)

----

===Section 252: Part 2, Chapter 5, Section 2===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dagny and Hank are in Colorado to buy any machinery that can be salvaged from closed businesses. They leave on the last run of the John Galt line. They hear other passengers quoting various popular sayings of the time, about their needs being important because of that need, about the greed of the industrialists.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**On a Taggert train
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dany Taggert 
**Hank Reardon 
**Ted Neilsen (mentioned)
**Roger Marsh (mentioned)
**Dr. Floyd Ferris (mentioned)
**Dubious Sellers
**various passengers
----

===Section 253: Part 2, Chapter 5, Section 3===

*'''Plot summary:'''
Lillian meets Jim for lunch. He accuses her of double crossing him regarding Hank's behavior at his trial for illegally selling steel. She was supposed to control Hank. She tells him she didn't betray him, she just failed, and she doesn't yet know why.

Lillian decides to meet Hank when his train comes in, but there is no car reserved for anyone named Hank Rearden. She realizes that Hank must be in a car under some other name, and suspects that he is having an affair. This pleases her, as she has been waiting for this moment. She saw that Hank was good and pure and hated him for it. She married him solely to destroy the good in him.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**A fancy restaurant in New York City
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Lillian Rearden
**Jim Taggart
**Mr. Weatherby
**Gwen Ives
**Dagny Taggart (mentioned)
**Hank Rearden (mentioned)
**Wesley Mouch (mentioned)
**Balph Eubanks (mentioned)
----

===Section 254: Part 2, Chapter 5, Section 4===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Lillian confronts Hank at Taggart Terminal. She was hoping that Hank's mistress was a nobody, and is angry to learn that it is Dagny because Dagny is a true threat. Hank confirms the affair but is completely unapologetic, he tells Lillian to either divorce him or let it be. Either way, she is not to speak to him of Dagny again.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**The Taggart Terminal
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Lillian Rearden
**Hank Rearden
**Dagny Taggart

----

{{Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis}}</text>
      <sha1>836ohjr6u1tkcah8negbqvthne4wv20</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Section 2A</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3197</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2709501</id>
      <parentid>2709452</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-02T15:31:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>108.212.198.13</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Section 263: Part 2, Chapter 6, Section 3 */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis}}

=[[Atlas Shrugged]], Part 2, Chapters 6-10=

==CHAPTER SIX: Miracle Metal==

===Section 261: Part 2, Chapter 6, Section 1===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**The Washington gang discuss their problems with revenue &amp; jobs. They decide it is time to move forward with Directive 10-289, which dictates that:
# Workers can't quit
# Businesses can't close for any reason
# Patents and copyrights are to be signed over to the government
# No new inventions are to be allowed
# Businesses will produce the same output as the last year, no more, no less
# Every private citizen will spend the same per year as they did the year before.
# Wages, profits, dividends are frozen as is
# A new Unification Board will be the judge of all disputes
**Fred Kinnan who represents labor insists that the Unification Board be all labor men, and through threats of causing trouble with the workers he gets his way.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Entry
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Mr. Thompson
**Wesley Mouch
**James Taggart
**Orren Boyle
**Dr. Floyd Ferris
**Mr. Weatherby
**Fred Kinnan
**Eugene Lawson
**Others
----

===Section 262: Part 2, Chapter 6, Section 2===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dagny wakes in her office around 9:30am, having worked into the early hours. She learns of Directive 10-289 via a call from Francisco and resigns. She tells Eddie that she'll be at the Taggert cabin in Woodstock, although he is not to tell anyone else.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Dagny's office at Taggert Transcontinental
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggert
**Eddie Willers
**Francisco d'Anconia (via phone)
----

===Section 263: Part 2, Chapter 6, Section 3===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Workers are quitting at Reardon Steel at a slow but steady pace, just disappearing. Dr. Ferris visits Hank without an appointment but Hank sees him. He wants Hank to sign a Gift Certificate giving away his rights to Reardon Steel. He blackmails Hank by threatening to expose Dagny as his mistress, to ruin her reputation. Hank signs.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Hank's office at Reardon Steel
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Hank Reardon
**Gwen Ives
**Dr. Ferris
----
----

==CHAPTER SEVEN: The Moratorium on Brains==

===Section 271: Part 2, Chapter 7, Section 1===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Eddie Willers is in the cafeteria at Taggert Terminal talking to &quot;the anonymous worker&quot;, telling him just about everything. He talks about Dagny quitting and even includes where she is (the Taggert cabin outside Woodstock). He also tells him about the orders to take the extra diesel engine from the mouth of the Taggert Tunnel for Chick Morrison's publicity tour. 
**He tells how Hank Reardon signed over his metal to the government, how Orren Boyle was going to start making it until his mill was blown up by Ragnar.
**The anonymous worker mentions that he will be gone on vacation for a month.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**The cafeteria at Taggert Transcontinental
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Eddie Willers
**The Mysterious Worker
----

===Section 272: Part 2, Chapter 7, Section 2===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Hank Reardon is walking home in the dark from his mills to his apartment in Philidelphia. Ragnar steps out from some bushes to give Hank a bar of gold. He explains that the gold is repayment for money taken from him by force.
**Ragnar says he wants to kill off the idea of Robin Hood, that he himself is the opposite of Robin Hood. Ragnar takes from the (thieving) poor and gives to the (productive) rich.
**He explains that he never attacks private ships. Nor does he attack military vessels because the military is a proper function of government. He attacks looter's ships filled with goods that were taken by force from productive men, or relief ships.
**He explains that he sells the goods for gold, either to some American friends or to black marketeers in the People's States of Europe (who he considers forced into crime by their laws).
**A cop car comes by, looking for Ragnar, the policemen recognize Hank. Instead of turning Ragnar in Hank protects him, telling the police that Ragnar is his bodyguard.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**The road between Reardon Mills and Hank Reardon's apartment
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Hank Reardon
**Ragnar Danneskjold
**A couple cops
----

===Section 273: Part 2, Chapter 7, Section 3===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**A Taggert train loses its diesel engine just short of the Taggert Tunnel in Colorado. Kip Chalmers is on board and demands that a replacement engine be found.
**The spare diesel engine kept by the tunnel for exactly this situation has been ordered elsewhere by the government. The story leads us through the various Taggert personnel who don't want to make a decision. The only engine available is a coal burner. This is very risky because of the fumes and the length of the tunnel. But Kip Chalmers orders it so that he can make it to a big rally. Finally an engineer with a record of safety lapses who is also drunk agrees to drive it.
**The men swapping the engines and switching the tracks know that they are creating a dangerous situation but do nothing to stop the train.
**We are told about some of the people on the train, and why they are worthless. Lastly, the train goes into the tunnel and we know they are going to die.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
** A Taggert Train
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Kip Chalmers
** Various railroad workers
** Various passengers

----
----

==CHAPTER EIGHT: By Our Love==

===Section 281: Part 2, Chapter 8, Section 1===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Having quit her job, Dagny is staying at a cabin on a self imposed vacation, but she is having a hard time enjoying herself, she feels the urge to work. Francisco visits, telling her that he is destroying d'Anconia Copper to avoid giving it to the looters.
**On the radio, Dagny hears of the Taggert Tunnel disaster, she immediately leaves for New York to deal with it.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**The Taggert Cabin
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggert
**Francisco d'Anconia
----

===Section 282: Part 2, Chapter 8, Section 2===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**At Taggert Transcontinental, Jim is contemplating his resignation over the tunnel disaster. He yells at Eddie to tell him where Dagny is, which Eddie refuses to do. Dagny shows up, and starts planning how to deal with the disaster. Wesley Mouch calls from Washington full of promises. Dagny calls Hank to let him know she is back. He tells her about the &quot;Gift Certificate&quot;, signing over Reardon Metal to the government.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Taggert Transcontinental
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Jim Taggert
**Eddie Willers
**Dagny Taggert
**Hank Reardon(via phone)
----
----

==CHAPTER NINE: The Face Without Pain or Fear or Guilt==

===Section 291: Part 2, Chapter 9, Section 1===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dagny wakes in her apartment, feels for the first time that her work is pointless. Francisco visits, essentially admits that he is with &quot;the destroyer&quot;. Hank shows up and is angry that Francisco is there and slaps him. Francisco leaves without fighting back. Dagny gets letter from Quentin Daniels that he will no longer work for her on the motor. He will keep working, but plans to keep any discoveries he might make to himself. Dagny arranges to take the Taggert Comet to see Daniels to convince him to continue.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggert's apartment
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggert
**Francisco d'Anconia
**Hank Reardon
----

===Section 292: Part 2, Chapter 9, Section 2===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Eddie Willers is at Dagny's apartment getting instructions while she packs. He sees a man's robe with the initials H.R. and realizes that she is having an affair with Hank. He feels jealous and realizes that he loves her. 
**Later he goes to the company cafeteria and meets the anonymous worker. Eddie tells him about Quentin, and about Hank. The worker excuses himself.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggert's apartment
**The cafeteria at Taggert Terminal
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Eddie Willers
**Dagny Taggert
**The Anonymous Worker
----
----

==CHAPTER TEN: The Sign of the Dollar==

===Section 2A1: Part 2, Chapter 10, Section 1===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dagny is on the Comet train heading out West. She meets a &quot;bum&quot; hiding in the vestibule of her car who used to be a skilled lathe operator. He once worked at the 20th Century Motor Company. He described the &quot;new plan&quot; put into place 12 years ago by the children of the company founder after his death. It was based on the idea of &quot;to each according to his need, from each according to his ability&quot;. He was there at the company meeting when John Galt said, &quot;I will stop the motor of the world&quot;. As their company started to fail, the bum and his coworkers started the phrase &quot;Who is John Galt&quot; to express hopelessness.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**A Taggert train
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggert
**Owen Kellogg
----

===Section 2A2: Part 2, Chapter 10, Section 2===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dagny wakes to find that the train has stopped. She find that Owen Kellog is on the train. They walk up the tracks to find an emergency phone and she arranges for a new crew. She walks to a small nearby airport and buys a plane. She flies to Afton to see Quentin Daniels, to convince him to continue working on the motor for her. When she lands, the airport staff member tells her that Quentin Daniels just left in the plane that took off as she landed. She follows that plane, back to Colorado. She encounters a strange phenomenom that stalls her engine, and she goes down in a crash landing.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**A Taggert train
**An airport
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggert
** Owen Kellogg
----
----

{{Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis}}</text>
      <sha1>94ybdnze5g2h068t6eaiczt82egrykc</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Section 3</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3198</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2489518</id>
      <parentid>2487009</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-02-19T15:32:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>199.4.21.2</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Section 331: Part 3, Chapter 3, Section 1 */ Project X has a 100-mile radius, not a 100-mile diameter.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis}}

=[[Atlas Shrugged]], Part 3, Chapters 1-5=

==CHAPTER ONE: Atlantis==

===Section 311: Part 3, Chapter 1, Section 1===

*'''Plot summary:'''
*Dagny is unconscious from crashing her plane in the Colorado Valley. When she wakes up, she is shocked to discover John Galt beside her. She soon finds out that the industrialists who have disappeared now live and work in the Colorado Valley. Some of these industrialists include: Midas Mulligan, Ellis Wyatt and Richard Halley. Galt talks to Dagny and shows her around this new place, while showing her around this place he takes her to where the motor is kept in which everyone is looking for.

*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**The Colorado Valley
***Dr. Akston’s home
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggart
**John Galt
**Hugh Akston
**Midas Mulligan
**Dr. Hendricks
**Quentin Daniels
**Dwight Sanders
**Dick McNamara
**Ellis Wyatt
**Ted Nielsen (mentioned as lumberjack)
**Roger Marsh (mentioned as cabbage tycoon)
**Andrew Stockton
**Ken Danagger
**Richard Halley (mentioned)
**Judge Narragansett

*'''Mysteries:'''
** “I swear by my life, and my love of it, that I will never live for the sake of another man, nor ask another man to live for mine.” John Galt tells Dagny that quote is a secret and he doesn’t mind telling it to her because he knows that she “won’t pronounce those words until you [Dagny] mean them the way I intended them to be meant.” How did he intend for it to be meant?

&lt;!--[[User:24.63.187.228|24.63.187.228]] 17:31, 16 November 2005 (UTC)Tayla Polia and Kaitlyn Cargill (added a little to it)--&gt;
----

===Section 312: Part 3, Chapter 1, Section 2===


*'''Plot summary:'''
*Dagny goes to dinner at Midas Mulligans house where Galt and the others explain to her that they are all on strike
. At the end of dinner, Dagny goes home with John Galt and spends the night at his house in “a room he never intended her to occupy”.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
** The Colorado Valley
***Midas Mulligan’s home
***John Galt’s home
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggart
**John Galt
**Midas Mulligan
**Ellis Wyatt
**Ken Danagger
**Hugh Akston
**Dr. Hendricks
**Quentin Daniels
**Richard Halley
**Judge Narragansett
*'''Mysteries:'''
**Is John Galt a labor worker for Taggart Transcontinental?
**Why does John Galt say to Dagny, “This is the room I never intended you to occupy”. but then let her sleep there?
&lt;!--[[User:24.63.187.228|24.63.187.228]] 17:33, 16 November 2005 (UTC)Tayla Polia--&gt;

----
----

==CHAPTER TWO: The Utopia of Greed==

===Section 321: Part 3, Chapter 2, Section 1===

*'''Plot summary:'''
*Dagny has breakfast with John Galt and Ragnar Danneskjold. She learns that Danneskjold is married to Kay Ludlow and that they were married four years ago by Judge Narragansett. She also talks with John Galt about how long she plans to stay in the Colorado Valley and John tells her he has already decided she will stay for one month. 
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggart
**John Galt
**Ragnar Danneskjold
**Kay Ludlow (mentioned)
&lt;!--[[User:24.63.187.228|24.63.187.228]] 17:33, 16 November 2005 (UTC)Tayla Polia--&gt;

===Section 322: Part 3, Chapter 2, Section 2===
*'''Plot summary:'''
*Owen Kellogg tells Dagny that everyone in the “outside world” thought she was dead. Dagny also thought about Hank Rearden a few times, but those thoughts and feelings went away every time she saw John Galts face. Francisco tells Dagny how much he loves her and will always love her.
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggart
**John Galt
**Owen Kellogg
**Francisco d’Anconia
*'''Mysteries:'''
**Why do Dagny’s feelings about Hank Rearden go away as soon as she sees John Galt?
&lt;!--[[User:24.63.187.228|24.63.187.228]] 17:33, 16 November 2005 (UTC)Tayla Polia--&gt;

===Section 323: Part 3, Chapter 2, Section 3===
*'''Plot summary:'''
*Francisco talks to Dagny about the “rebirth of d’Anconia Copper”. He tells her that to start this “rebirth” he needs to start out again here in he Colorado Valley, so he bought land from Midas to start. Dagny realizes that she is in love with John Galt and that he has everything she is looking for.
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Francisco d’Anconia
**Dagny Taggart
**John Galt
&lt;!--[[User:24.63.187.228|24.63.187.228]] 17:43, 16 November 2005 (UTC)Tayla Polia--&gt;

===Section 324: Part 3, Chapter 2, Section 4===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dagny speaks with various residents of Galt's Gulch:  Richard Halley and Kay Ludlow explain their opinions on art, music, and stage performance.  An unnamed mother describes raising her two sons as a &quot;profession&quot;.  Dr. Akston reminisces about teaching the young John, Francisco, and Ragnar at university.
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Richard Halley
**Dagny Taggart
**Kay Ludlow
**The Wife and children of Dick McNamara
**Hugh Akston
**John Galt
**Francisco d’Anconia
**Ragnar Danneskjold

===Section 325: Part 3, Chapter 2, Section 5===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Francisco takes Dagny and John Galt to see the first d’Anconia mine of Galt's Gulch.  Later, a small private plane is seen flying search patterns over the Gulch, though the community remains hidden by the giant holographic ray screen.  The plane eventually moves on.  Dagny anxiously presumes the pilot is Hank Rearden, searching for the wreckage of her own missing aircraft.
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggart
**Francisco d’Anconia
**John Galt
**Hank Rearden
**''Minor appearances:''
***Lawrence Hammond
***Dwight Sanders

===Section 326: Part 3, Chapter 2, Section 6===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dagny decides to return to the &quot;outside world&quot; to save her railroad.  Galt announces he will follow, though remain hidden, watching and waiting for Dagny's decision to return.  Mulligan, Akston, and Francisco voice disagreement with Galt's decision to leave, citing the dangers of the collapsing society outside, but they also voice respect for his choice.
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggart
**John Galt
**Midas Mulligan
**Hugh Akston
**Francisco d’Anconia

===Section 327: Part 3, Chapter 2, Section 7===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Galt flies Dagny, blindfolded, back to the &quot;outside world&quot;.
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggart
**John Galt

----
----

==CHAPTER THREE: Anti-Greed==

===Section 331: Part 3, Chapter 3, Section 1===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dr. Stadler is ordered to Iowa by Dr. Ferris. There he witnesses a demonstration of the new weapon, &quot;Project X&quot;. It is based on sound waves and has a range of 100 miles, using principles discovered by Dr. Stadler.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**At Project X, in Iowa, about 50 miles west of the Mississippi River.
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dr. Stadler
**Mr. Thompson
**Dr. Ferris
**Wesley Mouch
**Dr. Simon Pritchett
----

===Section 332: Part 3, Chapter 3, Section 2===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dagny, having left Galt's Gulch, returns to New York City. She speaks to Hank.
**She returns to her office, where she meets Cuffy Miegs, the Unification Director and learns of the Railroad Unification Plan.
**They want her to appear on the radio show of Bertrum Scudder, to say that she endorses the actions of the government, their directives. She refuses.
**Dagny is visited by Lillian Reardon, who tells Dagny that she knows about her affair with Hank, and blackmails Dagny into appearing on the radio show. She also tells Dagny that Hank signed over Reardon Metal for the same reason, to keep the affair quiet, and that is was she, Lillian, who told authorities about the affair. Lillian takes pleasure in the thought that she took Reardon Metal away from Hank.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**The streets of New York City
**Taggert Terminal, Dagny's office.
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggert
**Jim Taggert
**Eddie Willers
**Cuffy Meigs
**Lillian Reardon
----

===Section 333: Part 3, Chapter 3, Section 3===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dagny makes her appearance on the Bertrum Scudder radio show. She short circuits the blackmail by announcing her affair with Hank on the air. Then she tells the listeners that Hank only signed the Gift Certificate due to the blackmail, and that Directive 10-289 is horrible.
**Chaos breaks out and Dagny leaves the radio station, returning to her apartment. There she finds Hank, who tells her he loves her. She tells him she doesn't love him anymore, that she love someone else, John Galt, &quot;the destroyer&quot;. Hank says that he already knows, because on the radio she spoke of him only in the past tense. He says he is ok with it. She also tells Hank that John invented the motor.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Radio station
**Dagny's apartment
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggert
**Bertram Scudder
**Jim Taggert
**Lillian Reardon
**Chick Morrison
**Hank Reardon

----
----

==CHAPTER FOUR: Anti-Life==

===Section 341: Part 3, Chapter 4, Section 1===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**A long conversation between Jim Taggert and his wife Cheryl. She married Jim because she admired Taggert Transcontinental and thought he was the brilliant mind running it, thought he was a great man. A year after the marriage, she now understands that Dagny runs Taggert and that Jim is a looter.
**Jim tells her about the upcoming deal wherein on Sept 2nd, Chile will nationalize d'Anconia Copper. Chile will appoint a new company &quot;Interneighborly Amity and Development Corporation&quot; to run all the industrial properties of South America. Jim and his buddies are going to sell their shares of d'Anconia Copper and invest in &quot;Interneighborly Amity and Development Corporation&quot;, thereby become very much richer.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Jim and Cheryl Taggert's apartment
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Jim Taggert
**Cheryl Taggert

----
===Section 342: Part 3, Chapter 4, Section 2===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Cheryl visits Dagny and apologizes for insulting Dagny at her wedding and Jim's wedding. They part on good terms.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggert's apartment
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggert
**Cheryl Taggert

----

===Section 343: Part 3, Chapter 4, Section 3===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Lillian Reardon visits Jim Taggert. She spends some time complaining about Hank. Jim mentions the impending September 2nd nationalization. Jim and Lillian go to bed together.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Jim and Cheryl Taggert's apartment
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Jim Taggert
**Lillian Reardon

----

===Section 344: Part 3, Chapter 4, Section 4===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Cheryl comes home, hears the noise of Jim and Lillian from behind the closed door. She and Jim fight, she leaves. She commits suicide, jumping off a bridge.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Jim and Cheryl Taggert's apartment
**The streets of New York
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Cheryl Taggert
**Jim Taggert

----
----

==CHAPTER FIVE: Their Brothers' Keepers==

===Section 351: Part 3, Chapter 5, Section 1===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dagny is aware that all of the Taggert supplies are being stolen, by men who only recently started working for Taggert. Also, her trains are being re-routed without her control. Government men have authority to commandeer trains and they take bribes to send trains on special runs.
**In Jim's office, he complains that she is supposed to keep the company running regardless of the looting. She says she can't, and won't.
**The Argentinian government tries to nationalize d'Anconia Mines, but at the time of the announcement, all the mines and all d'Anconia facilities worldwide (ports, warehouses, ships, etc.) blow up.
**Dagny meets Hank at a restaurant. Once there she mentions her problems with the trains being diverted. He mentioned that his mill is running at full capacity. Other restaurant goers are complaining about the copper shortage. Through a window, she sees the big city calendar change days at midnight, only to show a message from Francisco, &quot;You asked for it&quot;. Hank laughs to see it.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Taggert Terminal
**A restaurant in New York City
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggert
**Jim Taggert
**Hank Reardon

----

===Section 352: Part 3, Chapter 5, Section 2===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**The copper mines in Montana themselves need copper wire to repair machinery so that at least some copper can be produced. Dagny sends them half of what she has in Minnesota.
**Reardon's brother Philip comes to ask for a job, although really he was told go be a spy at the mills for the Washington gang.
**The Wet Nurse asks Reardon for a job, wants to quit his government post. He mentions that he has a degree in metallurgy, but that it isn't worth anything. Reardon explains that the government won't let him go, that he has to stay at his present job.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Taggert Terminal
**Reardon mills
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggert
**Jim Taggert
**Eddie Willers
**Hank Reardon
**Philip Reardon
**The Wet Nurse

----

===Section 353: Part 3, Chapter 5, Section 3===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**People are becoming desperate for various supplies and are begging Dagny to find these supplies for them. A soy bean project in Louisiana advocated by Ma Chalmers the socialist is brought up. 
**Cuffy Meigs is mentioned as a looter and a racketeer.
**Wheat production is concentrated in Minnesota. However much of the wheat harvest in Minnesota winds up left to rot. Almost half of the trains had been diverted to the new harvest of soy beans. But the soy beans had been reaped too early and were unfit to eat. The desperate story of trying to find as many train cars for Minnesota is described, as well as the efforts of farmers to transport their harvest to the grain elevators in other ways. The road network is in disrepair as are the farmers' cars and trucks, so few make it. Other farmers riot, burning government builders and even their own farms. 
**Whatever crop there may be next year will be much smaller with so many farmers dead and so many farms destroyed.
**And as for this year, large portions of the nation's population will be starving to death by Spring.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Minnesota: at the local Taggert terminal, grain elevators, farms, and roads.
**Taggert Transcontinental 
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Various farmers and Taggert employees

----

===Section 354: Part 3, Chapter 5, Section 4===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Jim asks Dagny to attend a dinner with the Washington gang. They are deciding whether to shut down Taggert's Minnesota line, deciding between Minnesota and the western part of the country.
**Dagny tells them they must shut down Taggert's lines to the west. She says to let agriculture go back to manual labor but that they must save the Eastern seaboard and its industry. She says that if the industrial base is destroyed, it will take centuries to rebuild it.
**Cuffy Meigs pushes to keep trains running to the west, because there is still plenty to loot there. He says Minnesota is milked dry so they should abandon Minnesota.
**The signaling system at Taggert Terminal breaks down. Dagny leaves the dinner to attend to it. She arranges the loan of a repair person from her competitor, but in the meantime organizes a large number of men with lanterns into a manual signaling system. One of these men is John Galt. She talks to him for a while, then he leaves to go be a human lamppost.

*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**A restaurant at the Wayne-Falklands Hotel
**Taggert Terminal
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggert
**Jim Taggert
**Wesley Mouch
**Dr. Ferris
**Cuffy Meigs
**John Galt

----
----

{{Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis}}</text>
      <sha1>fds5au30kkvj6z6ildgji3slwxu2kjo</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Section 3A</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3199</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2598774</id>
      <parentid>2597927</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-01-06T21:25:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Recent Runes</username>
        <id>66908</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Section 371: Part 3, Chapter 7, Section 1 */ spelling</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis}}

=[[Atlas Shrugged]], Part 3, Chapters 6-10=

==CHAPTER SIX: The Concerto of Deliverance==

===Section 361: Part 3, Chapter 6, Section 1===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Hank finds out that the Steel Workers Union went to the Unificiation Board to demand a raise, and was denied. The mood in the mill becomes tense and there are some minor altercations. Hank finds it odd that he has had no part in any of this.
**Hank is informed that there was a hearing about a tax issue, that he was found guilty, and that all his assets are frozen. He decides to do nothing. Then he is informed that it was all a mistake and will be rectified, although it will take a little time. He is asked to go to New York the evening of Nov 4th, which he agrees to. He knows there is a trap in all that has been happening, but does not yet see it.
**His mother calls and asks to see him, insists that he come before going to New York. When he gets there, he finds that his mother has had Lillian living there as well. They beg him for money, he says he doesn't presently have any. He realizes that they hate him and want to destroy him. They let slip that they are worried that he will drop out. He realizes that Lillian only married him in order to try and break him, to corrupt him. They all want him to take care of them and try to use guilt and scorn to motivate him. But he realizes that they have just been using him, and tells them that he no longer cares about any of them, or what happens to them, and leaves.
**In New York, he sees the Washington gang, who try to flatter him. They reveal their intentions for a Steel Unification Plan. Basically, they want him to hand over his profits to Orren Boyle, to run his mill at a loss and to put the last of his wealth into the mill. They want what he has left, and do not think beyond the present to the time when Hank will be broke. They just assume that Hank will figure something out, that he will save them all. Hank leaves.
**On the way home, he comes to the mill. He finds a staged riot in progress. It was supposed to happen while he was still in New York, except that Hank left earlier than planned. The Washington gang wanted it to look like his workers were very unhappy and mistreated. But his workers defended the mill in an armed battle. One of Hank's furnace supervisors saw what was coming, got the workers ready and directed the battle. The Wet Nurse was part of the gang's plan but wouldn't go along so they shot him. As Hank tried to enter the mill via a back way, he finds The Wet Nurse, who has finally figured things out just as he is dying in Hank's arms. Hank enters the mill and is attacked by some stray thugs but is saved. It was the furnace supervisor who saved Hank, and who turns out to be Francisco. Hank is finally ready to hear what Francisco has to say.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Hank Reardon's apartment, in Philedelphia
**Hank Reardon's house (where his mother and brother live)
**The Wayne-Falkland Hotel in New York
**Reardon Mills
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Hank Reardon
**Hank Reardon's mother
**Philip Reardon, Hank's brother
**Lillian Reardon
**Mr. Thompson
**Dr. Ferris
**Tinky Holloway
**Jim Taggart
**Claude Slagonhop
**The Wet Nurse
**The mill supervisor
**Francisco d'Anconio
----

===Section 362: Part 3, Chapter 6, Section 2===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Entry
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Entry
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Entry
----
----
==CHAPTER SEVEN: &quot;This is John Galt Speaking&quot;==

===Section 371: Part 3, Chapter 7, Section 1===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**In a panic, Jim wakes Dagny at her apartment to tell her that Hank is gone, as are the top people at his mill. And the news is out. Dagny notes that people notice his absence more than they ever noticed his achievements. Businesses that rely on steel in turn start going out of business. Some of those people commit suicide.
**Dagny gets a note from Hank, he has met John Galt, is aware that Dagny now loves John, and is ok with it.
**She knows Galt works at Taggart Terminal but resists seeking him out.
**Through railroad reports, Dagny is aware of escalating lawlessness around the country, new not mentioned in the papers.
**The radio announces an important speech by Mr. Thompson to be on Nov 22, in a week.The speech is widely publicized.
**Jim asks Dagny to come see Thompson at the studio, but promises he isn't trying to get her to participate and endorse the speech. At the studio, every main character is there. Jim had lied to her, they wanted her to join the discussion all along. But she refuses.
**The head technician tells them they can't broadcast, some strange transmission is blocking and overpowering theirs, country side. At 8pm, instead of Thompson, John Galt speaks. The remainder of the section is his speech:
- - - - 
**&quot;I have deprived you of victims, and thus destroyed your world.&quot; I will tell you why you are perishing, you who dread knowledge.
**You sacrificed justice to mercy, independence to unity, reason to faith, wealth to need, self esteem to self denial, happiness to duty.
**I have withdrawn those who live by the mind. I have stopped your motor, deprived your world of man's mind.
**We don't owe you, your need is no claim on us. We, the men of the mind, are on strike. On strike against self immolation, that life is guilt. You said we were evil, so we left. The battle has been whether your life belongs to god or to your neighbor. No one has told you that your life belongs to you.
**Man's mind is his basic tool of survival. Plants and animals can't decide, they just live by instinct.
**Man has the power to act as his own destroyer, which is how he has acted through most of history.
**Your own life must be your motive and goal, otherwise you are an agent of death.
**Man's life is not the life of a mindless brute but of a thinking being. Not survival at any price since there is only one price that pars for man's survival: reason.
**A doctrine that gives you as an ideal, the role of sacrificial anima seeking slaughter on the alter of others is giving you death as a standard.
**Since life requires a specific course of action, any other course will destroy it.
**The purpose of morality is to teach you not to suffer and die, but to enjoy yourself and live.
**Sweep aside those who preach that the highest virtue man can practice is to hold his own life as no value.
**If you choose not to think, you default on existence and pass along the deficit to some moral man expecting him to sacrifice his good for the sake of letting you survive by your evil.
**When a man declares &quot;Who am I to know&quot; he is declaring &quot;Who am I to live&quot;.
**You who prattle that morality is social and that man would need no morality on a desert island - it is on a desert island that he would need it most. Let him there try to claim that a rock is a house, that sand is clothing, that food will leap into his mouth.
**Some paragraphs about
***Rationality
***Independence
***Integrity
***Justice
***Productiveness
***Pride
**The symbol of all relationships among such men, the moral symbol of respect for human beings, is THE TRADER.
**No man may INITIATE the use of physical force against others.
**I have no benefits to seek from human vices: from stupidity, dishonesty, or fear.
**Original Sin is supposed to be when man at of the fruit of the tree of knowledge.
**I am speaking to man the victim, not man the killer, the word that has destroyed you is sacrifice, the rejection of the good for the sake of the evil.
**They wish you to sacrifice materially but they also wish you to sacrifice your values.
**The mystics of spirit, the mystics of muscle
**A is A, the identity principle.
**They say, I want it, therefore it is.
**The law of identity does not permit you to have your cake and eat it too. The corrallary to causeless in matter is the unearned in spirit.
**Who pays for the orgy? Who causes the causeless? Who are the victims condemned to remain unacknowledged?
**WE are, we, the men of the mind.
**They proclaim that the only requirement for running a factory is the ability to turn the cranks of the machines, and blank out the question of who created the factory.
**They are taking you back to darker ages than any your history has known. The goal is not the era of pre-science, but the era of pre-language.
**Let the cannibal that snarls that the freedom of man's mind was needed to CREATE an industrial civilization, but is not needed to maintain it, be given an arrowhead and bearsking, not a university chair of economics.
**To a savage, the world is not the unknown, but the unknowable.
**He can count on nothing, he can only wish.
**They proclaim that every man born is entitled to exist without labor and is entitled to receive his minimum sustenance with no effort on his part, as his due &amp; birthright.
**Every man, they announce, owns an equal share of the technological benefits created in the world.
**Your gangs of mystics, of spirit and muscle, are fighting for power to rule you, you who have agreed to have no mind.
**Society - all of it is the same performance for the same &amp; only purpose: to reduce you to the kind of pulp that has surrendered the validity of your consciousness. But it cannot be done without your consent. If you permit it to be done, you deserve it.
**A mystic, afraid to think, is left at the mercy of unidentified feelings. He struggles to hide from himself that the nature of his feelings is terror. His lust is to command, not to convince.
**The forces let loose in your world today do not want to own your fortune, they want you to lose it. They do not want to succeed, they want you to fail. They keep running, trying not to learn that the object of his hatred is himself.
**Theirs is a conspiracy against the mind, against life and man.
**It is a conspiracy of those who seek, not to live, but to GET AWAY with living. The professor who, unable to think, cripples the minds of his students. The businessman who, to protect his stagnation, takes pleasure in chaining the ability of his competitors. The eunuch who takes pleasure in the castration of all pleasure.
**We are no longer there to save you from the effects of your chosen belief.
**You have been living on borrowed time - and I am the man who has called in the loan.
**Twelve years ago when I worked in your world, I discovered a source of energy available since the birth of the globe, but which men had not known how to use. I created a motor that would have made a fortune for me and those who hired me. Then one night at a factory meeting, I heard three parasites assert that my brain and my life were their property. That my right to exist was dependant upon satisfying their desires. I had no right to live by reason of my competency, their right to live was unconditional, by reason of their incompetence.
**Then I saw what was wrong with the world, and that the only weapon of evil was the willingness of good to serve it.
**I quit that factory and your world. I made it my job to warn your victims and to give them the method and the weapon to fight you.
**Ask yourself how much you have invented and how much you make of others inventions.
**When you clamor for public ownership of the means of production, you are clamoring for public ownership of the mind.
**Did you want to know who is John Galt? I am the first man of ability who refuses to regard it as guilt.
**I have done by plan and intention what has been done throughout history by silent default, gone on strike.
**The Dark Ages were an era of intelligence on strike.
**The road of human history was a string of blank-outs with only a few brief bursts of sunlight when the released energy of the men of the mind performed the wonders you gaped at, admired, and then promptly extinguished.
**I have foreshortened the usual course of history and have let you discover the nature of the payments you had hoped to switch to the shoulders of others. Do not pretend that a malevolent reality defeated you - you were defeated by your own evasions.
**But to those of you who still retain a love of your life I offer a chance to make a choice - be &quot;moral&quot; or live.
**pg 965 - mentions he has spoken for two hours.
**But the price is to start from scratch, reversing a costly historical error, to declare, &quot;I am, therefore I'll think.&quot;
**The three of us, Francisco, Ragnar, and myself started this and I am completing it. We resolved to avenge this country that was built on MY morality, but you failed to live up to it.
**We will not return until the road is clear to rebuild this country, until the wreckage of the morality of sacrifice has been wiped out of our way.
**The source of man's right is the law of identity.
**No right can exist without the right to translate one's rights into reality, which means, the right of property.
**The only proper functions of government are the police, the army, and the courts.
**Look past the moment, you who fear to compete with men of superior intelligence. When you live in a society where men are free to trade the value of your work is determined not only by your effort but by the effort of the best productive minds around you.
**When you work in a modern factory you are paid not only for your labor, but for all the productive genius which has made that factory possible (industrialist, investor, inventor, engineer, scientist).
**It is the value of his time that the strong of intellect transfers to the weak.
**Material products can't be shared, it is only the value of an idea that can be shared with unlimited numbers of men, making all sharers richer at no one's sacrifice or loss, raising the productive capacity of labor.
**In proportion to mental energy spent, the inventor receives a small percentage of the value he created no matter what his material payment. But a janitor receives an enormous payment in proportion to his mental effort.
**We dragged you out of your hovels but you called our palaces and yachts unfair.
**We asked to deal with your minds, you chose to deal using your gun. Our answer was &quot;May you be damned&quot;.
**Some of you might please ignorance. But the guiltiest among you are those who had the CAPACITY to know. The intellects who create weapons are the unforgivable (Dr. Stadler).
**To those who love life and the mind, I urge you to go on strike as I did.
**If you have to stay among them, keep your inventions to yourself, as a captive should. If you have a chance to vanish into a wilderness beyond their reach, do so. We will return after the collapse, of the morality of sacrifice. Our city will act as a rallying point for such hidden refuges as you create.
**The dollar sign will be our symbol.
**In the name of the best within us....
**My last words are to those heroes who still are held prisoner by their virtues and desperate courage. They hold you by your innocence, which gives them the benefit of the doubt (Dagny)
**You can win this new world, by a total break with the old. His oath is &quot;I swear - by my life and my love of it - that I will never live for the sake of another man, nor ask another man to live for mine&quot;
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggart's apartment
**The broadcasting studio in New York City
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**James Taggart
**John Galt (via radio)
**Mr Thompson
**Most all of the group from Washington
----
----

==CHAPTER EIGHT: The Egoist==

===Section 381: Part 3, Chapter 8, Section 1===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**The Washington group talk about Galt's speech, flustered. Fred Kinnon finally brings up the food crisis, but the group has no solution. Dagny tells them that they have no answers but John Galt does, so they should step aside and let John Galt take charge.
**Thompson realizes she is right but rather than give up power he thinks to himself that he can coopt Galt. Dagny leaves with Eddie Willers. Thompson resolves to find Galt and make him solve the problem. They set a tail on Dagny so she'll lead them to him.
**Alone now, Eddie tells Dagny that he realized that he's known John Galt for years as a common track worker at the Taggart Company. Dagny tells him that if he doesn't want Galt destroyed that he is to forget ever knowing him, never to tell anyone.
**All around the country, the &quot;better men&quot; are now starting to &quot;drop out&quot; as a result of the impending food crisis and John Galt's speech. They are heading off into isolated &amp; unpopulated areas of the country.
**Nobody qualified can be found to fill meaningful, important positions. People turn down raises and promotions rather than take a position of responsiblity. The country starts to fall apart. Inflation takes hold.
**Thompson goes on the radio to send a message to John Galt that they will negotiate, that they will do whatever he says.
**With Hank having dropped out, Reardon Steel is taken over by the government, but the mill is closed after several months of mismanagement culminating in a fire.
**Feb 3 is the last date mentioned in this decline (in a passage about a pilot who sees no flame from Reardon Steel).
**Thompson tells Dagny to contact Galt and to tell him that Thompson wants to negotiate. He also says that Ferris and others are trying to find Galt in order to kill him, and perhaps have already killed him. He frightens her into contacting Galt.

*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Wayne-Falkland Hotel
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Mr. Thompson
**Dr. Ferris
**Wesley Mouch
**Jim Taggart
**Fred Kinnan
**Dagny Taggart
**Eddie Willers
**Tinky Holloway
**Chick Morrison
**Eugene Lawson
**Ma Chalmers
**Dr. Simon Pritchett
**Mr Mowen
----

===Section 382: Part 3, Chapter 8, Section 2===
*'''Plot summary:'''
** Dagny doesn't have a way to contact John Galt, but thinks she can find him. While working at the Taggart company, he had given a home address. She goes there and finds that he is in fact there. They spend a little time together. He shows her his laboratory hidden in the apartment, including the static electricity motor.
**He warns her that she has been followed and that they are coming to take him. He urges her that when they come she should act as though she was tracking him down to turn him in, that she is on their side. They come, and she does. They force their way into his laboratory, but he has booby-trapped it and everything inside is dust before they can gain entrance.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**The streets of New York City
**John Galt's apartment
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
** Dagny Taggart
** John Galt
** Four thugs
----

===Section 383: Part 3, Chapter 8, Section 3===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Thompson pleads with Galt to take control of the economy, but refuses to cede power or change the overall system. Galt refuses. Thompson tries various forms of persuasion. He slyly asks if Galt has any loved ones he'd like to speak to. Galt knows that these loved ones would become hostages and says that there is no one.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Wayne-Falkland Hotel
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Mr. Thompson
**John Galt
----

===Section 384: Part 3, Chapter 8, Section 4===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Chick Morrison explains that their propaganda that John Galt is with them and planning a solution isn't convincing anyone. They mention factory closings, and also hunger riots in West Virginia. We learn of South Dakota farmers marching on their capital, burning state buildings and luxury houses. The State of California is in civil war between various factions.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Wayne-Falkland Hotel
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Chick Morrison
**Mr. Thompson
**Wesley Mouch
**Dr. Ferris
**Fred Kinnon
**Dagny Taggart
----

===Section 385: Part 3, Chapter 8, Section 5===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Thompson summons Dagny to see him. She is still acting as though she is on their side. She tricks Thompson into showing John his confidential reports on the chaos around the nation, which she knows will encourage John.
**Mr. Thompson &amp; Jim Taggart try to persuade Galt to no effect. The next day, Thompson brings Chick Morrison, who does no better.
**Dr. Ferris is next but also fails. The importance of the Taggart Bridge across the Mississippi River is brought up.
**Dagny talks to Eddie Willer at the Taggart Compnay. Eddie leaves for San Francisco and says good-bye to Dagny as he doesn't expect to see her again.
**Dr. Stadler is ordered to talk to Galt. Stadler tries to make excuses to John for selling out.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Wayne-Falkland Hotel
**The Taggart Company
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Mr. Thompson
**Dagny Taggart
**John Galt
**Jim Taggart
**Chick Morrison
**Dr. Ferris
**Eddie Willer
----

===Section 386: Part 3, Chapter 8, Section 6===
*'''Plot summary:'''
**Chick has Galt brough at gunpoint to a dinner gala to announce the John Galt Plan. It is also being broadcast over television and radio. They are trying to tempt him with what they themselves would want as a bribe (The dinner held in his honor, the power). Mouch makes a speech promising contradictory things. The plan to lower taxes but raise government spending. The rich get to keep everything they have but the poor get more. Higher wages but lower prices.
**When the TV camera goes to Galt, Galt dodges away from the man holding a gun to his back so that the gun is apparent to the camera, thus showing that the leaders have been lying, that he isn't cooperating, and there is no John Galt Plan.  Galt then says to the camera &quot;Get the hell out of my way!&quot;. 
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Wayne-Falkland Hotel
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Chick Morrison
**John Galt
**Mr. Thompson
**Jim Taggart
**Dagny Taggart
**Wesley Mouch

----
----

==CHAPTER NINE: The Generator==

===Section 391: Part 3, Chapter 9, Section 1===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dr. Robert Stadler drives out to Project X (the weapon based on sound waves). An armed militia has taken it over, calling themselves &quot;The Friends of the People&quot;.
**Dr. Stadler talks his way in, and is taken to see the leader, Cuffy Meigs, in the control room. Cuffy is drunk and talks about his ambitions and demands.
**He and Dr. Stadler get into a fight over who will control Project X, they hit into the control levers, and Project X is randomly activated. It destroys itself and everything in a 100 mile radius; buildings and people. The vital Taggart Bridge over the Mississippi River is among the destroyed.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Project X, somewhere in Iowa, within 100 miles of the Mississippi River
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dr. Stadler
**Cuffy Meigs
**Various militia men.
----

===Section 392: Part 3, Chapter 9, Section 2===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**The washington group argues about how to make Galt take control and save their system. Dagny is present and listening but the group still doesn't consider her an enemy. When the talk turns to torture, she slips out to call Francisco and warn him of their plans for Galt. She packs some things and meets him at a nearby street corner.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**Wayne Falkland Hotel
**Dagny's apartment
**The streets of New York City
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Mr. Thompson
**Dr. Ferris
**Jim Taggart
**Dagny Taggart
**Wesley Mouch
**Tinky Holloway
**Chick Morrison
**Eugene Lawson
----

===Section 393: Part 3, Chapter 9, Section 3===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Galt is hooked up to an electric shock torture machine. His torturers want to break him so that he'll do what they want. But they are also afraid of killing him because they want him to save their system. Galt endures the pain but doesn't break. As the torture grows more severe, Galt remains steadfast but the torturers become more and more afraid of possibly killing him. The machine breaks and nobody can fix it. Galt tells them how to fix it, which partially freaks them out. Jim Taggart realizes that he actually hates himself and not John Galt and this fact breaks Jim, leaving him unresponsive. This freaks out the others and they use Jim as an excuse to stop torturing Galt for the night, planning to return the next day.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**The &quot;Project F&quot; building at the State Science Institute in New Hampshire. The &quot;F&quot; stands for Ferris.
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dr. Ferris
**Wesley Mouch
**Jim Taggart
**John Galt
----
----

==CHAPTER TEN: In the Name of the Best within Us==

===Section 3A1: Part 3, Chapter 10, Section 1===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Dagny, Francisco, Hank, and Ragnar force their way into Project F, killing several guards and capturing several others. Hank is shot in the shoulder. They rescue John Galt, freeing him from an electric shock torture machine that had been used on him. 
**They fly back to their secret town of Galt's Gulch in the Colorado mountains. Passing over New York City, they see the gridlocked masses attempting to flee the impending catastrophic food shortage. As they fly by, the city goes black as the power stations are abandoned.
**John, Francisco, and Ragnar look at the dying city and take satisfaction, as it is the culmination of 12 years of work. 
**Dagny is also happy, and focuses on the future. She considers the world a blank slate waiting to be written upon.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
**The &quot;Project F&quot; building at the State Science Institute in New Hampshire
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Dagny Taggart
**Ragnar Danneskjold
**Hank Rearden
**Francisco d'Anconia
**The Guards
**John Galt

===Section 3A2: Part 3, Chapter 10, Section 2===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**Despite the fighting in the streets of lawless San Francisco, Eddie Willers was able to get a Comet train out of from San Francisco, only to have it break down in the middle of the Arizona desert. The crew can't fix it and there is no Taggart company left to send repairmen. An old fashioned wagon train pulled by horses comes by and invites the passengers to join them. Eddie looks at the people on the wagon train and thinks that they don't have what it takes to survive. Even though he is in the desert with no food and water, Eddie Willers stays with the train. The crew and other passengers load into covered wagons and leave.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
** A Taggart Comet Train (the last one)
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Eddie Willers

----

===Section 3A3: Part 3, Chapter 10, Section 3===

*'''Plot summary:'''
**It is late winter, and we visit various cabins in Galt's Gulch to see what the characters are doing.
**Richard Halley is playing his Fifth Concerto. It is triumphant, it &quot;swept space clean and left nothing but the joy of an unobstructed effort&quot;.
**Midas Mulligan is thinking about investments he'll make in New York, Chicago, Cleveland, Philedelphia, other places.
**Dagnar and Kay are relaxing.
**Judge Narrangansett is rewriting the constitution, &quot;Congress shall make no law abridging the freedom of production and trade...&quot;.
**Francisco, Hank, and Ellis are together. Francisco is planning a smelter for Hank, Hank envisions a railroad. John will design the engines. Dagny will run it.
**Elsewhere John and Dagny are out walking. He says &quot;The road is cleared. We are going back to the world.&quot; 
**End of the story.
*'''The following [[Places in Atlas Shrugged]] are used as settings in this section:'''
** Galt's Gulch, a Colorado Valley
*'''The following [[Characters in Atlas Shrugged]] appear in this section:'''
**Richard Halley
**Midas Mulligan
**Ragnar Danneskjold
**Kay LudLow
**Judge Narragansett
**Hank Rearden
**Francisco d'Anconia
**Ellis
**Dagny Taggart
**John Galt
*'''Quotations:'''
**&quot;The road is cleared. We are going back to the world&quot; page 1069 said by John Galt

----

{{Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis}}</text>
      <sha1>6dky35mjfjfey08zfewdy7pai4bwm0u</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Atlas Shrugged/Structure</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3200</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1898796</id>
      <parentid>1898795</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-07-23T16:42:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>fixed links for transclusion</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Atlas Shrugged is divided into three parts, with ten chapters in each part.  Chapters are divided into any number of sections.

{|
|-
|
===Part 1 - Non-Contradiction===

#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Chapters_1-5#CHAPTER_ONE:_THE_THEME|The Theme]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Chapters_1-5#CHAPTER_TWO:_THE_CHAIN|The Chain]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Chapters_1-5#CHAPTER_THREE:_THE_TOP_AND_THE_BOTTOM|The Top and the Bottom]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Chapters_1-5#CHAPTER_FOUR:_THE_IMMOVABLE_MOVERS|The Immovable Movers]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Chapters_1-5#CHAPTER_FIVE:_THE_CLIMAX_OF_THE_D'ANCONIAS|The Climax of the D'Anconias]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Chapters_6-10#CHAPTER_SIX:_THE_NON-COMMERCIAL|The Non-Commercial]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Chapters_6-10#CHAPTER_SEVEN:_THE_EXPLOITERS_AND_THE_EXPLOITED|The Exploiters and the Exploited]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Chapters_6-10#CHAPTER_EIGHT:THE_JOHN_GALT_LINE|The John Galt Line]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Chapters_6-10#CHAPTER_NINE:THE_SACRED_AND_THE_PROFANE|The Sacred and the Profane]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Chapters_6-10#CHAPTER_TEN:WYATT'S_TORCH|Wyatt's Torch]]
|
===Part 2 - Either-Or===

#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Section 2#CHAPTER_ONE:_The_Man_Who_Belonged_on_Earth|The Man who Belonged on Earth]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Section 2#CHAPTER_TWO:_The_Aristocracy_of_Pull|The Aristocracy of Pull]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Section 2#CHAPTER_THREE:_White_Blackmail|White Blackmail]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Section 2#CHAPTER_FOUR:_The_Sanction_of_the_Victim|The Sanction of the Victim]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Section 2#CHAPTER_FIVE:_Account_Overdrawn|Account Overdrawn]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Section_2A#CHAPTER_SIX:_Miracle_Metal|Miracle Metal]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Section_2A#CHAPTER_SEVEN:_The_Moratorium_on_Brains|The Moratorium on Brains]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Section_2A#CHAPTER_EIGHT:_By_Our_Love|By Our Love]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Section_2A#CHAPTER_NINE:_The_Face_Without_Pain_or_Fear_or_Guilt|The Face without Pain or Fear or Guilt]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Section_2A#CHAPTER_TEN:_The_Sign_of_the_Dollar|The Sign of the Dollar]]
|
===Part 3 - A Is A===

#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Section_3#CHAPTER_ONE:_Atlantis|Atlantis]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Section_3#CHAPTER_TWO:_The_Utopia_of_Greed|The Utopia of Greed]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Section_3#CHAPTER_THREE:_Anti-Greed|Anti-Greed]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Section_3#CHAPTER_FOUR:_Anti-Life|Anti-Life]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Section_3#CHAPTER_FIVE:_Their_Brothers'_Keepers|Their Brothers' Keepers]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Section_3A#CHAPTER_SIX:_The_Concerto_of_Deliverance|The Concerto of Deliverance]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Section_3A#CHAPTER_SEVEN:_This_is_John_Galt_Speaking|&quot;This is John Galt Speaking&quot;]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Section_3A#CHAPTER_EIGHT:_The_Egoist|The Egoist]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Section_3A#CHAPTER_NINE:_The_Generator|The Generator]]
#[[Atlas Shrugged/Synopsis/Section_3A#CHAPTER_TEN:_In_the_Name_of_the_Best_within_Us|In the Name of the Best within Us]]
|}
{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>2iurs3c54k5r9yx221ejhd6wzf3v929</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Kingturtle</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>3202</id>
    <revision>
      <id>155196</id>
      <timestamp>2003-12-12T03:08:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kingturtle</username>
        <id>364</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>I teach U.S. History, World Cultures and Psychology in a California public high school.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">I teach U.S. History, World Cultures and Psychology in a California public high school.</text>
      <sha1>dn4xlsp60walmgjnayhs7lb8pbiroqj</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Wikibooks:Block log</title>
    <ns>4</ns>
    <id>3244</id>
    <restrictions>sysop</restrictions>
    <revision>
      <id>1465937</id>
      <parentid>1382988</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-04-12T18:29:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mike.lifeguard</username>
        <id>55262</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>was kept</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{historical project page|1=This MediaWiki log page has been superseded by [http://en.wikibooks.org/w/index.php?title=Special:Log&amp;type=block the block log]}}
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;19:32, 15 Dec 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;61.145.130.190&quot; with an expiry time of 26 fortnights &lt;em&gt;(Chinese linkspam to the main page and others.  No soup for you, come back, 1 year)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;14:12, 9 Dec 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;202.105.135.4&quot; with an expiry time of 1 fortnight &lt;em&gt;(chinese link spam)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;09:21, 9 Dec 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;221.197.18.150&quot; with an expiry time of 1 fortnight &lt;em&gt;(chinese link spam)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;13:47, 8 Dec 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;213.91.217.118&quot; with an expiry time of 3 fortnights &lt;em&gt;(repeated spam creation)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;03:13, 7 Dec 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;219.82.149.199&quot; with an expiry time of 120 hours &lt;em&gt;(Chinese link spam)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;08:32, 3 Dec 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;219.134.13.148&quot; with an expiry time of 1000000 seconds &lt;em&gt;(SPAM is not nice)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;14:04, 2 Dec 2004 [[User:Yann|Yann]] blocked &quot;83.217.41.117&quot; with an expiry time of 2 hours &lt;em&gt;(spam on home page)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11:45, 2 Dec 2004 [[User:Yann|Yann]] blocked &quot;68.238.62.184&quot; with an expiry time of 1 hour &lt;em&gt;(vandalism on Home page)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;07:41, 30 Nov 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;221.197.19.225&quot; with an expiry time of 1000000 seconds &lt;em&gt;(spamers go home)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;08:58, 29 Nov 2004 [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] blocked &quot;61.232.113.104&quot; with an expiry time of indefinite &lt;em&gt;(spam will not be tolerated)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;20:08, 23 Nov 2004 [[User:Yann|Yann]] blocked &quot;24.16.75.24&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(vandalism on 15 pages)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;13:30, 22 Nov 2004 [[User:Yann|Yann]] blocked &quot;218.85.211.148&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(chinese spammer)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;09:43, 22 Nov 2004 [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] blocked &quot;221.197.16.10&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(spamming)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;03:39, 22 Nov 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;210.82.76.17&quot; with an expiry time of 1 month &lt;em&gt;(repeated chinese link spam from this address)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;15:46, 20 Nov 2004 [[User:Yann|Yann]] blocked &quot;218.85.207.8&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(spam)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11:40, 20 Nov 2004 [[User:Yann|Yann]] blocked &quot;81.165.241.54&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(vandalism)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;08:25, 20 Nov 2004 [[User:Yann|Yann]] blocked &quot;202.74.184.202&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(spam)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;08:25, 20 Nov 2004 [[User:Yann|Yann]] blocked &quot;222.47.73.51&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(spam)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;08:24, 20 Nov 2004 [[User:Yann|Yann]] blocked &quot;222.47.73.35&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(spam)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;08:24, 20 Nov 2004 [[User:Yann|Yann]] blocked &quot;221.197.20.66&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(spam)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;08:23, 20 Nov 2004 [[User:Yann|Yann]] blocked &quot;221.197.22.1&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(spam)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;08:23, 20 Nov 2004 [[User:Yann|Yann]] blocked &quot;221.196.11.2&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(spam)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;08:15, 20 Nov 2004 [[User:Yann|Yann]] blocked &quot;218.85.209.33&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(spam)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;14:29, 17 Nov 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;221.198.74.111&quot; with an expiry time of 150000 seconds &lt;em&gt;(you&amp;#39;re just a spam machine)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;16:43, 16 Nov 2004 [[User:Yann|Yann]] unblocked &quot;68.95.184.206&quot; &lt;em&gt;(dynamic address, this user&amp;#39;s IP address has changed)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;00:13, 16 Nov 2004 [[User:Yann|Yann]] blocked &quot;68.95.184.206&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(repeating vandalism on Home Page)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;06:02, 15 Nov 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;221.198.74.111&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(80000 seconds)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;19:02, 12 Nov 2004 [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] blocked &quot;209.242.128.10&quot; with an expiry time of 1 month &lt;em&gt;(googlebombing)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;19:01, 12 Nov 2004 [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] blocked &quot;222.47.72.247&quot; with an expiry time of 1 month &lt;em&gt;(goolebombing)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;09:26, 9 Nov 2004 [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] blocked &quot;193.230.197.6&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(spam will not be tolerated. you will be reported to your ISP if you return and spam)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;09:53, 8 Nov 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;221.197.16.90&quot; with an expiry time of 1000000 seconds &lt;em&gt;(spam is bad)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;05:59, 6 Nov 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;221.197.16.90&quot; with an expiry time of 10000 seconds &lt;em&gt;(spam)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;07:47, 3 Nov 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;219.82.139.89&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(link spam on the main page)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;08:45, 1 Nov 2004 [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] blocked &quot;219.134.15.142&quot; with an expiry time of 48 hours &lt;em&gt;(spam will not be tolerated)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11:01, 31 Oct 2004 [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] blocked &quot;Micutzu&quot; with an expiry time of indefinite &lt;em&gt;(spam will not be tolerated)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:57, 31 Oct 2004 [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] blocked &quot;193.41.249.111&quot; with an expiry time of 48 hours &lt;em&gt;(spam will not be tolerated)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;07:45, 31 Oct 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;203.219.210.10&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(potty mouth)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;07:41, 27 Oct 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;221.219.0.0/16&quot; with an expiry time of 2 weeks &lt;em&gt;(Excessive link spam has come from this ISP. Please contact your service provider and complain)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;05:28, 27 Oct 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;221.219.56.212&quot; with an expiry time of 1 month &lt;em&gt;(link spam.  As a repeat offender, you are now blocked for a month)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;01:09, 26 Oct 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;221.219.62.169&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(spamming the main page)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;00:20, 20 Oct 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] unblocked &quot;24.251.242.236&quot; &lt;em&gt;(discussion on IRC)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;17:15, 17 Oct 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;24.251.242.236&quot; with an expiry time of 72 hours &lt;em&gt;(deleting valid listing from vfd)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:15, 14 Oct 2004 [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] blocked &quot;218.69.192.43&quot; with an expiry time of 48 hours &lt;em&gt;(spam will not be tolerated)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;02:19, 14 Oct 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;218.69.192.43&quot; with an expiry time of 72 hours &lt;em&gt;(excessive link spam.  No soup for you.  Come back, one year)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;09:33, 12 Oct 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;219.134.14.7&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(spamming the main page, no soup for you, come back 1 year)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;08:41, 10 Oct 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;210.82.76.17&quot; with an expiry time of 1 month &lt;em&gt;(Spamming the main page)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;03:39, 10 Oct 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;221.198.0.0/16&quot; with an expiry time of 1 week &lt;em&gt;(excessive link spam has come from this ISP.  Please contact your service provider and complain)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;03:38, 10 Oct 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;221.197.0.0/16&quot; with an expiry time of 1 week &lt;em&gt;(Excessive link spam has come from this ISP.  Please contact your service provider and complain)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;03:37, 10 Oct 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;221.196.0.0/16&quot; with an expiry time of 1 week &lt;em&gt;(repeated link spam has come from this ISP.  Please contact your service provider and complain)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;03:35, 10 Oct 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] unblocked &quot;221.196.0.0/23&quot; &lt;em&gt;(too narrow)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;03:31, 10 Oct 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;221.196.0.0/23&quot; with an expiry time of 2 weeks &lt;em&gt;(excessive link spamming from a user of this ISP has been observed)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;03:12, 10 Oct 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;221.197.19.228&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(spam)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;04:46, 9 Oct 2004 [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] blocked &quot;218.18.85.2&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(spam will not be tolerated)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;15:05, 8 Oct 2004 [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] blocked &quot;221.198.74.212&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(spam will not be tolerated)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;09:31, 8 Oct 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;221.197.17.179&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(link spam)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;12:53, 5 Oct 2004 [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] blocked &quot;221.196.142.68&quot; with an expiry time of 64 hours &lt;em&gt;(spam will not be tolerated)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;02:49, 5 Oct 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;221.196.82.147&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(link spaming)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;02:48, 5 Oct 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;221.196.82.147&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(link spaming)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;19:19, 21 Sep 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;60.25.127.199&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(spam on the main page)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;19:30, 19 Sep 2004 [[User:Guanaco|Guanaco]] blocked &quot;DX&quot; with an expiry time of indefinite &lt;em&gt;(vandalism including an attempt to place a shock site script in the main page)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;23:40, 14 Sep 2004 [[User:Guanaco|Guanaco]] unblocked &quot;#19&quot; &lt;em&gt;(blocked username has been unblocked)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;04:38, 13 Sep 2004 [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] blocked &quot;221.198.73.159&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(spam linking)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;22:20, 12 Sep 2004 [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] blocked &quot;DX&quot; with an expiry time of 48 hours &lt;em&gt;(vandalism. you were warned. next time, the block will be indefinite.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;20:50, 7 Sep 2004 [[User:Guanaco|Guanaco]] blocked &quot;221.196.57.131&quot; with an expiry time of 1 week &lt;em&gt;(returning spammer)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;06:30, 6 Sep 2004 [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] blocked &quot;70.240.80.252&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(vandalism)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;06:28, 6 Sep 2004 [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] blocked &quot;81.157.71.59&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(vandalism)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:44, 18 Aug 2004 [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] blocked &quot;202.45.107.1&quot; with an expiry time of 3 days &lt;em&gt;(vandalism)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:43, 18 Aug 2004 [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] blocked &quot;203.40.120.49&quot; with an expiry time of 3 days &lt;em&gt;(vandalism)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;17:33, 2 Jul 2004 [[User:Guanaco|Guanaco]] blocked &quot;68.102.29.237&quot; with an expiry time of 05:00 5 Jul 2004 &lt;em&gt;(I am banned from editing all Wikimedia projects until the time specified. Please use any means necessary to enforce this if I attempt to evade the block.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;04:15, 27 Jun 2004 [[User:Guanaco|Guanaco]] unblocked &quot;148.221.17.251&quot; &lt;em&gt;(transparent)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;02:49, 23 Jun 2004 [[User:Guanaco|Guanaco]] unblocked &quot;69.69.20.216&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;22:49, 22 Jun 2004 [[User:Guanaco|Guanaco]] blocked &quot;69.69.20.216&quot; with an expiry time of infinite &lt;em&gt;(Sorry, &amp;#91;&amp;#91;en:User:Bird&amp;#124;Bird]] is not the word. This kind of interwiki vandalism will not be tolerated.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;12:23, 22 Jun 2004 [[User:Guanaco|Guanaco]] blocked &quot;222.95.26.215&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(spam)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;17:34, 21 Jun 2004 [[User:Guanaco|Guanaco]] blocked &quot;218.19.154.28&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(spam)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;17:14, 21 Jun 2004 [[User:Guanaco|Guanaco]] blocked &quot;192.129.3.92&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(spam)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;04:07, 21 Jun 2004 [[User:Guanaco|Guanaco]] unblocked &quot;67.71.86.84&quot; &lt;em&gt;(dynamic IP)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;04:06, 21 Jun 2004 [[User:Guanaco|Guanaco]] unblocked &quot;61.11.80.192&quot; &lt;em&gt;(blocked since Apr 16)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;04:06, 21 Jun 2004 [[User:Guanaco|Guanaco]] unblocked &quot;61.11.80.0/24&quot; &lt;em&gt;(not a spambot, ISP uses more than this range)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;04:04, 21 Jun 2004 [[User:Guanaco|Guanaco]] unblocked &quot;61.50.131.185&quot; &lt;em&gt;(dynamic IP)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;04:04, 21 Jun 2004 [[User:Guanaco|Guanaco]] unblocked &quot;61.50.131.0/24&quot; &lt;em&gt;(not a spambot, range is incomplete for the ISP)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;02:55, 21 Jun 2004 [[User:Guanaco|Guanaco]] blocked &quot;222.181.116.143&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(spammer)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;07:10, 4 Jun 2004 [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] blocked &quot;218.19.60.143&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(spam)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;12:20, 24 May 2004 [[User:Perl|Perl]] blocked &quot;68.3.190.85&quot; with an expiry time of 24 hours &lt;em&gt;(vandalizing hte main paig)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;17:34, 23 May 2004 [[User:Perl|Perl]] blocked &quot;67.71.86.84&quot; &lt;em&gt;(spam)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;13:08, 9 May 2004 [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] blocked &quot;220.176.99.67&quot; &lt;em&gt;(spamming)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;13:46, 2 May 2004 [[User:Perl|Perl]] blocked &quot;61.50.131.0/24&quot; &lt;em&gt;(range block do to spambot)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;13:42, 2 May 2004 [[User:Perl|Perl]] blocked &quot;61.50.131.185&quot; &lt;em&gt;(spambot)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;19:49, 1 May 2004 [[User:Perl|Perl]] blocked &quot;61.11.80.0/24&quot; &lt;em&gt;(spambot)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11:32, 16 Apr 2004 [[User:Perl|Perl]] blocked &quot;61.11.80.192&quot; &lt;em&gt;(advertiser)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;23:48, 30 Mar 2004 [[User:Perl|Perl]] blocked &quot;129.93.121.163&quot; &lt;em&gt;(repeated vandalism)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;15:27, 11 Mar 2004 [[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]] blocked &quot;129.93.121.163&quot; &lt;em&gt;(two vandalous edits)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;00:05, 16 Feb 2004 [[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]] blocked &quot;207.44.154.35&quot; &lt;em&gt;(vandalized staff lounge and spanish contents page)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;02:10, 23 Jan 2004 [[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]] blocked &quot;24.43.150.107&quot; &lt;em&gt;(trashing pages like crazy)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11:12, 12 Dec 2003 [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] blocked &quot;212.152.28.66&quot; &lt;em&gt;(rael vandalism)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;</text>
      <sha1>875uvkk7ni79tru6mmasrcsfmmcbc5i</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>C++ Programming/Examples/Hello world</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3245</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2603168</id>
      <parentid>2603155</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-01-23T09:47:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Panic2k4</username>
        <id>2865</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rejected the last text change (by [[Special:Contributions/58.69.77.98|58.69.77.98]]) and restored revision 2598218 by Panic2k4</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">=== Hello World - Writing, Compiling and Running a C++ Program ===
Below is an example of a simple C++ program:
{{:C++ Programming/Examples/Hello World}}

When you write a program you use a development environment. Your development environment can be a basic text editor or a feature rich C++ integrated development environment (IDE). You should not use a word processor like Microsoft Word, because it adds formatting codes to the text. 

If a compiler is not already available to you, see the [[C++ Programming/Compiler/Where to get|Where to get a compiler Section]] of the book. 

Open your development environment and type the program shown (or copy and paste it) and save it as '''hello.cc'''.

Now compile it using the C++ compiler:

 COMMAND_PROMPT&gt; ''g++ hello.cc -o hello''

The example uses GCC, the GNU Compiler Collection ( http://gcc.gnu.org ) but you could use any other compiler, or use an IDE to compile it. The above command would produce an executable called '''hello''' or '''hello.exe'''. Invoke the executable to run your first C++ program:

''Unix:''
 COMMAND_PROMPT&gt; ''./hello''
 '''Hello World!'''
 COMMAND_PROMPT&gt;

''Microsoft Windows:''
 COMMAND_PROMPT&gt; ''hello''
 '''Hello World!'''
 COMMAND_PROMPT&gt;

Text that is ''italicized'' is typed by you and the '''bold''' text is output by the program. If you use an [[w:Integrated development environment|IDE]], it might automatically color the code for you based on the syntax.

==== Troubleshooting ====
;g++: command not found
You don't have the GNU C++ compiler installed.  If you have a different compiler, check it's documentation for the correct compilation command.  

{{NOTE|There is detailed information on how to get a compiler and how to install it on the [[C++ Programming/Compiler/Where to get|Where to get a compiler Section]].&lt;br&gt;In [[C++ Programming/Weblinks#Compilers and IDEs|Appendix B:External References]] you will also find references to other freely available compilers and even full IDEs you can use.}}

;Wrong Compiler Command
Lot of weird errors, mentioning many times:

 undefined reference to `std::basic_ostream' [..]

Usually ending with:

 collect2: ld returned 1 exit status

To use &lt;tt&gt;g++&lt;/tt&gt; to compile your hello.cc use:

 ''g++ hello.cc -o hello''

For &lt;tt&gt;gcc&lt;/tt&gt; use:

 ''gcc hello.cc -o hello -lstdc++

{{NOTE|For simplicity we assume that the file is in the path you are using...}}

;hello: command not found
You did not type the full path, try:

 ''./hello''

Is there a &lt;tt&gt;hello&lt;/tt&gt; program in this directory? Can you see it when you type &lt;tt&gt;ls&lt;/tt&gt;? If not, your compilation (&lt;tt&gt;g++ hello.cc -o hello&lt;/tt&gt;) failed or you have changed to a wrong directory.

If you do not specify &lt;tt&gt;-o hello&lt;/tt&gt;, &lt;tt&gt;g++&lt;/tt&gt; names the output file &lt;tt&gt;a.out&lt;/tt&gt; ([[w:assembler|assembler]] output) for historical reasons. In such a case, type:

 ''./a.out''

to execute the program.

=== Your First C++ Program Explained ===
==== The preprocessing directive ====
Some features of C++ are part of the language and some others are part of a '''standard library'''. The standard library is a body of code that is available with every C++ compiler that is standards compliant. When the C++ compiler compiles your program it usually also links it with the standard C++ library.

When you use features from the library, C++ requires you to ''declare'' the features you will be using. The first line in the program is a '''preprocessing directive'''. In our example it is shown bold and italicized:

; The preprocessing Directive for IOStreams
&lt;source lang=cpp&gt;
 #include &lt;iostream&gt;
&lt;/source&gt;

This line causes the C++ declarations which are in the &lt;tt&gt;iostream&lt;/tt&gt; ''header'' to be included for use in your program. Usually the compiler inserts the contents of a '''header file''' called &lt;tt&gt;iostream&lt;/tt&gt; into the program. Where it puts it depends on the system. The location of such files may be described in your compiler's documentation. A list of standard C++ header files is in [[C++ Programming/Standard Headers|the standard headers reference tables]].

The &lt;tt&gt;iostream&lt;/tt&gt; header contains various declarations for input/output (I/O). It uses an abstraction of I/O mechanisms called '''streams'''. For example there is an output stream object called &lt;tt&gt;std::cout&lt;/tt&gt; which is used to output text to the standard output. Usually, this displays the text on the computer screen.

The ''preprocessor'' is a part of the compiler which does some transformations to your code before the ''actual'' compiler sees it. For example, on encountering a &lt;tt&gt;#include &lt;iostream&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; directive, it replaces the directive with the contents of the &lt;tt&gt;iostream&lt;/tt&gt; header file.

==== &lt;tt&gt;main&lt;/tt&gt; Function ====
&lt;source lang=cpp&gt;
int main()
{
    // ...
}
&lt;/source&gt;

The lines above represent a block of C++ code, given the name &lt;tt&gt;main&lt;/tt&gt;. Such a named block of code is called a '''function''' in C++ parlance. The contents of the block are called the ''body'' of the function.

The word &lt;tt&gt;'''int'''&lt;/tt&gt; is shown in bold because it is a '''keyword'''. C++ keywords have some special meaning and are also '''reserved words''', i.e., cannot be used for any purpose other than what they are meant for. On the other hand &lt;tt&gt;main&lt;/tt&gt; is not a keyword and you can use it in many places where a keyword cannot be used (though that is not recommended, as confusion could result).

Every (standards-compliant) C++ program must define a function called &lt;tt&gt;main&lt;/tt&gt;. This is where the execution of the program begins. As we shall see &lt;!--TODO add link to a section in a page --&gt;later, &lt;tt&gt;main&lt;/tt&gt; may ''call'' other functions which may call yet other functions. The compiler arranges for &lt;tt&gt;main&lt;/tt&gt; function to be called when the program begins executing. (Although this is generally true, it is not always true. There is an exception to &lt;tt&gt;main&lt;/tt&gt;'s being executed at the very beginning that we will see later.)

Now let us look at the code inside the &lt;tt&gt;main&lt;/tt&gt; function.

==== Printing Hello World! ====
The first line in &lt;tt&gt;main&lt;/tt&gt; uses the &lt;tt&gt;std::cout&lt;/tt&gt; object to print the ''string'' (sequence of characters) &lt;tt&gt;Hello World!&lt;/tt&gt; and end the line:

 std::cout &lt;&lt; &quot;Hello World!\n&quot;;

This line is a '''C++ statement'''. C++ statements are terminated by a semicolon (&lt;tt&gt;;&lt;/tt&gt;). Within the statement &lt;tt&gt;&lt;&lt;&lt;/tt&gt;, called the ''insertion operator'' is used to output the string using the &lt;tt&gt;std::cout&lt;/tt&gt; stream. C++ strings are enclosed within double quotes (&lt;tt&gt;&quot;&lt;/tt&gt;). The quotes themselves are not part of the string and hence not printed. The sequence &lt;tt&gt;\n&lt;/tt&gt; is used within a string to indicate the end of the current line. Though the sequence is represented by two characters, it takes up only one character's worth of memory space. Hence the sequence &lt;tt&gt;\n&lt;/tt&gt; is called the newline character. The actual procedure to start a new line is system-dependent but that is handled by the C++ standard library transparent to you.

{{NOTE|C Programmers should not confuse the insertion operator with the bitwise shift operator in C. C++ has a feature called ''operator overloading'' which allows the two interpretations of &lt;tt&gt;&lt;&lt;&lt;/tt&gt; to coexist.  In C++, I/O is the primary use of &lt;tt&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/tt&gt;, and bit shifting is a relatively uncommon use.}}

=== Modifications to the Above Program ===
Here is the same program with minor modifications:

{{:C++ Programming/Examples/Displays a string}}

==== Comments ====
The line added at the beginning:

 ''// This program justs displays a string and exits''

is a comment that tries to explain what the code does. Comments are essential to any non-trivial program so a person who is reading the code can understand what it is expected to do. There is no restriction to what is contained between the comment delimiters. The compiler just ignores all that is there in the comment. Comments are shown italicized in our examples. C++ supports two forms of comments:

* Single line comments start with a &lt;tt&gt;//&lt;/tt&gt; and extend upto the end of the line. These can also be used to the right of statements to explain what that statement does.

* Multi-line comments start with a &lt;tt&gt;/*&lt;/tt&gt; sequence and end with a &lt;tt&gt;*/&lt;/tt&gt; sequence. These can be used for comments spanning multiple lines. These are also known as C-style comments as this is the only type of comments available in C. e.g.:
 ''/* This program displays a string''
 ''   and then it exits */''

Comments are also used at times to enclose code that we temporarily want the compiler to ignore, but intend to use later. This is useful in '''debugging''', the process of finding out '''bugs''', or errors in the program. If a program does not give the intended result, by &quot;commenting out&quot; code, it might be possible to track which particular statement has a bug. As C-style comments can stop before the end of the line, these can be used to &quot;comment out&quot; a small portion of code within a line in the program.

==== Flushing the Output Stream Buffer ====
Whenever you ''write'' (i.e., send any output) to an output stream, it does not immediately get written. It is first stored in memory and may actually get written any time in the future. This process is called ''buffering'' and the regions in memory used for storing temporary data like this are called ''buffers''. It is at times desirable to ''flush'' the output stream buffers to ensure all data has been written. This is achieved by applying the insertion operator to an output stream and the object &lt;tt&gt;std::endl&lt;/tt&gt;. This is what is done by the line:

 std::cout &lt;&lt; std::endl;

Before flushing the buffer, &lt;tt&gt;std:endl&lt;/tt&gt; also writes a newline character (which explains its name, '''end''' '''l'''ine). Hence the newline is omitted in the string printed in the previous line.

==== Returning Success Code ====
In most operating systems, every program is allowed to communicate to the invoker whether it finished execution successfully using a value called the '''exit status'''. As a convention, an exit status of 0 stands for success and any other value indicates failure. Different values for the exit status could be used to indicate different types of failures. In our simple program, we would like to exit with status 0.

C++ allows the &lt;tt&gt;main&lt;/tt&gt; function to ''return'' an integer value, which is passed to the operating system as the exit status of the program. The statement:

 '''return''' 0;

makes &lt;tt&gt;main&lt;/tt&gt; to return the value 0. Since the &lt;tt&gt;main&lt;/tt&gt; function is required to return an ''integer'', the keyword &lt;tt&gt;'''int'''&lt;/tt&gt; is used to begin the function definition. This statement is optional since the compiler automatically generates code to return 0 for the &lt;tt&gt;main&lt;/tt&gt; function for the cases where control ''falls off'' without a &lt;tt&gt;'''return'''&lt;/tt&gt; statement. This is why the first program worked without any return statements. Note that this is only a special case that applies only to the &lt;tt&gt;main&lt;/tt&gt; function. For other &lt;!--TODO add link to a section in a page --&gt;functions you must return a value if they are declared to return anything.

'''Common Programming Error 1'''
Though the &lt;tt&gt;'''return'''&lt;/tt&gt; statement is optional, &lt;tt&gt;main&lt;/tt&gt; should not be declared to return &lt;tt&gt;'''void'''&lt;/tt&gt; (a function declared as ''void'' is a function which does not return anything) as in some other languages like Java. Some C++ compilers may not complain about this, but it is wrong. Doing this could be equivalent to returning just about any random number that happened to be stored in a particular memory location or register, depending on the platform. This practice can also be potentially damaging to some operating systems, which rely on the return code to determine how to handle a crash or other abnormal exit.

==== Whitespace and Indentation ====
Spaces, tabs and newlines (line breaks) are usually called ''whitespace''. These are ignored by the compiler except within quotes, apart from the rule that preprocessing directives and C++-style comments end at a newline. So the above program could as well be written as follows:

{{:C++ Programming/Examples/Displays a string1}}

Note, however, that spaces are required to separate adjacent words and numbers.
To make the program more readable, whitespace must be used appropriately.

The conventions followed when using whitespace to improve the readability of code constitute an [[w:Indent style|Indent style]]. For example with alternate indent styles the program could be written like this:

{{:C++ Programming/Examples/Displays a string2}}

or like this:

{{:C++ Programming/Examples/Displays a string}}

[[Category:C++ Programming|{{SUBPAGENAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>k1c33j58qfq4l45ai0g61h09rr5p08s</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>C Programming/Beginning exercises</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3246</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2700560</id>
      <parentid>2700122</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-09-15T19:45:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>169.236.57.11</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{C Programming/Navigation|File IO|Arrays}}

==Variables==
=== Naming ===

# Can a variable name start with a number?
# Can a variable name start with a typographical symbol(e.g. #, *, _)?
# Give an example of a C variable name that would ''not'' work.  Why doesn't it work?

{{Solution|title=Solution|text=
# No, the name of a variable must begin with a letter (lowercase or uppercase), or an underscore.
# Only the underscore can be used.
# for example, '''#nm*rt''' is not allowed because # and * are not the valid characters for the name of a variable.

&lt;pre&gt;
#include&lt;stdio.h&gt;
main()
{
    int a,b,c,max;
    clrscr();
    printf(&quot;\nenter three numbers &quot;);
    scanf(&quot;%d %d %d&quot;,&amp;a,&amp;b,&amp;c);
    max=a;
    if(max&lt;b)
        max=b;
    if(max&lt;c)
        max=c;
    printf(&quot;\nlargest=%d \n&quot;,max);
    getch();
}
&lt;/pre&gt;
}}

=== Data Types ===

# List at least three data types in C
## On your computer, how much memory does each require?
## Which ones can be used in place of another?  Why?
### Are there any limitations on these uses?
### If so, what are they?
### Is it necessary to do anything special to use the alternative?
# Can the name we use for a data type (e.g. 'int', 'float') be used as a variable?

{{Solution|title=Solution|text=
* 3 data types : '''long int''', '''short int''','''float'''.
* On my computer :
** long int : 4 byte
** short int : 2 bytes
** float : 4 bytes
* we can not use 'int' or 'float' as a variable's name.
}}

=== Assignment ===

# How would you assign the value 3.14 to a variable called pi?
# Is it possible to assign an ''int'' to a ''double''?  
## Is the reverse possible?

{{Solution|title=Solution|text=
* The standard way of assigning 3.14 to pi is: 
&lt;source lang=&quot;C&quot;&gt;
double pi;
pi=3.14;
&lt;/source&gt;
** Since pi is a constant, good programming convention dictates to make it unchangeable during runtime. Extra credit if you use one of the following two lines:
&lt;source lang=&quot;C&quot;&gt;
const float pi = 3.14;
#define pi 3.14
&lt;/source&gt;
* Yes, for example :
&lt;source lang=&quot;C&quot;&gt;
int a=67;
double b;
b=a;
&lt;/source&gt;
* Yes, but a cast is necessary and the double is truncated:
&lt;source lang=&quot;C&quot;&gt;
double a=89;
int b;
b=(int) a;
&lt;/source&gt;

}}

=== Referencing ===

# A common mistake for new students is reversing the assignment statement.  Suppose you want to assign the value stored in the variable &quot;pi&quot; to another variable, say &quot;pi2&quot;:
## What is the correct statement?
## What is the reverse?  Is this a valid C statement (even if it gives incorrect results)?
## What if you wanted to assign a constant value (like 3.1415) to &quot;pi2&quot;:  
##: '''a'''. What would the correct statement look like?
##: '''b'''. Would the reverse be a valid or invalid C statement?

{{Solution|title=Solution|text=
# &lt;code&gt;pi2 = pi;&lt;/code&gt;
# The reverse, &lt;code&gt;pi = pi2;&lt;/code&gt; is a valid C statement if &lt;code&gt;pi&lt;/code&gt; is not a constant and &lt;code&gt;pi2&lt;/code&gt; is initialized.
# '''a'''. &lt;code&gt;pi2 = 3.1415;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br&gt;'''b'''. The reverse: &lt;code&gt;3.1415 = pi2;&lt;/code&gt; is not valid since it is impossible to assign a value to a literal.
}}

==Simple I/O==
&lt;pre&gt;
#include&lt;stdio.h&gt;
int main(){
  char a,b,c;
  a=2058;
  b=270;
  c=a^b;
  printf(&quot;%d\n&quot;,c);
}
&lt;/pre&gt;
=== String manipulation ===
1. Write a program that prompts the user for a string, and prints its reverse.
{{Solution|title=Solution|text=
One possible solution could be:
&lt;source lang=&quot;C&quot;&gt;
#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
#include &lt;string.h&gt;

int main(void)
{   
    char s[81]; // A string of upto 80 chars + '\0'
    int i;
    
    puts(&quot;Please write a string: &quot;);
    fgets(s, 81, stdin);

    puts(&quot;Your sentence in reverse: &quot;);
    for (i= strlen(s)-1; i &gt;= 0; i--)
    {
        if (s[i] == '\n')
            continue; // don't write newline
        else
            putchar(s[i]);
    }
    putchar('\n');
    return 0;
}
&lt;/source&gt;
}}
2. Write a program that prompts the user for a sentence, and prints each word on its own line.
{{Solution|title=Solution|text=One possible solution could be:
&lt;source lang=&quot;C&quot;&gt;
#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int main(void)
{
    char s[81], word[81];
    int n= 0, idx= 0;

    puts(&quot;Please write a sentence:&quot;);
    fgets(s, 81, stdin);

    /* %s matches a sequence of non-whitespace character, which is a
     *    fair definition of &quot;word&quot; in this context.
     * %n matches nothing, but stores the number of characters that have
     *    been processed. i.e. if s is &quot;Hello, World!&quot;, then word and n
     *    will be &quot;Hello,&quot; and 6 respectively in the first iteration. In
     *    the second iteration they will be &quot;World!&quot; and 7 (6 chars +
     *    the space in front of the word).
     */
    while ( sscanf(&amp;s[idx], &quot;%s%n&quot;, word, &amp;n) &gt; 0 )
    {
        idx += n;
        puts(word);
    }
    return 0;
}
&lt;/source&gt;
}}

=== Loops ===
1. Write a function that outputs a right isosceles triangle of height and width ''n'', so ''n = 3'' would look like
&lt;pre&gt;
*
**
***
&lt;/pre&gt;
{{Solution|title=Solution|text=
One possible solution:
&lt;source lang=&quot;C&quot;&gt;
void isosceles(int n)
{
    int x,y;
    for (y= 0; y &lt; n; y++)
    {
        for (x= 0; x &lt;= y; x++)
            putchar('*');
        putchar('\n');
    }
}
&lt;/source&gt;
}} 
2. Write a function that outputs a sideways triangle of height ''2n-1'' and width ''n'', so the output for ''n = 4'' would be:
&lt;pre&gt;
*
**
***
****
***
**
*
&lt;/pre&gt;
{{Solution|title=Solution|text=
One possible solution:
&lt;source lang=&quot;C&quot;&gt;
void sideways(int n)
{
    int x,y;
    for (y= 0; y &lt; n; y++)
    {
        for (x= 0; x &lt;= y; x++)
            putchar('*');
        putchar('\n');
    }
    for (y= n-1; y &gt; 0; y--)
    {
        for (x= 0; x &lt; y; x++)
            putchar('*');
        putchar('\n');
    }
}
&lt;/source&gt;

or like this (all math)

&lt;source lang=&quot;C&quot;&gt;
void sideways(int n)
{
    int i=0,j=0;
    for(i=1;i&lt;2*n;i++){
        for(j=1;j&lt;=(n-(abs(n-i)));j++){
	    printf(&quot;*&quot;);
	}
	printf(&quot;\n&quot;);
    }
}
&lt;/source&gt;

}}

3. Write a function that outputs a right-side-up triangle of height ''n'' and width ''2n-1''; the output for ''n = 6'' would be:
&lt;pre&gt;
     *
    ***
   *****
  *******
 *********
***********
&lt;/pre&gt;
{{Solution|title=Solution|text=
One possible solution:
&lt;source lang=&quot;C&quot;&gt;
void right_side_up(int n)
{
    int x,y;
    for (y= 1; y &lt;= n; y++)
    {
        for (x= 0; x &lt; n-y; x++)
            putchar(' ');
        for (x= (n-y); x &lt; (n-y)+(2*y-1); x++)
            putchar('*');
        putchar('\n');
    }
}
&lt;/source&gt;
}}

==Program Flow==

1. Build a program where control passes from main to four different functions with 4 calls.

2. Now make a while loop in main with the function calls inside it. Ask for input at the beginning of the loop. End the while loop if the user hits Q

3. Next add conditionals to call the functions when the user enters numbers, so 1 goes to function1, 2 goes to function 2, etc.

4. Have function 1 call function a, which calls function b, which calls function c 

5. Draw out a diagram of program flow, with arrows to indicate where control goes

==Functions==

1. Write a function to check if an integer is negative; the declaration should look like
bool is_positive(int i);

2. Write a function to raise a floating point number to an integer power, so for example to when you use it

float a = raise_to_power(2, 3);    //a gets 8

float b = raise_to_power(9, 2);    //b gets 81

float raise_to_power(float f, int power);    //make this your declaration

==Math==

1. Write a function to calculate if a number is prime. Return 1 if it is prime and 0 if it is not a prime. 
{{Solution|title=Solution|text=
One possible solution using a naïve [[w:primality test|primality test]]:
&lt;source lang=&quot;C&quot;&gt;
// to compile: gcc -Wall prime.c -lm -o prime

#include &lt;math.h&gt;    // for the square root function sqrt()	
#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int is_prime(int n);

int main() 
{
  printf(&quot;Write an integer: &quot;);
  int var;
  scanf(&quot;%d&quot;, &amp;var);
  if (is_prime(var)==1) {
    printf(&quot;A prime\n&quot;);
  } else {
    printf(&quot;Not a prime\n&quot;);
  }
  return 1;
}

int is_prime(int n)
{
  int x;
  int sq= sqrt(n)+1;
 
  // Checking the trivial cases first
  if ( n &lt; 2 )
    return 0;
  if ( n == 2 || n == 3 )
    return 1;
 
  // Checking if n is divisible by 2 or odd numbers between 3 and the
  // square root of n.
  if ( n % 2 == 0 )
    return 0;
  for (x= 3; x &lt;= sq; x += 2)
    {
      if ( n % x == 0 )
	return 0;
    }
 
  return 1; 
}

&lt;/source&gt;
}}
2. Write a function to determine the number of prime numbers below n.

3. Write a function to find the square root by using Newton's method.

4. Write functions to evaluate the trigonometric functions:

5. Try to write a random number generator.

6. Write a function to determine the prime number between 2 and 100:

== Recursion ==
==== Merge sort ====
1. Write a C program to generate a random  integer array with a given length n ,  and sort it recursively using the Merge sort algorithm.
* The merge sort algorithm is a recursive algorithm .

- sorting a one element array is easy.

- sorting two  one-element arrays,  requires the merge operation. The merge operation looks at two sorted arrays as lists, and compares
the head of the list , and which ever head is smaller, this element is put on the sorted list and the head of that list is ticked off, so the
next element becomes the head of that list. This is done until one of the lists is exhausted, and the other list is then copied onto the end
of the sorted list.

- the recursion occurs, because merging two one-element arrays produces one two-element sorted array, which can be merged with another two-element
sorted array produced the same way. This produces a sorted 4 element array, and the same applies for another 4 element sorted array.

- so the basic merge sort, is to check the size of list to be sorted, and if it is greater than one, divide the array into two, and call merge sort again on the two halves. After wards, merge the two halves in a temporary space of equal size, and then copy back the final sorted array onto the original array.

{{Solution|title=Solution|text=
One possible solution , after reading online descriptions of recursive merge sort, e.g. Dasgupta :
&lt;source lang=&quot;C&quot;&gt;
// to compile: gcc -Wall rmergesort.c -lm -o rmergesort

/*
 ============================================================================
 Name        : rmergesort.c
 Author      : Anon
 Version     : 0.1
 Copyright   : (C)2013 under CC-By-SA 3.0 License
 Description : Recursive Merge Sort, Ansi-style
 ============================================================================
 */
#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
#include &lt;stdlib.h&gt;
#include &lt;string.h&gt;

//const int MAX = 200;
const int MAX = 20000000;

int *b;

int printOff = 0;

// this debugging print out of the array helps to show
// what is going on.
void printArray(char* label, int* a, int sz) {
	int h = sz/ 2;
	int i;

	if (printOff) return;

	printf(&quot;\n%s:\n&quot;, label);

	for (i = 0; i &lt; h; ++i ) {

		printf(&quot;%d%c&quot;, a[i],
					// add in a newline every 20 numbers
					( ( i != 0 &amp;&amp; i % 20 == 0 )? '\n': ' ' ) );
	}

	printf(&quot; | &quot;);
	for (;i &lt; sz; ++i) {
		printf(&quot;%d%c&quot;, a[i],
					( ( i != 0 &amp;&amp; i % 20 == 0 )? '\n': ' ' ) );
	}

	putchar('\n');


}

void mergesort(int* a, int m ) {

	printArray(&quot;BEFORE&quot;, a, m);

	if (m &gt; 2) {
		// if greater than 2 elements, then recursive
		mergesort(a, m / 2);
		mergesort(a + m / 2, m - m / 2);


	} else if (m == 2 &amp;&amp; a[0] &gt; a[1]) {
		// if exactly 2 elements and need swapping, swap
		int t = a[1];
		a[1] = a[0];
		a[0] = t;
		goto end;

	}

	// 1 or greater than 2 elements which have been recursively sorted

	// divide the array into a left and right array
	// merge into the array b with index l.

	int n = m/2;
	int o = m - n;

	int i = 0, j = n;
	int l = 0;
	// i is left, j is right ;
	// l should equal m the size of the array
	while (i &lt; n) {
		if ( j &gt;= m) {
			// the right array has finished, so copy the remaining left array
			for(; i &lt; n; ++i) {
				b[l++] = a[i];
			}

		// the merge operation is to copy the smaller current element and
		// increment the index of the parent sub-array.
		} else if(  a[i] &lt; a[j] ) {
			b[l++] = a[i++];
		} else {
			b[l++] = a[j++];
		}
	}

	while ( j &lt; m) {
		// copy the remaining right array , if any
		b[l++] = a[j++];
	}

	memcpy(a, b, sizeof(int) * l );

end:
	printArray(&quot;AFTER&quot;, a, m);

	return;

}

void rand_init(int* a, int n) {
	int i;
	for (i = 0; i &lt; n; ++i ) {

		a[i] = rand() % MAX;

	}
}

int main(void) {
	puts(&quot;!!!Hello World!!!&quot;); /* prints !!!Hello World!!! */

//	int N = 20;
//    int N = 1000;
//    int N = 1000000;
	int N = 100000000;  // still can't make a stack overflow on ubuntu,4GB, phenom
	printOff = 1;

	int *a;

	b = calloc( N, sizeof(int));

	a = calloc( N, sizeof(int));

	rand_init(a, N);

	mergesort(a, N);

	printOff = 0;

	printArray(&quot;LAST&quot;, a, N);

	free(a);
	free(b);

	return EXIT_SUCCESS;
}


/* Having failed to translate my concept of non-recursive merge sort,
 * I tackled the easier case of recursive merge sort.
 * The next task is to translate the recursive version to a non-recursive
 * version. This could be done by replacing calls to mergesort, with
 * pushes onto a stack of
 * tuples of ( &lt;array start address&gt;, &lt;number of elements to process&gt; )
 */

/* The central idea of merging, is that two sorted lists can be
 * merged into one sorted list, by comparing the top of each list and
 * moving the lowest valued element onto the end of the new list.
 *  The other list which has the higher valued element keeps its top
 *  element unchanged. When a list is exhausted, copy the remaining other list
 *  onto the end of the new list.
 */

/* The recursive part, is to defer any work in sorting an unsorted list,
 * by dividing it into two lists until there is only 1 or two elements,
 * and if there are two elements, sort them directly by swapping if
 * the first element is larger than the second element.
 *
 * After returning from a recursive call, merge the lists, which will
 * begin with one or two element sorted lists. The result is a sorted list
 * which will be returned to the parent of the recursive call, and can
 * be used for merging.
 */

/* The following is an imaginary discussion about what a programmer
 * might be thinking about when programming:
 *
 * Visualising recursion in terms of a Z80 assembly language, which
 * is similiar to most assembly languages, there is a data stack (DS) and
 * a call stack (CS) pointer, and each recursive call to mergesort
 * pushes the return address , which is the program address of the instruction
 * after the call , onto the stack pointed to by CS and CS is incremented,
 * and the address of the array start and integer which is the subarray length
 * onto the data stack pointed to by DS, which will be incremented twice.
 *
 * If the number of recursive , active calls exceed the allowable space for either the call stack
 * or the data stack, then the program will crash , or a process space protection
 * violation interrupt signal will be sent by the CPU, and the interrupt vector
 * for that signal will jump the processor's current instruction pointer to the
 * interrupt handling routine.
 */



&lt;/source&gt;
}}

==== Binary heaps ====
2.  '''Binary heaps''' :
* A binary max-heap or min-heap, is an ordered structure where some nodes are guaranteed greater than other nodes, e.g. the parent vs two children.  A binary heap can be stored in an array , where , 

- given a position '''i''' (the parent) , '''i*2''' is the left child, and '''i*2+1''' is the right child. 

- ( C arrays begin at position 0, but 0 * 2 = 0, and 0 *2 + 1= 1, which is incorrect , so start the heap at position 1, or add 1 for parent-to-child calculations, and subtract 1 for child-to-parent calculations ). 

* try to model this using with a pencil and paper, using 10 random unsorted numbers, and inserting each of them into a   &quot;heapsort&quot; array of 10 elements.

* To insert into a heap,  '''end-add''' and '''swap-parent''' if higher, until parent higher.

* To delete the top of a heap,   move   '''end-to-top''',  and  '''defer-higher-child''' or '''sift-down''' , until no child is higher. 

* try it on a pen and paper the numbers 10, 4, 6 ,3 ,5 , 11. 

{{Solution|title=pen-and-paper-solution|text=

* 10, 4, 6, 3, 5, 11  -&gt; 10
* 4, 6,3, 5, 11 -&gt;  10, 4  : 4 is end-added, no swap-parent because 4 &lt; 10.
* 6, 3, 5, 11 -&gt;   10, 4, 6  : 6 is end-added, no swap-parent because 6 &lt; 10.
* 3, 5, 11 -&gt; 10, 4, 6, 3 : 3 is end-added, 3 is position 4 , divide by 2 = 2, 4 at position 2, no swap-parent  because 4 &gt; 3.
* 5 , 11 -&gt; 10, 4, 6, 3 , 5 : 5 is end-added , 5 is position 5, divided by 2 = 2, 4 at position 2,  swap-parent as 4 &lt; 5; 5 at position 2, no swap-parent because 5 &lt; 10 at position 1. 

- 10 , 5, 6, 3, 4

* 11 -&gt; 10, 5, 6, 3, 4, 11 : 11 is end-added, 11 is position 6, divide by 2 = 3, swap 6 with 11, 11 is position 3, swap 11 with 10, stop as no parent.

- 11, 5, 10, 3, 4, 6  

- 11 has children 5, 10 ;  5 has children 3 and 4 ; 10 has child 6. Parent always &gt; child. 
 
}}

* the answer was 11, 5, 10, 3, 4 , 6.   

*EXERCISE:  Now try removing each top element of 11, 5, 10, 3, 4, 6  , using  end-to-top and sift-down ( or swap-higher-child) to get the numbers
in descending order. 

{{Solution|title=pen-and-paper-solution|text=
* 11 leaves  * , 5, 10, 3, 4, 6 -&gt; 6 , 5, 10, 3, 4 -&gt; '''sift-down''' -&gt; choose greater child 5 (2*n+0) or 10 ( 2*n+1) -&gt; is 6 &gt; 10 ? no -&gt; swap 10 and 6 -&gt;

- 10, 5, *6, 3, 4 -&gt;  4 is greatest child as no +1 child. is 6 &gt; 4 ? yes, stop.

* 10 leaves  * , 5 , 6 , 3, 4 -&gt; *4, 5, 6, 3 -&gt; is left(0) or right(+1) child greater -&gt; +1 is greater; is 4 &gt; +1 child ? no , swap 

-  6,5, *4, 3  -&gt; *4 has no children so stop.

* 6 leaves *, 5, 4, 3 -&gt; *3, 5, 4  -&gt; +0 child is greater -&gt; is 3 &gt; 5 ? no , so swap -&gt; 5, *3, 4 , *3 has no child so stop.
is 
* 5 leaves so  3, 4 -&gt; *4, 3 -&gt; +0 child greatest as no right child  -&gt; is 4 &gt; 3 ? no , so exit

* 4 leaves  3 . 

* 3 leaves *.

* numbers extracted in descending order 11, 10, 6, 5, 4, 3.

}}

* a priority queue allows elements to be inserted with a priority , and extracted according to priority. ( This can happen usefully, if the element has a paired structure, one part is the key, and the other part the data. Otherwise, it is just a mechanism for sorting ). 

* EXERCISE: Using the above technique of insert-back/challenge-parent, and delete-front/last-to-front/defer-higher-child, implement either heap sort or a priority queue.

====Dijsktra's algorithm ====
Dijsktra's algorithm is a searching algorithm using a priority queue. It begins with inserting the start node with a priority value of 0. All other
nodes are inserted with priority values of large N. Each node  has an adjacency list of other nodes, a current distance to start node, and previous pointer to previous node used to calculate current node. Alternative to an adjacency list, is an adjacency matrix, which needs n x n  boolean adjacencies.

The agorithm basically iterates over the priority queue, removing the front node, examining the adjacent nodes, and updating with a distance equal to the sum of the front nodes distance for each adjacent node , and the distance given by the adjacency information for an adjacent node. 

After each node's update, the extra operation '''&quot;update priority&quot;''' is used on that node :  

''while'' the node's distance is less than it's parents node ( for this priority queue, parents have lesser distances than the children), the node is swapped with the parent. 

After this, ''while'' the node is greater distance than one or more of its children, it is swapped with the least distant child, so the least distant child becomes parent of its greater distant sibling, and parent to the greater distant current node.  

With updating the priority, the adjacent node to the current node has a back pointer changed to the current node. 

The algorithm ends when the target node becomes the current node removed, and the path to the start node can be recorded in an array by following back pointers, and then doing something like a quick sort partition to reverse the order of the array , to give the shortest path to target node from the start node.

==== Quick sort ====
3. Write a C program to recursively sort using the Quick sort partition exchange algorithm.
* you can use the &quot;driver&quot;, or the random number test data from Q1. on mergesort. This is &quot;re-use&quot;, which is encouraged in general. 
- an advantage of reuse is less writing time, debugging time, testing time.
* the concept of partition exchange is that a partition element is (randomly) selected, and every thing that needs sorted is put into 3 equivalance
classes : those elements less than the partition value, the partition element, and everything above (and equal to ) the partition element.
* this can be done without allocating more space than one temporary element space for swapping two elements. e.g a temporary integer for integer data.
* However, where the partition element should be using the original array space is not known. 
* This is usually implemented with putting the partition on the end of the array to be sorted, and then putting two pointers , one at the start of the array,
and one at the element next to the partition element , and repeatedly scanning the left pointer right, and the right pointer left.
* the left scan stops when an element equal to or greater than the partition is found, and the right scan stops for a smaller element than the partition value,
and these are swapped, which uses the temporary extra space.
* the left scan will always stop if it reaches the partition element , which is the last element; this means the entire array is less than partition value.
* the right scan could reach the first element, if the entire array is greater than the partition , and this needs to be tested for, else the scan doesn't stop.
* the outer loop exits when then left and right pointers cross. Testing for pointer crossing and outer loop exit
should occur before swapping, otherwise the right pointer may be swapping a less-than-partition element
previously scanned by the left pointer.
* finally, the partition element needs to be put between the left and right partitions, once the pointers cross.
* At pointer crossing, the left pointer may be stopped at the partition element's last position in the array, and the right pointer not progressed past the
element just before the last element. This happens when all the elements are less than the partition. 

- if the right pointer is chosen to swap with the partition, then an incorrect state results where the last element of the left array becomes less than the partition element value.

- if the left pointer is chosen to swap with the partition, then the left array will be less than the partition, and partition will have swapped with an element with value greater than the partition
or the partition itself.   

* The corner case of quicksorting a 2 element &lt;b&gt;out-of-order&lt;/b&gt; array has to be examined. 

- The left pointer stops on the first '''out of order''' element. The right pointer begins on the first &lt;b&gt;out-of-order&lt;/b&gt; element,
but the outer loop exits because this is the leftmost element. The partition element  is then swapped with the left pointer's first element, and the two elements are now '''in order'''. 

- In the case of a 2 element '''in order''' array, the leftmost pointer skips the first element which is less than the partition, and stops on the partition. The right pointer begins on the first element and exits
because it is the first position. The pointers have crossed so the outer loop exits. The partition swaps with itself, so the in-ordering is preserved.

* After doing a swap, the left pointer should be incremented and right pointer decremented, so the same positions aren't scanned again, because an endless loop can result ( possibly when the left pointer exits when the element is equal to or greater than the partition, and the  right element is equal to the partition value).  One implementation, Sedgewick,  starts the pointers with the left pointer minus one and right pointer
the plus one the intended initial scan positions, and use the pre-increment and pre-decrement operators e.g. ( ++i, --i) .

{{Solution|title=Solution|text=
One possible solution , can be to adapt this word sorting use of quicksort to sort integers. 
Otherwise , an exercise would be to re-write non-generic qsort functions of qsortsimp, partition, and swap for integers.

&lt;source lang=&quot;C&quot;&gt;

/*
 * qsortsimp.h
 *
 *  Created on: 17/03/2013
 *      Author: anonymous
 */

#ifndef QSORTSIMP_H_
#define QSORTSIMP_H_
#include &lt;stdlib.h&gt;
void qsortsimp( void* a, size_t elem_sz, int len, int(*cmp) (void*,void*) );
void shutdown_qsortsimp();

#endif /* QSORTSIMP_H_ */

//----------------------------------------------------------------------------

/*   qsortsimp.c
 *   author : anonymous
 */
#include &quot;qsortsimp.h&quot;
#include&lt;stdlib.h&gt;
#include&lt;string.h&gt;

	static void * swap_buf =0;
	static int bufsz = 0;


void swap( void* a, int i, int j, size_t elem_sz) {
	if (i==j)return;
	if (bufsz == 0 || bufsz &lt; elem_sz) {
		swap_buf = realloc(swap_buf, elem_sz);
		bufsz=elem_sz;
	}

	memcpy( swap_buf, a+i*elem_sz, elem_sz);
	memcpy( a+i*elem_sz, a+j*elem_sz, elem_sz);
	memcpy( a+j*elem_sz, swap_buf, elem_sz);
}

void shutdown_qsortsimp() {
	if (swap_buf) {
		free(swap_buf);
	}
}

int partition( void* a, size_t elem_sz, int len, int (*cmp)(void*,void*) ) {

	int i = -1;
	int j = len-1;
	void* v = a + j * elem_sz;

	for(;;) {
		while( (*cmp)(a + ++i * elem_sz , v  ) &lt; 0);
		while ( (*cmp)(v, a + --j * elem_sz) &lt; 0 ) if (j==0) break ;
		if( i&gt;=j)break;
		swap(a, i, j, elem_sz);
	}
	swap( a, i, len-1, elem_sz);
	return i;

}

void qsortsimp( void* a, size_t elem_sz, int len, int(*cmp) (void*,void*) ) {
	if ( len &gt; 2) {
		int p = partition(a, elem_sz, len, cmp);
		qsortsimp( a, elem_sz, p, cmp);
		qsortsimp( a+(p+1)*elem_sz, elem_sz, len - p -1, cmp );
	}

}



//------------------------------------------------------------------------------

/*
Name        : words_quicksort.c
 Author      : anonymous
 Version     :
 Copyright   :  
 Description : quick sort the words in moby dick in C, Ansi-style
 ============================================================================
 */

#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
#include &lt;stdlib.h&gt;
#include &lt;ctype.h&gt;
#include &lt;string.h&gt;
#include &quot;qsortsimp.h&quot;


void printArray(const char* a[], int n) {
	int i;
	for(i=0; i &lt; n; ++i) {
			if(i!=0 &amp;&amp; i% 5 == 0) {
				printf(&quot;\n&quot;);
			}
			if (i%1000000 ==0) {
				fprintf(stderr,&quot;printed %d words\n&quot;, i);
			}
			printf(&quot;%s  &quot;, a[i]);

	}
	printf(&quot;\n&quot;);

}

const int MAXCHARS=250;
char ** wordlist=0;
int nwords=0;
int remaining_block;
const size_t NWORDS_PER_BLOCK = 1000;

//const char* spaces=&quot; \t\n\r&quot;;
//inline isspace(const char ch) {
//	int i=0;
//	while(spaces[i]!='\0') {
//		if(spaces[i++] == ch)
//			return 1;
//	}
//	return 0;
//}

void freeMem() {
	int i = nwords;
	while(i &gt; 0 ) {
			free(wordlist[--i]);

	}
	free(wordlist);

}

static char * fname=&quot;~/Downloads/books/pg2701-moby-dick.txt&quot;;

void getWords() {

	char buffer[MAXCHARS];
	FILE* f = fopen(fname,&quot;r&quot;);
	int state=0;
	int ch;
	int i;
	while ((ch=fgetc(f))!=EOF) {
		if (isalnum(ch) &amp;&amp; state==0) {
			state=1;
			i=0;
			buffer[i++]=ch;
		} else if (isalnum(ch)  &amp;&amp; i &lt; MAXCHARS-1) {
			buffer[i++]=ch;
		} else if (state == 1) {
			state =0;
			buffer[i++]= '\0';
			char* dynbuf = malloc(i);
			int j;
			for(j=0; j &lt; i; ++j) {
				dynbuf[j] = buffer[j];
			}
			i=0;
			if (wordlist == 0 ) {

				wordlist = calloc(NWORDS_PER_BLOCK, sizeof(char*));
				remaining_block = NWORDS_PER_BLOCK;
			} else if ( remaining_block == 0) {
				wordlist = realloc(wordlist, (NWORDS_PER_BLOCK + nwords)* sizeof(char*));
				remaining_block = NWORDS_PER_BLOCK;
				fprintf(stderr,&quot;allocated block %d , nwords = %d\n&quot;, remaining_block, nwords);

			}
			wordlist[nwords++]= dynbuf;
			--remaining_block;
		}

	}
	fclose(f);


}
void testPrintArray() {

	int i;

	for(i=0; i &lt; nwords;++i) {
		printf(&quot;%s | &quot;, wordlist[i]);

	}
	putchar('\n');
	printf(&quot;stored %d words. \n&quot;,nwords);
}

int cmp_str_1( void* a, void *b) {
		int r = strcasecmp( *((char**)a),*((char**)b));
		return r;
}

int main(int argc, char* argv[]) {
	if (argc &gt; 1) {
		fname = argv[1];
	}
	getWords();
	testPrintArray();

	qsortsimp(wordlist, sizeof(char*), nwords, &amp;cmp_str_1);

	testPrintArray();

	shutdown_qsortsimp();
	freeMem();
	puts(&quot;!!!Hello World!!!&quot;); /* prints !!!Hello World!!! */
	return EXIT_SUCCESS;
}
&lt;/source&gt;
}}

{{C Programming/Navigation|File IO|Arrays}}

[[fr:Exercices en langage C]]
[[et:Programmeerimiskeel C/Harjutused]]
[[pl:C/Ćwiczenia dla początkujących]]</text>
      <sha1>8ovdmnl1usf92l2h02uizkt60d9ye74</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:PhilBoswell</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>3247</id>
    <redirect title="User:Phil Boswell" />
    <revision>
      <id>930356</id>
      <parentid>155200</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-07-25T20:35:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>PhilBoswell</username>
        <id>216</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>for some strange reason, I seem to have ended up with two accounts…I prefer the other one</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">#REDIRECT [[User:Phil Boswell]]</text>
      <sha1>cvx36amotuszxsgbu84edghg7kmloyo</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:DrBob</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>3248</id>
    <revision>
      <id>155201</id>
      <timestamp>2003-12-12T18:44:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DrBob</username>
        <id>347</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">You can find me on Wikipedia [[en:User:DrBob|here]].

I'll be trying to work on science and physics topics in general and optics in particular. I enjoy doing diagrams (you can see some of my stuff on [[en:Lens|Wikipedia]]), so if you have any requests, leave them here.</text>
      <sha1>faf4iudyfdhojzviv51xr7a05syw0zz</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:Grendelkhan</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>3250</id>
    <revision>
      <id>442366</id>
      <parentid>155203</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-04-29T10:39:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">Hi Grendelkhan :) Welcome to Wikibooks!

Thanks for fixing up those bugs in [[Discrete mathematics/Set theory]] :) [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 23:12, 12 Dec 2003 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>6sjo25k4c7739ncnuotswvlzcgqemuy</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Chinese (Mandarin)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3251</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2700193</id>
      <parentid>2681995</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-09-13T18:18:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Courcelles</username>
        <id>379867</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>(Script) [[commons:COM:FR|File renamed]]: [[File:Bejing-città proibita.jpg]] → [[File:Beijing-città proibita.jpg]] FR2; typo</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Beijing-città proibita.jpg|right|thumb|300px|The Forbidden City in Beijing 北京紫禁城]]
Welcome to the '''Chinese''' wikibook, a free Chinese textbook on the Standard Mandarin dialect. This page links to lessons using simplified characters (used in mainland China, Singapore and Malaysia). There is also a [[/Traditional|Traditional Character Version]] available (used in Taiwan, Macau, and Hong Kong).

{{ambox|type=notice|image=|text=&lt;font color=&quot;#cc0000&quot;&gt;'''''Note''''':&lt;/font&gt; To use this book, your web browser must first be configured to [[/Displaying Chinese Characters|display Chinese characters]] If the characters in the grey box below appear as blank boxes or garbage such as �?�?􏿾, it is not properly configured.}}



{| border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; cellpadding=&quot;6&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;
| style=&quot;background-color:#eeeeee;&quot; | 我们需要您的帮助！如果您谙悉中文，请协助编撰本教科书。&lt;br&gt;我們需要您的幫助，如果您諳悉中文，請協助編撰本教課書。
|}
{{Category 3}}

== Lessons / 课程==
{| border=0  width=75%
|-
|valign=top width=48%|
'''Introduction / 介绍'''
*[[/About Chinese|About Chinese - 关于中文]] {{stage short|100%|Jan 24, 2005}}
*[[/How To Use This Textbook|How to use this textbook - 如何使用这本教科书]] {{stage short|100%|Jan 24, 2005}}
*[[/How To Study Chinese|How to study Chinese - 如何学习中文]] {{stage short|100%|Jan 24, 2005}}
*[[/Writing in Chinese|Writing in Chinese - 如何用中文写作]] {{stage short|100%|Dec 21, 2006}}

'''Pronunciation / 发音'''
*[[/Pinyin Pronunciation|Pinyin Pronunciation Basics]] {{stage short|100%|Jan 24, 2005}}
*[[/Pronunciation of Initials|Pronunciation of Initials]] {{stage short|100%|Apr 26, 2012}}
*[[/Pronunciation of Finals|Pronunciation of Finals]] {{stage short|100%|Apr 26, 2012}}
*[[/Using Tones|Using Tones]] {{stage short|100%|Apr 26, 2012}}
*[[/Pinyin|More About Pinyin]]{{stage short|25%|Oct 2, 2014}}
'''Vocabulary 生字/字汇'''
#[[/Family|Family - 第一部分:家庭]]
#[[/Commodities|Commodity - 第二部分:日用品]]
#[[/Transport|Transport - 第三部分:交通]]
#[[/Food|Food - 第四部分:食物]]
#[[/Animals|Animals - 第五部分:动物]]
| width=1% |
| valign=top width=48%|
'''Lesson Texts / 课文'''
#[[/Lesson 1|Hello! -  第一课：你好！]] {{stage short|100%|Jan 24, 2005}}
#[[/Lesson 2|Are you busy today? - 第二课：今天你忙不忙?]] {{stage short|75%|Jan 24, 2005}}
#[[/Lesson 3|An introduction to particles - 第三课：助词]] {{stage short|75%|Jan 24, 2005}}
#[[/Lesson 4|Word order and Verbs - 第四课：词序和动词]] {{stage short|00%|Jan 24, 2005}}
#[[/Lesson 5|Measure words/Counters - 第五课：量词]] {{stage short|75%|August 16, 2009}}
#[[/Lesson 6|More on interrogatives - 第六课：疑问助词]] {{stage short|00%|Jan 24, 2005}}
#[[/Lesson 7|What's this? - 第七课：这是什么?]] {{stage short|100%|Jan 24, 2005}}
#[[/Lesson 8|Who is she? - 第八课：她是谁?]] {{stage short|25%|Jan 24, 2005}}
#[[/Lesson 9|Where is the railway station? - 第九课：火车站在哪里？]] {{stage short|00%|Oct 5, 2008}}
#[[/Lesson 10|A telephone conversation - 第十课：电话]] {{stage short|00%|Dec 30,2009}}
#[[/Taiwan|Taiwan - 第十一课：台湾]] {{stage short|00%|Dec 30,2009}}
#[[/Mandarin is so interesting|Mandarin is so interesting! - 第十二课：华语真好玩]] {{stage short|00%|Dec 30,2009}}
#[[/I'm sick|I'm sick - 第十三课：我生病了]] {{stage short|00%|Dec 30,2009}}
#[[/Drinking tea|Drinking tea - 第十四课：喝茶]] {{stage short|00%|Dec 30,2009}}
#[[/China|China - 第十五课：中国]] {{stage short|00%|Sep 12，2010}}

#[[/Chinese History|Basic Chinese History - 第十六课：基本中国历史]]{{stage short|00%|Jan 12，2012}}
|}

== Appendices / 附录==
{| border=0  width=75%
|-
|valign=top width=48%|
*[[/Common Phrases/]] {{stage short|100%|May 21, 2012}}
*[[/Everyday Phrases/]] {{stage short|50%|May 21, 2012}}
*[[/Answer Key|Answer Key - 答案]] {{stage short|0%|May 21, 2012}}
*[[/Chinese-English Dictionary|Chinese-English Dictionary - 汉英字典]]
*[[/English-Chinese Dictionary|English-Chinese Dictionary - 英汉字典]] {{stage short|50%|May 21, 2012}}
*[[/Table of Initial-Final Combinations|Table of Initial-Final Combinations]] {{stage short|100%|Mar 08, 2006}}
| width=1% |
| valign=top width=48%|
*[[/Greetings|Greetings - 问候语]] {{stage short|100%|Jan 24, 2005}}
*[[/Numbers|Numbers - 数字]] {{stage short|75%|Jan 24, 2005}}
*[[/Nations of the World|Nations of the World - 世界各国]] {{stage short|50%|Jan 24, 2005}}
*[[/Radicals|Radicals - 部首]] {{stage short|100%|Jan 24, 2005}}
*[[/Slang|Slang - 俚语]] {{stage short|100%|May 21, 2012}}
*[[/Web Resources|Web Resources - 网络资源]] {{stage short|75%|Jan 24, 2005}}
|}

=== Related Books ===
{{PDF version|Chinese (Mandarin)|File size: 272KB}}
{{Print version}}
{{InterWiki|code=zh}}

*[[Pinyin]]
*[[Cookbook:Cuisine of China]]
*[[Written Chinese|Written Chinese]]
*[[East Asian Calligraphy|Guide to Writing East Asian Languages - 汉字书写]]
*[[voy:Chinese phrasebook|Chinese Phrasebook]] (on WikiVoyage)
*[[Cantonese|Cantonese (Yue) - 广东话]]
*[[Min Nan|Min Nan (Taiwanese) - 闽南话 (台湾话)]]
*[[Pinyin/Pinyin-English News Summary|Pinyin-English News Summary for learners of Chinese language]]

==Contributors==
* [[/Contributor's Guide|Contributor's Guide]] {{stage short|75%|Oct 3, 2013}}'''Update Needed - 需要更新'''
* [[/Planning|Textbook Planning - 课文安排]] {{stage short|75%|Oct 3, 2013}}'''Update Needed - 需要更新'''
* [[/Development History|Development History]] {{stage short|75%|Oct 3, 2013}}'''Update Needed - 需要更新'''
* [[/Contributors|Contributors - 撰文者]] {{stage short|100%|Apr 22, 2006}}

{{Subjects|Chinese language}}
{{alphabetical|C}}
{{status|75%}}
__NOTOC__ __NOEDITSECTION__
[[de:Chinesisch]]
[[es:Chino Mandarín]]
[[fr:Enseignement du chinois]]
[[ko:중국어 입문]]
[[it:Cinese]]
[[mk:Кинески јазик]]
[[nl:Algemeen Beschaafd Chinees]]
[[ja:中国語]]
[[pl:Chiński]]
[[fi:Kiinan kieli]]
[[tr:Mandarin]]
[[uk:Китайська мова]]
[[zh:汉语]]</text>
      <sha1>bsnr8dpclvhqbwu4yhs5m6t4nq11dkj</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Chinese (Mandarin)/About Chinese</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3252</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2689164</id>
      <parentid>2292568</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-06T05:26:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>水思</username>
        <id>1501326</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* About Chinese */ correct wrong pinyin</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Chinese Intro TOC}}
{{Chinese (Mandarin)TOC}}
=About Chinese=

{| align=&quot;right&quot;
|-
| &lt;center&gt;[[Image:Flag of the People's Republic of China.svg|100px|Flag of the PRC]]&lt;/center&gt;
| &lt;center&gt;[[Image:Flag of Singapore.svg|border|100px|Flag of Singapore]]&lt;/center&gt;
|-
| &lt;center&gt;&lt;small&gt;中华人民共和国 (中国)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
| &lt;center&gt;&lt;small&gt;新加坡共和国 (新加坡)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
|-
| &lt;center&gt;&lt;small&gt;''People's Republic of China&lt;br&gt;(China)''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
| &lt;center&gt;&lt;small&gt;''Republic of Singapore&lt;br&gt;(Singapore)''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=3 | [[Image:Map-Chinese World.png|320px]]
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=3 | The Chinese cultural sphere of influence
|}

The '''Chinese language''' (汉语/漢語, 华语/華語 or 中文; [[Pinyin]]: [[Hanyu]], [[Huayu]], [[Zhongwen]]) is a member of the Sino-Tibetan family of languages. About one-fifth of the world speaks some form of Chinese as its native language, making it the most common natively-spoken language in the world.

There is great internal variety within Chinese, and spoken Chinese languages such as Standard Mandarin (Putonghua), Shanghainese (Wu), and Cantonese, which are not mutually intelligible. Nevertheless, there is a single standardized form of Chinese known as Standard Mandarin (国语), which is based on the dialect of Beijing, which is in turn its own Mandarin dialect, among a large and diverse group of Chinese dialects spoken in Northern and Southwestern China. Standard Mandarin is the official language of Mainland China and Chinese Taiwan, one of four official languages of Singapore, and one of six official languages of the United Nations. Standard Mandarin also corresponds to the modern standard written Chinese language used by people speaking all forms of Chinese from all corners of China, including Mandarin, Wu, Cantonese, Hakka, Min-nan, and so forth. This textbook will teach Standard Mandarin, both spoken and written.

Chinese grammar is in many ways simpler than European languages (for example, you will see no tenses, plurals, or subject-verb agreement), but there are also plenty of pitfalls that will trip up the unsuspecting beginner (for example, you will encounter tones, measure words, and discourse particles, which do not feature as strongly in European languages.) In addition, the complexity of the writing system often daunts newcomers, as Chinese is one of the few languages in the world that does not use an alphabet or a syllabary; instead, thousands of characters are used, each representing a word or a part of a word. However, most complex Chinese characters are composed of only a few hundred simpler characters and many contain phonetic hints. There is a common Western misconception of Chinese writing as having thousands of distinct and idiomatic symbols each representing a single word, however, Chinese writing is surprisingly mnemonic, granted it is not as simple as the writing of Romance languages. The government of China has developed a system of writing Standard Mandarin pronunciation in the Roman alphabet, known as ''Hanyu Pinyin'', or simply, ''pinyin'' (汉语拼音/漢語拼音, &quot;spelling according to sounds&quot;). Hanyu Pinyin is used to write out Chinese words phonetically in an effort to help learners of Chinese with their pronunciation. This wikibook will teach you Hanyu Pinyin first, before any actual sentences. All examples and new vocabulary will always be given together with Hanyu Pinyin.

There are two character sets: Simplified Chinese characters (简体字/簡體字, [[Pinyin]]: [[Jiǎntǐzì]]) and Traditional Chinese characters (繁体字/繁體字, [[Pinyin]]: [[Fántǐzì]]). Traditional characters trace their lineage through thousands of years of Chinese history, and continue to be used in Hong Kong, Macau, Taiwan, and among many overseas Chinese. Simplified Chinese characters were the result of reforms carried out in Mainland China to increase literacy rates and is now used in Singapore as well. The two systems share many of the same characters or with systematic, predictable reductions in stroke; however, some changes are not as formulaic. As a result, most native Chinese speakers are able to write in only one of the two systems, though they can usually read both. You are recommended to do the same. It is considered easier for people who learn Traditional to read both sets than people who learn Simplified only, but Simplified characters are less intimidating for beginners. In this wikibook, all examples and vocabulary are given in both systems, and you are encouraged to choose one system and stick with it throughout.

Chinese characters have also been used in the past by other neighbouring Asian countries, and are still being used by some of them today. Some older Koreans still know how to read and write Chinese characters, but although the members of younger generations are taught Chinese characters or ''hanja'', they are rarely used and unnecessary for literacy in Korean, with the native alphabet, ''hangul''. Chinese characters are occasionally used for abbreviations, to clarify technical vocabulary (as Chinese serves roughly the same role in Korean that Latin serves in English), and to write family and many personal names. The Japanese still preserve many Chinese characters or ''kanji'' today and use them along with two syllabaries to write the Japanese language.

{{Chinese Intro TOC}}

{{Chinese (Mandarin)TOC}}

[[Category:{{FULLBOOKNAME}}|{{FULLCHAPTERNAME}}]]

[[it:Cinese/Introduzione]]
[[pl:Chiński/O języku chińskim]]
[[tr:Mandarin/İçindekiler/Mandarin hakkında]]</text>
      <sha1>b2vzhrco4cbxs9ae0yj9kfcfviw5gb6</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Chinese (Mandarin)/Web Resources</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3253</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2714116</id>
      <parentid>2611323</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-16T00:39:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DashDaring</username>
        <id>1893704</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Added additional resource under &quot;Lessons&quot; section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Chinese (Mandarin)TOC}}
== Sites in English (beginners) ==
;Dictionaries / Translators
*[http://cc-cedict.org/ CC-CEDICT] - CC-BY-SA dictionary. Extensive, compiled by volunteers. Available under GNU licence.
*[http://www.fastchinese.org/dictionary Chinese Tutor Dictionary] - A Chinese dictionary searchable by Pinyin, Hanzi, or English. It is fast and easy to use.
*[http://translate.google.com Google Translate] - Surprise, surprise! Has dictionary, pinyin, and example sentences.'''May not work well when translating long sentences to Chinese.'''
*[http://www.chinese-dictionary.org/ Multilingual Chinese Dictionary] - A no-frills Chinese dictionary with 9 languages
*[http://www.nciku.com nciku] - Chinese-English dictionary with handwriting recognition, lots of examples, a text-to-speech system, and other learning materials.
*[http://www.rikai.com/perl/HomePage.pl?Language=Zh Rikai.com] - A web-mediator that adds mouseover pinyin readings and English meanings to Chinese webpages.
*[http://dictionary.writtenchinese.com WrittenChinese.Com] Free Chinese-English dictionary. Search results are ranked by frequency of occurrence in everyday Chinese text.
*[http://zhongwen.com Zhongwen.com] - A Chinese character dictionary and cultural reference. Characters are represented by images, meaning they are still viewable without Chinese fonts. Detailed character trees.
;Lessons
*[http://yoyochinese.com/ Yoyo Chinese] - Learn Mandarin Chinese with over 400+ video lessons featuring authentic Chinese dialogue filmed right on the streets of China. One of the only Mandarin language programs that has a day-by-day study schedule.
*[http://mandarinplay.tk/ Mandarin Play] - Learn Mandarin Chinese with simple and fun mini-games. The games combine English, Pinyin, Hanzi and audio to help you learn beginner and intermediate Mandarin Chinese in an interactive way.
*[http://www.chinesepod.com ChinesePod] - Free Chinese podcasts for beginners on various topics.
*[http://www.chinese-tools.com/learn/chinese Learn chinese online] - 40 lessons courses for beginners.
*[http://learnchinese.elanguageschool.net/ Learn to Speak Chinese Online] - Learn Mandarin Chinese online for free.
*[http://www.mandarin123.com Mandarin 123] - Site focused on Chinese Mandarin vocabulary, pronunciation, grammar, reading and writing.
*[http://www.melnyks.com Melnyks Chinese] - Theme-based Chinese Podcasts.
*[http://www.ZapChinese.com ZapChinese] - Mandarin Chinese audio vocabulary. A large list of useful words in Chinese and an audio file showing how to pronounce them.
;Pinyin reading matters
*[[Pinyin/Pinyin-English News Summary|Pinyin-English News Summary for learners of Chinese language]]
*[[Pinyin/The Problems of Hanzi Application in IT|The Problems of Hanzi Application in IT]]
;Other
*[http://www.fastchinese.org/flashcards Chinese Tutor Flashcards] - Online flashcards that focus on words the learner is having difficulty with.
*[http://www.chinese-outpost.com The Chinese Outpost] - Site focused on Chinese language learning and culture, centered around an &quot;Introduction to Mandarin Chinese&quot; with readable and entertaining units on pronunciation, characters and grammar.
*[http://www.learnchineseok.com/ LearnchineseOK.com] - Web's biggest directory of free online resources for learning Mandarin Chinese language
*[http://mnemosyne-proj.org/index.php Mnemosyne] - Free, reliable flashcard program. Has special &quot;vocabulary&quot; cards.
*[http://www.chinesewithmike.com Chinese with Mike] - Blogger focused on the Chinese language.
*[http://www.mandarintools.com/ On-line Chinese Tools] - Site with many helpful links for learners, including online dictionaries, character converters and free flashcard programs for learning characters.
*[http://www.skype.com/ Skype.com] - Skype is a freely downloadable program that allows free, [[w:VoIP|VoIP]] calling. You can find native Chinese speakers looking for language partners via skype at [http://www.language-exchanges.org the Mixxer]
*[http://www.lib.unimelb.edu.au/collections/asian/chi-web/index.html University of Melbourne Chinese Studies Virtual Library] - Large collection of Chinese-related links, organized by topic.
*[http://books.google.com/books?id=YHjv78eIgWYC&amp;pg=ISBN+0967370523 ''Complete Conduct Principles for the 21st Century: The English - Simplified Chinese Page to Page Correspondence Display Edition, Useful for Learning Chinese'' John Newton, Ph.D. (哲腊曙博士). (2008). ISBN 0967370523.] - Advanced-level learning Simplified Chinese for English users and at the same time learning better conduct for the coming years.
*[http://books.google.com/books?id=zactjieio18C&amp;dq=ISBN+0967370558 ''Complete Conduct Principles for the 21st Century: The English - Traditional Chinese Page to Page Correspondence Display Edition, Useful for Learning Chinese'' John Newton, Ph.D. (哲臘曙博士). (2009). ISBN 0967370558.] - Advanced-level learning Traditional Chinese for English users and at the same time learning better conduct for the coming years.

== Sites in Chinese (advanced) ==
;General
*[http://www.gutenberg.org/browse/languages/zh Project Gutenberg's Chinese Books]
*[http://zh.wikipedia.org Wikipedia in Chinese]
*[http://tw.dictionary.yahoo.com/ Yahoo!奇摩字典] - Chinese-English dictionary from Yahoo! for English learners in Taiwan.
;Search engines
*[http://www.baidu.com Baidu] - Simplified Chinese, The most widely used search engine in mainland China
*Google
**[http://www.google.com.hk Google Hong Kong] - Both Simplified and Traditional Chinese
**[http://www.google.com.tw Google Taiwan] - Traditional Chinese
**Or you can just change your Google Language settings.
*Yahoo!
**[http://www.yahoo.com.cn Yahoo! China] - Simplified Chinese
**[http://www.yahoo.com.hk Yahoo! Hong Kong] - Traditional Chinese
**[http://www.yahoo.com.tw Yahoo! Taiwan] - Traditional Chinese
;Other major websites
*[http://www.xinhua.org/ Xinhua] - A major official Chinese news agency
*[http://www.sina.com.cn/ Sina] - Web portal
*[http://www.sohu.com Sohu] - Web portal
*[http://www.qq.com Tencent] - Web portal
*[http://www.163.com/ NetEase] - Web portal

==WikiMedia Sites==
*[[zh:|Wikibooks]]
*[[w:zh:|Wikipedia]]
*[[wikt:zh:|Wiktionary]]

See more at [[w:zh:Template:Wikipediasister|Wikipedia]].
[[Category:{{FULLBOOKNAME}}|{{FULLCHAPTERNAME}}]]


----

{{Chinese (Mandarin)TOC}}

[[Category:{{FULLBOOKNAME}}|{{FULLCHAPTERNAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>e7mpcgk76bstef6ftlwn44tydxo8ojc</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Template:Incomplete</title>
    <ns>10</ns>
    <id>3254</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2349571</id>
      <parentid>2349570</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-05-19T15:07:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Liam987</username>
        <id>582918</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;span class=&quot;noprint&quot;&gt;{{#switch:{{{type|{{{2|box}}}}}}
|box={{&lt;noinclude&gt;a&lt;/noinclude&gt;mbox|type={{{mbox-type|{{{box-type|notice}}}}}}|text='''{{{text|&lt;includeonly&gt;{{is book|This book is currently incomplete.|&lt;/includeonly&gt;The text in its current form is incomplete.&lt;includeonly&gt;}}&lt;/includeonly&gt;}}}'''{{#if:{{{date|}}}|&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;''(As of {{{date}}})''&lt;/small&gt;|}}}}
|text='''{{{text|The text in its current form is incomplete.}}}''' {{#if:{{{date|}}}|&lt;small&gt;''(As of {{{date}}})''&lt;/small&gt;|}}
}}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;noinclude&gt;
{{Documentation}}
&lt;/noinclude&gt;</text>
      <sha1>2eamgkyas6qotd8tzsbbttxknc1veby</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:High School Mathematics Extensions/Mathematical Proofs</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>3255</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2622176</id>
      <parentid>2622107</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-03-28T08:22:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ranadeakshay</username>
        <id>1483295</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Feedback */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Could anybody prove that &lt;math&gt;n-m = -1*(m-n)&lt;/math&gt;? [[User:R3m0t|r3m0t]] 14:44, 13 Dec 2003 (UTC)

== comment 1 ==

Uhhh...
Take the right hand side and expand
:-''m'' - (-1)''n''
which is equivalent to
:-''m''+(-1)(-1)''n''
which is
:-''m''+1''n''
:n-m
which is the desired result.

[[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 00:03, 14 Dec 2003 (UTC)

:&lt;nowiki&gt;*grin*&lt;/nowiki&gt; Cool. Now I really know it's true! ;) [[User:R3m0t|r3m0t]] 00:32, 14 Dec 2003 (UTC)

I found a good example for the visual proofs section - prove that the series &lt;math&gt;1^2+2^2+...+n^2&lt;/math&gt; multiplies by 4 and adds 1 when ''n'' is increased by one. No idea? Think about how many squares there are on a 16&amp;times;16 grid. [[User:212.135.1.53|212.135.1.53]] 08:29, 5 Jan 2004 (UTC) (r3m0t)

:Okay, good work. Let me think why it is so... [[User:Xiaodai|Xiaodai]] 09:49, 5 Jan 2004 (UTC)
::Whoops. Never even tried it out on paper, I was so convinced. No, that isn't even true *grins*. Ah well, in which case, a good recursion exercise is finding out how many squares (of any size) there are on a 16&amp;times;16 grid. The answer happens to be 1,496 (or aleph-one, depending on how you interpret the question...) I will however try and investigate how to fix that times 4 and plus 1 rule, but chances are the outcome will be pretty complicated. [[User:R3m0t|r3m0t]] 19:11, 5 Jan 2004 (UTC)

Is the following line correct, it would seem more logical to prove v=w instead of v = u:
2. Prove using only the axioms if u + v = u + w then v = u (subtracting u from both sides is not accepted as a solution)
I can't find the solution to this problem, so it would be great if you could give me a hint
Problemset nr 1 seems to be wrong as well, the greater than sign should be turned around, otherwise simply trying n=2 will show you that it's not true[[User:Mmartin|Mmartin]] 19 july 2004
:Thanks I corrected the error. As an hint to this type of problems, we always use 0 e.g. a = a + 0. If you are still scratching your head, the solutions is as follows:
:&lt;math&gt;
\begin{matrix}
v &amp;=&amp; v + 0\\
  &amp;=&amp; v + (u - u)\\
  &amp;=&amp; (v + u) - u\\
  &amp;=&amp; (w + u) - u\\
  &amp;=&amp; w + (u - u)\\
  &amp;=&amp; w + 0 \\
  &amp;=&amp; w
\end{matrix}
&lt;/math&gt;
:as  required. Thank you very much for you question. I love getting questions, it assures me that somebody out there is reading my work. [[User:Xiaodai|Xiaodai]] 08:42, 20 Jul 2004 (UTC)

== Hum?? ==

I've trouble on doing question 3 of the first exercise. Can you give me some hints? (Also it seems the question itself has some minor typing mistakes)
-lemontea

:Thanks for pointing it out lemontea, fixed. [[User:Xiaodai|Xiaodai]] 04:11, 18 Dec 2004 (UTC)

::Now I'm completely stucked. I tried doing binomial expansion of that (i-1)^k and cancel out the highest power i^k, leaving only smaller power behind so I can employ induction, but this method failed. How did you do it? (Though I have an idea on making use of the generating function, but them this can expand to a project which the size is comparable to the project in the first chapter) [[User:Lemontea|Lemontea]] 18:11, 26 Dec 2004 (GMT+8)

:::I hope you dont mind, i will write out the complete solution here. You may have been confused by the questions. Anyway..

:::It's clear that 1&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; + 2&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; + ... = (n+1)n/2. So we can start the induction from there.
:::Suppose that
::::&lt;math&gt;\sum_{i=1}^ni^j&lt;/math&gt;
:::has an explicit formula in terms of ''n'' for all ''j'' &lt; ''k'' (**), we aim to prove that
::::&lt;math&gt;\sum_{i=1}^ni^k&lt;/math&gt;
:::also has an explicit formula.

:::Indeed, consider
::::&lt;math&gt;\sum_{i=1}^n[i^{k+1} - (i-1)^{k+1}] = n^{k+1}&lt;/math&gt;
:::I think you may have consider ^k instead of ^(k+1). Also, looking at it from another way
::::&lt;math&gt;\sum_{i=1}^n[i^{k+1} - (i-1)^k] = \sum_{i=1}^n[i^{k+1} - i^{k+1} + i^k - i^{k-1} + ... \ 1]&lt;/math&gt;
:::as you have mentioned the i&lt;sup&gt;k+1&lt;/sup&gt; cancels, leaving smaller powers, rearraging to get
::::&lt;math&gt;\sum_{i=1}^ni^k&lt;/math&gt;
:::on the left hand side and using the induction hypothesis (**) then we are done. Hope this has been helpful. [[User:Xiaodai|Xiaodai]] 00:13, 28 Dec 2004 (UTC)

Thanks! That helped. (Oh no, I found I was just a few steps away from the end of the solution, a ghost must have covered my eyes, ahhhhhhhhh...)
However, it seems the ending part could be written more clearly, and the above did contain some minor error...
&lt;math&gt;\sum_{i=1}^n[i^{k+1} - (i-1)^{k(??)}]&lt;/math&gt;
&lt;math&gt; = \sum_{i=1}^n[i^{k+1} - i^{k+1} + i^k - i^{k-1} + ... \ 1]&lt;/math&gt;(Shouldn't there be some binomial coefficient when expanding out?)

I thought the principle would be like the below:
&lt;math&gt;\sum_{i=1}^n[i^{k+1} - (i-1)^{k+1}] = n^{k+1}&lt;/math&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;math&gt;\sum_{i=1}^n[i^{k+1} - \sum_{j=0}^{k+1} {k+1 \choose j} i^j] = n^{k+1}&lt;/math&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;math&gt;\sum_{i=1}^n[i^{k+1} - {k+1 \choose k+1} i^{k+1} - \sum_{j=0}^k {k+1 \choose j} i^j] = n^{k+1}&lt;/math&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;math&gt;\sum_{i=1}^n[\sum_{j=0}^k {k+1 \choose j} i^j] = n^{k+1}&lt;/math&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;math&gt;\sum_{j=0}^k[\sum_{i=1}^n {k+1 \choose j} i^j] = n^{k+1}&lt;/math&gt;(Huh, I think I'll have to write another sub-chapter on the nested/2-dimensional sum notation operation...)&lt;p&gt;
&lt;math&gt;\sum_{j=0}^k[{k+1 \choose j} \sum_{i=1}^n i^j] = n^{k+1}&lt;/math&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I think things should be clear now :)

However, after doing this question I feel the urge to feedback my strong opinion on this solution. The exsistence of a formula is usually to help people do calculation faster and easier, but like above, the result is that the formula relies on combining all of the pervious formula in that series, although the formula is still a finite calculation, but when k increases to somewhere like 10, the so called &quot;formula&quot; will become so complex that it lost its elegence, and that it doesn't serve the function of reliefing difficulties in calculations anymore.
[[User:Lemontea|Lemontea]] 10:37, 28 Dec 2004 (GMT+8)
:You are right about the coefficient, i just forgot. Good wook. You comment about the solution is correct, may i remind you that the point of the question is to test induction skills, although you are absolutely right about the deficiency of the question. Thanks. [[User:Xiaodai|Xiaodai]] 03:01, 28 Dec 2004 (UTC)

I know that for mathematicians, it is considered an art to say just enough....to find a balance between not giving every single step, but yet making the point clear to a fellow mathematician.  However, non-mathematicians don't necessarily think this way.  I know we want the reader to think and ask, but we don't also want them to think they're stupid and give up.  It seems that one of the beauties of this sort of media is that perhaps we can provide the extra explanation, yet bury it with hyperlinks, etc.  The above discussion is one such example.[[User:Lizmaemom|Lizmaemom]] ([[User talk:Lizmaemom|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Lizmaemom|contribs]]) 23:56, 3 July 2011 (UTC)

== M5? ==

M5:for every a there exist b such that ab=1

What about 0? Does a inverse of 0 exist?
--[[User:Lemontea|Lemontea]] 13:42, 1 Mar 2005 (UTC)

: See, that's what I mean about messy (I don't mean the omission, that's an easy mistake to make, but the ''way'' the thing was structured). There's a better way of saying this (which I'll just say now, so you'll see what I mean). [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 22:25, 1 Mar 2005 (UTC)


== Incorrect Proof ==
A lot can be learned by being asked to find the mistaken logic in an incorrect proof, of which many can be found online.  One is as follows for Goldbach's conjecture:
::step 1:  Any even number &gt;=6 can be described by 6Q +b, b={-2,0,+2}
(thus any even number is either 2 behind, 2 ahead, or coincident with, a multiple of 6)
Thus, we can write E = 6Q +b
::step 2:  a recognized required (but not sufficient) condition for any prime&gt;=5 is that they are of the form 6N +/1 (it is 1 ahead or behind a multiple of 6)

::step 3:  rewrite step 1 as  (any) even = 6L+/-1 + 6M +/-1

We can substitute step 2 into step 3 and get:
::step 4:  (any &gt;3) even  = prime1 + prime2

the above essentially &quot;proves&quot; GC - where is the mistake in the proof?--[[User:Billymac00|Billymac00]] ([[User talk:Billymac00|talk]]) 02:41, 10 March 2008 (UTC)

== Feedback ==
This section is fascinating. I hope you can improve it. Some examples are tough to understand and I hope you can explain them better. --[[Special:Contributions/200.120.252.46|200.120.252.46]] ([[User talk:200.120.252.46|talk]]) 01:08, 5 May 2010 (UTC)

Shouldn't math mode be used for writing mathematical statements? --[[User:Ranadeakshay|ranade]]

== Additive Inverse ? ==

Here is axiom three in the Axioms and inference section :
A3: For every a, there exist b (written -a), such that a + b = 0 (existence of an additive inverse)
Not that I am mathematician or anything but I think inverse is not the right word, -a is the &lt;u&gt;opposit&lt;/u&gt; of a, right?

Would you have a place for this approach?
[http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/62/Sum_of_i.pdf A scientific approach to mathematics - Observation of patterns then proving them]

Mathematics is a hobby of mine and on more than one occasion, I've reinvented the wheel.  This paper is one such example.  Therefore, even though it is original work for me, Bernoulli was the first to use this approach.  At least that is what a Washington University professor told me.  This also means that it can be published on Wiki without violating the policy against original work.  It also means that I am free to offer it as public domain.  I have solved problems that only the greats in mathematics are given credit, but I lack a formal education in mathematics, so I would never be able to convince any journal to publish my work.  Yet, I've been able to impress others with my knowledge and ability to invent new approaches to solve problems.  Being in a position without the credentials, I always provide irrefutable evidence that my approaches are correct.  Most Ph.D professors can't say the same.  I don't need credit for any of my work in math nor do I need any money.  I'm making a comfortable living using my mind in the sciences.  But, I would be greatly rewarded if I could share some of my understanding with young people.  I'd like to get other people to think outside the box.  The traditional lessons are important, but I would also like to see young people learn the value of creativity.  Mathematics is also tainted with an image of logic and theory instead of as a true science.  The paper that I'm offering here is a good example of how a problem can be solved by starting with observation.</text>
      <sha1>2p3xv3crsu1bmiza2gpu35yk9o85rca</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Thunderbunny</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>3260</id>
    <revision>
      <id>155211</id>
      <timestamp>2003-12-13T22:53:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Thunderbunny</username>
        <id>344</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">I am a software engineer from Pennsylvania.

I currently am working on the C book on Wikibooks.</text>
      <sha1>519ayhrpjr6e75i7i2qamty5u6539me</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Pingveno</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>3262</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1072683</id>
      <parentid>479030</parentid>
      <timestamp>2008-01-01T21:52:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>67.189.107.89</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">AIM at Pingveno42

[[wikipedia:User:Pingveno|User Page from Wikipedia]]</text>
      <sha1>rom0taezcdv38dsfj1fu1jl2olch2mq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>