<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Peanut Curry Sauce</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>4347</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2688385</id>
      <parentid>1760151</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-03T18:58:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Austncorp</username>
        <id>1540792</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Austncorp moved page [[Cookbook:Peanut Sauce]] to [[Cookbook:Peanut Curry Sauce]]: This name is more descriptive of the actual recipe.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{recipe}} | [[Cookbook:Sauces|Sauces]]
{{recipesummary|Sauce recipes|2|30 minutes|2}}

==Ingredients==
*¾ [[Cookbook:Cup|cup]] (about 170 [[Cookbook:mL|mL]]) roasted [[Cookbook:Peanut|peanut]]s (unsalted)
*4 cups (about 1 [[Cookbook:L|L]]) [[Cookbook:Coconut Milk|coconut milk]] (unsweetened) 
*2 [[Cookbook:Tablespoon|tbsp.]] (about 30 mL) [[Cookbook:Red curry paste|red curry paste]]
*2 tbsp. (about 30 mL) [[Cookbook:Sugar|sugar]]
*3 tbsp. (about 45 mL) [[Cookbook:Lemon Juice|lemon juice]]
*3 [[Cookbook:Teaspoon|tsp.]] (about 15 mL) [[Cookbook:Fish Sauce|fish sauce]]
==Procedure==
#Chop or grind peanuts into a fine meal.
#Heat half the coconut milk in a medium [[Cookbook:Saucepan|saucepan]] on high heat, and add red curry paste. Stir until curry paste is dissolved and then continue to heat on high for 10 - 12 minutes (not stirring) until the oil from the coconut milk has risen to the top.
#Decrease heat to medium-high and add ground peanuts. Stir and add the rest of the coconut milk, bring to a full boil then decrease heat, add the sugar, lemon juice and fish sauce.
#Continue to cook (stirring occasionally) for 15-20 minutes, until the sauce has thickened and the oil has risen to the surface again.
#Take off heat and let set for about half an hour. Stir to blend in the oil that has risen, the sauce should be not quite as thick as peanut butter. If it seems too thick add about a teaspoon of water or coconut milk.

Enjoy this as a dip or sauce on most any [[Cookbook:Grilling|grilled]] [[Cookbook:Meat|meat]], or thin with water to [[Cookbook:Marinating|marinate]] or use as a dressing.

[[Category:Curry recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Sauce recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Thai recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Peanut recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Coconut recipes|{{PAGENAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>9wzzgf4nzu2o3ums894vjwkygsw9mos</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:Karl Wick/Archive 1</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>4348</id>
    <revision>
      <id>374671</id>
      <parentid>156128</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-02-22T21:24:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>formatting</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">The document I wrote was designed to ''supplement'' a particular physics textbook, and moreover, was written at a high school level.  I don't know how well it could be adapted to this project, but I will see what I can do.  Unfortunately, I am slightly burdened by (a) a summer class from 8:30AM to 5:00PM, and (b) summer reading, and most of my free time is going to the calculus textbook.

I am glad to see that you are doing organic chemistry -- I really like chemistry, but my chemistry class never made it to the chapter on organic chemistry, so this is a good oppurtunity for me to learn more about it.
 -- [[User:IntMan|IntMan]]
----
I've changed some of your book title capitalizations. It seems to me that these are not Wikipedia articles. If we'd expect any of these to stand alone as a publication, then we ought to capitalize titles. OK? ....[[User:LouI|LouI]] 11:50 26 Jul 2003 (UTC)

:Yeah - books and chapters are capitalized a lot. --[[User:Maveric149|Maveric149]] 12:08 26 Jul 2003 (UTC)

:OK -- [[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]] 15:01 26 Jul 2003 (UTC)
----
Karl, would you please delete [[Textbook developement process]]. My inability to spell is recorded in page history (I moved the page). We don't need a redirect page as additional proof. :). ... Thanks, [[User:LouI|LouI]] 20:24 27 Jul 2003 (UTC)
:Done - (I am personally one of the worlds worst spellers). [[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]] 22:59 27 Jul 2003 (UTC)
----
Hi Karl, thanks for your excitement about the Spanish book. I am _very_ glad
to got you as a bilingual speaker interested (I am actually just starting to learn Spanish by my own and took the recommendation by heart that encourages
not just teachers but also students of any subject to write Wikibooks :). Your
organic chemistry book is nicely structured, I'll certainly browse through it
every once in a while to track the progress (maybe even contribute some stuff,
though my organic chemistry is a little bit rusty since I had it in my German
high school about six years ago...)
:Thats great man. Just to make sure, you are not copying anything directly from a published Spanish textbook right ? We have to be careful to create new content only. I will certainly lend a hand in the Spanish book and best of luck learning the language. You must already speak German then .. any other languages ? --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

::Hi Karl, I really appreciate your nice comments about the Spanish book. That really keeps me motivated. About other languages: I had French in high school for a couple of years but haven't used it since... [[User:ThomasStrohmann|Thomas]]
----
Please delete that page, [[The Empires]]. I made it by mistake. [[User:LittleDan|LittleDan]] 14:02 7 Aug 2003 (UTC)
----
Hi Karl. Yes, the succinct contents page looks good. I think it will be especially convenient for frequent users of the book to quickly check on certain vocabulary/grammar. [[User:ThomasStrohmann|Thomas]]

Me again :) Your table of contents are definitely very helpful. I also really appreciate that it is now possible to edit just a part of a document (was this a general update of the wiki software running here?). Your pictures are nice, they should make the book more fun to read. [[User:ThomasStrohmann|Thomas]]&lt;br&gt;
P.S. You should consider yourself as well to be one of the 'founders' of the Spanish/language textbooks with all the effort you have put it. Thanks so much for that!
-----
Answer to your comment in the talks [[User_talk:Wintermute|Wintermute]] page.

Karl, thanks to you by the project. I like it a lot. My first language is spanish.

[[User:Wintermute|Wintermute]] 22:02, 12 Aug 2003 (UTC)
----
Thanks for updating Main page, it looks better. As good news and bad news, we may soon need to stop listing all the books or go to a more compressed or framed page like Wikipedia uses. ...[[User:LouI|LouI]] 19:17, 13 Aug 2003 (UTC)

:If we have too many books to list easily I take that as AWESOME news. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

---------------
Hey Karl. What is the copyright status of [[:Image:Novios.jpg]]? And even if the copyright status is OK, we also need permission from the people photographed that we can use their likeness here. Only celebrities don't have this right. --[[User:Maveric149|mav]] 01:12, 17 Aug 2003 (UTC)

:Hey Mav, I took the photo myself of a couple of friends, and am sure that they will have no problem with us using it but can talk to them about it to make sure. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

------------
k:&quot;A poco hablas el espanol ... yo estuve viviendo en Mexico por unos anos, en DF .. me encanto, todavia estaria alla si huberia encontrado otro trabajo. Me encantan las chicas latinas y en general toda la cultura latina. De donde eres ? Latinoamerica o Espana o otro lugar ?&quot;

w: Espana

k: Entonces vas a poder corregir el mal espanol que ponemos en el libro de Spanish (por favor !) 

w: I will try..

Where k = Karl

and   w = [[User:Wintermute|Wintermute]] 21:38, 17 Aug 2003 (UTC)
   
----------
Karl,
&lt;br&gt;
If you by any chance intend to do a mass import of Shakespeare plays into
Wikibooks please take a look at
http://metalab.unc.edu/xml/examples/shakespeare/. It is a repository of
Shakespeare in XML that with a small quick script can convert all Shakespeare
to Wikipedia markup.&lt;br&gt;--[[User:Kpjas|Kpjas]] 06:50, 27 Aug 2003 (UTC)

:Thanks man, I couldn't get it to run in my MS browser on Mac 9.x but will check it out when I am on another machine. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
::I don't know if you are familliar with XML. This is file format of tagged text and the real benefit is that it is machine-readable data and there is plethora of scripts, libraries and programs that can extract or transform the textual information any way you wish.&lt;br&gt;It is not very exciting to view in a browser but with a rather simple script you can convert '''all''' Shakespeare plays into for example Wikipedia markup in a matter of minutes.&lt;br&gt;--[[User:Kpjas|Kpjas]] 22:14, 27 Aug 2003 (UTC)

::Wow that sounds real cool .. is there a script already written or would someone have to write it ? All I know about XML is what I glean from science mags, I've not used it .. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
----
I'm glad you like my diagrams. I intend to add loads more as time goes on.I love this project and will be dividing my spare time unequally between here and wikipedia from now on. [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 15:21, 29 Aug 2003 (UTC)

----
Thanks for the [[Main Page]] praise, but I only made a little fix to[[User::Geoffrey]]'s table, he did all the work. --[[User:Magnus Manske|Magnus Manske]]
----
[[:Image:Sp3.jpg]] made me smile. It's bloody brilliant! [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 17:41, 1 Sep 2003 (UTC)

----
Karl when you upload a new version of an old image, you should do so with the same file name. That way the image is updated on all the pages it's linked to without any further effort on you part, plus you don't get orphan images. You don't lose the old image either, it's there on the description page, so you can just revert if you want to. [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 21:28, 4 Sep 2003 (UTC)

:Oh .. yeah .. thanks. -- [[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
----

You've probably seen this before, but if not- enjoy![[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]]
http://www.bris.ac.uk/Depts/Chemistry/MOTM/silly/sillymols.htm

----
Hi,

About adding the rest of Othello. 
I have hacked up a small Perl script to turn XML into Wiki markup and it was
quite easy. I am a little hesitant to add more because I don't know if
minor glitches (like some capitalisations or some text escaping wikification)
are acceptable and if the problems with annotations have been resolved yet.
&lt;br&gt;Please give me a go-ahead and blessing and I can add all Shakespeare
plays at the rate of 2-3 a day.
&lt;br&gt;The script is not very brilliant and surely can be still improved. Even
amateurs have sometimes to have a go at coding to get things done.
&lt;br&gt;[[User:Kpjas|Kpjas]] 00:00, 10 Sep 2003 (UTC)

----
Sorry, dude, accidentally rev'd your sp3 image...I think I fixed it but y'all might want to check. I'm new to the whole 'wiki' thing. :)

BTW, sweet image, takes me back to chem class just looking at it.

: [[User:Etothex|Etothex]] 05:04, 10 Sep 2003 (UTC)

----
I can see you are having fun (re: [[Botany]] Study Guide) ;^)  Changes look good INMHO. - [[User:Marshman|Marshman]] 19:11, 10 Sep 2003 (UTC)

:Thanks Marshman, at your humble service. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

:Don't you love what can be accomplished when people collaborate? -- [[User:Marshman|Marshman]]

----
Thanks for pointing out me error in wording for [[Organic Chemistry/Foundational concepts of organic chemistry/Covalent bonding|covalent bonding]]. What I actually said was not what I meant at all, I have fixed it now {Hopefully} [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 20:23, 11 Sep 2003 (UTC)

----
===The Shakespeare plays===
&lt;br&gt;Sure I will put a long string of Shakespeare plays on Wikibooks.
&lt;br&gt;'''''Romeo and Julliet''''' is in the pipeline.
&lt;br&gt;Wikimedia servers were rather slow in the past few days.
&lt;br&gt;I have been thinking and wondering - what about navigation through
scenes and acts. What about annotations - has anything been decided yet ?
&lt;br&gt;BTW did you know that Polish transliteration of the name &quot;Shakespeare&quot; is
&quot;Szekspir&quot;.  
&lt;br&gt;[[User:Kpjas|Kpjas]] 21:44, 11 Sep 2003 (UTC)

:Huh ... About navigations, that would be great if we could do that automatically, to at least have a link back to the contents page of the play and to the next and previous scenes. Magnus I think was writing up some code to allow for annotatios but I'm guessing it has to be approved before it is added to the official Wiki software update. That will be a great feature for the shakesperean plays as well as my textbooks .. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

----
Thanks for welcoming me back, Karl :) I really enjoy being part of the Wikibooks community -- [[User:ThomasStrohmann|Thomas]]

===Botany page===
Karl. When you were setting up the separate pages for the Botany Guide, one of them got misspelled (''Introducion'' instead of ''Introduction'') I do not have status to correct this. Can you?  Thanks! - [[User:Marshman|Marsh]] 00:56, 20 Sep 2003 (UTC)

:Oops ! Sorry about that Marshman. I kent spell reel good, even when it counts. But its correctid now. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
----
Thanks for thinking about making me an administrator. I would definitely be interested
in doing that - [[User:ThomasStrohmann | Thomas]]

-----------------
What? Where was the discussion about a logo change? [[Wikibooks:Staff_lounge#Logo]] is much better concept, IMO. For one thing it has more than one book. --[[User:Maveric149|mav]] 08:59, 24 Sep 2003 (UTC)

----
You've already nominated me for adminship here [[Wikibooks:Requests for adminship]] I think that no developer has got around to doing it yet though :-(

Can you take a look at  [[:Image:Microscope diagram 1.png]] and [[:Image:Microscope diagram.png]] for me please. I tried to copy them from wikipedia and it just won't upload properly. I can't see what I am doing wrong. [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 17:05, 24 Sep 2003 (UTC)
::(later) actually &quot;microscope diagram 1&quot; is fine. I just need you to delete &quot;microscope diagram&quot; for me. I think I must have &quot;saved target&quot; rather than &quot;save picture&quot; when I copied it. [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 17:25, 24 Sep 2003 (UTC)
-----
Hey Karl, is there a reason why you are ignoring my logo question? --mav

:I didn't realize you had a question. What is it? --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
:Oh, you must mean, discussion about the logo change. Well, I think hands-down the one I have up there now is better than the old one. I have no problem with getting rid of it when we have a better one... I personally my current one better than the one on the staff lounge but if &quot;the people&quot; have another opinion the community decides. However I hope our new logo will be nicer-looking than the one they just chose for the Wikipedia, which I think is a step down from the previous one. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
-----
To Karl Wick, Greeting.

My book on the Constitution and Government appears to be complete (for the time being.) Do you know of any related topics about which persons might be curious?
[[User:c|Lord Emsworth]]

:Lord Emsworth, Dude, you rock !! You have the notoriety of having the very first &quot;finished&quot; Wikibook. I'll look it over and keep my eyes open to learn a lot about it. Let me get back to you about related topics .. the government and political processes are not my strength. Are you a history buff ? Social sciences wizard ? You seem to work a lot faster than I do, or maybe know your material a lot better. I am going to send out an email announcing your accomplishment. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
----
Hi,

Concerning annotation. I think you as a respected figure behind the whole idea of Wikibooks should alert developers and other good people that we need annotation badly. Without it, it hardly makes sense to flood Wikibooks pages with streams of words fine crafted by Shakespeare.
&lt;br&gt;Another thing. While Wikipedia is lovable for its content and since it is
our encyclopedia it can stand against other commercial encyclopedias (and win in the end) even without all the glamour of multimedia, I am not so sure as far as wiki textbooks go. I wish we had some software power that we could eventually use and we don't even have table wiki markup. To instruct with streams of printed words only would be enough. To assess progress of students even without Javascript capabilities ? Brainstorm... in wikitech-l ?
&lt;br&gt;Regards,
&lt;br&gt;[[User:Kpjas|Kpjas]] 20:11, 30 Sep 2003 (UTC)

:Kpjas, I agree about getting some software backing us up. I would write some myself if I had any idea how. My hope is that with time and more content, we can attract more developer attention to the project. I have asked around about the annotation feature, and could use it myself. I'll be a bit more persistant now and see what I can get going. I think it will help when the contributions start flowing into the foundation, maybe we could hire somebody full time to write code. Although that seems like what Brion and some of these other guys do already ... --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
-----
Good day.

I express my sincere thanks for adding navigational links to [[US Constitution and Government]]. I find your page on [[User:Lord Emsworth|myself]] most intriguing, as well, especially the reference to a &quot;borrowed internet browser.&quot; [[User:Lord Emsworth|Lord Emsworth]] 21:59, 2 Oct 2003 (UTC)

Sorry, I entirely overlooked the first chapter of [[US History]]. My sincere apologies, [[User:Lord Emsworth|Lord Emsworth]] 23:31, 4 Oct 2003 (UTC).

-----------------
Opps! The tag is &lt;nowiki&gt;__NOTOC__&lt;/nowiki&gt; not _NOTOC_ . --[[User:Maveric149|mav]]

:Got it. Thanks, Mav. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
----------
Good day.

Your message regarding the official California Standards interests me. I will definitely look into them and see how well they can be applied to the present textbook on US History. 

It appears that the standards can be best approached as follows: Writing the book according to present structure for the time being, but then conducting a complete revision of the book based on California's standards. The standards are very exhaustive while the book as present does not go into as much detail. [[User:Lord Emsworth|Lord Emsworth]] 22:39, 10 Oct 2003 (UTC)

:Lord Emsworth: if you can write a book that meets the standards, you will singlehandedly put Wikibooks on the map. Well, its always a team thing I guess .. but you know what I mean. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
----
I'm sorry, I can't find your username on the main wikipedia. I just got your email, and I'd like to know, exactly what unconstructive email are you refering to? I ''try'' to consider whether or not my emails are constructive, and often, I don't send an email because I realise that it's not constructive. [[User:LittleDan|LittleDan]] 22:11, 11 Oct 2003 (UTC)
----
Karl Wick,

I have no particular expertise in history. I am just intersted in the topic. I know bits and pieces of information, and what I don't know, I merely look up. --[[User:Lord Emsworth|Lord Emsworth]] 22:52, 11 Oct 2003 (UTC)

----

==Smart quotes==
Hi :) Just a little thing, do you think using smartquotes is the best thing to use? They won't show up with non-unicode-supporting browsers/fonts. Would it be best to stick to the Wikip' smartquote policy? [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 08:07, 12 Oct 2003 (UTC)

:Hi Dysprosia, I'm probably not the best person to know the answer to this question. I didn't know that there were browsers that did not support them, or that WP had a policy about it. You mean quotes like the one on my organic chemistry [[organic chemistry|splash page]]? M$IE, Netscape family, and Konquerer all support them right ? &amp;quot; --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

::Yep, on the splash page is where I saw it - as far as I know IE, Moz, Firebird all show it, not sure about Konq. The real issue is people trying to view the pages on something old like a pre-OS X Macintosh, or on many older browsers that don't support Unicode/all the little HTML doodads :) 
:: Maybe it would be best to switch to straight-quotes, a whole less trouble all round. Some educational institutions may be using older software.
:: As to WP's stance, you can see on [[en:Wikipedia:Special characters]]. [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 22:29, 14 Oct 2003 (UTC)

== Annotation feature ==

Hi Karl, the annotation feature (well, parts of it) were deleted by accident. I'll try to get it back and working soon. --[[User:Magnus Manske|Magnus Manske]] 17:07, 21 Oct 2003 (UTC)

----
Hi Karl. 
I'm glad you missed me. I've been off work for a couple of weeks for the half term holiday. I stayed at my sister's [doesn't own a computer :-( ], but not to worry I'm back now. (refreshed after my break and ready to go).

----
Thanks for the quiz maker link, but it uses javascript :-( [which isn't parsed by the wiki software) I'll keep it in mind for the future though. [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]]

----
Hi Karl. I (sort of) finished my draft of the first [[biochemistry]] chapter and noticed that (unsurprisingly) it shares quite a few items with [[Organic Chemistry]], e.g. Gibb's free enrgy, pKa values etc. I think these are more OC than BC, so if you like anything in my text, feel free to loot :-) --[[User:Magnus Manske|Magnus Manske]] 21:18, 16 Nov 2003 (UTC)
----
Karl, Thanks for the '''personalised''' welcome!!
--[[User:Noldoaran|Noldoaran]] 03:17, 21 Nov 2003 (UTC)
----
Hello, Karl. I was merely taking a temporary break from the site, concentrating on the main Wikipedia for a while. I shall soon return. [[User:Lord Emsworth|Lord Emsworth]] 20:17, 22 Nov 2003 (UTC)
----
Thanks for the welcome; I'm afraid I might not have a lot of time to devote, but hopefully slow and steady will get the job done. :) - [[User:Hephaestos|Hephaestos]] 06:01, 2 Dec 2003 (UTC)

==Picture floating==

making the text of an article float around the text is fairly easy.  Instead of just typing in the image's address, use the following table.

&lt;nowiki&gt;
&lt;div
&lt;style=&quot;float:right;width:XXXpx;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Image:Name of Image.pgn]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;small&gt;''Caption''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;

Obviously, change the float to where you want it on the page, left right or center, the Width:XXXpx to the image's width in pixels (I usually add 5-10 pixels to keep a border between the image and the text).

Hope this helps. :) [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] 00:41, 9 Jan 2004 (UTC)

Don't worry too much about the languages thing - I always go to the Recent Changes page straight off. So it's no extra clickyclicky for me! [[User:R3m0t|r3m0t]] 08:40, 18 Jan 2004 (UTC)

You can cry on my sholder anytime. IMO the language thing will get sorted out in time. Meanwhile your work has not been lost. [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]] 08:22, 19 Jan 2004 (UTC)

== Spirituality? ==

What's this new page you've made?
:Just a little note to myself and for a couple of non-wiki-initiated friends .. but feel free to use it if you think it can serve you. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]] P.S. Thanks for the note, just when I started to wonder if anyone would write me ever again ..</text>
      <sha1>0aun5lhjlbw66rhhcih3t51cwlq2z8l</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Chinese (Mandarin)/Lesson 7</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4349</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2516929</id>
      <parentid>2063976</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-04-27T11:38:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Andyhowlett</username>
        <id>717786</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* 的 */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Chinese (Mandarin)TOC}}
&lt;div class=&quot;noprint&quot;&gt;{{TOCright}}&lt;/div&gt;
= Lesson 7: 这是什么? What's this? =

===Text 1===

''[[#Translation for the text|You can check out the translations here.]]''
*{{audio|Chinese-lesson-7-dialogue-1.ogg|Listen to audio}}

{| width=&quot;65%&quot;
|王明：这是什么？&lt;br&gt;
李红：这是书。&lt;br&gt;
王明：那是什么？&lt;br&gt;
李红：那是钢笔。&lt;br&gt;
王明：那是杂志吗？&lt;br&gt;
李红：不，那不是杂志。那是字典。&lt;br&gt;
||
Wáng Míng: Zhè shì shěnme?&lt;br&gt;
Lǐ Hóng: Zhè shì shū.&lt;br&gt;
Wáng Míng: Nà shì shěnme?&lt;br&gt;
Lǐ Hóng: Nà shì gāngbǐ.&lt;br&gt;
Wáng Míng: Nà shì zázhì ma?&lt;br&gt;
Lǐ Hóng: Bù, nà bùshì zázhì. Nà shì zìdiǎn.&lt;br&gt;
|}

===Text 2===
*{{audio|Chinese-lesson-7-dialogue-2.ogg|Listen to audio}}

{| width=&quot;70%&quot;
|王明是中国人。&lt;br&gt;
王明是学生。&lt;br&gt;
史密斯是美国人。&lt;br&gt;
史密斯是王明的朋友。&lt;br&gt;
史密斯是律师。&lt;br&gt;
||
|Wáng Míng shì Zhōngguórén.&lt;br&gt;
Wáng Míng shì xuéshēng.&lt;br&gt;
Shīmìsī shì Měiguórén.&lt;br&gt;
Shīmìsī shì Wángmíng de péngyǒu.&lt;br&gt;
Shīmìsī shì lǜshī.&lt;br&gt;
|}

===Vocabulary===
{| width=&quot;80%&quot;
|-
|&lt;li&gt;王明 (Wáng Míng)
|''n.'' Wang Ming [personal name] [Wang= Family Name, Ming=First name/Personal name]
|-
|&lt;li&gt;李红／李紅 (Lǐ Hóng)
|''n.'' Li Hong [personal name] [Li= Family Name, Hong= First/Personal name]
|-
|&lt;li&gt;这/這 (zhè)
|''pron.'' this
|-
|&lt;li&gt;是 (shì)
|''v.'' to be (is/are)
|-
|&lt;li&gt;什么／甚麼 (''Mainland'' shěnme&lt;br /&gt;and ''Taiwan'' shěme)
|''pron.'' what
|-
|&lt;li&gt;那 (nà)
|''pron.'' that
|-
|&lt;li&gt;笔 (bǐ)
|''n.'' pen; a generic term for all pens
|-
|&lt;li&gt;钢笔 (gāngbǐ)
|''n.'' fountain pen
|-
|&lt;li&gt;铅笔 (qiānbǐ)
|''n.'' pencil
|-
|&lt;li&gt;原子笔 (yuánzíbǐ)
|''n.'' ballpoint pen
|-
|&lt;li&gt;毛笔 (máobǐ)
|''n.'' brush (calligraphy pen)
|-
|&lt;li&gt;杂志 (zázhì)
|''n.'' magazine
|-
|&lt;li&gt;报纸 (bàozhī)
|''n.'' newspaper
|-
|&lt;li&gt;书本 (shūběn)
|''n.'' book
|-
|&lt;li&gt;传单 (chuándān)
|''n.'' pamphlet
|-
|&lt;li&gt;吗 (ma)
|final interrogative particle used&lt;br /&gt;to form a question sentence
|-
|&lt;li&gt;不 (bù)
|''adv.'' no
|-
|&lt;li&gt;字典 (zìdiǎn)
|''n.'' dictionary
|-
|&lt;li&gt;人 (rén)
|''n.'' person/people
|-
|&lt;li&gt;中国人 (Zhōngguórén)
|''n.'' PRC Chinese (中国：China　人：people)
|-
|&lt;li&gt;外国人 (WàiGuórén)
|''n.'' Foreigners (外：Outside　国：Country　人：People)
|-
|&lt;li&gt;日本人 (Rìběnrén)
|''n.'' Japanese (日本：Japan 人：People)
|-
|&lt;li&gt;英国人 (Yīngguórén)
|''n.'' British (英国：Britain 人：People)
|-
|&lt;li&gt;新加坡人 (Xīnjiāpōrén)
|''n.'' Singaporean （新加坡：Singapore)
|-
|&lt;li&gt;美国人 (měiguórén)
|''n.'' American
|-
|&lt;li&gt;学生 (xuéshēng)
|''n.'' student
|-
|&lt;li&gt;老师 (lǎoshī)
|''n.'' teacher
|-
|&lt;li&gt;校长 (xiàozhǎng)
|''n.'' principal
|-
|&lt;li&gt;史密斯 (Shǐmìsī)
|''n.'' Smith
|-
|&lt;li&gt;美国人 (Měiguórén)
|''n.'' American
|-
|&lt;li&gt;朋友 (péngyǒu)
|''n.'' friend
|-
|&lt;li&gt;律师 (lǜshī)
|''n.'' lawyer
|}
{| width=&quot;80%&quot;
|
* 笔记本/筆記本 (bǐjìběn)
* 铅笔/鉛筆 (qiānbǐ)
* 英国人/英國人 (Yīngguórén) 
* 法国人/法國人 (Fǎguórén)
* 报纸/報紙 (bàozhǐ)
* 老师/老師 (lǎoshī)
* 作家 (zuòjiā)
||
|
''n.'' notepads &lt;br /&gt;
''n.'' pencil &lt;br /&gt;
''n.'' British people &lt;br /&gt;
''n.'' French people &lt;br /&gt;
''n.'' newspaper&lt;br /&gt;
''n.'' teacher &lt;br /&gt;
''n.'' writer &lt;br /&gt;
|}

==== Stroke orders  ====
:[[Image:王-bw.png|250px]]
:[[Image:明-bw.png|450px]]
:[[Image:李-bw.png|400px]]

''More [[:commons:Category:Chinese_stroke_order_in_BW_pictures|stroke orders]] will be added if it's helpful.''

==Grammar==
===Chinese Names===
{| border=&quot;0&quot; cellpadding=&quot;5&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; 
|-
|style=&quot;background:#FFFFCC;&quot; | In Chinese names, the family name comes before the given name. Family names are passed down paternally and usually have only one character. Chinese given names are usually two characters long, but may also be one character.

Hence a man called 王明 (Wáng Míng) is addressed as Mr. Wang, not Mr. Ming. A woman called 李红 (Lǐ Hóng) is addressed as Mrs./Miss Li.

However, if the person has a western personal name, it is presented in the GIVEN-NAME/FAMILY-NAME format, following the Western convention. Hence if 李红 (Lǐ Hóng) has a western-style personal name of Mary, she is usually introduced as &quot;Mary Li&quot; and not &quot;Li Mary&quot;
|}&lt;br&gt;

In this lesson, we learn how to say &quot;something is something&quot; in Chinese. The first thing you need to know is that the sentence structure of Chinese is very similar to that of English in that they both follow the pattern of Subject-Verb-Object (SVO). But unlike many Western languages, verbs in Chinese aren't conjugated and noun and adjective endings don't change. They are never affected by things such as time or person.

===这(/那)是什么？===
This sentence means &quot;What's this/that?&quot;:
#这是什么？(What's this?)
#那是什么？(What's that?)

The sentences, if broken down literally, shows that the ordering of words differs in English and Chinese:
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|------------------------------
| 这/那      || 是 ||  什么 || ?
|------------------------------
| this/that || is || what || ?
|------------------------------
|}

The order of the sentences may seem a little bit tricky, but don't worry about that, we will discuss this later.

===A　是　B===
This sentence means &quot;A is B.&quot;

&quot;是&quot; (shì), the equational verb ''to be'', can be used as the English ''is'' or ''equals''. When used in a simple Subject-Verb-Object sentence, the subject defines the object. Since Chinese verbs never change, no other forms for shì exist such as ''was'' or ''am'' in English. Also, articles like ''a'' and ''the'' are absent in Chinese. They are not translated.

For example:
#这是书 (zhe4 shi4 shu1): this is (a) book.
#那是杂志 (na4 shi4 za2 zhi4): that is (a) magazine.

===A　不是　B===
This sentence means &quot;A is not B.&quot; in which shì is negated when preceded by &quot;不&quot; (bu). &quot;不&quot; literally means &quot;no&quot;, &quot;not&quot;.

For example: 
*这不是书 (zhè bú shì shū): this is not (a) book.

Now, we come back to the &quot;what's this/that?&quot; questions. We already see that the order is a bit tricky comparing to the English question order. But comparing to the latter pattern &quot;A　是　B&quot;, we find the similarity: their orders are identically the same. In fact, like particles, question words make statements into questions without changing the order of the sentence. To make one, simply substitute the QW in for place the subject would be in the answer.

Comparison:
#这是'''书'''。(This is (a) book.)
#这是'''什么'''？(This is '''what'''?)

#那是'''杂志'''。(That is (a) magazine.)
#那是'''什么'''？(That is '''what'''?)

===吗===
&quot;吗&quot;(ma) is a final interrogative particle used to form a question sentence. Adding this character at the end of a '''statement''' transforms the sentence into a question. 

Example 1:
*这是书 (zhe4 shi4 shu1)。(This is (a) book.)
*:::: ↓
**这是书'''吗''' (zhe4 shi4 shu1 ma)？(Is this (a) book'''?''')

Example 2:
*这不是杂志 (zhe4 bu2 shi4 za2 zhi4)。(This is not (a) magazine.)
*:::: ↓
**这不是杂志'''吗'''(zhe4 bu2 shi4 za2 zhi4 ma)？(Isn't this (a) magazine'''?''')

===是/不===
&quot;是&quot; (shi4) can be used to answer a simple yes/no question. In this case, &quot;是&quot; means ''yes'', whilst &quot;不&quot; (bu2) or &quot;不是&quot; (bu2 shi4) means ''no'' (literally, ''not is'').

How to answer yes/no questions correctly in Chinese? Usually, it's the same as in English, but pay attention if the questions are negative, like &quot;Isn't this a book?&quot;. In Chinese, you answer to the questions, not the fact. If the question itself is a negative answer, use &quot;不是&quot; or simply &quot;不&quot;, vice versa. For example:
*A: 这不是书吗？zhe4 bu2 shi4 shu1 ma?  (Isn't this (a) book? = This is not a book, right?)
**B: '''是'''，这不是书。shi4, zhe4 bu2 shi4 shu1. ('''No''', this is not (a) book. = You are right; this is not a book.)
**B: '''不'''，这是书。bu4, zhe4 shi4 shu1. ('''Yes''', this is (a) book. = You're wrong; this ''is'' a book.)

A asks if that's a book in a negative way. If the object is not a book, you should nevertheless approve A's saying first. So we use &quot;是&quot; to acknowledge that A is correct, and then say &quot;this is not (a) book&quot; to emphasis A is right; In the case of that is a book, you should deny A's saying first, using &quot;不&quot; (no) to point out A is wrong, then make a new statement by noting that &quot;这是书&quot; (this ''is'' (a) book). One more example:
*他今天晚上不来参加宴会了，对吗？(He's not going to the party tonight, is he?)
**'''不'''，他肯定要来。('''Yes''', he's definitely coming.)
**'''是''' 啊，他很忙呢！('''No''', he's so busy!)

===的===
Character &quot;的&quot; (de) indicates that the previous word has possession of the next one. In English it functions like '''s'' or like the word ''of'' but with the position of possessor and possessee switched. For example:
#史密斯(Shǐ mì Sī)的书(shū: book) &lt;-&gt; Smith's book
#王明的钢笔 &lt;-&gt; Wang Ming's pen
#约翰** (Yuēhàn: John)的朋友** (péngyǒu: friend) &lt;-&gt; John's friend or a friend of John's

== Exercise ==
#Replace the underline words, and practice.
##史密斯是&lt;u&gt;美国人&lt;/u&gt;。
##*英国人
##*法国人
##这不是&lt;u&gt;杂志&lt;/u&gt;。
##*书
##*笔记本*
##*铅笔
#Replace the underline words, and then answer the questions with both positive answers and negative answers.
#*Example:
#*史密斯是&lt;u&gt;法国人&lt;/u&gt;吗？
#**是，史密斯是&lt;u&gt;法国人&lt;/u&gt;。
#**不，史密斯不是&lt;u&gt;法国人&lt;/u&gt;。
##那是&lt;u&gt;杂志&lt;/u&gt;吗？
##*钢笔
##*铅笔
##*报纸*
##王明是&lt;u&gt;学生&lt;/u&gt;吗？
##*律师
##*老师*
##*作家*
#Translate the following English into Chinese.
##Wang Ming is not a teacher. Wang Ming is a student. Wang Ming is a Chinese. Wang Ming is not an American.
##*Answer(答):王明不是位老師，王明是位學生。王明是位中國人，(但)王民不是位美國人。
##Smith is a lawyer. Smith is not a writer. Smith is an American. Smith is not a French.
##*Answer(答):Smith是位律師，Smith不是位作家。Smith是位美國人，Smith不是位法國人。
##This is Smith's book. That is Wang Ming's pen.
##*Answer(答):這是Smith的書，那是王明(Wang Ming)的筆。

== Further reading ==
'''Read the following article, and then answer the questions in Chinese.'''
:你好(nǐhǎo, hello)，我(wǒ, I)是王明。我是学生，我是中国人。这是史密斯。史密斯是我的&lt;sup&gt;'''1'''&lt;/sup&gt; 朋友，史密斯是律师。那是史密斯的妻子(qīzi, wife)，安娜(Ana)。安娜是我的英语(yīngyǔ, English language)老师。

::'''1.'''&lt;small&gt;&quot;我　的&quot; means &quot;my&quot;, we will discuss this in the next lesson.&lt;/small&gt;

'''Questions:'''
#Who is &quot;I&quot;?
#What does Smith do?
#Who is Ana?
#What does Ana do?

== Useful phrases ==

{| class=&quot;toccolours&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 2em 0 2em;&quot; width=&quot;95%&quot;
|-
|'''Greetings. How to greet people in Chinese?'''
*你好！(nǐhǎo): Hello!
*嗨！(hài): Hi!
*幸會 (xìng huì) Great to meet you!
*你吃过饭了吗？(nǐ chī guò fàn le ma?): Have you had your meal? (This is a causal greeting between friends etc. But it doesn't mean you are asked to a dinner! Another derivation of this phrase commonly used in Beijing is &quot;你吃了吗？&quot;)
*再见。(zàijiàn): Goodbye
*拜拜。(bāibāi): Bye-bye
*回头见。(huítóu jiàn): See you later.
|-
|}

==Translation for the text==
{| border=1 cellpadding=4 cellspacing=0 align=center
|------------------------------
|Chinese characters
||Sentences breakdown
||English translation
|------------------------------
|'''Text 1'''
王明：这是什么？&lt;br&gt;
(王明：這是什麼？)&lt;br&gt;
李红：这是书。&lt;br&gt;
(李紅：這是書。)&lt;br&gt;
王明：那是什么？&lt;br&gt;
(王明：那是什麼？)&lt;br&gt;
李红：那是钢笔。&lt;br&gt;
(李紅：那是鋼筆。)&lt;br&gt;
王明：那是杂志吗？&lt;br&gt;
(王明：那是雜誌嗎？)&lt;br&gt;
李红：不，那不是杂志。那是字典。&lt;br&gt;
(李紅：不，那不是雜誌。那是字典。)&lt;br&gt;
||'''Text 1'''
Wang Ming: This is what?&lt;br&gt;
Li Hong: This is book.&lt;br&gt;
Wang Ming: That is what?&lt;br&gt;
Li Hong: That is pen.&lt;br&gt;
Wang Ming: That is magazine (''final interrogative particle'')?&lt;br&gt;
Li Hong: No, that not is magazine, this is dictionary.&lt;br&gt;
||'''Text 1'''
Wang Ming: What's this?&lt;br&gt;
Li Hong: This is a book.&lt;br&gt;
Wang Ming: What's that?&lt;br&gt;
Li Hong: That's a pen.&lt;br&gt;
Wang Ming: Is this a magazine?&lt;br&gt;
Li Hong: No, that's not a magazine. That's a dictionary.&lt;br&gt;
|------------------------------
|'''Text 2'''
王明是中国人。&lt;br&gt;
王明是学生。&lt;br&gt;
史密斯是美国人。&lt;br&gt;
史密斯是王明　的　朋友。&lt;br&gt;
史密斯是律师。&lt;br&gt;
||'''Text 2'''
Wang Ming is Chinese.&lt;br&gt;
Wang Ming is student.&lt;br&gt;
Smith is American.&lt;br&gt;
Smith is Wang Ming's friend.&lt;br&gt;
Smith is lawyer.&lt;br&gt;
||'''Text 2'''
Wang Ming is a Chinese.&lt;br&gt;
Wang Ming is a student.&lt;br&gt;
Smith is an American.&lt;br&gt;
Smith is Wang Ming's friend.&lt;br&gt;
Smith is a lawyer.&lt;br&gt;
|------------------------------
|}
----

{{Chinese (Mandarin)TOC}}

[[Category:{{FULLBOOKNAME}}|{{FULLCHAPTERNAME}}]]

[[de:Chinesisch: Lektion 7]]
[[it:Cinese/Lezione 7]]
[[pl:Chiński/Podstawy/Lekcja 7]]</text>
      <sha1>5b0h40d24l55j566184stqdyaynebeg</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Chinese (Mandarin)/Lesson 1</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>4350</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2255520</id>
      <parentid>2068840</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-01-22T21:57:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>79.176.136.189</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Question With 是 */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{WikiProject Languages}} 

==Question Words Section - Last Yellow Paragraph ==
I just added this blob as well as the brackets in examples 1 and 3 right above.  Feel free to remove or change it... I believe this generalization is correct but I am not that fluent.

==Is 他们 equivalent to 她们?==

In the 'sentences using shi' section, it's replaced, without any explanation.  Is it like French, with the ils/elles versions of 'they?'
:It is like the French ''ils/elles''; 他们 means a group of men or of men and women, while 她们 means a group of women exclusively. The example sentence is refering to a group of women.

==redundancy==

when the traditional and simplified characters are the same, i'll remove it to save space.
:Thanks for your help :) Now that lesson 1 is more or less done... time for lesson 2 I guess. How to get more people to participate though? -- [[User:Ran|Ran]] 06:56, 30 Oct 2004 (UTC)
:I would suggest advertising on the Chinese wikipedia.. or do a chinese lessons / english lessons exchange.
::I did a bit of advertising by putting the '''&lt;nowiki&gt;{{book}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;''' template tag in several Wikipedia articles like [[w:standard Mandarin|standard Mandarin]], [[w:Beijing dialect|Beijing dialect]], [[w:Chinese language|Chinese language]] and [[w:Mandarin (linguistics)|Mandarin]] and then redirects to the Chinese Wikibook contents page. --[[User:Everlong|Everlong]] 04:53, 21 Dec 2004 (UTC)
:I've removed the Beijing dialect link... (sorry.... but it seemed a bit far-fetched to me...) Thanks for the other three, though. ;) -- [[User:Ran|Ran]] 05:37, 21 Dec 2004 (UTC)

== '我叫艾美' is not a good example ==

:In English, you can say 'I'm Called duke'.It, however, means '我被叫作&quot;公爵&quot;' instead of '我叫公爵'。
:Actually, '叫' is not a common use here.You can consider it as 'am'(or 'be') in English.
:in chinese,sb. + be + ppl. = sb. + 被 + verb.'被' is the preposition here(of course,you can regard it as the helping verb)
:Ergo, this example would lead you to the wrong road in learning Chinese.
:in the end, sorry about my lame English^_^(and I would appreciate it if you could point out my mistake^_^)--[[User:Zhouxiao|Zhouxiao]] 12:21, 19 Mar 2005 (UTC)
::i wouldnt worry too much about it. the main thing is to get learners to say 我叫王 rather than 我是王, right? [[User:Nateji77|Nateji77]] 07:01, 7 October 2005 (UTC)
::I don't agree with [[User:Zhouxiao|Zhouxiao]].
--[[User:Dingar|Dingar]] 01:55, 19 October 2005 (UTC)
:: yeah, im a chinese and i dont agree with what Zhouxiao babbled neither, in the least [[User:KonW|KonW]] ([[User talk:KonW|talk]]) 14:39, 30 April 2009 (UTC)

== Archived Discussion ==

[http://en.wikibooks.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:Chinese_Lesson_1&amp;oldid=137060|19 Mar 2005]

== Tradtional and simplified characters ==

In the vocaublary lists, shouldn't the tradional and simplified words be in different columns to make it easier? -[[User:Pichu826|Pichu826]] 06:02, 29 Jun 2005 (UTC)
:I considered that when I made the original layout for the vocabulary, but I still think the one-column design is best and least distracting. It allows the closest side-by-side comparison without making a mostly empty column that would interfere with straight-across readings.  --[[User:Everlong|Everlong]] 04:43, 2 Jul 2005 (UTC)


I added &quot;when different&quot; just to add a little clarity (Yes, might be obvious, but this is lesson one of a language most have little to no familiarity with.  It's also unclear if the gender differences in the character for &quot;ni&quot; are only present in Traditional Chinese.  Also, with other pronouns.  Maybe that needs to be added separately as a lesson section. [[User:67.141.84.9|67.141.84.9]] 00:46, 30 May 2006 (UTC)

== Rearranging of the dialogues ==

I'm starting to learn Chinese, and I believe it would be helpfull to me (and very likely to others) if a dialogue was presented with all the translations; that is: dialogue 1 (simplified+traditional + pinyin + english) ;
dialogue 2 (simplified+traditional+pinyin+english)

That way, it is easier to find what every character means, without having to scroll continually up and down. 

I don't know how to change that myself, but I think that would be an improvement to an otherwise excellent page. 

Greetings,
--[[User:80.58.3.172|80.58.3.172]] 10:11, 19 July 2005 (UTC)

== SVO/S是O ==

in &quot;我是中国人&quot; etc, is ''zhongguoren''really an object? it's going back a long time to 7th grade english, but i thought it was a prepositional noun phrase or something similar, not an object (a direct object would take an accusative pronoun, him/her/us, while a prepositional noun would take a nominative, he/she/we, iirc). [[User:Nateji77|Nateji77]] 06:57, 7 October 2005 (UTC)

:You're right, Nateji. &quot;Be&quot; is an exception to the standard SVO-rule. It's actually a [[:w:Copula#Chinese|complement]]. I think it's fair to say that the analysis is valid for Chinese as well, since &quot;是&quot; is used as a copula in almost the exact same manner as in English.
:[[User:Peter Isotalo|Peter]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Peter Isotalo|Isotalo]]&lt;/sup&gt; 15:06, 8 April 2006 (UTC)

== 你vs.妳 ==

why does owen say 你 instead of 妳 in the traditional chinese dialogue in reference to ginny? [[User:Nateji77|Nateji77]] 07:05, 7 October 2005 (UTC)

:Thanks for pointing that out. An oversight in the writing, sorry. Now corrected. --[[User:Everlong|Everlong]] 08:28, 16 November 2005 (UTC)

I'm pretty sure &quot;妳&quot; is bogus, not commonly used in modern Chinese.
Only one of the four Chinese dictionaries at hand lists it, and I don't
recall ever seeing it in any textbook (just double-checked a couple).
And my Chinese teacher, who is a native speaker, said she thinks it may
have been used in classical Chinese but not in modern Chinese.  So
lesson 1 should show 你, not 妳.
--[[User:Yakowenko|Yakowenko]] ([[User talk:Yakowenko|talk]]) 03:35, 17 March 2009 (UTC)

:your teacher is no doubt a mainlander ,cause ppl in Taiwan(or maybe Hongkong Macau still now)use 妳.[[User:KonW|KonW]] ([[User talk:KonW|talk]]) 14:22, 30 April 2009 (UTC)

== Proper Nouns ==

I'm new to editing wiki stuff, sorry if I make stupid mistakes... But... In the Proper nouns section, I think it would look better if the country names had their traditional writings inside parentheses, as stated near the subtitle... E.g.: &quot;中国 (中國)&quot;.

:You're right. When I first made up the vocab list I thought it would look cluttered to list the alternate writing for one character so manyt times, but it's better to have a consistent format all the way through. Made the changes to bring it in line with the rest of the vocabulary.   --[[User:Everlong|Everlong]] 08:22, 16 November 2005 (UTC)

== New Vocabulary Table ==

I think that we should use wikitables for the vocabulary lists. The current vocab lists are too cluttered and are hard to read. We could make a clearer division between simplified and traditional characters by putting them into separate colums, rather than parenthases. Also, this is easier to show masculine and feminine types of characters without putting them into parenthases, as those changes could be mistaken for traditional characters. I hope everyone understands what I mean.

[[User:Geoking66|Geoking66]] 07:54, 20 March 2006 (UTC)
:I personally think the current arrangement is better than it would be using the wikitable template. I originally tablified the vocab (before it was a bulleted list), and put a lot of thought into its construction. 

:The wikitable change took away the vocab numbering, decreased the contrast from the background (especially in printed versions), and spread columns apart due to the wide traditional column. I had debated having traditional in it's own column when I first made the vocab table, but ultimately decided that it would be best close to the simplified (making comparisons easier), and not taking up a whole column which also separates the characters from the pinyin and meaning columns. It's better to have them in closer proximity than that. 

:About possible masculine/feminine confusion, the current setup is technically correct, as the character 妳 does not exist in simplified, so the m./f. distinction only exists in the traditional, thus it was put in parentheses. I agree it's maybe a little more confusing than it needs to be, so I'll add a note of warning later on. In any case, no more sexed personal pronouns have to be introduced and masculine/feminine doesn't exist in Chinese, so the issue only comes up within the first lesson. So I don't think the m./f. issue should be used as a reason for effecting a change that impacts the design of vocab presentation for every lesson (someday there will be more than two :).

:Believe me that I understand your argument and had debated myself over the very same design decision. It's still debatable, granted, but from my personal experience using several Chinese textbooks, and from trying to learn traditional while using a simplified-only text, this setup would most appeal to me as a learner.
::--[[User:Everlong|Everlong]] 16:46, 22 March 2006 (UTC)

== Audio template needed ==

The audio template has to be used in some form of another. It's not so much an issue of providing a help link, but rather that the license information has to be easily available to make sure people can easily check that that files are indeed under a free license, and to make it easier to show where to upload replacement files by native speakers.

[[User:Peter Isotalo|Peter]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Peter Isotalo|Isotalo]]&lt;/sup&gt; 10:40, 31 March 2006 (UTC)

:I know, I'm sorry for not coming up with a replacement for the Info links right away, but I just felt using the Audio template made the vocab list look really cluttered. My thoughts for how to make a better format include:
:#adding miniature pictures alongside the pinyin sort of like '{{stage short|100%|Info page for this file}}' that leads to the file info.
:#making a small speaker icon ([[Image:Gnome-speakernotes.png|15px|(Play this file)]]) that's the Media link while the pinyin is the info page link.
:#a separate page with all the sound file Info links, sort of like the Stroke Order page
:#or a new &quot;'''Listen'''&quot; column on the right side that shows &quot;[[Image:Gnome-speakernotes.png|15px|(Play this file)]] &lt;small&gt;([[:Image:zh-ta1.ogg|info]])&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&quot; for every word
:[[User:Everlong|Everlong]] 17:48, 31 March 2006 (UTC)


== I just wanted to say... ==
THANK YOU !!!!!!!!!!!!
(please erase if it's inappopriate)

== Individual word meanings needed ==

I think it would be very useful in this and following lessons for learners to be able to see the meanings of the individual words that make up phrases.

For example, the meaning of &quot;Nǐ hǎo&quot; is provided as &quot;Hello.&quot; This is fine, but it doesn't let the learner know that &quot;nǐ&quot; means &quot;you&quot; and &quot;hǎo&quot; means good and that when saying &quot;hello&quot; in Chinese, one is saying literally &quot;you good.&quot;

Providing this information allows the learner to learn the meaning of individual words in a meaningful context of the phrase or sentence being learned. And it also lets the learner get a feeling for the syntax of Mandarin.

I think this could best be done by abandoning the format currently used which divides things up into four quadrants of Simplified Chinese, Traditional Chinese, Pinyin and English and instead using multiple lines of information, something like this:

Simplified Characters
Traditional Characters
Pinyin
English word meanings
English phrase/sentence meaning.

 金 妮: 你 好。
 金 妮: 你 好。
 Jīnní: Nǐ hǎo
 Ginny: you good
 Ginny: Hello.
[[User:Gary Cziko|Gary Cziko]] 14:43, 2 August 2006 (UTC)


::I agree. I think we should explain the literal meanings of words, the actual meanings, and how the literal meaning is related to the actual meaning. For example, 哪国人 literally is &quot;Which nation person?&quot;, it means &quot;Which nationality?&quot;, so it is like saying &quot;Person of which nation?&quot; or &quot;Which nation's person?&quot;. I'm learning Chinese now and I find making connections like this to be very helpful. For example, with thinking of 你好 as &quot;you good&quot;, it made it easier for me to understand that I could also say &quot;老师好&quot; or &quot;您好&quot;. [[User:Tojo940|Tojo940]] ([[User talk:Tojo940|talk]]) 22:19, 21 November 2008 (UTC)

== By Lie-Hap-Po==

妳is a non standard character and should not be used.

Yes, agreed.

== Names could be localized ==
Since this is a Chinese course, names should be better as Chinese names. I proposal to use 張三 instead of 金妮 and 李四 instead of 歐文 here. The two names are like those ''foo'' and ''bar'' in English, very well suitable for this case. [[User:221.219.97.5|221.219.97.5]] 17:32, 28 December 2006 (UTC)
: I agree that the choice of names should be rethought. There are enough basic words I need to master as a beginner in Chinese, learning how to write Ginny is pretty low on my priority list. I've never even come across a Ginny in the US, it would be much more worthwhile learning names that I am actually likely to come across in Chinese. [[User:AmRadioHed|AmRadioHed]] 20:59, 11 April 2007 (UTC)

==Moving dialogue 2 to second lesson ==

I think one dialoge is enough for the first lesson. The second lesson would make and ideal &quot;Lesson Two&quot;. Any objections to me moing it?[[User:86.137.109.142|86.137.109.142]] 11:25, 23 February 2007 (UTC)

==Is 麽 a character in Traditional Chinese?==
Hi,

I'm using this book to learn some Mandarin. I've never studied it before, what is written here is the first thing I'm learning about it.
I'm also trying to reproduce the characters I see with a word processor using Pinyin, and I had problems inserting the &quot;me&quot; in &quot;shénme&quot;. The text says that the traditional character for it is 麽, but Wiktionary http://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/%E9%BA%BC says that this symbol is simplified Chinese, ad the traditional symbol for it is 麼. In fact, using the Pinyin input method UIM-Pinyin-BIG5 with SCIM under Linux, I can't reproduce the first character, but only the second.

I would like to thank the authors for this great work! :-) [[User:83.187.196.123|83.187.196.123]] 18:08, 28 February 2007 (UTC)


:If you look at the Wiktionary for http://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/么 then you see that two traditional forms are listed. I remember we learned the 'traditional' form when I was studying in Taiwan, but even there I saw people use the very simple form of it. My guess is that the very similar looking character is what came out after putting 麼 through the a strict interpretation of the simplification rules (you'll notice that many parts of different characters are the same, so a rule can simplify that part in all the characters it is present in). Guess it wasn't simple enough for some people. :)

== 什 vs. 甚 ==

Isn't 甚麽 the traditional form of 什么 ?
--[[User:Yakowenko|Yakowenko]] ([[User talk:Yakowenko|talk]]) 05:37, 17 March 2009 (UTC)
: no, the traditional form is 什麽. i dont know what's the diff between 什么 and 甚么 thou。

== Suggestions from a newbie ==

I do like this page - but as a newcomer to Chinese language I do have some suggestions.

First, there is a lot in each lesson and introducing Chinese characters so early makes everything look more difficult. My initial goal is to learn spoken Chinese to follow conversation and pinyin helps me do this. I have not tried to learn the characters as I see this as something which does not need to be attempted yet. The examples by exercise 2 have dropped pinyin altogether -I would like to use pinyin  for a while. 

I would find it useful to have practice drills in pinyin - something you could work on together with a Chinese speaker using VOIP. It is repetition and speaking which makes you at ease in a language. Once you are able to introduce yourself,count, construct simple sentences, and ask basic questions, maybe then it is time for characters.

What do others think? [[User:Herne|Herne]] ([[User talk:Herne|talk]]) 10:36, 27 September 2009 (UTC)

== Confusion about tones ==

The [[Chinese_(Mandarin)/Using_Tones|tones page]] says the 3rd tone changes when preceding other tones. In this lesson, hǎo sounds like a half-third tone but it's at the end of a sentence. Also, ní in Jīnní and wén in Ōuwén are written as 2nd tone, but sound low. Shén in Shénme sounds low as well. What am I missing? --[[User:ZBrisk|ZBrisk]] ([[User talk:ZBrisk|talk]]) 22:14, 28 October 2010 (UTC)

== Question With 是 ==

In S+是+O and S+不+是+O, does the 是 act like a linking verb (am, is, are, was, were)? --[[User:ThePCKid|ThePCKid]] ([[User talk:ThePCKid|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/ThePCKid|contribs]]) 22:10, 11 March 2011 (UTC)

==Pinyin Hyperlinks To Wiktionary==

Seems to me they range from broken (relatively good) to misleading (bad). They should be erased. [[Special:Contributions/79.176.136.189|79.176.136.189]] ([[User talk:79.176.136.189|discuss]]) 21:57, 22 January 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>pgvd4t39079pakuksw01x2s72vvm5hb</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Engineering Thermodynamics/First Law</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4351</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2600755</id>
      <parentid>2570158</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-01-15T11:04:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>138.38.210.227</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Work in a Polytropic Process */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{msg:EngTherm}}
----

== Energy ==

'''We use the notion of energy of a body '''from Newton's second law, and thus total energy is conserved.'''Common forms of energy''' in physics are potential and kinetic energy.
The potential energy is usually the energy due to matter having certain position (configuration) in a field, commonly the gravitational field of Earth.
Kinetic energy is the energy due to motion relative to a frame of reference.
In thermodynamics, we deal with mainly work and heat, which are different manifestations of the energy in the universe.

== Work ==

Work is said to be done by a system if the effect on the surroundings can be reduced solely to that of lifting a weight.
Work is only ever done at the boundary of a system.
Again, we use the intuitive definition of work, and this will be complete only with the statement of the second law of thermodynamics.

Consider a piston-cylinder arrangement as found in automobile engines.
When the gas in the cylinder expands, pushing the piston outwards, it does work on the surroundings.
In this case work done is mechanical.
But how about other forms of energy like heat?
The answer is that heat cannot be completely converted into work, with no other change, due to the second law of thermodynamics.

In the case of the piston-cylinder system, the work done during a cycle is given by ''W'', where ''W = &amp;minus;&amp;int; F dx = &amp;minus;&amp;int; p dV'', where ''F = p A'', and ''p'' is the pressure on the inside of the piston (note the minus sign in this relationship).
In other words, the work done is the area under the ''p-V'' diagram.
Here, ''F'' is the external opposing force, which is equal and opposite to that exerted by the system.
A corollary of the above statement is that a system undergoing free expansion does no work.
The above definition of work will only hold for the quasi-static case, when the work done is reversible work.

[[Image:work_notstate_Engineering_Thermodynamics.png|Work not a State Function]]

A consequence of the above statement is that work done is not a state function, since it depends on the path (which curve you consider for integration from state 1 to 2).
For a system in a cycle which has states 1 and 2, the work done depends on the path taken during the cycle.
If, in the cycle, the movement from 1 to 2 is along ''A'' and the return is along ''C'', then the work done is the lightly shaded area.
However, if the system returns to 1 via the path ''B'', then the work done is larger, and is equal to the sum of the two areas.

[[Image:Indicator_Engineering_Thermodynamics.png|Indicator Diagram p vs V]]

The above image shows a typical indicator diagram as output by an automobile engine.
The shaded region is proportional to the work done by the engine, and the volume ''V'' in the ''x''-axis is obtained from the piston displacement, while the ''y''-axis is from the pressure inside the cylinder.
The work done in a cycle is given by ''W'', where

&lt;math&gt;
  W = -\oint p dV
&lt;/math&gt;

Work done by the system is negative, and work done on the system is positive, by the convention used in this book.

=== Flow Energy ===

So far we have looked at the work done to compress fluid in a system.
Suppose we have to introduce some amount of fluid into the system at a pressure ''p''.
Remember from the definition of the system that matter can enter or leave an open system.
Consider a small amount of fluid of mass ''dm'' with volume ''dV'' entering the system.
Suppose the area of cross section at the entrance is ''A''.
Then the distance the force ''pA'' has to push is ''dx = dV/A''.
Thus, the work done to introduce a small amount of fluid is given by ''pdV'', and the work done per unit mass is ''pv'', where ''v = dV/dm'' is the specific volume.
This value of ''pv'' is called the flow energy.

=== Examples of Work ===

The amount of work done in a process depends on the irreversibilities present.
A complete discussion of the irreversibilities is only possible after the discussion of the second law.
The equations given above will give the values of work for quasi-static processes, and many real world processes can be approximated by this process.
However, note that work is only done if there is an opposing force in the boundary, and that a volume change is not strictly required.

=== Work in a Polytropic Process ===

Consider a polytropic process ''pV&lt;sup&gt;n&lt;/sup&gt;=C'', where ''C'' is a constant.
If the system changes its states from 1 to 2, the work done is given by

&lt;math&gt;
  W = -\int_{V_1}^{V_2}\frac{C}{V^n}dV = \frac{p_2V_2 - p_1V_1}{1 - n}
&lt;/math&gt;

And additionally, if n=1

&lt;math&gt;
  W = -\int_{V_1}^{V_2}\frac{C}{V^n}dV = -C \ln \frac{V_2}{V_1}
&lt;/math&gt;

== Heat ==

Before thermodynamics was an established science, the popular theory was that heat was a fluid, called ''caloric'',  that was stored in a body.
Thus, it was thought that a hot body transferred heat to a cold body by transferring some of this fluid to it.
However, this was soon disproved by showing that heat was generated when drilling bores of guns, where both the drill and the barrel were initially cold.

Heat is the energy exchanged due to a temperature difference.
As with work, heat is defined at the boundary of a system and is a path function.
Heat rejected by the system is negative, while the heat absorbed by the system is positive.

=== Specific Heat ===

The ''specific heat'' of a substance is the amount of heat required for a unit rise in the temperature in a unit mass of the material.
If this quantity is to be of any use, the amount of heat transferred should be a linear function of temperature.
This is certainly true for ideal gases.
This is also true for many metals and also for real gases under certain conditions.
In general, we can only talk about the average specific heat, ''c&lt;sub&gt;av&lt;/sub&gt; = Q/m&amp;Delta;T''.
Since it was customary to give the specific heat as a property in describing a material, methods of analysis came to rely on it for routine calculations.
However, since it is only constant for some materials, older calculations became very convoluted for newer materials.
For instance, for finding the amount of heat transferred, it would have been simple to give a chart of ''Q(&amp;Delta;T)'' for that material.
However, following convention, the tables of ''c&lt;sub&gt;av&lt;/sub&gt;(&amp;Delta;T)'' were given, so that a double iterative solution over ''c&lt;sub&gt;av&lt;/sub&gt;'' and ''T'' was required.

Calculating specific heat requires us to specify what we do with Volume and Pressure when we change temperature.  When Volume is fixed, it is called specific heat at constant volume (C&lt;sub&gt;v&lt;/sub&gt;).  When Pressure is fixed, it is called specific heat at constant pressure (C&lt;sub&gt;p&lt;/sub&gt;).

=== Latent Heat ===

It can be seen that the specific heat as defined above will be infinitely large for a phase change, where heat is transferred without any change in temperature.
Thus, it is much more useful to define a quantity called ''latent heat'', which is the amount of energy required to change the phase of a unit mass of a substance at the phase change temperature.

=== Adiabatic Process ===

An ''adiabatic'' process is defined as one in which there is no heat transfer with the surroundings, that is, the change in amount of energy dQ=0
.
A gas contained in an insulated vessel undergoes an adiabatic process.
Adiabatic processes also take place even if the vessel is not insulated if the process is fast enough that there is not enough time for heat to escape (''e.g.'' the transmission of sound through air).
Adiabatic processes are also ideal approximations for many real processes, like expansion of a vapor in a turbine, where the heat loss is much smaller than the work done.

== First Law of Thermodynamics ==

=== Joule Experiments ===

[[File:Joule apparatus.png|Joule's Experiments for First Law]]

[[Image:joule_first_bath_Engineering_Thermodynamics.png|Joule's Experiments for First Law]]

It was well known that heat and work both change the energy of a system.
Joule conducted a series of experiments which showed the relationship between heat and work in a thermodynamic cycle for a system.
He used a paddle to stir an insulated vessel filled with fluid.
The amount of work done on the paddle was noted (the work was done by lowering a weight, so that work done = ''mgz'').
Later, this vessel was placed in a bath and cooled.
The energy involved in increasing the temperature of the bath was shown to be equal to that supplied by the lowered weight.
Joule also performed experiments where electrical work was converted to heat using a coil and obtained the same result.

== Statement of the First Law for a Closed System==

The first law states that ''when heat and work interactions take place between a closed system and the environment, the algebraic sum of the heat and work interactions for a cycle is zero''.

Mathematically, this is equivalent to 

 dQ + dW = 0 for any cycle closed to mass flow

Q is the heat transferred, and W is the work done on or by the system. Since these are the only ways energy can be transferred, this implies that the total energy of the system in the cycle is a constant.

One consequence of the statement is that the total energy of the system is a property of the system.
This leads us to the concept of internal energy.

=== Internal Energy ===

In thermodynamics, the ''internal energy'' is the energy of a system due to its temperature.
The statement of first law refers to thermodynamic cycles.
Using the concept of internal energy it is possible to state the first law for a non-cyclic process.
Since the first law is another way of stating the conservation of energy, the energy of the system is the sum of the heat and work input, ''i.e.'', ''&amp;Delta;E = Q + W''.
Here ''E'' represents the internal energy (U) of the system along with the kinetic energy (KE) and the potential energy (PE) (''E = U + K.E. + P.E.'') and is called the ''total energy'' of the system. This is the statement of the first law for non-cyclic processes, as long as they are still closed to the flow of mass. The KE and PE terms are relative to an external reference point i.e. the system is the gas within a ball, the ball travels in a trajectory that varies in height H and velocity V and subsequently KE and PE with time, but this has no affect upon the energy of the gas molecules within the ball, which is dictated only by the internal energy of the system (U). Thermodynamics does not define the nature of the internal energy, but it can be rationalised using other theories (i.e. the gas kinetic theory), but in this case is due to the KE and PE of the gas molecules within the ball, not to be mistaken with the KE and PE of the ball itself.

For gases, the value of ''K.E.'' and ''P.E.'' is quite small, so the important term is the internal energy function ''U''.
In particular, since for an ideal gas the state can be specified using two variables, the state variable ''u'' is given by ''u(v, T)'', where ''v'' is the specific volume and ''T'' is the temperature.

Introducing this temperature dependence explicitly is important in many calculations. For this purpose, the constant-volume heat capacity is defined as follows: ''c&lt;sub&gt;v&lt;/sub&gt; = (&amp;part;u/&amp;part;t)&lt;sub&gt;v&lt;/sub&gt;'', where ''c&lt;sub&gt;v&lt;/sub&gt;'' is the specific heat at constant volume. A constant-pressure heat capacity will be defined later, and it is important to keep them straight. The important point here is that the other variable that U depends on &quot;naturally&quot; is v, so to isolate the temperature dependence of U you want to take the derivative at constant v.

=== Internal Energy for an Ideal Gas ===

In the previous section, the internal energy of an ideal gas was shown to be a function of both the volume and temperature.
Joule performed an experiment where a gas at high pressure inside a bath at the same temperature was allowed to expand into a larger volume.

[[Image:joule_Engineering_Thermodynamics.png|Joule's Experiment Temperature Invariance]]

In the above image, two vessels, labeled A and B, are immersed in an insulated tank containing water.
A thermometer is used to measure the temperature of the water in the tank.
The two vessels A and B are connected by a tube, the flow through which is controlled by a stop.
Initially, A contains gas at high pressure, while B is nearly empty.
The stop is removed so that the vessels are connected and the final temperature of the bath is noted.

The temperature of the bath was unchanged at the end of the process, showing that the internal energy of an ideal gas was the function of temperature alone.
Thus ''Joule's law'' is stated as ''(&amp;part;u/&amp;part;v)&lt;sub&gt;t&lt;/sub&gt; = 0''.

== Enthalpy ==

According to the first law, 
''dQ + dW = dE''

If all the work is pressure volume work, then we have

''dW = &amp;minus; p dV''

&amp;rArr; ''dQ =  dU + pdV = d(U + pV) - Vdp''

&amp;rArr; ''d(U + pV) = dQ + Vdp''

We define ''H &amp;equiv; U + pV'' as the ''enthalpy'' of the system, and ''h = u + pv'' is the specific enthalpy.
In particular, for a constant pressure process,

''&amp;Delta;Q = &amp;Delta;H''

With arguments similar to that for ''c&lt;sub&gt;v&lt;/sub&gt;'', ''c&lt;sub&gt;p&lt;/sub&gt; = (&amp;part;h/&amp;part;t)&lt;sub&gt;p&lt;/sub&gt;''.
Since ''h'', ''p'', and ''t'' are state variables, ''c&lt;sub&gt;p&lt;/sub&gt;'' is a state variable.
As a corollary, for ideal gases, ''c&lt;sub&gt;p&lt;/sub&gt; = c&lt;sub&gt;v&lt;/sub&gt; + R'', and for incompressible fluids, ''c&lt;sub&gt;p&lt;/sub&gt; = c&lt;sub&gt;v&lt;/sub&gt;''

=== Throttling ===

[[Image:throttling_Engineering_Thermodynamics.png|Throttling Process]]

''Throttling'' is the process in which a fluid passing through a restriction loses pressure.
It usually occurs when fluid passes through small orifices like porous plugs.
The original throttling experiments were conducted by Joule and Thompson.
As seen in the previous section, in adiabatic throttling the enthalpy is constant.
What is significant is that for ideal gases, the enthalpy depends only on temperature, so that there is no temperature change, as there is no work done or heat supplied.
However, for real gases, below a certain temperature, called the ''inversion point'', the temperature drops with a drop in pressure, so that throttling causes cooling, ''i.e.'', ''p&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;lt; p&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;rArr; T&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;lt; T&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;.''
The amount of cooling produced is quantified by the Joule-Thomson coefficient ''&amp;mu;&lt;sub&gt;JT&lt;/sub&gt; = (&amp;part;T/&amp;part;p)&lt;sub&gt;h&lt;/sub&gt;''.
For instance, the inversion temperature for air is about 400&amp;deg;C.

----
{{msg:EngTherm}}

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>3hj7d02zowo5upp6q9ccp6cc8kltadt</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Araisyohei</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>4352</id>
    <revision>
      <id>156132</id>
      <parentid>45603</parentid>
      <timestamp>2004-07-26T04:28:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Araisyohei</username>
        <id>553</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[w:User:Araisyohei]] [[ja:利用者:Araisyohei]]

My name is Arai-Syohei (japanese &amp;#33618;&amp;#20117;&amp;#12288;&amp;#32724;&amp;#24179;)
I'm the first grade of junior high-school of a Japanese birth. English can be spoken only a little.</text>
      <sha1>71ftc9baxqxtr6t9urdyovlx1145n61</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Botany/Leaves (forms)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4355</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2614196</id>
      <parentid>2613383</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-03-05T00:09:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Xania</username>
        <id>40302</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>no reason given for large image and text removal - Rejected the last 2 text changes (by [[Special:Contributions/190.80.120.221|190.80.120.221]]) and restored revision 773314 by Reece</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;small&gt;&lt;&lt; [[Botany#Contents|Contents Page]] | &lt;&lt; [[Botany/Plant_structure|Chapter 3]] | &lt;/small&gt;Leaves (forms) 
----
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;big&gt;Chapter 3. Plant Cells and Tissues&lt;big&gt;&lt;br&gt;Leaves (forms)&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/big&gt;  
&lt;/center&gt;

== Leaf Shapes, Margins, Apices, and Bases ==

=== Simple, Angiosperm Leaves ===

This page presents the terminology used to describe the shapes and forms of leaves. The following examples are all '''simple''' leaves.  All are from flowering plants (angiosperms). Descriptive terms are given for the lamina shape (that is, its overall shape in outline), the lamina margin, the form or shape of both the apex (tip) and the base (lamina junction with petiole) of the leaf, and (in some cases) other qualities evident in the example picture presented. 


{|
|-
| WIDTH=&quot;50%&quot; |
&lt;div style=&quot;float:left;margin:0 1em 1em 0;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;[[image:leaf_shape_04.jpg|alt text]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;1. ''Chamaesyce celastroides''&lt;br&gt;(EUPHORBIACEAE)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
'''1.''' 'Akoko&lt;p&gt;
SHAPE: '''oblong''' to '''elliptic'''&lt;br&gt;
MARGIN: '''entire'''&lt;br&gt;
TIP: '''retuse'''&lt;br&gt;
BASE: '''rounded'''
| WIDTH=&quot;50%&quot; VALIGN=&quot;top&quot; |
&lt;div style=&quot;float:left;margin:0 1em 1em 0;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;[[image:leaf_shape_02.jpg|alt text]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;3. ''Ageratina riparia''&lt;br&gt;
(ASTERACEAE)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
'''2.''' Mist flower&lt;p&gt;
SHAPE: '''rhombic'''&lt;br&gt;
MARGIN: '''serrate'''&lt;br&gt;
TIP: '''attenuate'''&lt;br&gt;
BASE: '''cuneate'''
|-
|
&lt;div style=&quot;float:left;margin:0 1em 1em 0;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;[[image:leaf_shape_10.jpg|alt text]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;2. indet.&lt;br&gt;(?LAMIACEAE)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
'''3.''' indet.&lt;p&gt;
SHAPE: '''ovate'''&lt;br&gt;
MARGIN: '''crenate'''&lt;br&gt;
TIP: '''acute'''&lt;br&gt;
BASE: ~ '''rounded'''&lt;br&gt;
OTHER: color '''bright green'''
|
&lt;div style=&quot;float:left;margin:0 1em 1em 0;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;[[image:leaf_shape_01.jpg|alt text]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;4. ''Ficus religiosa''&lt;br&gt;(MORACEAE)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
'''4.''' Bo tree&lt;p&gt;
SHAPE: '''cordate'''&lt;br&gt;
MARGIN: '''entire''', slightly '''undulate'''&lt;br&gt;
TIP: '''caudate'''&lt;br&gt;
BASE: '''cordate'''
|-
|
&lt;div style=&quot;float:left;margin:0 1em 1em 0;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;[[image:leaf_shape_11.jpg|alt text]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;''Macadamia'' sp.&lt;br&gt;(PROTEACEAE)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
'''5.''' Macadamia nut&lt;br&gt;
SHAPE: '''linear'''&lt;br&gt;
MARGIN: '''undulate''' and '''spinose'''&lt;br&gt;
TIP: (not visible) '''acute'''
|
&lt;div style=&quot;float:left;margin:0 1em 1em 0;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;[[image:leaf_shape_12.jpg|200 px|alt text]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;Richardia brasiliensis&lt;br&gt;(RUBIACEAE)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
SHAPE: &lt;br&gt;
MARGIN: lobes '''ciliate'''&lt;br&gt;
TIP: '''acute'''
|-
|-
|
&lt;div style=&quot;float:left;margin:0 1em 1em 0;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;[[image:leaf_shape_05.jpg|alt text]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;'' ''&lt;br&gt;(CYPERACEAE)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
SHAPE: '''linear'''&lt;br&gt;
MARGIN: '''entire'''&lt;br&gt;
TIP: '''acute'''
|
&lt;div style=&quot;float:left;margin:0 1em 1em 0;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;[[image:leaf_shape_03.jpg|alt text]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;''Coronopus didymus''&lt;br&gt;(BRASSICACEAE)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
SHAPE: '''oblong''' in outline, deeply '''pinnatifid'''&lt;br&gt;
MARGIN: lobes '''dentate'''&lt;br&gt;
TIP: (not visible) '''acute'''
|-
|
&lt;div style=&quot;float:left;margin:0 1em 1em 0;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;[[image:leaf_shape_07.jpg|alt text]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;''Ammania auriculata''&lt;br&gt;(LYTHRACEAE)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
SHAPE: '''linear'''&lt;br&gt;
MARGIN: '''entire'''&lt;br&gt;
TIP: '''acute'''
| VALIGN=&quot;top&quot; |
&lt;div style=&quot;float:left;margin:0 1em 1em 0;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;[[image:leaf_shape_14.jpg|alt text]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;''Myriophyllum aquaticum''&lt;br&gt;(HALORAGACEAE)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
SHAPE: '''pinnatifid''', segments '''capillary'''&lt;br&gt;
MARGIN: N/A&lt;br&gt;
TIP: N/A&lt;br&gt;
BASE: N/A&lt;br&gt;
OTHER: leaves '''whorled'''
|-
|
&lt;div style=&quot;float:left;margin:0 1em 1em 0;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;[[image:leaf_shape_13.jpg|alt text]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;''Brachiaria mutica''&lt;br&gt;(POACEAE)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
SHAPE: '''linear'''&lt;br&gt;
MARGIN: '''entire'''&lt;br&gt;
TIP: '''acute'''&lt;br&gt;
OTHER: Base '''sheathing'''
|}

=== Compound, Angiosperm Leaves ===

These examples are all '''compound''' leaves. In these leaves, it is not always very instructive to describe the &quot;leaf outline&quot; and better to describe the number (or range) of leaflets. If the number is odd, there will be an unpaired leaflet at the tipp.  The shape terminology can be applied to the individual leaflets.


{|
|-
| WIDTH=&quot;50%&quot; |
&lt;div style=&quot;float:left;margin:0 1em 1em 0;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;[[image:leaf_shape_06.jpg|alt text]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;''Canavalia sericea''&lt;br&gt;(FABACEAE)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Silky jackbean&lt;br&gt;
SHAPE: '''orbicular''' to '''elliptic '''&lt;br&gt;
MARGIN: '''entire'''&lt;br&gt;
TIP: '''obtuse'''&lt;br&gt;
BASE: '''obtuse'''&lt;br&gt;
| WIDTH=&quot;50%&quot; VALIGN=&quot;top&quot; |
&lt;div style=&quot;float:left;margin:0 1em 1em 0;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;[[image:leaf_shape_09.jpg|alt text]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;''Toona ciliata''&lt;br&gt;(MELIACEAE)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Australian redcedar&lt;br&gt;
SHAPE: '''lanceolate''' to '''elliptic'''&lt;br&gt;
MARGIN: '''entire'''&lt;br&gt;
TIP: '''cuspidate'''&lt;br&gt;
BASE: '''oblique '''&lt;br&gt;
|}
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;BR&gt;
&lt;HR&gt;
== Links ==

[http://www.calflora.net/botanicalnames/botanicalterms.html Botanical Terms]

[[Category:Botany]]</text>
      <sha1>1ls20yne3oh1nf5m13yiw7v0lcxmfe1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Leaf shape 01.jpg</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>4356</id>
    <revision>
      <id>905656</id>
      <parentid>900480</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-06-21T09:43:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Webaware</username>
        <id>27565</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>licensing</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">One of many examples of leaf forms; provided by Eric Guinther and released under the GNU Free Documentation License.

==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>c915skq5812k6jsjz4dqwjob8hex597</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Leaf shape 02.jpg</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>4357</id>
    <revision>
      <id>905657</id>
      <parentid>900481</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-06-21T09:44:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Webaware</username>
        <id>27565</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>licensing</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">One of many examples of leaf forms; provided by Eric Guinther and released under the GNU Free Documentation License.

==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>c915skq5812k6jsjz4dqwjob8hex597</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Leaf shape 03.jpg</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>4358</id>
    <revision>
      <id>905658</id>
      <parentid>900482</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-06-21T09:44:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Webaware</username>
        <id>27565</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>licensing</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">One of many examples of leaf forms; provided by Eric Guinther and released under the GNU Free Documentation License.

==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>c915skq5812k6jsjz4dqwjob8hex597</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Leaf shape 04.jpg</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>4359</id>
    <revision>
      <id>905660</id>
      <parentid>900483</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-06-21T09:46:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Webaware</username>
        <id>27565</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>licensing</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">One of many examples of leaf forms; provided by Eric Guinther and released under the GNU Free Documentation License.

==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>c915skq5812k6jsjz4dqwjob8hex597</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Discrete Mathematics/Number theory</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>4360</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1578468</id>
      <parentid>921888</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-07-24T15:52:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>moved [[Talk:Discrete mathematics/Number theory]] to [[Talk:Discrete Mathematics/Number theory]]: Title casing.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">I'm thinking that the idea of groups (that is, sets-with-operations) should be well introduced before this section. That way, division can be described as, for a set ''S'', &lt;math&gt;f:S\times (S-\{0\})\to S&lt;/math&gt;. By suddenly assuming that operations (which, yes, are really just functions with two arguments) are known and defined, we're doing much, much more hand-waving than is healthy.

Yes, it's an intuitive idea, but one of the big parts of discrete math is formally defining things that we've learned to take for granted.

[[User:Grendelkhan|Grendelkhan]]

: I do strongly think that it's important to introduce groups ''afterward''. I mean how can one introduce something like the group ''Z''&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; under addition modulo 3 without having to explain the &quot;modulo 3&quot; part?

: If there's too much handwaving, we can surely put our hands down and clean up the text. Do you think that we should define things about division in '''Z''' more formally? [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 06:20, 7 Feb 2004 (UTC)

:: Finite groups may require a bit of handwaving (thought the group consisting of {1, -1} and multiplication is pretty intuitive), but infinite groups like ('''Z''',+) and ('''Q'''&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;,*) can be introduced right after sets and functions.

:: I notice that there's already an in-depth treatment of groups in [[Abstract_algebra/Groups]]; maybe a quick introduction geared to the material at hand? Something like &quot;A group is a set along with an operation. An operation is a function of two arguments. An in-depth treatment of groups is over at [[Abstract_algebra/Groups]], but these are the essentials for right now.&quot; Cosets, *morphisms, order---these things don't need to get described until formal group theory.

:: It'll also depend on how much group theory's going to come up in chapters between here and its formal introduction. If you don't define the basics here, you might end up doing it piecemeal over the following bunch of chapters, all hodge-podgey. [[User:Grendelkhan|Grendelkhan]] 17:05, 9 Feb 2004 (UTC)

:: Wouldn't it be somewhat useful to not introduce groups in this book, but give link to that Groups book entirely? After all, that is the best thing about a web book like this, linking. [[User:huopa|huopa]] 14 Jul 2004

Isn't it GCF (greatest common factor), not GCD? At least, that's the way I was always taught. - [[User:SamE|SamE]] 04:35, 25 Jun 2004 (UTC)

: It does have different names. Let's just stick with the notation that's there? [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 05:26, 25 Jun 2004 (UTC)

I'm surprised this isn't its own text.  Is there some reason for it to be part of Discrete Math? [[User:MikeBorkowski|MikeBorkowski]] 12:00, 1 May 2005 (UTC)

No discussion of primes is complete without mention of the primorials--[[User:Billymac00|Billymac00]] 14:59, 12 July 2007 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>diyz5s22ldxcs02i0tg5d07u4qxwqyg</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>UK Constitution and Government</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4361</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2376340</id>
      <parentid>1856114</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-07-11T17:40:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Planotse</username>
        <id>640710</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;!-- Generated for the page, UK Constitution and Government, by Wikiversal version 1.12.72 on 7/11/2012. --&gt;
__NOEDITSECTION__ __NOTOC__

=== &lt;font size=1 color=dimgray&gt;Presentation&lt;/font&gt; ===
&lt;table height=1 border=1 style=&quot;border-collapse:collapse; border-color:LightSkyBlue; background-color:AliceBlue;&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=left&gt;&lt;table width=&quot;100%&quot; align=left&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;[[File:Gohome.png|frameless||none||x40px|link=http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/UK_Constitution_and_Government#Presentation]]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td nowrap&gt;&lt;font size=6 color=teal&gt;{{SUBPAGENAME}}&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:1rightarrow.png|frameless||none||x40px|link=http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/UK_Constitution_and_Government/Introduction#Presentation||Introduction]]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:2rightarrow.png|frameless||none||x40px|link=http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/UK_Constitution_and_Government/Topic_List#Presentation||List of Topics]]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&quot;99%&quot;&gt; &amp;nbsp; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;[[File:1rightarrow.png|frameless||none||x40px|link=http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/UK_Constitution_and_Government/Introduction#Presentation||Introduction]]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;!-- -- -- -- -- -- -- -- -- -- -- --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;p align=center&gt;&lt;font size=7 color=&quot;seagreen&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;UK Constitution and Government&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
{{center|&lt;big&gt;&lt;big&gt;&lt;big&gt;'''The Constitution and Government of the United Kingdom'''&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/big&gt;}}
&lt;noinclude&gt;
{{featured book|print=Print version|PDF={{PAGENAME}}}}
__NOTOC__ __NOEDITSECTION__
&lt;div class=&quot;noprint&quot;&gt;
* '''View UK Constitution and Government Edition 1.0 as a single PDF document''', for speed right click on the link &quot;PDF File 1.0&quot; and &quot;save target as&quot; or click directly on [[Media:UK Constitution and Government.pdf|PDF File 1.0]].
* [[/Print version|Print version - view the whole book as a continuous file.]] (&lt;span class=&quot;plainlinks&quot;&gt;[{{SERVER}}{{localurl:UK_Constitution_and_Government/Print version|action=edit}} edit]&lt;/span&gt;) [[Image:Exquisite-print printer.png|22px]] &lt;/div&gt;

==Table of contents==
[[File:Westminster.jpg|366px|thumb|''The Palace of Westminster'']]
===Part I: Political History===
#[[/Normans|The Normans]]
#[[/Plantagenets|The Plantagenets]]
#[[/Houses of Lancaster and York|The Houses of Lancaster and York]]
#[[/House of Tudor|The House of Tudor]]
#[[/House of Stuart and the Commonwealth|The House of Stuart and the Commonwealth]]
#[[/House of Hanover|The House of Hanover]]
#[[/Houses of Saxe-Coburg-Gotha and Windsor|The Houses of Saxe-Coburg-Gotha and Windsor]]

===Part II: Present System===
#[[/Constitution|The Constitution]]
#[[/Sovereign|The Sovereign]]
#[[/Parliament|The Parliament]]
#[[/Government|Her Majesty's Government]]
#[[/Judiciary|The Judiciary]]
#[[/Devolved Administrations/]]
#[[/Elections/]]

===Part III: Appendices===
#[[/British Monarchs|List of British Monarchs]]

{{alphabetical|U}}
{{Subjects|Public administration}}
{{status|100%}}

[[es:Sistema político del Reino Unido]]
[[fr:Système politique du Royaume-Uni]]
[[ms:Perlembagaan dan Kerajaan United Kingdom]]
&lt;/noinclude&gt;</text>
      <sha1>nafv5ypy8sjdlw3i9qvphf96q5bg45w</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Leaf shape 05.jpg</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>4367</id>
    <revision>
      <id>905662</id>
      <parentid>900484</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-06-21T09:46:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Webaware</username>
        <id>27565</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>licensing</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">One of many examples of leaf forms; provided by Eric Guinther and released under the GNU Free Documentation License.

==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>c915skq5812k6jsjz4dqwjob8hex597</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Leaf shape 06.jpg</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>4368</id>
    <revision>
      <id>905663</id>
      <parentid>900485</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-06-21T09:47:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Webaware</username>
        <id>27565</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>licensing</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">One of many examples of leaf forms; provided by Eric Guinther and released under the GNU Free Documentation License.

==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>c915skq5812k6jsjz4dqwjob8hex597</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Leaf shape 07.jpg</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>4369</id>
    <revision>
      <id>905664</id>
      <parentid>900486</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-06-21T09:47:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Webaware</username>
        <id>27565</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>licensing</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">One of many examples of leaf forms; provided by Eric Guinther and released under the GNU Free Documentation License.

==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>c915skq5812k6jsjz4dqwjob8hex597</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Vuara/Webpage Format 1</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>4371</id>
    <revision>
      <id>616187</id>
      <parentid>156149</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-10-18T04:28:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Guanabot</username>
        <id>5478</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>User-controlled Bot: table syntax updated</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">
{| border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; cellpadding=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;'border-collapse:collapse;&quot;
border:none'
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;&lt;b&gt;Maharishi’s Introduction &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;&lt;b&gt;Giothieu &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;The Science of Being and Art of Living is the summation of both
the practical wisdom of integrated life advanced by the Vedic Rishis of
ancient India and the growth of scientific thinking in the present-day
western world. &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;The Science of Being and Art of Living is the summation of both
the practical wisdom of integrated life advanced by the Vedic Rishis of
ancient India and the growth of scientific thinking in the present-day
western world. &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;It presents a philosophy of life in fulfillment and brings forth
a practice suitable for all men everywhere in the world to glorify all
aspects of their day-to-day life. It deals with the fundamentals of all
problems of life and suggests one sure cure to eradicate all sufferings. &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;It presents a philosophy of life in fulfillment and brings forth
a practice suitable for all men everywhere in the world to glorify all
aspects of their day-to-day life. It deals with the fundamentals of all
problems of life and suggests one sure cure to eradicate all sufferings. &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;This book presents a practical thesis of integrated life which
has long been the abstract goal of the various sciences, religions, and
metaphysical thought groups. This thesis will enable all men to harmonize
their inner spiritual content with the glories of the outer material life and
find their God within themselves. &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;This book presents a practical thesis of integrated life which
has long been the abstract goal of the various sciences, religions, and
metaphysical thought groups. This thesis will enable all men to harmonize
their inner spiritual content with the glories of the outer material life and
find their God within themselves. &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;Science explores into the actuality of forms and phenomena. All
the branches of science are the various ways to realize the truth of
existence. The approach of each of them starts from the obvious known and
aims at investigating the hidden unknown. The ultimate truth of life is being
approached from all directions. All the sciences are exploring the various
strata of creation, from the gross to the subtler fields of existence. &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;Science explores into the actuality of forms and phenomena. All
the branches of science are the various ways to realize the truth of
existence. The approach of each of them starts from the obvious known and
aims at investigating the hidden unknown. The ultimate truth of life is being
approached from all directions. All the sciences are exploring the various
strata of creation, from the gross to the subtler fields of existence. &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;The Science of Being, as does every other science, starts its
investigation into the truth of existence from the gross, obvious level of
life and later enters into the subtle regions of experience. The Science of
Being, however, eventually transcends these subtle regions and arrives at the
direct experience of the transcendental field of eternal Being. &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;The Science of Being, as does every other science, starts its
investigation into the truth of existence from the gross, obvious level of
life and later enters into the subtle regions of experience. The Science of
Being, however, eventually transcends these subtle regions and arrives at the
direct experience of the transcendental field of eternal Being. &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;The Science of Being is a deep and practical philosophy of life.
It is a systematic investigation into the true nature of the ultimate
reality. Although, like any other science, it is theoretical in its nature,
its applied aspects reach much farther horizons of the supreme reality of
life than those of abstract metaphysical speculations. &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;The Science of Being is a deep and practical philosophy of life.
It is a systematic investigation into the true nature of the ultimate
reality. Although, like any other science, it is theoretical in its nature,
its applied aspects reach much farther horizons of the supreme reality of
life than those of abstract metaphysical speculations. &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;This book is divided into four sections: “Science of Being”;
“Life”; “Art of Living”; and “Fulfillment.” The last three sections of the
book present the most practical wisdom of day-to-day life, and this greatest
wisdom of practical life is based on the deep philosophical significance
contained in the section on the Science of Being. &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;This book is divided into four sections: “Science of Being”;
“Life”; “Art of Living”; and “Fulfillment.” The last three sections of the
book present the most practical wisdom of day-to-day life, and this greatest
wisdom of practical life is based on the deep philosophical significance
contained in the section on the Science of Being. &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;The Science of Being serves to provide a deep and significant
basis for the art of living. As a matter of fact, the art of living is
applied Science of Being. &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;The Science of Being serves to provide a deep and significant
basis for the art of living. As a matter of fact, the art of living is
applied Science of Being. &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;To those who have never had an interest in metaphysical study,
the section on “Science of Being” may at first appear to be highly abstract,
but once they have stepped into “Life” and “Art of Living” and have completed
the section on “Fulfillment,” they will find that without dwelling on the
abstract features of the Science of Being, the whole wisdom of the book would
have no practical basis. &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;To those who have never had an interest in metaphysical study,
the section on “Science of Being” may at first appear to be highly abstract,
but once they have stepped into “Life” and “Art of Living” and have completed
the section on “Fulfillment,” they will find that without dwelling on the
abstract features of the Science of Being, the whole wisdom of the book would
have no practical basis. &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;A gardener has to have a knowledge of the unseen root of the
tree before he can be expected to give his concentrated effort to watering
its root so that the whole tree remains fresh and green. &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;A gardener has to have a knowledge of the unseen root of the
tree before he can be expected to give his concentrated effort to watering
its root so that the whole tree remains fresh and green. &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;Likewise, a man in the practical field of life must first be
given a good understanding about the fundamental reality of life that lies in
the field of abstract Being, in order to glorify the whole of the rest of
life. That is why the Science of Being is the first section of this book, and
the sections of practical value follow. &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;Likewise, a man in the practical field of life must first be
given a good understanding about the fundamental reality of life that lies in
the field of abstract Being, in order to glorify the whole of the rest of
life. That is why the Science of Being is the first section of this book, and
the sections of practical value follow. &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;The word “science” comes from the Latin root word scire, to
know. It means knowledge; systematized knowledge is science. &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;The word “science” comes from the Latin root word scire, to
know. It means knowledge; systematized knowledge is science. &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;The Science of Being means systematized knowledge of
Being—systematized knowledge of existence or the actuality of life. &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;The Science of Being means systematized knowledge of
Being—systematized knowledge of existence or the actuality of life. &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;The field of Being or absolute existence was for many centuries
considered in terms of mysticism. The present scientific age hesitates to
assign value to anything shrouded in the garb of mysticism, and that is why
the study of Being, the absolute field of creation, has not been a part of
any branch of science until now. &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;The field of Being or absolute existence was for many centuries
considered in terms of mysticism. The present scientific age hesitates to
assign value to anything shrouded in the garb of mysticism, and that is why
the study of Being, the absolute field of creation, has not been a part of
any branch of science until now. &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;The growth of scientific thinking in the present generation has
brought Being to the level of scientific study and scrutiny. &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;The growth of scientific thinking in the present generation has
brought Being to the level of scientific study and scrutiny. &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;A systematic method has been developed that enables an
individual to experience directly the pure state of Being. It is done by
consciously entering into the experience of the subtle strata of a thought,
eventually arriving at the direct experience of the subtlest state of the
thought, and then arriving at the very source of thought. Then the conscious
mind attains the pure state of Being. &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;A systematic method has been developed that enables an
individual to experience directly the pure state of Being. It is done by
consciously entering into the experience of the subtle strata of a thought,
eventually arriving at the direct experience of the subtlest state of the
thought, and then arriving at the very source of thought. Then the conscious
mind attains the pure state of Being. &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;The Science of Being, which gives rise to the practical art of
living, is a science which is much more valuable for human life than all the
sciences known so far to the human mind. For, up to now, the basis of all the
sciences has been the human mind functioning from a limited field of
consciousness or limited potential. The Science of Being, through the
practice of Transcendental Meditation, enlarges the conscious capacity of the
mind to infinite values and therefore functions not only as the basis for the
great expansion of knowledge in every field of science, but also brings to
man a direct way to fulfillment. &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;The Science of Being, which gives rise to the practical art of
living, is a science which is much more valuable for human life than all the
sciences known so far to the human mind. For, up to now, the basis of all the
sciences has been the human mind functioning from a limited field of
consciousness or limited potential. The Science of Being, through the
practice of Transcendental Meditation, enlarges the conscious capacity of the
mind to infinite values and therefore functions not only as the basis for the
great expansion of knowledge in every field of science, but also brings to
man a direct way to fulfillment. &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;For all this knowledge my indebtedness is to the holy tradition
of Jagadguru Bhagwan Shankaracharya, the main source of all my inspirations
and activity. &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;For all this knowledge my indebtedness is to the holy tradition
of Jagadguru Bhagwan Shankaracharya, the main source of all my inspirations
and activity. &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;My first thanks are due to Henry Nyburg, the head of the
Spiritual Regeneration Movement in Europe, who first felt the need and
conceived the idea of such a book as this one about three years ago. &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;My first thanks are due to Henry Nyburg, the head of the
Spiritual Regeneration Movement in Europe, who first felt the need and
conceived the idea of such a book as this one about three years ago. &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;My thanks are also due to blessed Ma from London, who, like a
mother, sat with a stick over the child to get the task completed. Leona
Simpson from Canada, Guri Mehellis from Norway, and Dick Bock from Los
Angeles, have also been of great assistance in maintaining the breath of the
writing and the writer. Jerry Jarvis and his dear wife Debby, who worked hard
transcribing and editing the tapes and preparing the final manuscript, also
deserve to share my feelings of appreciation and thanks for them. Certainly
the warmth of the atmosphere created by love of Mother Olson and Roland
Olson, Helen Lutes, and the dear Verrills and Granvilles had its own share in
bringing out this book. &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;My thanks are also due to blessed Ma from London, who, like a
mother, sat with a stick over the child to get the task completed. Leona
Simpson from Canada, Guri Mehellis from Norway, and Dick Bock from Los
Angeles, have also been of great assistance in maintaining the breath of the
writing and the writer. Jerry Jarvis and his dear wife Debby, who worked hard
transcribing and editing the tapes and preparing the final manuscript, also
deserve to share my feelings of appreciation and thanks for them. Certainly
the warmth of the atmosphere created by love of Mother Olson and Roland
Olson, Helen Lutes, and the dear Verrills and Granvilles had its own share in
bringing out this book. &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;This is a book of revival for the age. If the golden era is ever
to dawn on human society, if the Age of Enlightenment is ever to be on earth,
this book will provide a freeway for it to come. A new humanity will be born,
fuller in conception and richer in experience and accomplishments in all
fields. Joy of life will belong to every man, love will dominate human
society, truth and virtue will reign in the world, peace on earth will be
permanent, and all will live in fulfillment in fullness of life in God
Consciousness. &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;This is a book of revival for the age. If the golden era is ever
to dawn on human society, if the Age of Enlightenment is ever to be on earth,
this book will provide a freeway for it to come. A new humanity will be born,
fuller in conception and richer in experience and accomplishments in all
fields. Joy of life will belong to every man, love will dominate human
society, truth and virtue will reign in the world, peace on earth will be permanent,
and all will live in fulfillment in fullness of life in God Consciousness. &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;Jai Guru Dev &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;Jai Guru Dev &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;—MAHARISHI MAHESH YOGI &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;—MAHARISHI MAHESH YOGI &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;Lake Arrowhead &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;Lake Arrowhead &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;California &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;California &lt;/p&gt;
|-
| valign=top style='width:221.4pt;
border-top:none;padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;January 12, 1963 &lt;/p&gt;
| valign=&quot;top&quot; style=&quot;'width:221.4pt;&quot; padding:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt' |
&lt;p class=MsoNormal&gt;January 12, 1963 &lt;/p&gt;
|}</text>
      <sha1>8x2w0xzt77pvd1xzj81ufdcyyzkzmoj</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>UK Constitution and Government/Normans</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4375</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2504101</id>
      <parentid>2376343</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-21T15:50:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dirk Hünniger</username>
        <id>343292</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;noinclude&gt;
&lt;!-- Generated for the page, UK Constitution and Government/Normans, by Wikiversal version 1.12.72 on 7/11/2012. --&gt;
__NOEDITSECTION__ __NOTOC__

=== &lt;font size=1 color=dimgray&gt;Presentation&lt;/font&gt; ===
&lt;table height=1 border=1 style=&quot;border-collapse:collapse; border-color:LightSkyBlue; background-color:AliceBlue;&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=left&gt;&lt;table width=&quot;100%&quot; align=left&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;[[File:1leftarrow.png|frameless||none||x40px|link=http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/UK_Constitution_and_Government/Introduction#Presentation||Introduction]]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Gohome.png|frameless||none||x40px|link=http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/UK_Constitution_and_Government#Presentation]]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td nowrap&gt;&lt;font size=6 color=teal&gt;{{SUBPAGENAME}}&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:1rightarrow.png|frameless||none||x40px|link=http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/UK_Constitution_and_Government/Plantagenets#Presentation||Plantagenets]]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:2rightarrow.png|frameless||none||x40px|link=http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/UK_Constitution_and_Government/Topic_List#Presentation||List of Topics]]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&quot;99%&quot;&gt; &amp;nbsp; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;[[File:1rightarrow.png|frameless||none||x40px|link=http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/UK_Constitution_and_Government/Plantagenets#Presentation||Plantagenets]]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;!-- -- -- -- -- -- -- -- -- -- -- --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;big&gt;&lt;big&gt;The Normans (1066-1154)&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/big&gt;

[[UK Constitution and Government/Plantagenets|Next Chapter]]
------
&lt;/noinclude&gt;
==William I==

&lt;!--  Commented out because image was deleted: [[Image:WilliamI.JPG|frame|Figure 1-1: William I]] --&gt;


The course of English political, legal and cultural history was changed in 1066, when William, Duke of Normandy (also called William the Conqueror) successfully invaded the nation and displaced the Saxon king, Harold II.

In 1066 King Edward, also called St Edward the Confessor, died. His cousin, the Duke of Normandy, claimed that the childless King had named him heir during a visit to France, and that the other claimant to the throne, Harold Godwinson, had pledged to support William when he was shipwrecked in Normandy. The veracity of this tale, however, is doubtful, and Harold took the crown upon King Edward's death. William, however, invaded England in September, and defeated (and killed) Harold at the famous Battle of Hastings in October.

==William II==
In 1087, King William I died, and divided his lands and riches between his three sons. The eldest, Robert, became Duke of Normandy; the second, William, became King of England; the youngest, Henry, received silver. Henry, however, eventually came to possess all of his father's dominions. William II died without children, so Henry became King. Henry later invaded Normandy, imprisoned his brother, and took over the Duchy of Normandy. 

==Henry I, Stephen and Matilda==
Henry, whose sons had predeceased him, took an unprecedented step: naming a woman as his heir. He declared that his daughter Matilda would be the next Queen. However, Matilda's claim was disputed by Stephen, a grandson of William I in the female line. After Henry I died in 1135, Stephen usurped the throne, but he was defeated and imprisoned by Matilda in 1141. Later, however, Matilda was defeated, and Stephen took the throne.

Matilda, however, was not completely defeated. She escaped from Stephen's army, and her own son, Henry Plantagenet, led a military expedition against Stephen. Stephen was forced to agree to name Henry as his heir, and when Stephen died in 1154, Henry took the throne, commencing the Plantagenet dynasty.

{{BookCat}}

[[ms:Perlembagaan dan Kerajaan United Kingdom: Dinasti Normandy]]</text>
      <sha1>nnb59x1nb3hlwcebubrjg5cn9tqe1uj</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>UK Constitution and Government/Plantagenets</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4376</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2504123</id>
      <parentid>2504102</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-21T16:01:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dirk Hünniger</username>
        <id>343292</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;noinclude&gt;
&lt;!-- Generated for the page, UK Constitution and Government/Plantagenets, by Wikiversal version 1.12.72 on 7/11/2012. --&gt;
__NOEDITSECTION__ __NOTOC__

=== &lt;font size=1 color=dimgray&gt;Presentation&lt;/font&gt; ===
&lt;table height=1 border=1 style=&quot;border-collapse:collapse; border-color:LightSkyBlue; background-color:AliceBlue;&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=left&gt;&lt;table width=&quot;100%&quot; align=left&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;[[File:1leftarrow.png|frameless||none||x40px|link=http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/UK_Constitution_and_Government/Normans#Presentation||Normans]]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Gohome.png|frameless||none||x40px|link=http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/UK_Constitution_and_Government#Presentation]]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td nowrap&gt;&lt;font size=6 color=teal&gt;{{SUBPAGENAME}}&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:1rightarrow.png|frameless||none||x40px|link=http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/UK_Constitution_and_Government/Houses_of_Lancaster_and_York#Presentation||Houses of Lancaster and York]]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:2rightarrow.png|frameless||none||x40px|link=http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/UK_Constitution_and_Government/Topic_List#Presentation||List of Topics]]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&quot;99%&quot;&gt; &amp;nbsp; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;[[File:1rightarrow.png|frameless||none||x40px|link=http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/UK_Constitution_and_Government/Houses_of_Lancaster_and_York#Presentation||Houses of Lancaster and York]]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;!-- -- -- -- -- -- -- -- -- -- -- --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;big&gt;&lt;big&gt;The Plantagenets (1154-1399)&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/big&gt;

[[UK Constitution and Government/Normans|Previous Chapter]] | [[UK Constitution and Government/Houses of Lancaster and York|Next Chapter]]
------
&lt;/noinclude&gt;
==Henry II==
With the death of King Stephen, Henry Plantagenet took the throne as King Henry II. He already had control over the duchy of Normandy; he had also inherited Anjou from his father Geoffrey. Furthermore, he acquired many territories from his wife, Eleanor of Aquitaine. Henry thus had a vast territory when he came to the throne; as King of England, he took over Ireland.

Henry II made other remarkable achievements in England. He established courts throughout England and introduced trial by jury. Furthermore, he reduced the power of ecclesiastical courts. The Archbishop of Canterbury and Lord High Chancellor, Thomas à Becket, opposed the King's attempt to take power from the Church. At a confrontation between the two in 1170, Henry II famously said, &quot;Who will rid me of this turbulent priest?&quot; Four of his knights took him literally, and in December murdered Becket. 

Henry, however, did not have good relations with his sons. In 1170, his eldest son Henry was crowned, and is known as Henry the Young King. In 1173, the Young King and his brothers revolted against Henry II, planning to dethrone him and leave the Young King as the sole ruler in England. In 1174, the revolt failed, and all of the brothers surrendered. Later, in 1189, Henry II's third son, Richard, attacked and defeated him. Henry II died days after his defeat, and Richard, nicknamed &quot;the Lionheart,&quot; became King.

==Richard I==
Richard the Lionheart is often portrayed as a hero, but he did not do much for England. In fact, he spent almost all of his time outside the nation, and did not even find it necessary to learn English. He is most famous for his fighting in the Crusades, a holy war seeking to assert Christian dominance over Jerusalem. 

==John==
Richard's successor was his brother, John Allin. Henry II had granted John the lands of Ireland, so when John came to the throne, the titles Lord of Ireland and King of England were united. However, though Ireland became a dominion of the Crown, several lands on the Continent, including most of Normandy, were lost during John's reign. 

King John was very unpopular with the nation's magnates, the barons, whom he taxed. A particularly resented tax was the scutage, a penalty paid by barons who failed to supply the King with military resources. In 1215, after John had been defeated in France, several barons rebelled. Later in that year, John compromised and signed the ''Magna Carta'', or Great Charter. It guaranteed political liberties and provided for a church free from domination by the monarchy. These liberties and privileges, however, were not extended to the common man; rather, they were granted to the barons. Nonetheless, the document is immensely significant in English constitutional history as it is a major indication of a limitation on the power of the Crown.

King John, however, broke the provisions of the Charter later, claiming that he agreed to it under duress. In the next year, when he was retreating from a French invasion, John lost England's most valuable treasures - the Crown Jewels - in a marsh known as The Wash. His mental and physical health deteriorated, and he later died from dysentery.

==Henry III==
John was succeeded by his son, Henry, who was only nine years old. Henry III, despite a reign that lasted over half a century, is not a particularly memorable or noteworthy monarch. Nonetheless, a very significant political development occurred during Henry III's reign. In 1258, one of Henry's opponents, Simon de Montfort, called a Parliament, the forerunner of the modern institution. It, however, bears little resemblance to the modern body, as it had little power.

Simon de Montfort, who was married to Henry III's sister, defeated and imprisoned his brother-in-law in 1264. He was originally supported by Henry's son Edward, but the latter later returned to his father's side. Edward defeated de Montfort in 1265 at the Battle of Evesham and restored Henry III. In 1270, the ageing Henry gave up most of power to his son; two years later, he died, and Edward succeeded to the throne.

==Edward I==


Edward I was the monarch who brought the entire British Isles under English domination. In order to raise money in the war against the rebellious Wales, Edward instituted a tax on Jewish moneylenders. The tax, however, was too high for the moneylenders, who eventually became too poor to pay. Edward accused them of disloyalty and abolished the right of Jews to lend money. He also ordered that all Jews wear a yellow star on their clothing; that idea was later adopted by Adolf Hitler in Germany. Edward also executed hundreds of Jews, and in 1290 banished all of them from England.

In 1291, the Scottish nobility agreed to submit to Edward. When Queen Margaret I died, the nobles allowed Edward to choose between the rival claimants to the throne. Edward installed the weak John Balliol as monarch, and easily dominated Scotland. The Scots, however, rebelled. Edward I executed the chief dissenter, William Wallace, further antagonising Scotland.

==Edward II==
When Edward I died in 1307, his son Edward became King. Edward II abandoned his father's ambitions to conquer Scotland. Furthermore, he recalled several men his father had banished. The barons, however, rebelled against Edward. In 1312, Edward agreed to hand over power to a committee of barons known as &quot;ordainers.&quot; These ordainers removed the power of representatives of commoners to advise the monarch on new laws, and concentrated all power in the nobility. Meanwhile, Robert the Bruce was slowly reconquering Scotland. In 1314, Robert's forces defeated England's in battle, and Robert gained control over most of Scotland. 

In 1321, the ordainers banished a baron allied with the King, Hugh le Despencer, along with his son. In 1322, Edward reacted by recalling them and attacking the barons. He executed the leader of the ordainers, the Earl of Lancaster, and permitted the Despencers to rule England. The Despencers declared that all statutes created by the ordainers were invalid, and that thereafter, no law would be valid unless it had received the assent of the Commons, representatives of the commoners of England. However, the Despencers became corrupt, causing them to be very unpopular, even with Edward's own wife, Isabella. In 1325, Isabella went to France, and in 1326, she returned, allied with Roger Mortimer, one of the barons Edward had defeated. The two killed the Despencers and forced Edward to resign his crown to his son, also named Edward. Edward II was imprisoned and later killed.

==Edward III==
Since Edward III was a child, Isabella and Roger Mortimer ruled England in his stead. When Edward III became eighteen, however, he had Mortimer executed and banished his mother from court. In 1328, when Charles IV, Isabella's father and King of France, died, Edward claimed France, suggesting that the kingdom should pass to him through his mother. His claim was opposed by Philip VI, who claimed that the throne could only pass in the male line. Edward declared war on Philip, setting off the Hundred Years' War. The British claim to the French throne was not abandoned until the nineteenth century.

==Richard  II==
Richard II succeeded his grandfather, Edward III, in 1377. Richard II was only about ten years old when coming to the throne. Even as an adult, Richard II was a rather weak king. In 1399, he was deposed by his cousin, Henry of Bolingbroke, and probably murdered the next year.

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>is4eylq2eix4vhzpgxd6s609b1iooqk</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:SamE</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>4377</id>
    <revision>
      <id>755439</id>
      <parentid>755438</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-02-15T00:55:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>128.235.249.80</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rv</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">I am not an active user anymore. Feel free to change any articles that I have created or edited significantly. I'm currently (as of February 2007) a junior at [[w:Poudre High School|Poudre High School]] and so over my head with many other activities that I no longer have the time that I had back in 8th grade to create and maintain books on this site. Maybe that will change some day. But for now, I will not be able to spend time working on this site.

When I was active, back in 2004-2005, I was most noted for my work on the [[German]] Wikibook. I proposed and created the first few lessons for [[German: Level I]], but that was it. Coming back three years later, I find that there still isn't much more than what I put into it, so it would be great if someone could devote a little more than just administrative effort to the book.

I also did create a couple video game guides due to my interests at the time. However, those &quot;books&quot; became little more than introductions, and I have moved on from many of those games anyway. Again, feel free to edit or delete anything I have written on those pages.

Below is a copy of what information I had on my user page when I was active on this site.

Farewell, enjoy what I created, and improve on it. After all, that's what Wikibooks is all about.

==What my user page looked like back in 2004-2005==

I joined '''Wikibooks''' (after '''Wikipedia''') on February 5th, 2004. If you want to send me a message see my [[User talk:SamE|Talk page]].

I'm also SamE at [[w:User:SamE|Wikipedia]] and [[m:User:SamE|Meta]], but I'm one of the few who spend more time here at Wikibooks than at either of those.

I'm also [[Special:Contributions/67.176.76.147|User:67.176.76.147]] if I'm not logged on.

===Wikibooks I'm Editing===

I am currently working on the [[German]] book, specifically [[German: Level I]]. I have done most of the editing there; see the history for [[German:Beginner Lesson 2]] for example.

I've worked on the [[Chip's Challenge]] game walkthrough, but my computer crashed and I lost the game.

I am also helping write the [[Civilization]] walkthrough, as I play [[Civ:Civilization III|Civilization III]].

I'm working on the [[Super Mario World]] and [[TI-83 Plus: Phoenix|Phoenix]] game guides, but they are currently very bad.

Towards the end of 2004, I did a lot to improve the [[Main Page]] in various ways. I've also written [[Help:How to start a book]], which newbies seem to be using (they're following the directions in the order they are on the page).

I like to look into a book ([[US History]] for example) and start reading it, and of course, there are errors. Most of the time I will correct those errors.

Over the summer I hope to be editing more and more often.

===Wikibooks and Parts I've Created===

====2004====

I created [[German: Level I]] on March 6th, and [[Game Guides and Strategy]] on March 27th.

I created [[Super Mario World]] on April 11th, and [[TI-83 Plus: Phoenix|Phoenix]] on May 12th.

====2005====

===Copypastes===

Ä ä

Ö ö

Ü ü

ß

Colored Text:

&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;color: #FFFFFF;&quot;&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;

(For font color, replace '#FFFFFF' with color name/number)</text>
      <sha1>ofhzyqoogy00hypyg2jqxxf8plakg9n</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>