<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>Help:FAQ/Overview</title>
    <ns>12</ns>
    <id>736</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2711939</id>
      <parentid>2711912</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-09T12:13:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>QuiteUnusual moved page [[Help:Royal Academy of Buttfucking]] to [[Help:FAQ/Overview]] without leaving a redirect</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{wikibooks help}}

==What is a wiki?==
A [[w:Wiki|wiki]] is a [[w:collaborative software|collaborative collection]] of interlinked open content web pages, all of which can be visited and edited by anyone at ''any'' time. You could even edit this page by clicking the &quot;edit&quot; link, the third tab at the very top of this page, or edit only a section by clicking on &quot;[edit]&quot; to its right. If you don't have anything to add or correct on this page and you just want to see how it works, try making some test edits in the [[Wikibooks:Sandbox|Sandbox]]. See [[w:Wiki|wiki]] and the [[Help:FAQ/Editing|Editing FAQ]] for more on wikis and editing.

==What is Wikibooks?==
Wikibooks is a project to produce a new kind of instructional resource that is comprehensive and [[w:free content|free]]. See [[Wikibooks:Welcome]] for more information.

==What are the aims of Wikibooks?==
Wikibooks's goal is to create a free instructional resource—indeed, the largest instructional resource in history, both in terms of breadth and depth, to become a reliable resource. It's an ambitious goal which will probably take many years to achieve.

==How did Wikibooks start?==
Wikibooks was started on July 10, 2003 as a sister project to [[w:Wikipedia|Wikipedia]]. It was opened in response to a request by Wikipedia user Karl Wick for a place to start building open-content textbooks. Longtime Wikipedia contributor Daniel Mayer helped Karl advocate for starting such a project, and once the project was started, he helped set it up and coined the name &quot;Wikibooks&quot; and registered the domain names for the project. Soon the focus of the project was expanded to include any book resource that may be used in the classroom. This does not include encyclopedias, dictionaries or quote books, since there are specific [[w:Wikimedia|Wikimedia]] projects for those (see next FAQ entry).

==Who owns Wikibooks?==
Wikibooks is managed by a non-profit parent organization, [[w:Wikimedia Foundation|Wikimedia Foundation]], which also manages the operation of similar projects like [[w:Wikipedia|Wikipedia]] (a wiki encyclopedia), [[w:Wiktionary|Wiktionary]] (a wiki dictionary), and [[w:Wikiquote|Wikiquote]] (a wiki quote book), and owns all domain names  and servers that the Wikimedia projects run on. [[w:Bomis|Bomis]], Inc, a company mostly owned by [[w:User:Jimbo Wales|Jimbo Wales]], currently provides free [[w:bandwidth|bandwidth]] and power to the servers.

The modules hosted on this site are released by their authors under the [[WB:GFDL|GNU Free Documentation License]]; this means they are [[w:open content|open content]] and may be reproduced freely under the terms of the license. See [[Wikibooks:Copyrights|Copyrights]] and [[Help:FAQ/Readers|Readers' FAQ]] for information on how you can use Wikibooks content.

It is important to note that the '''content''' of Wikibooks is not owned by the Wikimedia Foundation, but instead individually owned by each of the contributing authors, usually noted on the history tab on each page.  A notable exception to this is that content found elsewhere may be added here that has been either given copyright clearance by the original author or is already in the public domain.  In these cases, a responsible Wikibook contributor would note that in the discussion pages of the module.

==Who is responsible for pages on Wikibooks?==
[[Wikibooks:Wikibookians|Wikibookians]]. Wikibooks is a [[w:collaborative|collaborative]] endeavor. Many people have contributed to different parts of this project, and anyone can do so, including you. All you need is to know [[Wikibooks:How to edit a page|how to edit a page]], and have some knowledge you want to share.

You can learn who is responsible for the most recent versions of any given page by clicking on the &quot;Page history&quot; link. For example, you can look at the full history of this FAQ [http://en.wikibooks.org/w/index.php?title=Help:FAQ/Overview&amp;action=history just by clicking here]. You can also see who is most responsible for a particular Wikibook by reading that book's &quot;authors&quot; page (if it has one). If you spot an error in the latest revision of an module you are highly encouraged to [[Wikibooks:Be bold|be bold]] and correct it. This practice is one of the basic review mechanisms that maintains the reliability of this instructional resource.

If you are uncertain or find the wording confusing, quote the material on the associated [[Wikibooks:Talk page|talk page]] and leave a question for the next person. This helps eliminate errors, inaccuracies or misleading wording more quickly and is highly appreciated by the community.

==What software is used to run Wikibooks?==
:Wikibooks and its sister [[w:Wikimedia|Wikimedia]] projects all use the [[m:MediaWiki|MediaWiki]] software. See [[mw:Installation|Installing MediaWiki]] for information on what's required to run mediawiki.

==How about the hardware?==
:See [[m:Wikimedia servers|Wikimedia servers]].

==How do I report bugs or suggest new features?==
[[mediazilla:|MediaZilla]] is used by mediawiki software developers to keep track of [[w:software bug|software bug]]s and feature requests. For more information, see [[w:WP:BUGS|bug reports and feature requests]]. If you don't report bugs or feature requests, then it will probably never be fixed or implemented. You can discuss feature ideas that would benefit Wikibooks with other Wikibookians at [[WB:PROPOSALS|proposals reading room]].

==What kind of [[w:markup language|markup language]] does Wikibooks use?==
:Wikibooks uses a very simple markup based on [[w:UseModWiki|UseModWiki]]. For more details, see [[Wikibooks:How does one edit a page]].

== Can you tell me anything about the Wikibooks logo? ==
More information about the logo and versions of it are best found at [[Meta:Wikibooks/Logo]].

== How is Wikibooks backed up? Could an accident destroy everything? ==
Database dumps are made periodically. Anyone can [[Help:Database download|store their own copies]].

==Is it possible to download the contents of Wikibooks?==
:Yes, the whole contents of Wikibooks can be downloaded.  See [[Help:database download]].

:Note that downloading the database dumps is '''much''' preferred over trying to spider the entire site. Spidering the site will take you much longer, and puts a lot of load on the Wikimedia server (especially if you ignore our [http://www.Wikibooks.org/robots.txt robots.txt] and spider over billions of combinations of diffs and whatnot). Heavy spidering can lead to your spider, or your IP, being barred with prejudice from access to the site. Legitimate spiders (for instance search engine indexers) are encouraged to wait about a minute between requests, follow the robots.txt, and if possible only work during less loaded hours (2:00-14:00 UTC is the lighter half of the day).

== Can I get wiki books on paper? ==
You are welcome to print out your own copy.
See [[Using Wikibooks/The Wikibooks Reader/Printing A Wikibook]] for tips.

==How can I contact the project by email?==
Given the massively collaborative nature of the project, there's no official email address. If you're looking for a project leader, it would be best to get in contact with [[w:User:Jimbo Wales|Jimbo Wales]] ([mailto:jwales@bomis.com jwales at bomis.com]). Otherwise, see the next question.  Note that if you want a faster response and from active participants in the project, you might want to send the e-mail to the mailing list.  You can also send an e-mail directly to [[Wikibooks:Administrators|some active Administrators]] through the web-based e-mail form.  Administrators are usually quite active and can be considered some of the project leaders.

==Where can I talk about Wikibooks with others?==
There are some [[Wikibooks:Mailing lists|mailing lists]], and also the [http://meta.wikipedia.com Meta-Wiki]. If you want to communicate with a specific user, leave a message on their talk page; you can find a list of personal pages (and link to your own) at the [[Wikibooks:Wikibookians|Wikibookians]] list (this list is by no means complete). Many Wikibookians have also registered their email addresses, which you can use by clicking the &quot;Email this user&quot; link from the personal pages. Finally, if you're looking to talk about a specific module or page, the best place to put your comments is on that page's Talk page. Use the ''discuss this page'' link in any module to get to the talk page. Every page has a talk page, even this one, so there is always a way to discuss the content with others. See also: [[Wikibooks:Contact us]]

== How should I link to Wikibooks? ==
We don't require you to do so in any particular way. Please use your own best judgment.

==Should I create an account? Can't I just edit anonymously?==
Users with account names enjoy several benefits, among them is the positive reputation that goes with quality work. Editors with an established history are respected especially with regard to neutralising module disputes. This is not to say there is a hierarchy ''per se''—though there are editors with administrative abilities (see [[Wikibooks:Administrators]]), these are approved by the community, and the goal of most Wikibookians is to maintain that [[w:democracy|democracy]], albeit with a little [[w:anarchy|anarchy]], remains the supreme power on Wikibooks. Also, Wikibookians with user names are in a sense ''more'' anonymous than contributors that are not logged in: while everyone can see the [[w:IP address|IP address]] of a user who did not log in when they edited, only server administrators can find the IP of a logged-in user. So if you're concerned about privacy and anonymity, you may prefer to create a username for yourself in order to hide your IP. See also [[WB:LOGIN|How to log in]].

== Is there any legal implications in allowing anyone to edit? Is it safe? ==
In practice, illegal material gets removed from active wikis quite quickly. See [http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?WikiAndIllegalMaterial this discussion] on [[w:Ward's Wiki|Ward's Wiki]] for more thoughts.

== I have a problem not on this list, where do I go? ==
: If you cannot find answers to your specific technical problems in this FAQ, try asking in the [[WB:TECH|technical reading room]].

[[Category:Wikibooks FAQ|Overview]]

[[ja:ヘルプ:概要FAQ]]</text>
      <sha1>df7io50v454wy8f5odxhm62lk4w7nqr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Help talk:FAQ/Overview</title>
    <ns>13</ns>
    <id>737</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2711940</id>
      <parentid>2711914</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-09T12:13:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>QuiteUnusual moved page [[Help talk:Royal Academy of Buttfucking]] to [[Help talk:FAQ/Overview]] over a redirect without leaving a redirect</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Initial text adapted from [[w:en:Wikipedia:Overview FAQ]] --[[User:Maveric149|mav]] 01:31, 19 Aug 2003 (UTC)

== Problematic edition by anonymous user ==

Hey people, please take a look at the [http://en.wikibooks.org/w/wiki.phtml?title=Wikibooks:Overview_FAQ&amp;oldid=48177 new question added] by IP 63.229.84.90; I think this question should be placed on talk page, because it's a (weird) comment about our goals here, not a FAQ. [[User:Marcelo Reis|Marcelo Reis]] 17:05, 27 Nov 2004 (UTC)

Here it is: [[User:193.63.168.208|193.63.168.208]] 14:12, 11 Feb 2005 (UTC)
==Why should I expect Wikibooks to succeed?==
:If a text book is by popular definition a book you only read because it is required, why should Wikibooks garner sufficient reader/editor interest to succeed?  People want to know how to size the pipes in their sprinkler system, not learn about fluid mechanics or hydraulics engineering.  They want to figure how much they have to save to retire at age 50, not learn about mathematics.  But Wikibooks needs reader-editors to succeed.  So why should I expect it to succeed?

== text from GNU sites ie Wikipedia ==

I've been searching around to no avail, so I'll just breakdown and throw this out there. Whats the policy on importing work from Wikipedia into Wikibooks? Are there any special steps that need to be considered? [[User:RichMac|RichMac]] 03:59, 20 October 2006 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>jk3a09pjqw3optwi2s72hrdbn4zaqqn</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Help:FAQ/Readers</title>
    <ns>12</ns>
    <id>738</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2018893</id>
      <parentid>2000824</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-01-18T04:53:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>moved [[Help:Readers' FAQ]] to [[Help:FAQ/Readers]]: Subpages enabled.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{wikibooks help}}

==How do I search Wikibooks?==
Use [[Special:Search]] or use the search box in the sidebar. See [[Help:Navigating#Searching]] for more.

You can also use Google to search Wikibooks by [http://www.google.com/custom?sa=Google+Search&amp;domains=wikibooks.org&amp;sitesearch=Wikibooks.org following this link]. Google's index will, however, not be up to date.

== Where can I request new entries? ==
After you've exhausted [[WB:SEARCH|searching]] for the content, you may ask for more help in locating it in the [[Wikibooks:Reading room/Assistance|assistance reading room]], or add an entry to [[Wikibooks:Requested books]].

==What license does Wikibooks use for contents?==
The text of each page is covered by at least the [[WB:GFDL|GNU Free Documentation License]]. Some contents (notably images and other media files) may use compatible licenses for which you will need to check the terms. These may be public domain, use a copyleft license like Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike, or are used under [[w:fair use|fair use]] terms.

See [[Wikibooks:Copyrights]] and [[Wikibooks:Media]] for more.

==How do I cite a Wikibooks module?==
Cite it as you would any other web page in accordance with the normal citation practice the publication you are submitting the paper to follows. Because Wikibooks modules are constantly edited, you should include the URL for the specific version of the module you accessed. You can determine this URL by clicking the &quot;Page history&quot; link and clicking on the date of the version you want (likely the one at the top). The URL of the resulting page is a permanent link back to that version no matter what changes are made afterwards. Citing the individual authors is not necessary.

== How do I print a wikibook? ==
Newer browsers will be able to access the &quot;''print stylesheet''&quot; which removes the Wikibooks interface and some colors. Try a print preview (if your browser has this function) to see how it will print.

Alternatively, you can click the &quot;printable version&quot; link in the toolbox at the bottom of the menu on your left.

Some books provide special [[Help:Print versions|print versions]].

== Can I mirror Wikibooks on my website? ==
You can use, copy, redistribute, modify or mirror as much as you wish, as long as you follow the provisions of the GNU Free Documentation License and the licenses of any images or media you use.

See [[Wikibooks:Copyrights]], and [[Wikibooks:Media]].

== Can I get Wikibooks on CD, or download it for offline use? ==
There are no CDs currently available. You can however [[Help:Database download|download the database]]. Some books, furthermore, have [[Help:Print versions|print versions]].

== Am I required to use the GFDL for my site if I quote Wikibooks? ==
Citing Wikibooks is sufficient if you're quoting small bits (under the fair use doctrine). If you wish to quote substantial portions of it, you may wish to consult with a lawyer as it may constitute a derivative work. You are welcome to drop by the [[Wikibooks:Reading room]] to seek the opinion of Wikibookians. We're usually a good bunch and try not to bite. :-D

==How do you know if information is correct?==
As anyone can edit any module, it is of course possible for biased, out-of-date or incorrect information to be posted. However, because there are so many other people reading the modules and monitoring contributions using the [[WB:RC|Recent Changes]] page, incorrect information is usually put right quickly. Thus the overall accuracy of this instructional resource is improving all the time as it attracts more and more contributors. You are encouraged to help by correcting modules and passing on your own knowledge.

== Is there any peer-review process to validate included information? ==
In general, Wikibooks depends on contributors like you to fix any incorrect information, though Wikibooks does have a [[WB:REVIEW|system to review page revisions]]. Content should generally be easy to verify by checking other sources or through being able to reproduce similar results yourself.

[[Category:Wikibooks FAQ|Overview]]

[[ja:ヘルプ:読者FAQ]]</text>
      <sha1>02zwhybsthrkl2y61ejd6l0wqt1f4n3</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Help talk:FAQ/Readers</title>
    <ns>13</ns>
    <id>739</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2018895</id>
      <parentid>1790482</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-01-18T04:54:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>moved [[Help talk:Readers' FAQ]] to [[Help talk:FAQ/Readers]]: Subpages enabled.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Initial text adapted from [[:w:Wikipedia:Readers' FAQ]] --[[User:Maveric149|mav]] 01:45, 19 Aug 2003 (UTC)

== Download articles ==

The question '''Can I get Wikibooks on CD, or download it for offline use?''' really needs a better answer.  I can think of several textbooks that I have spent well over a hundred hours reading.  That is an insane amount of time to spend online for something that is probabably about 100 KB in length (a sub minute download time).  Downloading the entire database and setting up a mysql database, a http server, php ... is a huge overkill for one book.  I should be able to choose a book, download a zip or pdf of the html and then browse at my leisure later.  Many people who use these books will want to not pay per minute connection fees or will want to use it on their laptop away from a network connection.  I personally consider wikibooks useless from a reader's point of view until there is someway to download '''One''' text book and read it later offline.  Ditto for being able to print one text book. --Anon

:That requires software that has not been coded yet. But all that is planned. It will be some time before we have our first nearly complete book anyway so this isn't a pressing issue ''right now''. --[[User:Maveric149|mav]] 08:48, 23 Aug 2003 (UTC)

::Has this question been re-examined yet? There are now several books that are more or less complete, and at the very least, those should be packaged up and be made available for download in a nice pdf (or whatever, ps if it floats one's boat). This could be done manually, but I don't see why there couldn't be a simple script to convert the wiki markup into LaTeX (add in all the nicities like a chapter index and such automatically), then use that to generate both a PDF and HTML document. Zip those up, upload them to the site, and there you go. Run that once a day or so, and things should be up to date as well. --[[User:Kobold|Kish]] 08:10, 24 Dec 2004 (UTC)

:::Two years after the beginning of this discussion, there seems to be still no way to get a PDF/LaTex/whatever file containing a wikibook. Is it still planned or should we forget about that and remain with reduced usability for these books? -- 20 Jul 2005

: Until one can download a book this site is really pretty useless ''as a &quot;book site&quot;'' compared to old-fashioned sites.  Other book-like documents, even when split up in multiple pages, can usually be downloaded somehow - e.g. with wget of a directory and its subdirectores.  Text here can be read on-line, but ''not'' conveniently as books which is what the site claims to provide.  For authors to &quot;prepare a print version&quot; or whatever isn't very good either since that will presumably become outdated.  Asking people do download the whole site doesn' scale well either, even if you get it to work without needing to run SQL and whatnot.  My guess is that however much work it is, you need to reorganize so each book resides in its own directory.  That way wiki pages get auto-sorted into their correct book. [[User:129.240.186.42|129.240.186.42]] 13:31, 13 December 2006 (UTC)

Related to the above discussion, the answer to '''How do I print a wikibook?''' is not really very helpful for printing a whole book. Nearly every book is broken up into separate URLs, which means printing each URL separately. Obviously this isn't the end of the world, but it's not exactly user-friendly either. - [[User:Qaphsiel|Qaphsiel]] 19:58, 3 October 2005 (UTC)


=== Possible replacement ===

I have to say, as a long time &quot;linux&quot; user, I am truly horrified by that section on downloading a wikibook. First off, it seems like fully half of it is involved in setting up a directory in the root directory (bad bad bad bad!) and then in ''undoing'' it rather then simply create the directory in one's home directory in the first place and never have to worry about permissions and ownership thereafter; then it goes on to suggest that you should manually download each and every HTML page (badly!) and then cluelessly explains about a quoting error (which must then immediately be rectified). This last line just makes me want to wail in agony and tear out my eyes: &quot;You can place a new item on yor dektop for your wikibook. To do this you hit the right mouse key on a free space of your desktop frame. Choose New , File and Link to (URL). As the URL adress just put in /wiki/nameofthebook.&quot;

Here's a replacement, dependent on having wget installed.
 cd ; mkdir wikibooks/ ; mkdir wikibooks/NAME_OF_WIKIBOOK/ &amp;&amp; cd wikibooks/NAME_OF_WIKIBOOK/ &amp;&amp; mkdir en.wikibooks.org &amp;&amp; touch en.wikibooks.org/robots.txt  &amp;&amp; wget -kp --recursive --html-extension -l 2 --no-clobber -np -- http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/NAME_OF_WIKIBOOK &amp;&amp; cp -r en.wikibooks.org/wiki/NAME_OF_WIKIBOOK/* en.wikibooks.org/ &amp;&amp; rm -rf en.wikibooks.org/wiki

One could script this as well. The body of the script would be:
 cd ; mkdir wikibooks/ ; mkdir wikibooks/$1/ ; cd wikibooks/$1/ &amp;&amp; mkdir en.wikibooks.org &amp;&amp; touch en.wikibooks.org/robots.txt  &amp;&amp; wget -kp --recursive --html-extension -l 2 --no-clobber -np -- http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/$1 &amp;&amp; cp -r en.wikibooks.org/wiki/$1/* en.wikibooks.org/ &amp;&amp; rm -rf en.wikibooks.org/wiki
and then a 
 chmod +x script-name.sh ; sh script-name.sh NAME_OF_WIKIBOOK 

(This is a bit baroque, so I'll explain; the mkdir and touch are necessary so that the robots.txt file will exist before wget begins its download with the --no-clobber option forcing it to accept our fake blank robots.txt and ignore the real one on wikibooks which would tell wget to ''not'' do any recursive downloads. Of course, that's exactly what we want to do. The wget invocation does a two-level recursive download which appends .html to all HTML files and downloads all prerequisites for viewing a file while rewriting all URL links to point to the local copy if possible. However, a two-level recursive download has the major defect that many many files under the en.wikibooks.org/wiki/ will be downloaded but not needed! However, if you change &quot;-l 2&quot; to the much faster and fewer downloads of &quot;-l 1&quot;, then any subdirectories would fail to be downloaded. For example, in the Haskell book, -l 1 would not download [[Haskell/Write Yourself a Scheme in 48 Hours]].) 

Obviously, some testing would be good. This leaves a mess in the en.wikibook.org subdirectory and so far I've only tested it on Bash and my system. --[[User:Marudubshinki|maru]]  [[User talk:Marudubshinki|(talk)]] [[Special:Contributions/Marudubshinki|contribs]] 03:18, 9 August 2006 (UTC)

== Related to How to Print a WikiBook ==

It would be really nice if someone made a script such that a reader can select a book to be printed by one of the ondemand printers, such as [http://www.lulu.com Lulu].

== Please help me to translate this sentence ==

I have been translating this page to Turkish. But I couldn't figure out this sentence:

''Cite it as you would any other web page in accordance with the normal citation practice the publication you are submitting the paper to follows.''

Could anyone say what this sentence say? [[Special:Contributions/78.164.208.224|78.164.208.224]] ([[User talk:78.164.208.224|talk]]) 22:14, 8 May 2010 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>ee6dlt1f6sypzd7qlm7ebra89icjv3h</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Polish</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>743</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1865169</id>
      <parentid>1370241</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-06-28T21:35:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Adding {{WikiProject Languages}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{WikiProject Languages}} 

Should we split this into several pages? -- [[User:Emperorbma|Emperorbma]]
:I think so. Please go ahead. [[User:Kpjas|Kpjas]]
When I red this I wonder how I was capable to learn this language :) I think that it would be nice to write something about double negation in polish. Dryobates.
:: i'm not sure that i wouldn't say that i don't disagree with you. ;) [[User:Boud|Boud]] 12:01, 10 May 2007 (UTC)

I started a new link: Polish Idioms and Expressions. But I need someone else to write in it! Please, be a Polish person =) or someone who speaks Polish REALLY fluently :-) Dziewcyna Gwiazda

I'm from Poland and I can help you. Just say, what do you want?

----

Hi Dziewcyna Gwiazda, some of my friends on pl.wikipedia and other online forums might well enjoy making a list of boud-ish idioms and expressions in Polish ;), before they get lost because i forget my old errors... But that would be too cult-ish. [[User:Boud|Boud]] 13:49, 18 Mar 2004 (UTC)

There is an idiomatic expression in Polish which literally translates into English as: ''&quot;He is from Pipiduvec.&quot;'' Pipiduvec (sp.?) is a mythical town where only &quot;stupid people&quot; live, so the expression means, ''&quot;He is stupid,&quot;'' or ''&quot;he is an idiot.&quot;''  Do you know this expression?

: As far as I know (I'm native speaker but not a linguist), it's not exactly like that. &quot;pipidówa&quot; (pipi-doova) is a term for a small, primitive village. You could say &quot;damn, what a ''pipidówa'', they don't even have a shop here&quot;. --[[User:Derbeth|Derbeth]] [[User talk:Derbeth|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]] 18:04, 19 January 2007 (UTC)

== Naming convention change ==

Would anyone have something agains changing naming convention from archaic colon style to new slash style ([[Polish:Introductions]] would become [[Polish/Introductions]])? This change would provide readers with backlinks to the table of contents on top of every chapter.

This change can be done by a bot, with no need to edit anything manually. I just need consensus of book contributors. --[[User:Derbeth|Derbeth]] [[User talk:Derbeth|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]] 08:12, 11 May 2007 (UTC)

== Forum ==

If this is a book for the people who want to learn Polish, maybe it would be a good idea to create a sister-forum to this book? I mean, to create a forum where people who learn Polish could ask questions and some netives (like me) would answer them?

== Too focused in grammar ==

Hello. I am writing the polish wikibook in portuguese language and I would just like to say to the english writers that this course is too focused in grammar. A beginners course should have a more vocabulary then grammar. Take a look at the German wikibook for some inspiration. thanks --[[Special:Contributions/201.81.159.119|201.81.159.119]] ([[User talk:201.81.159.119|talk]]) 01:17, 11 June 2008 (UTC)

More pharses and useful words! 
(nie lubię angielskiego ;p)</text>
      <sha1>8mdi9qik2ryf02x7uymtaeh8ckio45s</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>CACS/Glossary/ISOC</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>744</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1508364</id>
      <parentid>1493442</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-05-25T23:54:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>recat, formatting</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Internet Society (ISOC)''' &lt;small&gt;''(Organization)''&lt;/small&gt; The '''ISOC''' ''(pronounced eye-sok)'' is a cooperative of commercial, professional and governmental organizations that promotes internet technologies.
It was founded in 1991 as a corporate umbrella for the ''Internet Engineering Task Force ([[CACS/Glossary/IETF|IETF]])'' and other ad-hoc activities
ISOC now sponsors an annual conference and other events.
It is headquartered in Virginia and Geneva, and its web address is [http://www.isoc.org/ www.isoc.org].

[[Category:{{FULLBOOKNAME}}|{{FULLCHAPTERNAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>h8dp5j06u1lqzedos4pdfyocwj2r6mf</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Guaka</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>745</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2357716</id>
      <parentid>2357715</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-05-30T15:03:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Liam987</username>
        <id>582918</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">For now, see [[w:en:User:Guaka]].</text>
      <sha1>5rpjhi2lhkzjwp46cudazh0mmu941e4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Computer Programming</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>758</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1597357</id>
      <parentid>1597134</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-08-01T18:37:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Panic2k4</username>
        <id>2865</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* merge */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{vfd-survived}}
{{Archive box|
* [[/Archive1|Oct 2003 - Oct 2004]] (first)
* [[/Archive2|Feb 2005]]
* [[/Archive3|Mar 2005 - Apr 2005]]
* [[/Archive4|Jul 2005 - Jun 2006]] (last)
}}

__TOC__

== Babelprog ==

Suppose I know how to do something in one language, and I want to translate it to another language. For example, I know how to sprintf in C, and I want to do the same in Haskell. Or I know lapply in R and I want to do it in Visual Basic. Is there any babelfish-like tool that could be used to help me? [[User:Albmont|Albmont]] 14:20, 28 March 2007 (UTC)

There exists a few specific translation tools:

* &quot;f2c&quot; ([[w:f2c]]), which translates from Fortran77 to the C programming language.
* there are several [http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;q=%22pascal+to+C%22&amp;btnG=Google+Search Pascal to C/C++] translaters.
* http://jython.org/ lets you write code in Python and run it on a Java virtual machine.

Please add to this list.
While translating from one programming language to another is much easier than natural-language translation, I imagine that translation into a completely different language family ( &quot;imperative&quot; C to &quot;functional&quot; Haskell) is much more difficult than the above same-family imperative-to-imperative translations.

Is there a better place for this list of translation tools somewhere in this book on programming?
--[[User:DavidCary|DavidCary]] 20:33, 4 April 2007 (UTC)

BTW, I have just found an interesting resource: [http://merd.sourceforge.net/pixel/language-study/syntax-across-languages/Mthmt.html http://merd.sourceforge.net/pixel/language-study/syntax-across-languages/Mthmt.html]. I guess there's no restriction to copy and paste it to Wikibooks (or wikipedia). [[User:Albmont|Albmont]] ([[User talk:Albmont|talk]]) 17:28, 16 December 2008 (UTC)

== Tables ==
I have found 2 tables that are almost identical, the task of maintaining the information on both is very hard, they should be merged (as one has 2 more rows) and a template should be elaborated so it will be easier to extend and update. I will get to it as time allows but if someone could take a shot at it, please do... txs.&lt;br&gt;
[[Computer programming/Language concepts]]  --[[User:Panic2k4|Panic]] 17:28, 11 May 2007 (UTC)

:Yeah, splitting the tables was my fault.  I wanted to avoid the kind of sprawl that made this book feel really mediocre and unhelpful.  This was probably not the best way to go about it, but to get an idea, compare this [http://en.wikibooks.org/w/index.php?title=Computer_programming&amp;oldid=571075 hyper-sprawl version] with its [http://en.wikibooks.org/w/index.php?title=Computer_programming&amp;oldid=841594 leaner and meaner counterpart].  Still not quite lean and mean enough.  I think that if we want to make this book halfway decent, we might need some radical surgery.  The book isn't any good if it's just everybody trying to squeeze in their favourite thing (i'm probably guilty of that too).  We need to cut and steer.  For example, could you live with the tables just being a subpage and not on the front page?  Or how about a show/hide link?  -- [[User:Kowey|Kowey]] 05:44, 19 May 2007 (UTC)

:I started updating the Table with some pages and noticed that the template didn't have the Perl section in so I updated it. One problem however is the [[Visual Basic .NET]] stuff. Doesn't seem to want to link to the pages no matter what I enter. The heading works fine just not the individual pages. Anyone got any ideas?? Oop's never mind the last I was brain dead for a second NET is not Net...[[User:Jwwicks|John]]

== it is useful to have a strong programming culture ==

In the present text, there is this awkward, although very understandable phrase &quot;...but it is useful to have a strong programming culture.&quot; I would assume this means '' '''cultural''' '', as in having a strong background of knowledge and or experience in programming, perhaps including pseudo-code, logic, etc... 
From Wikipedia entry [[culture]]: ...anthropologists commonly use the term &quot;culture&quot; to refer to the universal human capacity and activities to classify, codify and communicate their experiences symbolically.
Unfortunately as used as a noun here- it sounds analogous to &quot;culture&quot; as in a &quot;bacterial culture.&quot; he-heh!  And it may be a teleogy- what is a &quot;programming culture&quot; other than a culture/climate that consists of programmers programming?  I am afraid to replace the word as it might have common usage in the programming community that I am unaware of.???  There are surely better ways to phrase the usefulness of learning more than one computer language. [[User:Cuvtixo|Cuvtixo]] ([[User talk:Cuvtixo|talk]]) 16:03, 7 March 2008 (UTC)

:Probably '''background''' ?!? it seems at least on that phrase to make better sense (as I didn't search the context where it is being used), go ahead and change it... --[[User:Panic2k4|Panic]] ([[User talk:Panic2k4|talk]]) 16:49, 7 March 2008 (UTC)

== Development platforms ==

This article seems to be specificall about programming on the personal computer.  Although there are some suggestions about including how to program FOR another device (cell phone, mainframe, etc) ON a personal computer, this is significantly different from programming directly from a terminal on a VAX or mainframe, for example. I think there should be some specific information about what a development environment on a PC (IDE) is, what target platforms one can program for.  I can't imagine that there isn't some public domain printed material that has a more inclusive overview of all electronic computer programming and what programming languages are.

Some mention of scientific calculators, for example, and programming in languages like FORTH and assembler for Boot ROMs would be a lot more informative [[User:Cuvtixo|Cuvtixo]] ([[User talk:Cuvtixo|talk]]) 22:10, 7 March 2008 (UTC)

== book name ==

I see that recently this book was renamed from &quot;Computer programming&quot; (&quot;sentence casing like Wikipedia does&quot;) to &quot;Computer Programming&quot; (&quot;title casing like books often do&quot;).

Currently the [[Wikibooks:Manual of Style]] proposed guideline and the [[Wikibooks:Local manuals of style]] essay both specifically mention both of these styles as perfectly acceptable for a WikiBook.

Is there a reason to prefer one over the other for this specific book?
(Reasons to prefer one over the other, in general, should be discussed in the talk pages of the above guidelines).

If ever change the name of this book again, what name would you prefer?
Perhaps a more specific name, such as &quot;Comparing Computer Programming Languages&quot;?
--[[User:DavidCary|DavidCary]] ([[User talk:DavidCary|talk]]) 08:44, 2 January 2009 (UTC)

:I have been using (the casing) &quot;Computer programming&quot; for categories and &quot;Computer Programming&quot; for WIkibooks as to avoid commissions in general categories and book categories, that is &quot;Computer Programming&quot; as a Wikibook can have it's own category and coexist with &quot;Computer programming&quot; as a general category were various Wikibooks belong (in realty we are using &quot;Programming&quot;), hope that this helps and can be used to come up with a more consistent manual of style...  --[[User:Panic2k4|Panic]] ([[User talk:Panic2k4|talk]]) 19:56, 2 January 2009 (UTC)

== merge ==
I suggest merging the near-stub book [[The Complete Programming FAQ]] into a section of [[Computer Programming]].
Both seem to have the same scope -- a general overview of all programming languages, but not an in-depth tutorial on how to learn any one of them.
--[[User:DavidCary|DavidCary]] ([[User talk:DavidCary|talk]]) 14:03, 1 August 2009 (UTC)

:It seems logical, the [[The Complete Programming FAQ]] has no real structure and no defined scope...
:One thing that the outcome of the VfD indicated is that people have been moving/deleting content out of this book in place of trascluding or reusing it. It seems without giving any attribution to the source book. If I had the time I would also examine all programming books and rebuild this book with the generalist/conceptual information...    --[[User:Panic2k4|Panic]] ([[User talk:Panic2k4|talk]]) 18:37, 1 August 2009 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>om8m0wjrdxis6trbkycswdoc3a4qw1o</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:C Programming</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>759</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2497304</id>
      <parentid>2497298</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-03-05T06:59:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DavidCary</username>
        <id>973</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Yet more wiki that discuss the C programming language</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;div style=&quot;float:right;&quot;&gt;
* {{todolink|C Programming|Pages needing work}}
* [[/Q&amp;A Archive/]]
&lt;/div&gt;
==About==
* Started: 11 August 2003‎
* Size: 60,800 words (15 March 2012; determined from the printed version, so probably actually larger)
* {{rc}}
* {{Subpages link}}
* Headings Case: a mixture of title case and sentence case

== Programming:C Contributor style guide and discussion ==

I've trimmed the outline here. Specific details such as if, for statements and so on should go under their parent article. [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 08:56, 20 Aug 2003 (UTC)

I think lots of work needs to be done in reorganizing the Beginning C section. The variables section needs to be reorganized quite a bit, and I think the compilation page should go away. [[User:Thunderbunny|Thunderbunny]] 22:53, 13 Dec 2003 (UTC)

:Where is the ''pointer'' and ''functions''? I suggest we move the content in this cover to [[Programming:History of C]]. the fmt of this book is quite different from other books. --[[User:Yacht|Yacht]] ([[User talk:Yacht|talk]])[[Queer|Q]] 02:42, 21 Feb 2004 (UTC)

::[[Programming:C pointers and arrays|Pointers and relationship to arrays]] [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 03:20, 21 Feb 2004 (UTC)

:::something about macro definition and substitution? --[[User:Yacht|Yacht]] ([[User talk:Yacht|talk]])[[Queer|Q]] 02:52, 23 Feb 2004 (UTC)

:::: You can use #define for function/macro definitions, but they're rather evil. I'd use #define ''only'' for constants. [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 03:27, 23 Feb 2004 (UTC)

::: i meant do we need a separated chapter for that? --[[User:Yacht|Yacht]] 17:01, 28 Feb 2004 (UTC)

Pages should be limited to the context of the title, for example the &quot;Programming:C&quot; page should be restricted to the language itself: the history of the language is appropriate, the tutorial is not.  Anything that isn't universally &quot;the C language&quot; should be relocated to the appropriate page.

Additionally, C programs are not limited to unix environments.

--[[User:Eibwen|Eibwen]] 04:15, 25 Sep 2004 (UTC)

----
Hi there,

Let me start by saying that from what I have seen so far, I like this book very much. So much so, that I recommended it be featured on the front page after some polishing, as an example of what a textbook should look like.

However, there is one thing that seems to be severely lacking to me. In the introduction of this book, it is written: &quot;This book is intended to teach C programming, from beginning to advanced.&quot; This would seem to indicate to me that this is a book that teaches you how to program in C. However, from what I have seen so far, this is more like a reference manual for the C language. What's lacking is a C tutorial, something that explains concepts to me by letting me code small programs, and compile and test them. Is this intentional? 

I am not a coder myself, I cannot fill in perceived gaps in this manual, I am afraid.--[[User:Branko|Branko]] 17:26, 27 Mar 2004 (UTC)

:Perhaps there should be seperate tutorial and reference books?
----
I completely agree, and would like to add that some kind of assumptions need to be made about the user's level of programming experience and then &lt;i&gt;standardised throughout&lt;/i&gt; the book. I found it difficult to understand what I was expected to know reading this book. Though it supposedly takes you &quot;from beginning to advanced&quot;, I found that each chapter appears completely disconnected and independant of every other chapter. While some assume you don't know things that have already been covered, others seem far advanced to any previous chapters (e.g. the libraries section, which utterly confused me after a somewhat pleasent introduction to functions in C).

:Ok, I think this should be a high priority issue as the book in its present state is half unusable to both beginners and advanced coders. How about divide it to two parts: I Basics (intro to programming languages in general), II Advanced (C-specific topics and other advanced stuff: scopes, idioms, nothing platform-dependent though), III Appendix (C-keywords, precedence tables, ASCII charts etc.)? [[User:Epikuros|Epikuros]] 13:24, 27 October 2006 (UTC)

== Perhaps change history section a bit ==

I think the history section is slightly misleading, slightly innacurate and slightly inappropriate.

- The advent of the solid state era at Bell Labs is irrelevant to the software research done there. Computing (FotranAlgol etc) was developed on thermionic equipment, and the advent of C was on machines decades later. There is no direct link between the two. More important and germane would be the research done there by Shannon on encoding and information theory around 1950. C could have happened without solid satate, but not without information theory.

- The lineage from Fortran is innacurate. Algol weas created as a reaction to the multiplicity Fortran and all of the other high level languages at the time (there were many). Fortran was the most popular, but this &quot;begat&quot; is misleading. In the letter from the GAMM  committee on the higher level lanugage, written after a tour of America in 1957:
''&quot;We have endeavored from the beginning to avoid the possibility of  deviations from existing earlier proposals (Rutishauser 1951, FORTRAN, partly also PACT). Guided by tbe news and reports that Bauer and Bottenbruch have brought back from America, we have decided that our hitherto existing proposals also largely agree structurally with Perlis' IT language and the Remington-Rand Math-Matic. This agreement is most striking with Math-Matic, the most recent of the listed proposals.&quot;'' (cited in Bemer 1969)

This passage is important not only because of its explicit distancing from Fortran as a sole solution, but also of its mention of the many other language systems - including some excellent Eurpoean ones - that existed at the time.



- it is inappropriate in that ignores the rich tradition of programming language research being done at Bell in the period - notable languages are

1955 Wolontis-Bell Interpreter

1955 L3

1958 L2

1959 Bell SAP

1959 Macro SAP

1961 Music

1962 SNOBOL

1962 SCL

1963 ALPAKA

1963 ALPAK

1963 L6

1963 ALTRAN

1964 Process III

1965 OEDIPUS

1966 EPL

1966 ALPAKB

1966 VPRPAK

1966 IBMAP

1966 BEFAP

1967 MULTILANG

1967 GRIN

1967 AMPL

1968 B-LINE

1969 FASE

1970 SWAP

1971 BELL-CODE

All of which were in their way influential on the development of C. In particular, the tradition of macro-languages and macro-extensions to languages at Bell certainly was vital to the style and design of C. (Can you imagine C without the preprocessor?)

== Resources added ==

Added a resources link to the [[Pelles C]] page and [[Open Source]] page I created - Hope that is appropriate [[User:82.69.58.117|82.69.58.117]] 06:17, 25 Sep 2004 (UTC)

== Why are thereTWO tables of contents??? ==

I don't understand.  In the table of contents at the top of the page, there is a link halfway down to another table of contents with a nested subtree of data.  IMO, this adds unneeded complexity.  I want to flatten this out and just have one table of contents at the top, like 99% of the other texts on this site.

Any objections?  If not, I will make the change next weekend.  --[[User:Waxmop|Waxmop]] 15:49, 23 Oct 2004 (UTC)


I Added the {Free,Net,Open,Darwin,DragonFly}BSD information about they have the gcc on there systems. 

--[[User:Luís Vitório Cargnini|Luís Vitório Cargnini]] 14:19 (-03:00 GMT, -03:00 UTC) March 21, 2005.

== A beginner learning C ==

(moved to [[C Programming/Simple Input and Output]] )


== merge the cover page and the table of contents? ==

Someone recently split apart the cover page and the table of contents
( [[Programming:C]] and ).
I find it reminiscent of &quot;splash screens&quot;.
Many people recommend *not* using &quot;splash screens&quot;[http://www.websiteoptimization.com/speed/tweak/splash/] [http://www.newfangled.com/contentmgr/showdetails.php/id/3429].

Do those objections *not* apply to wikibooks, or should we merge the cover page and the table of contents?

:Hi, I'm the bastard that moved everything around :-). You raise a good point though, I absolutley hate splash screens on most websites. That being said I think the rules are a little different for books. As of right now the cover does suck though. So if we do decide to keep it a nifty graphic or something would be need to be added. But if you really think the pages should be merged than I'm all for it. Just as long as the first page isn't like what it was before I made my changes. That page was disorganized, had two tables of contents, and looked more like a long essay than a well organized online book. --[[User:Astone42|Astone42]] 13:09, 25 Jun 2005 (UTC)

== [[Wikibooks:Naming policy]] ==

You might want to consider the [[WB:NP]]. You current naming convention is depreciated and has several disadvantages - like it has no navigational links. Also you worthy effort is neiter considered a book nor a section inside a book. See [http://en.wikipedia.org/wikistats/wikibooks/EN/Wikibooks_EN.htm wikistats] which implements an exstensive book and section detector.

--[[User:Krischik|Krischik]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:Krischik|T]]&lt;/sup&gt; 07:15, 11 October 2005 (UTC)

== Compilers ==

Just a logical question here--Wouldn't it be better to teach C by standardizing a single compiler across platforms? We can be more in-depth in how things work, for example, if everyone uses GCC (either by means of direct install or MinGW).
[[User:Blank|Blank]] 14:11, 14 February 2006 (UTC)

''Allow me to quote the FAQ:''

::Many beginners fail to appreciate that C and C++ are used on a
::number of platforms, and that what works with a particular compiler
::is not necessarily going to work with another, even on the same
::platform. It is important that a learner be clear about the
::differences between programming in standard C or C++, and
::programming using platform- and compiler-specific extensions. In
::the long run, this approach - that of separating the idea of
::&quot;language&quot; and &quot;platform&quot; - leads to a better understanding of both
::the language and the platform. It is generally accepted that the
::sooner this is appreciated by the learner, the better.
:: -- [http://faqs.org/faqs/C-faq/learn/ the C FAQ]

''Does that answer your question?''

== other wiki that discuss the C programming language ==

Is there a better place to mention other wiki that discuss the C programming language ?
* clc-wiki http://clc-wiki.net/ &quot;computers.languages.c&quot;
* the original wiki http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?CeeIdioms
* [[Pelles C]]
* Wikipedia: &quot;C programming language&quot;
* Wikipedia: &quot;C syntax&quot;
Is &quot; http://wikibooks.org/wiki/C_Programming &quot; the appropriate link to use to get those other wiki to link back to the beginning of this book ?

-- [[User:DavidCary|DavidCary]] --[[User:70.189.73.224|70.189.73.224]] 03:11, 31 July 2006 (UTC)

* the [http://wiki.pellesc.de Pelles C Wiki]
* A [http://www.iso-9899.info wiki about C programming standards]
* The [http://ctips.pbworks.com/ C Programming Tips and Tricks Wiki].

--[[User:DavidCary|DavidCary]] ([[User talk:DavidCary|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/DavidCary|contribs]]) 06:59, 5 March 2013 (UTC)

== String function implementations ==
Does anyone have any objections to me re-writing some of the string function implementations?
Frankly including meaning-less variable names, along with the ternary conditional operator, is not the way to instruct others on C programming or on how the string functions work.
[[User:AmitDeshwar|AmitDeshwar]] 08:01, 11 February 2007 (UTC)

{{Wikipediapar||C programming language}}
{{Wikipediapar||C syntax}}

== Program Flow/Control ==

Why is the Control page called &quot;Program Flow&quot; in the table of contents, but &quot;Control&quot; elsewhere? --[[User:Kpengboy|Kpengboy]] 03:15, 4 May 2007 (UTC)Kpengboy

== In addition to ==

Few days ago I started writing [[et:Programmeerimiskeel_C|C Programming book in Estonian]] and i would like to link all the pages here. So could someone write [[et:Programmeerimiskeel C/Keelereeglid|&quot;Standard language rules&quot;]], so that I could verify what i have written and link it here? 

It should contain at least:
* syntax, something like: 
** C has free design
** Code segment is ended by &quot;;&quot;
** C differs capitals
* C needs the code segment to be defined or valuated before use, and also how it differs from
** recursion
** linked list data structure  
* Parts of code, where to write them and short description what thy are, something like
** comments on the written program
** pragma/include directives
** define directives
** structures
** global variables
** prototypes
** main function (with short overview how data is passed &amp; how value differs from reference)
** other functions 
* Unwritten rules (or links to them, like [[:C Programming/Structure and style|Element of style]])

== Exercises, anyone? ==

I think there should be some exercises at the end of each lesson - so that the reader can practice. # [[User:Peteturtle|Brandon Johnsonn]] 12:43, 18 June 2007 (UTC)

== Topics ==

It seems to me that the topics in this ebook are drifting around.  Is this book going to teach C programming language or the standard C library?  In my experience of teaching C it is best to start as simple as possible and cover the language and include only the bare minimum library calls, like printf, scanf, getc, etc.

I would suggest to start very slow with a general introduction then follow though with more specific topics such as types and variables, operators and expressions, flow control, functions, pointers and arrays, structures, and IO.  There is defiantly a need for a book on the standard library, more advanced topics such as macros, error handling, and whatnot, but not in an introductory text.

Remember that people will be reading this book because they don't know C and most likely very little about programming.  Jumping into advanced topics like error handling before you even cover what a variable will not get the response you are after.

I have had the most success when topics are covered in this order:  introduction, types and variables, operators and expressions, flow control, functions, pointers and arrays, structures, and IO.  Topics should be brief and general without getting to deep to avoid overloading the student. All other material should be moved to a new text or placed in an intermediate or advanced section of the book.

What does everyone else think? I can see that this book has been pretty slow so if I don't get any responses within a few days I will restructure the beginning C section and start hacking away...  I would rather have some community involvement with this rather then just a me thing. --[[User:Karl McClendon|Karl McClendon]] 02:37, 6 September 2007 (UTC)

I agree and would like to help if you are still on it -- [[User:Nefthy|Nefthy]] 11:16, 16 October 2007 (UTC)

== Use of the &quot;source lang&quot; tag ==

I've seen the use of the &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;source lang=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt; tag in [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inetd wikipedia] in order to achieve source code highlighting and was woundering what was preventing the use of it here ? is a call for a &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;code&gt; , &lt;pre&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt; etc. tag replacer bot in place ?

I think its a problem of information and history.

I think we shall change little by little to this &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;source lang=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt; to get a consistent style.--[[User:Hoxel|Hoxel]] 14:12, 15 November 2007 (UTC)

== C99 reference ==

As the WWW is a bit lacking in the &quot;good C99 reference&quot; department, I've decided to start out a section dedicated to it [[C Programming/C99 Reference|here]]. Thoughts? [[User:Mecanismo|Mecanismo]] ([[User talk:Mecanismo|talk]]) 18:40, 12 February 2008 (UTC)

:I noted the same thing as [[User:Mecanismo|Mecanismo]].  I have started filling in the gaps, starting with assert.h/assert().  This is my first attempt at wiki-ing, so if anyone has any comments on what I have done so far (especially layout), let me know. [[User:Electrobadger|Electrobadger]] ([[User talk:Electrobadger|talk]]) 22:31, 13 June 2008 (UTC)

== Something to consider ==

I just noticed, this book is a bit misleading. If you look at the Programming Bookshelf it says it's 50% completed, but it doesn't say so in any place in the book itself.

== Formatting of Examples in the PDF Version ==

The examples in the PDF version use indented paragraphs rather than tab/space characters, so that when copy-pasted to a text editor you lose the formatting.

For example, the following code:
&lt;code&gt;

 #include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
 
 int main(void) {
    printf(&quot;Hello, world!\n&quot;);
    return 0;
 }
&lt;/code&gt;

when copied from the on-line or print version, pastes OK into a text editor.

However, if you copy-paste from the PDF file, you get:
&lt;code&gt;

 #include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
 
 int main(void) {
 printf(&quot;Hello, world!\n&quot;);
 return 0;
 }
&lt;/code&gt;

How can this be fixed?

--[[User:Rickjpelleg|Rickjpelleg]] ([[User talk:Rickjpelleg|talk]]) 19:43, 27 November 2008 (UTC)

== another freely available C programming book ==

&quot;The C Book, second edition by Mike Banahan, Declan Brady and Mark Doran, originally published by Addison Wesley in 1991. This version is made freely available.&quot; http://publications.gbdirect.co.uk/c_book/

Is there anything we need to do before copying-and-pasting that entire book into this Wikibook?
--[[User:DavidCary|DavidCary]] ([[User talk:DavidCary|talk]]) 02:38, 22 March 2009 (UTC)

:I had noticed it before but thought that it was somehow problematic since it would involve checking that it was up-to-date and the license gives the impression that a 3rd party is licensing a work that it doesn't hold the rights of &quot;this online version and derived works is copyright Mike Banahan&quot;.
:The license text is a bit convoluted and there wouldn't be any problem if the license was granted directly by Mike Banahan, and &quot;The online version was prepared with the assistance of some Perl scripts written by Mike Banahan...&quot; doesn't directly imply the granting of those rights.
:You can try to get a clearer statement from the site (it has that content up from sometime now) or from Mike Banahan, I have taken similar steps successfully before.    --[[User:Panic2k4|Panic]] ([[User talk:Panic2k4|talk]]) 03:07, 22 March 2009 (UTC)

== Yet another book on C ==

Ever heard of &quot;Think Pyhton&quot;? There's a book with the same structure called &quot;Think C&quot;, and because it is published by Green Tea press it's under the GNU Free Document License. It would be great if we could add it here. &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[w:Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:148.201.1.205|148.201.1.205]] ([[User talk:148.201.1.205|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/148.201.1.205|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

: That is a good idea. I couldn't locate the book on the [http://www.greenteapress.com/ Green Tea Press] website though. Also the publisher or authors would need to grant permission for licensing under CC-BY-SA too. --&lt;span style=&quot;font: bold 10pt 'courier new', comic, sans, ms;&quot;&gt;[[User:Darklama|&lt;font color=&quot;midnightblue&quot;&gt;dark&lt;/font&gt;]][[User_talk:Darklama|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;lama&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 16:12, 28 January 2011 (UTC)

== Great book ==

Thanks very much for the clear explanation.
Good clarity is rare.
I've learnt a lot in a very short time!  {{unsigned|Johann.mahne|before 08:10, 5 February 2012‎}}

== Completed Status ==

In comparison to some of the other featured and &quot;completed&quot; books ([[Ada Programming]], [[Non-Programmer's Tutorial for Python 2.6|Python]], [[Haskell]], [[Write_Yourself_a_Scheme_in_48_Hours|Scheme in 48 Hours]]), this one in particular seems to be lacking significantly. It could use a large amount of restructuring, a consistent style across the book, full coverage of topics, exercises, standardizing the experience level of the reader across the book, etc. etc. Not that it isn't a great book so far, but I think it could be much more with some more work. Thoughts on removing the completed tag and beginning a restructure? [[User:CharmlessCoin|CharmlessCoin]] ([[User talk:CharmlessCoin|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/CharmlessCoin|contribs]]) 04:34, 26 February 2013 (UTC)

== list of standard library header files ==

: Which section of this book is the best for the list of standard library header files?
: I see a list of standard library header files at [[C Programming/Reference Tables]], [[C_Programming/Standard_libraries]], [[C Programming/C Reference/List of C functions]], and [[C Programming/C Reference]].
: If, for pedagogical reasons, a student reading through a printed copy of this book really needs that list repeated in various sections,
: would it be OK if someone made a template for that list?
: (Templates for text that is repeated in various parts of this book are listed at [[:category:C Programming/Templates]]).
: --[[User:DavidCary|DavidCary]] ([[User talk:DavidCary|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/DavidCary|contribs]]) 06:45, 5 March 2013 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>tiot8bkc4a5m376wycuzopof84iklsx</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Wikiversity</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>762</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1895779</id>
      <parentid>1202693</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-07-20T16:09:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>{{rfd-survived}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{rfd-survived}}

==Image Giant_Impact.jpg must be deleted ==
The image Giant_Impact.jpg used in Wikiversity must be deleted because of copyright violation. Please use instead of this another one.

== Collaboration ==

Please go to [http://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Talk:Wikiversity the Meta-Wiki] for discussions that involve the current formal proposal to make wikiversity an approved and independent wikimedia foundation project.

== Expansion ==
As we've all noticed, wikiversity is depressingly small. Why haven't student wikipedists asked their professors/teachers to come and contribute?
:That's a great idea, I'll do that as soon as I get back in school. The thing is, not all teachers are computer geeks like we are and may not want to :p --[[User:Tyciol|Tyciol]] 20:49, 30 January 2006 (UTC)
::Possibly they are waiting for a stable namespace and URL? Personally I get the impression only brilliant prose, the best of the best of the best etc. is wanted for unique &lt;b&gt;Textbooks only!&lt;/b&gt;  The subset of students having unpublished polished textbooks lying around idle is possibly vanishingly small.  Not everyone will ignore idiotic rules (for Wikiversity, not necessarily Wikibooks) while waiting for them to change. The current structure makes Wikiversity look subordinate to Wikibooks to anyone not familiar with the ongoing community sagas.  Who is going to add ugly incomplete personal notes to use as a starting substrate when anything but the best of the best textbooks must be deleted unless the author intends to complete the project in the nearterm?  I have attempted to start addressing this problem (as I currently percieve it) at policy here[http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Wikiversity:Productive_Forking_and_Tailoring_is_Encouraged], others insights welcome!  Let's have a good old fashioned discussion, debate, edit war, whatever sometime. [[User:70.110.35.3|70.110.35.3]] 01:13, 3 March 2006 (UTC)

== Another Idea ==

It would make sense, as to seperate wikiversity from wikibooks, to maybe have some audio or even video lectures in the course-work.  Feedback?  [[User:Fephisto|Fephisto]]
A very good idea indeed ... I have been thinking of creating/finding a linux livecd with tools for recording video and/or sound - that could be used by teachers to contribute with recorded lectures.
[[User:R.randal|R.Randal]]

== Page naming ==

Moved from /Test - [[User:Aya|Aya]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Aya|T]]&amp;nbsp;[[Special:Contributions/Aya|C]]&lt;/sup&gt; 15:42, 3 August 2005 (UTC)

As soon as there is a prominent link to [[Wikibooks:Wikiversity]] this page can replace the existing redirect there. [[User:Akagu|Akagu]] 14:42, 19 May 2004 (UTC)

I began to move it, but... Shall we place the main page in [[Wikibooks:Wikiversity]] or in [[Wikiversity]]?. I think it is better the second option, if not it looks like Wikiversity is a wikibook, or like Wikiversity is a project of wikibooks. But, actually, they do work with a different scope. --[[User:Javier Carro|Javier Carro]] 18:12, 19 May 2004 (UTC)

:How about just Wikiversity?  Instead of Wikibooks:Wikiversity.  Because the background color becomes yellow if it is Wikibooks:Wikiversity.  I'll go ahead and change it, but feel free to change it back if you like.

:It´s much better, personally, I like it more like that :) thank you--[[User:Javier Carro|Javier Carro]] 20:55, 19 May 2004 (UTC)

==New idea: WikiNotes==
See my posting at the Village Pump for proposals in wikipedia or check out the link below: 

[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WikiNotesBrainstorm WikiNotes Brainstormin'!]

=([[User:Yosofun|Yosofun]] 06:44, 25 Mar 2005 (UTC))

== Wikimania! ==
Registration for Wikimania, the first international Wikimedia conference, is [http://wikimania.wikimedia.org now open].  It will be brilliant fun.  Everyone is invited to join the event this summer... attendees from Wikiversity in particular will be welcome.

See also the [[m:Call_for_papers|call for papers]]; propose sessions on how to use wikis for education, and pass this announcement on to others interested in education.

== Research community ==

Since revision as of 16:47, 8 Apr 2005 wikiversity is no longer a research community.
What are the intentions behind this? [[User:84.160.197.225|84.160.197.225]] 09:20, 9 Apr 2005 (UTC)

:Sorry, my mistake, left word the important &quot;research&quot; out in edit merge of the two &quot;about wikiversity&quot; paragraphs! Could you please add back any other appropriate bits I might have missed? [[User:Makiaea|makiaea]] 20:34, 10 Apr 2005 (UTC)

== An Idea ==

I almost hate to suggest this, but I wonder if it's time for a sort of governing body of Wikiversity.  I agree it sounds sort of stupid, and I realize the idea is to move away from the traditional format, however, I feel like there's no direction.  There's no vision, it seems, and I feel that perhaps forming even a temporary leadership body to the entire Wikiversity might not be a terrible idea.  Although it maybe, but I wanted to share it.  [[User:Atrivedi|Atrivedi]]
:People do need to be told the difference between a book and a university course. It needs to be made clear that these things are not text books, that is covered by other wikis. One of the main problems, is that as of yet, there are no examples. [[User:Abc123|Abc123]].

==Faculty Patrons==
[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User_talk:Kils/Virtual_University please add here]

==Wikiversity's collapse==
Sadly, I think that the Wikimedia community has finally taken on a project too big for itself.  This project has collapsed.  There is little or no activity, and it is stalled as a Wikibooks module (that's how it operates technically anyway).  I feel like its time to either end this project, or rethink it entirely.  I think it has lost direction and is simply drawing away from Wikibooks in its present form.--[[User:Naryathegreat|Naryathegreat]]|[[User talk:Naryathegreat|(talk)]] 21:47, 24 Apr 2005 (UTC)

:I believe the same to be true of the traditional University. [[User:Downchuck|Downchuck]] 05:41, 10 July 2005 (UTC)

:Wikiversity will find its feet. What is really needs is students, and it takes a while for ideas to spread. The other thing, is that people are expecting a completed site straight away. Apart from the fact that Wikiversity will never be &quot;completed&quot;, everyone is more than happy to benefit from free things - but few people seem to be contributing. Until everyone starts to contribute just a little bit, it will be hard to see significant changes in the university.[[User:Abc123|Abc123]].

:I wouldn't give up on this so easily. I know a few folks who would most likely be interested in a project like this, myself included.  In my opinion, wikiversity has the potential to be very successful. It is a brilliant idea. One of its  failures at the moment is that nobody seems to know it exists. I've been looking things up on wikipedia on an almost daily basis for months now, and I'd never even heard of wikiversity until earlier today. When I asked a few of my online friends (who also use wikipedia regularly) if they had heard of the wikiversity project they told me that they didn't know anything about it, or indeed any of wikipedia's &quot;sister&quot; sites.  I myself would love to become a student of some of the subjects offered here in wikiversity, and I urge the people involved not to give up on it. I feel it is only a matter of time before more people, students and teachers alike, become interested in this project and help to develop it. --[[User:CHanratty|Strummer]] 02:19, August 2, 2005 (UTC)

::I agree! I for one think Wikiversity is an AMAZING resource, but it was difficult to find. Like [[User:CHanratty|Strummer]], I have been using Wikipedia for a long time and just recently discovered Wikiversity last night. I've been hooked since! I think it's a brilliant idea and has the potential to do truly brilliant things for the world.  --[[User:Endless melee|Endless Melee]] 12:00pm July 13, 2006

::I also agree! I just found out about this program an hour ago and I'm incredibly excited about it.  I really am excited that I have a place not only to hone my skills as a teacher but also as a writer.  I think we just need to find a way to get the name out there so people will want to come and learn.  I really don't think we should focus all to much on becoming an &quot;accredited university&quot; so much as just offering great, free, and accessible information to the public. I wonder how long it took the wikipedia to get to the point its at. I imagine it took a bit of time for it to get off the ground at first, but look where it is now! Now just imagine seamless integration of the Wikipedia and the Wikiversity and all the other wikimedia out there with not only articles and wikibooks, but lessons on how to put this information to use. To me the possibilities are exhilarating. --[[User:Jechasteen|Jechasteen]] 23:32, 27 July 2006 (UTC)

== A Great Idea ==

Sure there isn't much content as I have been surfing around looking at Wikiversity project. But here is the thing imagine a world that is no longer bound by credentialism, and the high price of a university education! A place where access to a higher education is free, to me however stalled it is a begining.  - Marlin --[[User:66.82.9.65|66.82.9.65]] 12:43, 11 Jun 2005 (UTC)

== Rethinking the project ==

I have a lot ideas for a revisioning of the project. It would give it a very different focus and way of doing things, but I think it would work really well. My question is though, is something that drastic needed here? There's a lot of not very optimistic comments on this page, but I'm just wondering how accurate it all is. Is the project really stalled? Or just slow going? If it is stalled, I'd love to start trying to share my ideas here. [[User:Zach Alexander|Zach]] [[User_talk:Zach Alexander|(talk)]] 23:20, 12 Jun 2005 (UTC)

Wikiversity sounds like a very ambitious idea. But I don't think it'll kick-off without people actually being able to &quot;graduate&quot; from it.

:: there are plenty of &quot;self taught&quot; people who would be happy for some quality, free textbooks.

== Other classes ==

It is great that wikiversity has an academic focus, orienting itself around different subjects like a university has departments, but it was cool if there was just one section that had eclectic topics like might be offered at the learning annex, classes teaching you how to cook, sew, and beat the legend of zelda.

:Funny you should bring Zelda up, I'd been thinking about that of late. Not about playing the games themselves, but imagine taking a course about the storylines and timeline theories and endings and mangas and whatnot, just as you would with any literary work. Could be fascinating.

:The other ideas could also be taught very easily with illustrations and maybe even a (live?) video feed to give Graham Kerr a run for his money!

:As for gaming, I doubt you could teach that better than a FAQ/Walkthrough does, unless you used webcams or a modified emulator with netplay support or something so you could watch what the player was doing wrong. But it's an interesting idea that will no doubt develop given time.

:I envision great things for Wikiversity, but I'm too busy with my real-world university study to start or participate in a course myself. But that doesn't mean I'm powerless, I will be here to give WV a good kick in the backside every few months to make sure it gets off the ground! [[User:Master Thief Garrett|Master Thief Garrett]] 06:05, 22 Jun 2005 (UTC)

== Provisional Opening ==

It seems what this project lacks most is intiative. I've been building up the School of History and am considering opening that department for business by offering an experimental course on a topic that I am familiar with, and seeing whether people enroll. It will be a first attempt at Wikiversity style course and will provie ''some'' imitatable model that others can imitate and expand on. The topic is [[Wikiversity:The Great War and Versailles|The Great War and Versailles]].

--[[User:Polizano|Polizano]] 15:42, 17 June 2005 (EST)

Preparing courses (for Wikiversity) and writing content (as for Wikibooks) are two entirely different kinds of creative effort. Although I am new to the Wiki family, I would venture to suggest that Wikiversity isn't working   because potential contributers are assuming they have to provide textbook-type content as well as pedagogical support material -- study guides, PowerPoints, quizzes, etc.  Let Wikibooks provide the content and Wikiversity provide the curricular material.


== Initiative? ==

I've had this idea in my head for a while but someone should see if there are any problems with this approach. I've always held that the best way to remember something or &quot;prove&quot; that you've learned something is if you are able to teach it to someone else. Now, I will be taking courses (Psych, Communications, Political Science, Computer Science) next year at a university, and I thought Wikiversity could be a very useful tool, not just for myself but for others. I wouldn't know about books but class material from real lectures could be posted as soon as  I take them. I don't know if there is copyright information that is to be considered, not only for the information but also the &quot;style&quot; of teaching that certain professors use. I plan to remain anonymous throughout this process and plan to do the posting very thoroughly, mainly for my own sake. Another factor is that I am also a student, NOT a professor or an authority on the subject. I merely wish to transfer the  knowledge I gain at university and by doing so, use wikiversity as a study tool. Also I'll help others who wish to gain this information without the big bucks of a college education. I personally think information should be free. Any complaints?

:That's pretty much what it's all about. As long as you are prett y confident you are making sense, then you can't be too far away from the truth! One thing to note though: Be sure not to reproduce Wikipedia or Wikibooks material in Wikiversity. You don't want to just double up on material already written. [[User:Abc123|Abc123]].

== Questions ==
I really love the idea of Wikiversity, I've been trying to use online resources like MIT Open Courseware that just doesn't cut it due to the lack of a book and discussion boards for most subjects.  Are there any active classes going on?  Or a list of classes looking for TAs, or people looking for certain classes?  I'd be happy to run a class on programing or math, if people can live with me being somewhat incommunicado for September. I appologize if this is the wrong place for this, I'm not sure where the right page is.


: On a related note- one thing that struck me about the idea of classes here is the books.  They're a little sparse for textbooks.  I don't mean missing subjects, I mean they tend to have few, if any examples. Proofs are hard to come by (for the math ones) and are very terse.  You pretty much need to have some pre-existing knowledge to understand them.  Is this a design decision of the books, or just a reflection of the writing talent/time required ot make them better.  Writing a good textbook is not an easy undertaking, but its a necessity for something like a wikiversity. --[[User:Javariel|Javariel]] 21:28, 30 Jun 2005 (UTC)

::: I believe it is a reflection of the state of Wikiversity, rather than the design. First, many editors tend to try to cover a large section of material themselves. This leads to minimal content over a large area. Of course, it would make more sense to focus on a small area and do that well, before moving onto the next secion, but that is very difficult to do in practice. The other thing to remember, is that technically, Wikiversity is not the place for text books, that's Wikibooks. Wikiversity should encourage research and critical thinking, and show students where to find information. I believe that rhese two difficulties have led to the current status of Wikiversity. [[User:Abc123|Abc123]].

::: The other thing to remember is that only contributions will improve the site. If you think something is lacking, it is really up to you to improve it, or else more and more people will think that Wikiversity is failing. Good luck! [[User:Abc123|Abc123]].

:: I would like to recommend looking at the [http://www.aduni.org aduni.org] course materials as grounds for a first set of computer science courses.  I helped teach some of those courses back when they were first offered, and would be glad to help others transfer and use the materials effectively.  [[User:Sj|Sj]] 10:57, 2 Jul 2005 (UTC)


:We have no courses running at present. &quot;The Great War and the Treaty of Versailles&quot; is being planned as a test-bed course. The other courses probably would welcome more help, just look at their sections or the editing history to see who is &quot;in charge&quot;. And you're certainly welcome to write and teach a course yourself, the more the merrier! As for the month of September you could perhaps find a substitute to teach for that month. It will all work out I'm sure. :)
:The books here are intended to be comprehensive textbooks on any given subject, and indeed to accompany and accent the Wikiversity classes, but there's only so much you can do in your spare time. Certainly some more contributors would help but right now Wikipedia's getting all the attention.
:Overall, just go ahead! The moment we have something actually underway things will get going, but until that time Wikiversity is just fluffy ideas and dreams. We need some action. :) [[User:Master Thief Garrett|Master Thief Garrett]] 21:44, 30 Jun 2005 (UTC)


::Thanks for the advice, both of you.  I'm moving in September (new job in Seattle), so I've decided to forgo teaching until then, I'm not able to really estimate the amount of time I need yet.  After I'm settled, I will give it a go, I just need to decide with what.  In the meantime, I plan on following the WWI course when it starts and work on some wikibooks as a way to contribute until then.  --[[User:Javariel|Gabe Sechan]] July 6, 2005 23:21 (UTC)

== Academic Journals ==
Have their been any discussions about access to Academic Journals?
Some of the most rewarding classes I've taken have involved a professor assembling a dozen or more essays from various journals into a reading packet.
While books are easily available at low prices (with fast shipping), journals are closely guarded secrets of the Illuminati.
I'm still a student, and this isn't so much a personal concern, as a concern for those who don't have easy access to a University library system.

:Um, that's a great idea of course, but the cost involved in setting up such a deal... it would be absolutely ruinous I would imagine. Especially considering the fact that we don't have a set roll. Thousands upon thousands of users could (potentially) sign up and access journals through us so any licensing fees would be unfair in their eyes. So we'll just have to make do I'm afraid. [[User:Master Thief Garrett|Garrett]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Master Thief Garrett|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 08:41, 10 July 2005 (UTC)

::There are increasing numbers of journals with free online content. For example, [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?CMD=search&amp;DB=pmc PubMed Central] is an online archive of life sciences journal with free access to the full text of articles (note: some journals delay free access to recently published articles). Also, it is now possible to start new [http://academia.wikicities.com/wiki/Main_Page peer-reviewed academic journals in wiki format]. Wikiversity could start its own wiki journals. --[[User:JWSchmidt|JWSurf]] 12:30, 10 July 2005 (UTC)

:::Oh, OK, that's a good idea. Yes there are some around but I've found very few. Unfortunately some publishers offer free back issues of their magazines/journals then change their minds, for example the ''Viking Heritage Magazine'' has taken down the PDFs of their back issues --that's strange, I can still access the orphaned download page and its files. Hm.

:::That's interesting about that Journals wiki, I was just going to host everything I wrote here, but I'll certainly take a look at that. Sounds very interesting. I just hope something actually gets done, it's hard work to write a journal... [[User:Master Thief Garrett|Garrett]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Master Thief Garrett|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 22:23, 10 July 2005 (UTC)

:::UPDATE: Well they say if you want something done right you've got to do it yourself! There are big gaps in the subjects covered at the [academia.wikicities.com/wiki/Main_Page Academic Publishing Wiki] so I've begun turning some of my old university essays into journal articles to pad things out!

:::As for Wikiversity starting journals, for now I think it would be better to keep everything at the Academic Publishing Wiki. They (we?) are working on guidelines for journal creation and improvement, and it would make more sense to let everything be under their jurisdiction for now.

::: Any more help with creating journal content over there would be greatly appreciated, even if you've just got an essay or two to wikify. [[User:Master Thief Garrett|Garrett]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Master Thief Garrett|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 22:54, 14 July 2005 (UTC)

::I suppose one negative about academic journals is that they are purely individual, rather than wiki orientated. It would be original thought. Personally, I don't have a problem with that, but may conflict with what a wiki is. Anyone with a better understanding of wiki conventions have an opinion? [[User:Abc123|Abc123]].

:::Actually I already have plans for some ''truly'' wiki journal articles. A topic will be selected, some point(s) it has to illustrate will be identified (although those too could adapt), and it will grow organically from there with the community controlling its growth and focus. Five years ago the idea of a from-scratch encyclopedia was laughable, so why should journals be different? [[User:Master Thief Garrett|Garrett]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Master Thief Garrett|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 23:32, 15 July 2005 (UTC)

::::Interesting. It just seems to me that an academic journal's purpose is to put forward/explain new ideas and research. That wouldn't fit with Wikibooks. Then again, the more I think about it, if there was a pure Wikijournal site, the rules could be a little different. [[User:Abc123|Abc123]]

::::My initial response is that writing journal articles in true wiki format would be difficult to control (in the scientific sense of the word). It would likely require one person or entity to carry out experiments in a single controlled environment. Just sayin'. - [[User:RealGrouchy|RealGrouchy]] 03:08, 27 September 2005 (UTC)

== Enrollment ==

One of the things you should consider doing is making it really, really easy to enroll.  I would like to enroll in the School of Economics.  I searched for about an hour for a way to do this, but never did find a way.

Put a link right near the top of the Wikiversity home page; &gt;&gt;&gt;ENROLMENT&lt;&lt;&lt;.  I'm not saying there isn't a way, but I didn't find it.  Make it simple for simple people like me.  Wilbur Wilson  wilsonw@harbornet.com

:There's no such thing as enrolling into Wikiversity. There are no timetabled classes, or even classes etc. [[User:Abc123|Abc123]]

:The problem is that no classes are running except The Great War and Versailles. THAT is why you can't find anywhere to sign up, because nothing's running yet. [[User:Master Thief Garrett|Garrett]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Master Thief Garrett|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 05:05, 17 July 2005 (UTC)

== Sister Project ==

Hi - I'm posting via my IP (I'm User:Manning Bartlett from the 'pedia). I think the Wikiversity is one of the coolest things I've seen. The problem is - I'd never heard of it until I stumbled in by accident. If this thing was a sister project (as per Wiktionary, Wikinews, etc) you'd have a lot more interest/traffic. Have you approached Jimbo?

:We already ''are'' a sister project (we were spawned on Meta), but we haven't got anything to show for our work yet (a single class running is not very impressive) so until such time as we get going we're going to be invisible I suppose. Hmmm... [[User:Master Thief Garrett|Garrett]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Master Thief Garrett|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 00:02, 19 July 2005 (UTC)

:: Well there you go. The Wikiversity is not listed as a sister project in anyplace **obvious** (like on Wikipedia's main page). A real shame. - Manning (User:Manning Bartlett at the 'pedia).

:::In a sense Wikiversity is a ''sister project'', but it's obviously not a fully-fledged one with its own users, admins, wiki and domain name. Instead it is ''hosted'' at Wikibooks. Personally, I'm doubtful we will separate from Wikibooks ever, as the projects have so much in common. But there seems a reasonable consensus that we need to grow a lot before separation will even be considered. 

:::Unfortunately, as the discussion above suggests, there's a chicken and egg situation here. We won't grow very fast until we are more visible, and we won't be more visible until we grow. That's a shame perhaps, but it's not hopeless. It's just possible we are still growing, slowly. But the graph is so noisy it's a bit hard to tell. [[User:Andrewa|Andrewa]] 09:39, 23 July 2005 (UTC)

::::My vote is to wait before we show ourselves to the world. We need to have a few example courses, from which others can set an example. There needs to be an emphasis that Wikiversity is not intended to reproduce material from other sources, but aid in learning that material. I think once we get a few example courses - there will be more cohesion, a greater sense of purpose, and then we can open Wikiversity up to the powers that be for &quot;Sisterhood&quot;. [[User:Abc123|Abc123]].

== Classes without teachers? ==

A friend and I have been planning a group-based teach-yourself style of a &quot;course&quot;.  We've been floundering around trying to find an acceptable way for online collaboration between ourselves and others that we either recruit or stumble across our page.  When I found wikiversity, I thought this might be a good place to do that.  I'm still really new to it and have little to no idea as to how to actually start up a normal class let-alone one that might not fit within the normal vision for this site.

In theory, this methodology would rely more heavily on blogging and open discussion rather than official reference material (but will likely link to wikibooks and other more official course material).  Is this idea compatible enough with the wikiversity vision?  If so, I'll need some instructions on how to get started. [[User:jhouse|jhouse]]

:Sounds fine. As for getting started, um, we haven't really laid anything out. What I think you need to do is first create a hubt with info about the class, a class list, etc. like [[Wikiversity:The Great War and Versailles]] has.
:You should also start a series of pages for each &quot;subject&quot;. Merely supply that &quot;day&quot;'s study topic etc. at the top and let people edit and discuss.
:Any other questions? Ask away. :) [[User:Master Thief Garrett|Garrett]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Master Thief Garrett|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 01:30, 22 July 2005 (UTC)

I've created an initial attempt [[User:jhouse|jhouse]].  Comments Are Welcome - [[Wikiversity:Study_Group_For_Relativity|Relativity Study Group]]

== Mapping real world-&gt;wiki learning ==

I've been giving some thought lately on what helped to learn in the real world, and how that could be ported to the wiki world.  The idea being that any successful way of teaching via wiki ought to support as many of them as possible, in addition to any wiki-specific methods we can come up with.  Comments on the feasibility and additions to the list are welcome.  Especially ways to use the wiki that don't work in normal school, lets find a way to use our unique points to an advantage.

How I found I learned in school, in no particular order:

#Textbook.   Obviously here we have a wiki book

#Lectures.  Should be more informational, dive down into a subtopic of a book.  Example heavy.  Almost a second wikibook on the topic, in small 1 hour chunks.  Audio, video, or slideshow a helpful addition here?
#Office hours.  Hard to wiki-ize, as the point of office hours is being able to talk to an authority on the subject.  Perhaps IRC sessions, with transcripts wiki-ized?  FOr that matter, IRC lectures may be useful too.
#Homework.  Assignments uploaded to wiki, and commented on by teachers.  Need some system where people can upload to unique pages so they don't overwrite each other.
#newsgroups (hey, my school had them and they helped)-  a wiki forum, policed to keep it on topic.  Hopefully students and teachers will comment on questions
#discussion with/working with other students-  harder to do, provide ways for people studying the material to talk and collaborate.  The wikiboard idea will help, so will the idea below.  A page where you can people currently studying a topic can post their emails to discuss issues out of band may help too.

In addition, I was thinking of things a wiki can do uniquely

#Large projects.  Make a project that to an equivalent level student would take 100s of hours, but is breakable into parts.  Let people do parts via wiki, and work together to complete the whole thing.  For example, a programming course for novices could have them write a large program-  a web browser maybe.   We could design the framework and break it down into chunks, and the students could write the individual chunks.  The large project would need to be retired ocassionally, so it doesn't degrade to people copying the old version.

After additional thought-  the last idea isn't just for large projects.  In place of/in addition to homework, you could sprinkle smaller, less ambitious projects throughout.



Breaking it down to what needs to be done, there are 3 roles-  student, teacher, course designer.  

Course designer:  writes wikibook, writes lectures, designs homework or big projects.  Requires full knowledge of the subject and great organizational and teaching skills.  Almost needs to be 1 person or a small, tight group, to keep everything focused.  If the school itself (such as the school of math, or school of CS) has a goal for each course, the course designer needs to be in sych with the overall designer.

Teacher: runs office hours, looks over homework and advises student, monitors newsgroup, monitors and advises on large projects.  Requires a lot of knowledge of the subject and good teaching skills.  Can be a large number of people, although pairing people up to a teacher may be helpful.  Does not need to be the one designing anything although they may refine things, they are meant to help teach established material.

student: responsible for learning it all :)

The distinction between course designer and teacher is important-  a designer needs most of the skills of a teacher, and its own subset.  By separating the two roles, you can have the designer move on and design more material, rather than merely rehash things.  Once the base material is completed, its much easier to plug someone in to continue teaching it.


I know some of these require a lot of teacher interaction that may seem counter to a normal wiki.  This is on purpose.  I have taught internet courses before (I TAed them in college), and I found the hardest part was keeping people working, even when they were paying for the class.  The reason for this interaction is to keep students involved and on track.  Without something to do so, we'll see a lot of people read one or two lessons, and never come back.  If the true goal is to teach the subject, we want them engaged.

--[[User:Javariel|Gabe Sechan]] 21:24, July 25, 2005 (UTC)


:That sounds like a reasonable collection of requirements.  My college experience had some teachers as the book writer/lecture planner with potentially little teaching ability, and the TA's grading homework and trying to give real-world explanations.  Of course, TA's are really just students a bit further than those in the class.
:I think the question really becomes &quot;How do we develop a culture such that past students help out new students in ways similar to how they were helped?&quot;.  I think it's a tough thing to develop that kind of culture on a website, especially when there's an attendence problem.  [[User:jhouse|jhouse]]

::Classes at MIT traditionally have a one-hour lecture a few times a week with up to a few hundred people in it, and then a one-hour recitation section, where you meet with a TA and 20-30 other students and ask questions and grind through problems.  At least one class has put the lecture up on the web instead, in video format.  This precludes the ability to interrupt and ask questions, but that's what recitation section is for, anyway.  It also makes it more convenient to see lecture and easier to catch up if you miss one.  In some classes, the lectures and the textbook are very different - almost complementary.  In others, they present the same material, and you can choose how you'd like it presented.

::As for communication channels, it's probably best to concentrate content.  That is, you shouldn't have a newsgroup, an e-mail list, and a wiki talk page all for the same class.  There should be one synchronous channel (IRC would work, certainly, and transcripts would be great, for future reference, and for those who miss class), and one asynchronous channel.  (I'd have to think about which might be best, but a LiquidThreads-enabled wiki might be nice.  And experience will tell.)

::In the short term, a good goal might be to actually partner with existing academic institutions.  I'm there are professors and TAs out there who would be able to make good use of Wikiversity content or collaboration mechanisms.  My guess is that there's just a lot of work to do before there's enough quality content to fill an entire class.  -- [[User:Beland|Beland]] 02:44, 28 July 2005 (UTC)

:: My friend Jason House ([[User:jhouse|jhouse]]) and I ([[User:Gonzosm|Gonzo]]) have started to put together a study group for Relativity ([[Wikiversity:Study_Group_For_Relativity|study group course on relativity]]), and we have a very simple plan: get a group of people together to focus on a topic, choose a book, and attempt to explain the book to each other via Wikiversity.  In order to actually learn you have to read the book, contribute to the wikipage, read peoples' feedback, rinse and repeat.  Jason and I call each other reguarly, and that of course would also be an option for future endeavors.  We may have chosen this format because there was no existing format, but there is so little involvement right now that things have to stay simple (KISS).

::The above essay mapping traditional training/educational processes is an excellent beginning.  I think it is important to keep in mind that initially the wikiversity will probably be serving nontraditional adult students (possibly with a lot of exposure or previous experience now formalizing their complete understanding of a subject or brushing up for more advanced impending work or in pursuit of specific goals) and traditional students &lt;b&gt;augmenting&lt;/b&gt; their studies in traditional environments.  We need to acknowledge and service the special requirements of interacting asynchronously, sporadically, on demand, on topic, with each individual student by allowing other students to firm up their understanding by helping less advanced students.  Personally I would not count on professional experts as teachers or instructors.  People with these qualifications have busy lives and careers.  When they get overloaded typically they will choose to impact volunteer activities at wikiversity rather than their family or professional career.  Thus in this forum and format they also will be drop in unreliable non realtime assets.  However, do not despair, every bit of time they manage to squeeze into their busy schedules can serve future students the second the student finds the correct link to the correct question or discussion regarding a matter he/she is studying or reviewing.  Development will be sporadic.  Delivery of properly mapped and structured material can be instantaneous to new study groups that are now ready by self selection (link mapping, quiz perequisites, browsing, etc.) for the specific material.  Notice that most of the material we need is already availalbe online, is being mapped by wikibooks, wikipedia, etc.  Our true challenge is to find presentation and format methods suited to the online tools available and supportable by the selected technology infrastructure.  It may be appropriate to explore the recent advances in peer to peer browser technology under development by the originator of freenet or mnet, gnunet, BOINC, oceanstore, and other low end grid components to enable each participant to help scale the delivery infrastructure as they participate. [[User:Lazyquasar|Lazyquasar]] 19:00, 23 November 2005 (UTC)

== My thoughts on the project ==

First of all, I've noticed that the German version of Wikiversity seems to have its own wiki already at de.wikiversity.org. Since this would seem to indicate it's an official Wikimedia-supported project, perhaps we should make some noises at [[m:Requests for new languages]] to get an equivalent wiki for en.wikiversity.org? I've added a request at [[m:Requests for new languages#Requests for new Wikiversity languages]], but we need at least 5 people to take on the project, help build it up, and administer it. Be aware that if the wiki becomes inactive, it may get shut down, so there may be an advantage in leaving it here.

Secondly, we seem to be suffering again from another case of badly-defined scope. Some of the existent 'schools' seem more like a book than a structured course. Books are generally an integral part of courses, but we really don't want to be duplicating the role of Wikibooks on another project, else we'll end up having endless debates as to what goes where.

What I think might be a good idea is to clearly separate the two by introducing official course textbooks for each course. The textbooks would be hosted at Wikibooks (obviously), while the Wikiversity project would be confined to things like:

* Course syllabus (The scope of the course, and what topics it intends to cover. This should be kept brief to avoid duplicating the material in course textbooks.)
* Course structure (How is the learning divided up into sessions/classes/lectures/etc.)
* Links to official course textbooks (It's important that this is made highly visible, to ensure that newbie Wikiversity editors don't end up duplicating the functionality of the textbook)
* Details of practical experiments or other things which might be inappropriate for a theory textbook (We want to keep the existing Wikibooks generic enough that they can be used as either a course text, or as an independent book for other interested parties.)
* Anything else? (suggestions wanted)

::New technology.  There is a lot of interest in the free/open source community at large as well as academia in scalable peer based grid components.  There are ways to structure study groups such that a lot of the information should remain on the student's private network but be made available to trusted associates.  Many of these students are going to be working on potentially lucrative proprietary implementations of the technology or material they are studying.  They naturally would like this material protected and available only legitimate members of their virtual organization doing the R&amp;D or considering startup or other commerical exploitation. [[User:Lazyquasar|Lazyquasar]] 19:24, 23 November 2005 (UTC)

The first thing to do when designing a new Wikiversity school ought to be writing the syllabus. Without this, it will be difficult to tell where one school ends, and the next begins.

::I disagree.  First thing is to find some students to achieve consensus on what they intend to study and how they would like to go about it. [[User:Lazyquasar|Lazyquasar]] 19:24, 23 November 2005 (UTC)
:::I think there should be a prominent paragraph on the main Wikiversity page that discusses what a  Wikiversity student is. In my view, a Wikiversity student should be an active Wikiversity editor. Wikiversity students and teachers should be [http://collaboration.wikicities.com/wiki/Wikiversity#Collaborative_learning collaborators] in Wikimedia projects. These could be [http://education.wikicities.com/wiki/Wikiversity#Wikiversity_Core_Courses_Initiative existing projects] (such as Wikipedia) or new learning projects within Wikiversity oriented around the needs of particular students. New learning projects could start as new student-created pages attached to existing courses or as new student-created learning project pages where students describe their learning goals. --[[User:JWSchmidt|JWSurf]] 16:19, 26 November 2005 (UTC)

For some courses there are already extensive Wikibooks on the subject (e.g. [[Physics]]), so we ought to take this into account. For courses which don't have such a textbook (please check thoroughly. I'm constantly finding many great texts hidden away at Wikibooks), I'd suggest beginning by writing such a text. Be sure to include textbook theory modules on everything covered in the course syllabus. This may require you to expand on existing Wikibooks to make them compliant, but it's easier than starting from scratch.

Comments? - [[User:Aya|Aya]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Aya|T]]&amp;nbsp;[[Special:Contributions/Aya|C]]&lt;/sup&gt; 18:09, 29 July 2005 (UTC)

*I think it is premature to transwiki Wikiversity over to another server yet, as I don't see much activity here.  Certainly not substantial course work.  Most of the discussion about what is going to happen with Wikiversity is also happening on Meta, which is IMHO the completely wrong place to put it, as comments like yours here on Wikibooks are not getting to the full audience that may be involved in setting up the project on a seperate server.  Better integration between Wikibooks and a future English Wikiversity can and should happen, and in particular a Wikibook should be completed and available as a textbook before Wikiversity gets &quot;turned on&quot;.

:This is an &quot;official Wikimedia Project&quot; so far as any can be that isn't on its own server.  To call it a crazy new user project run amock is depreciating the efforts of many users who have tried to contribute to this project so far.  That the German effort is better organized than the English one is more a surprise, but that doesn't mean we have to follow lock-step in their lead either. --[[User:Robert Horning|Rob Horning]] 05:01, 4 August 2005 (UTC)

==Just When I Thought I Was Out...==
...you folks manage to pull me back in!  I'm going to do my best to start putting the energy back into the [[Wikiversity:School of Literature and English Studies|School of Literature and English Studies]] and see if I can't get some courses better designed.  I had started some creative writing courses and even had one guy who sent me some poetry! I've added writers/poets to some of the classes I have in the Grad. area.  I was out, but I'm excited again, seeing how others seem to be excited and working as well!  [[User:Atrivedi|Atrivedi]]

==Protection==
Despite claims to the contrary, [[Wikiversity]] was certainly '''not''' protected at the advice of the Wikimedia Foundation. 

Perhaps it was advised by one member of that foundation, but other Board members were not consulted. I am disgusted this approach would be taken with no consensus from the community. 

Wikiversity has been running for a long time on Wikibooks and I see no agreement whatsoever for it to be suddenly shut down like this. 

Protection is a defense against vandalism, not a way of expressing one person's point of view on whether or not a sub-project of Wikibooks should exist. Please remove the misleading statements about protection and explain why you ever thought the Foundation would propose such an awful measure on a popular set of pages like Wikiversity. [[User:Angela|Angela]] 03:00, 4 August 2005 (UTC)

: You are correct in that not all the board members were consulted. I apologize for this accidentally misleading use of language, and I have re-worded the page accordingly. You have evidently not been following the discussions on Meta, but to be fair, it's difficult to find anything on that site, so a bit of background might help.

: I also believe the Wikiversity project has great potential, which is why I made a request in [[m:Requests for new languages]] (now at [[m:Talk:Requests for new languages#Requests for new Wikiversity languages]]) to get it its own wiki at en.wikiversity.org (similar to one existent at de.wikiversity.org). If you read that section, you will find that I was refused due it being decided that the project was not official, which kinda annoyed me.

: Having ascertained its status, I then came to the conclusion that the Wikiversity project was in violation of Wikibooks policy as decided by its community (we are not a free-content provider for pet-projects not approved by the Foundation AND more fundamentally, we are trying to build open-content textbooks, not university courses), so I inquired on #wikimedia whether I should perhaps delete the content, or protect it. According to policy, I'm not allowed to post the logs from #wikimedia, but to be fair, you were logged onto this channel at the time, so you may have the logs yourself, but I assume I'm allowed to summarize the conversations. One of the Foundation members suggested that protecting it would be okay, so I made the edits and protected the page. I still felt that I'd get complaints, so I posted the URL into the channel to get a second opinion. When the founding member expressed his support, I left it at that.

: If you really wish to help the project, I suspect you would do more good to propose this as a new official Wikimedia project in the appropriate place, rather than complaining about myself executing policy as decided by the Foundation and the community. I will support any proposal for this project subsequently made by anybody here; in fact part of my reasoning for this protection was to persuade somebody to make it official. I was concerned that the project might never become authorized, and the poor editors here would have been wasting their time.

: The point is, this content should never have been put here in the first place. In the interim, you are also free to transwiki the project to a non-Wikimedia server if that is more suitable. - [[User:Aya|Aya]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Aya|T]]&amp;nbsp;[[Special:Contributions/Aya|C]]&lt;/sup&gt; 04:22, 4 August 2005 (UTC)

::I've seen the IRC logs and I see no evidence of Anthere saying the page should be protected. The only mention of the word protection from her was &quot;but protect information&quot; - which I take to mean [[wiktionary:protect|protect]] as in &quot;keep safe&quot; rather than deleting it, not as in lock the page and state all further pages are candidates for speedy deletion. [[User:Angela|Angela]] 04:51, 4 August 2005 (UTC)

:::Yes, that is the correct interpretation. Sorry I was unclear in what I said, which could lead to a misunderstanding. [[User:Anthere|Anthere]]

::::Ah. Sorry. Seems this was all a misunderstanding. The word 'protect' has a very specific interpretation in the context of wiki pages. I also got the impression that Jimbo's comment was made rather half-heartedly. Perhaps it's best if I ignore the conversations in the IRC channel, especially considering most of the Wikibooks community are not a party to them. I should also have been more careful considering English is not Anthere's first language (although I assure you her English is far superior to my French). I suppose at the end of the day, the opinions of individual members of the Foundation should be considered equal to those of any other members of the community. Without a clear policy on who can make policy, it's difficult to tell whose opinions matter. Hopefully this is something I can tighten up on as time progresses, to prevent other admins from making similar mistakes in the future. I'd also appreciate it if you kept the discussions here, rather than posting them on mailing lists, since not all of the community follows the mailing lists. I shall re-word the page once more. - [[User:Aya|Aya]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Aya|T]]&amp;nbsp;[[Special:Contributions/Aya|C]]&lt;/sup&gt; 18:46, 4 August 2005 (UTC)

That's correct. There's absolutely no justification for protecting this page and adding an ex cathedra announcement like this. Wikibooks is a wiki, and policies and decisions are made in consensus. Please unprotect it immediately.--[[User:Eloquence|Eloquence]] 04:12, 4 August 2005 (UTC)

: Okay. It seems as if many people have a problem with this, so I will unprotect the page. I still stick by what I've said above. I really hope someone can help make this project official. - [[User:Aya|Aya]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Aya|T]]&amp;nbsp;[[Special:Contributions/Aya|C]]&lt;/sup&gt; 04:29, 4 August 2005 (UTC)

See the section: [[#Wikiversity Re-launch]] (below).

== Changes to [[Wikiversity]] page ==

As you can see from the top of the page, I have re-worded my concerns. I would like to ask the community how they see this project evolving conceptually. - [[User:Aya|Aya]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Aya|T]]&amp;nbsp;[[Special:Contributions/Aya|C]]&lt;/sup&gt; 19:14, 4 August 2005 (UTC)

== CS school organization ==

I'm asking this here, because there was no reaction on the talk page for the school of CS.  Who is deciding the breakdown of classes and schools?  It seems a little arbitrary to me.  For example, programming is broken into a minimum of 2 schools-  CS and Infomatics.  I've been programming for 10 years and never even heard of the term infomatics.  While I can understand wanting to concentrate on theory rather than particular APIs (and agree with the point, in fact), I think that breaking down the subject with an artificial barrier like that is counterproductive.  You'll end up having to duplicate large sections of courses, and confusing the users.  In addition, a lot of the existing framework for those courses that have it are falling into the encyclopedia problem again.  It doesn't read like a course, it reads like an encyclopedia entry or textbook.

In addition to the setup found at [[Wikiversity:School_of_Computer_Science| School of CS]], we have the [[Wikiversity:CSC_Course_Catalog|CS Course Catalog]] with an entirely separate breakdown.  One which, IMO, goes too far the other way-  not enough theory, too much a &quot;learn programming in 40 days&quot; type deal.

So who decides the breakdown?  I don't want to just delete something that has obviously had a lot of work put into it.  On the other hand, we currently have 2 competing projects, neither of which is seeing a lot of activity.  And we have my ideas at [[Talk:Wikiversity:School_of_Computer_Science#Organization_comments]] that I honestly think gets a good mix of the two.  THis is a case where I think we need some organization and forethought.  I'm willing to put in time to design a general CS outline and start on courses, but we do *not* need 3 competing efforts.  

I think I'll start working on a rough draft of how I think the course outline should be on my user page (I'll add a link here when its done).  In the meantime, what do other community members think?  Especially those who worked on either fo the two other effort.

--[[User:Javariel|Gabe Sechan]] 21:23, August 4, 2005 (UTC)

My rough draft can be found [[User:Javariel|here]].

--[[User:Javariel|Gabe Sechan]] 22:09, August 4, 2005 (UTC)

:It looks excellent to me - I'd wholly support replacing whatever is there with that. [[User:Ambi|Ambi]] 02:57, 5 August 2005 (UTC)

::Your draft looks good. It obviously needs some more work to begin with, so I'd be happy to help organize and actually start the CS courses; if you need any help, drop me a message :-) --[[User:Dionyziz|Dionyziz]] 12:47, 14 October 2005 (UTC)

== Where is the Link ==

Where is the link to Wikiversity on the Wikibooks sidebar? School's out for the summer? I would suggest adding a second line to Wikibooks main page under Welcome to Wikibooks something like, Who's your teacher: [[Wikiversity]] [[User:Athrash|&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;]] &amp;#45; [[User:Athrash|Athrash]] | [[User_talk:Athrash|&lt;small&gt;{Talk)&lt;/small&gt;]] 07:09, 5 August 2005 (UTC)
: If you care to read the text at the top of the page [[Wikiversity]], and earlier comments on this page, you will notice there is currently some debate as to whether this project will continue to be hosted on this site. In the interim, I felt it wise not to blatently advertise such a contraversial page. - [[User:Aya|Aya]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Aya|T]]&amp;nbsp;[[Special:Contributions/Aya|C]]&lt;/sup&gt; 17:12, 5 August 2005 (UTC)
You don't mean it, I was about to rev up Gospel 101 under [[Wikiversity:School of Theology]], but I will wait the outcome. [[User:Athrash|&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;]] &amp;#45; [[User:Athrash|Athrash]] | [[User_talk:Athrash|&lt;small&gt;{Talk)&lt;/small&gt;]] 04:14, 6 August 2005 (UTC)

Ideally, wouldn't the substantial or finished Wikibook be the course book, and the assignments reside on the School page(s), whereby school and book are in the same project namespace, simple link not transwiki. That arrangement obviously takes time to develop. Example, for now, [[Gospel 101 Verses for the Week]] could put the Theology students into the New Testament of [[Christianity]] The Book. [[User:Athrash|&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;]] &amp;#45; [[User:Athrash|Athrash]] | [[User_talk:Athrash|&lt;small&gt;{Talk)&lt;/small&gt;]] 00:42, 7 August 2005 (UTC)

: You are free to develop textbooks (such as [[Christianity]]), which would be appropriate in such a 'school'. This is in fact the whole point of this website. What I object to is using a textbook site to develop university courses, which are beyond the scope of this site. - [[User:Aya|Aya]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Aya|T]]&amp;nbsp;[[Special:Contributions/Aya|C]]&lt;/sup&gt; 19:02, 7 August 2005 (UTC)

== Research papers==

How would you guys feel in terms of adding scientific papers to wikibooks, with categories such as &quot;topic&quot;, &quot;university of origin&quot;, &quot;authors&quot;...keywords and such ? [[User:Anthere|Anthere]] 07:53, 9 August 2005 (UTC)
:I'm not quite sure what you mean. Do you mean...:
:# Have a library-like list of published journal articles? It's unmaintainable without database software designed for it.
:# Provide ''copies'' of said articles? That's not very legal.
:# allow readers to post their ''own'' articles? Original Research is not welcome here, but try the [[wikicities:c:academia|Academic Publishing Wiki]].
:# Something completely obvious but I overlooked due to it being 1 AM over here?
:Well, it'll be one of those. Choose one! :) Either way there will no doubt be a home for it. [[User:Garrett|Garrett]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Garrett|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 13:05, 9 August 2005 (UTC)


==Question on VFD and content changes==

Question on the VFD voting.  Ignoring the question of what exactly should happen and where-  lets say its transikied somewhere (I don't think anyone is voting for straight up deletion, after all).  I'm working on some new content to add.  If I add it now, will it get transwikied with the rest if the project gets transwikied?  Or will it fall into the void?  If its the second, I'll just make the content on my user pages as a sandbox for now.

Also, some of the content is a change to existing content, and may get reverted depending on other opinion.  When a transwiki occurs, does all history get transwikied as well, or does history get lost?  --[[User:Javariel|Gabe Sechan]] 22:01, August 12, 2005 (UTC)

:The idea is that everything at a certain cut-off date would be transwikied, and anything added after that would no doubt be frowned upon but probably moved as well.
:As for where yours should go, unless you're intending for others to read and edit it you could consider building it off-wiki (on your computer) until a new home is organised.
:You see, we don't actually move the actual page reversions as there's no way to do that. The so-called transwiki is just a manual cut-n-paste, with the page history copied onto the talk page [[Talk:Monopoly/Official Rules|as in this example]].
:So if you post it now someone's just going to have to manually move it. Not to say you shouldn't contribute, nono, but the less content involved in this already enormous move the better.
:Hope that explains everything, and if not ask away! :) [[User:Garrett|Garrett]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Garrett|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 02:19, 13 August 2005 (UTC)

::Ok, in that case I'll write it in a sandbox for syntax testing until this is all decided.  And I'll hold off on things that may be reverted as well, since we wouldn't be actually able to revert easily.  Thanks.  --[[User:Javariel|Gabe Sechan]] 04:27, August 13, 2005 (UTC)

== Proposed &quot;[[Wikiversity:About|About]]&quot; page ==

Based on some of the comments on the vfd page, I've made a proposed [[Wikiversity:About|about]] page specifying what the goals of wikiversity are, and why it differs from wikibooks.  I basicly ripped off wikibook's format and changed the content a bit, so it may not be 100%.  Comments welcome.  --[[User:Javariel|Gabe Sechan]] 07:00, August 16, 2005 (UTC)
:You forgot to tell us where it was. :) Looking good so far... maybe needs some more details but I can't think of anything at the moment. [[User:Garrett|Garrett]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Garrett|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 09:20, 16 August 2005 (UTC)

::Oopsie.  Well, I see you found it anyway, sorry about that.  If you think of anything, let me know.  --[[User:Javariel|Gabe Sechan]] 09:46, August 16, 2005 (UTC)

:I'm taking lack of objection as consensus, since I have limited time before losing net access for a few weeks.  I'm putting this on the meta page as well, to help address concerns about the project.  --[[User:Javariel|Gabe Sechan]] 07:19, August 18, 2005 (UTC)

== Wikiversity Re-launch ==

I'm sort of &quot;forcing the hand&quot; of the foundation on this point, but I am &quot;relaunching&quot; the [[meta:Proposals for new projects#Wikiversity|new project proposal on Meta]] for this project.  This includes a [[meta:Talk:Wikiversity#Wikiversity &quot;Relaunch&quot;|timeline for when this project can become active]] as an independent wiki, with specific steps that must happen, as required by Wikimedia Foundation policies.  I think there is a tremendous amount of support for this project, so I don't see it rejected out of hand.  Based on the participants and comments here it appears as though there are also going to be a number of contributors that will keep the project alive.

As far as organization issues are concerned (including the basic charter of the project), please keep that discussion on Meta.  In terms of editing issues on Wikibooks or content organization of stuff that is already here, just keep doing what you are doing and expand what is presently here.  All contributions to Wikiversity that happen right now will be preserved and carried over to the new project, where ever it may end up.  '''PLEASE DON'T STOP CONTRIBUTING'''  ''Something'' is going to happen with Wikiversity, and on the whole it will be positive for the entire community as well.  It will just be a painful few months for all involved, unfortunately.  --[[User:Robert Horning|Rob Horning]] 14:51, 16 August 2005 (UTC)


==Importance of Schools==

Another one of my (in)famous ideas on how this project should run- has anyone given any thought to the importance of schools?  From a quick looks, it seems like most or all schools are pretty much a collection of links to courses.  Has any thought gone into making the school itself a method of teaching and community building?  I remember back in college, the people in my year were some of the best resources I had for learning and help with material.  Since its logical that someone interested in one course of a school may be interested in learning more, this seems to be a good spot to draw people in at.  I think I've already mentioned that I believe community building around courses will be important to teaching courses.  If we can start it at a higher level, we ccan keep more people around and draw them into helping on the lower level courses.  --[[User:Javariel|Gabe Sechan]] 07:19, August 18, 2005 (UTC)
:&quot;community building&quot; is important....maybe each &quot;school&quot; needs a page where students can describe what they hope to learn....this might start a feedback loop to grow the school in the right direction. We should link to wikiversity from places like [http://students.wikicities.com/wiki/Main_Page this wikicity]. --[[User:JWSchmidt|JWSurf]] 13:24, 18 August 2005 (UTC)

== Math support? ==

[[User:gonzosm|My friend]] [[User:jhouse|and I]] are trying to start up a math intensive [[Wikiversity:Study_Group_For_Relativity|study group course on relativity]].  We've both taken a look at the math support on wikibooks and were appalled at how tough it is to do equations that are readable.  To copy a single sentence from [[Wikiversity:Special_Relativity|the special relativity page]]:

Most generally, this matrix looks like &lt;math&gt;L(v) =\left(\begin{matrix}a &amp; b \\ c &amp; d\end{matrix}\right)&lt;/math&gt;
and transforms &lt;math&gt;\left(\begin{matrix}t \\ x\end{matrix}\right)&lt;/math&gt; to &lt;math&gt;\left(\begin{matrix}t^\prime \\ x^\prime\end{matrix}\right)&lt;/math&gt; via &lt;math&gt;\left(\begin{matrix}t' \\ x'\end{matrix}\right) = \left(\begin{matrix}a &amp; b \\ c &amp; d\end{matrix}\right)\left(\begin{matrix}t \\ x\end{matrix}\right) &lt;/math&gt;.

This was created by typing:

&lt;nowiki&gt;
Most generally, this matrix looks like &lt;math&gt;L(v) =\left(\begin{matrix}a &amp; b \\ c &amp; d\end{matrix}\right)&lt;/math&gt;
and transforms &lt;math&gt;\left(\begin{matrix}t \\ x\end{matrix}\right)&lt;/math&gt; to &lt;math&gt;\left(\begin{matrix}t^\prime \\ x^\prime\end{matrix}\right)&lt;/math&gt; via &lt;math&gt;\left(\begin{matrix}t' \\ x'\end{matrix}\right) = \left(\begin{matrix}a &amp; b \\ c &amp; d\end{matrix}\right)\left(\begin{matrix}t \\ x\end{matrix}\right) &lt;/math&gt;.
&lt;/nowiki&gt;

That seems impossibly complex for a '''casual discussion'''.  Does anyone know of any ways to make this easier on the students in the course?

:I'm not having much success finding what kind of plugins are used by wikiversity/wikibooks.  I did find a math plugin online that used latex format for math.  Is that possibly true for wikiversity?  If so, is there a latex editor that anyone recommends? [[User:Jhouse|Jhouse]]

:I'm going to take a look at having a friend of mine convert Scientific Notebook into this format...maybe it will be easy...In the meantime I finished chapter 1 of &quot;Tensors, Differential Forms and Variational Principles&quot; [[User:Gonzosm|Gonzo]]

:You can try [http://www.lyx.org/ Lyx] to generate the LaTeX using a WYSIWYG interface. An alternative is to format it as ASCII art:

       [a b
 L(v) = c d]

You can also format the LaTeX itself on multiple lines to make it easier to read:
&lt;math&gt;L(v)=\left(
\begin{matrix}
a &amp; b \\
c &amp; d
\end{matrix}\right)&lt;/math&gt;
Or you could use some kind of template solution. [[User:Mshonle|MShonle]] 23:07, 12 September 2005 (UTC)

:Your suggestions are good, but I'm really really hoping for some nice wysiwig editor or something.  Between my friends and I, we've tried downloading a number of equation editors and haven't found any that generate compatible output.  Some output looks close (Tex, LaTex) but none match.  The editors we got use the array keyword instead and possibly have a few other quirks...
::I remember looking around for good WYSIWYG LaTeX editors, but I haven't really seen too many. TexMacs works pretty well, but it isn't really LaTeX. However, for online discussions like these, I would recommend staying away from LaTex, even if it requires more non-standard notation, ala Mathematica. For instance, you could just represent a matrix as {{a,b},{c,d}}. It may not be as pretty, but it should do the trick. Subscripts could be either a[0], or a_0. Summation can be sum(a[k],1,n) or something like that. 

::Notation always varies, and it is generally made to best suite the medium. There is no reason we have to be constrained to notation, that was meant for being written out by hand. The important thing is to stay relatively consistent.
----[[User:72.245.93.22|72.245.93.22]] 04:52, 12 November 2005 (UTC)

::I disagree somewhat.  Consistent nomenclature starts to lock us into talking to ourselves more effectively than the rest of the world.  This is poor preparation for the real world.  The important thing is to get started studying, translating, and exchanging information.  Most serious students will have specific goals and milestones and if they do not experience progress towards their personal goals participation will inevitably fall off.  Indeed.  This seems to be a problem across the board with the wikiversity concept.

::Regarding the equation editor ... as we get to serious topics and problem sets we will have pages and pages of calculations.  It was not uncommon for me when as an undergraduate with a heavy 400 level course load to turn in over a hundred pages of detailed equations a week between physics and engineering classes.  Good scanning printers are now available from Wallmart and elsewhere in the U.S. for under $100.  If we cannot find a good mathml or svg editor then perhaps we can scan pages of calculation and upload png files.  A graphics editor such as GIMP should allow us to cut &amp; paste to insert corrections, questions or alternate mathematical opinions or proofs.  IMO this is a critical issue.  If we cannot do the math, then it is not physics.  This means ultimately our serious students should be able to start on a problem with a few fundamentals or previous results and then manually/personally do the math to generate the desired results or conclusions.  It may be that modern keyboarding is not up to this ... we may need to work on paper and then use computers to augment or communicate results.  [[User:Lazyquasar|Lazyquasar]] 18:42, 23 November 2005 (UTC)

== Wikiversity Vote ==

[[m:Wikiversity/Vote/en|Voting]] has started for a new Wikimedia sister project proposal called [[m:Wikiversity|Wikiversity]].  This is a request for anybody that is interested to cast a vote either in support or opposition to this new project proposal.  The results of this vote will determine if this project will be started on its own seperate group of wikis as a Wikimedia sister project, together with approval from the Wikimedia Foundation Board.  Discussion about this proposal should take place [[Talk:Wikiversity|on the Wikiversity discussion page]].

P.S. I know that if you are active with the Wikiversity community that you perhaps already know this, but this notice is for the few stragglers that may have missed my &quot;spamming&quot; all of the Wikimedia projects in the past 24 hours.  I've been throwing up notices about this vote everywhere I can, and it appears as though it is getting a very good response from the vote.  Those who are opposed to the creation of Wikiversity are also voicing their concerns, which is a good thing as well.  At least news of this vote is making the rounds in may places, and others are starting to pick up the ball and try to make announcements as well.  The voting page has now been translated into five languages (+1 being English).  The response from the &quot;international&quot; community has been quite impressive in particular.  As of when I posted this message, the voting is 34 in favor, 10 opposed.  Your vote is needed now to determine the future of this project. --[[User:Robert Horning|Rob Horning]] 20:35, 16 September 2005 (UTC)

== Stubs, Stubs, Stubs ==
When I look around at the &quot;departments&quot; of Wikiversity, I find a ton of stubs, such as the course [[Wikiversity:Accounting/Acc 1000|Acc 1000]]. Perhaps there are some fully developed courses, but I failed to find them. I suggest using categories to indicate the stage of development for each course, e.g. &quot;category:Wikiversity courses - being taught now&quot;, &quot;category:Wikiversity courses - fully developed&quot;, and &quot;category:Wikiversity courses - being developed&quot;. --[[User:LA2|LA2]] 00:55, 26 September 2005 (UTC)

Another stub: I don't understand the point of
* [[Wikiversity:School_of_Computer_Security/Class_Room]]
when
* [[Wikiversity:School_of_Computer_Security]]
doesn't exist.
--[[User:DavidCary|DavidCary]] 02:28, 31 December 2005 (UTC)

== Wikieversity active at the moment? ==

Hi! Does it makes sense to work at this site while the vote is running? There doesn't seem to be any activity at the moment!

:Sure it does.  When we win (notice the lack of an if :), the more content we have to publicize, the better.  It helps make the doubters realize their mistakes.--[[User:Javariel|Gabe Sechan]] 22:39, 9 October 2005 (UTC)

:Feel free to work on wikiversity. I think we need to make a section of the main page that invites people to describe what they would like to learn about. I agree with the idea that wikiversity should work on community building and the development of collaborations between learners and teachers. Since wikiversity is getting the boot from wikibooks, I have been reluctant to work in this name space. I recently tried to summarize some of the recent discussions of the wikiversity project [http://collaboration.wikicities.com/wiki/Wikiversity here]. --[[User:JWSchmidt|JWSurf]] 23:12, 10 October 2005 (UTC)

== Wikiversity Vote on Meta ==

This is just a general notice to thank everybody who has participated with Wikiversity up until now.  It looks likly that Wikiversity will become an independent Wikimedia sister project, and the results of the vote have been submitted to the Wikimedia Foundation board where there will shortly be a formal decision to see if this project will get a green light or not.  --[[User:Robert Horning|Rob Horning]] 15:52, 2 November 2005 (UTC)
:I know that a lot is going to change, likely in the next few days pending board approval, but a voting status should probably be updated on the Wikiversity-related pages in Meta, Wikipedia, and Wikibooks. Also, http://wikiversity.org has an outdated [[m:Complete_list_of_wikimedia_projects#Proposed_projects|Proposals of new projects]] link. --[[w:User:RockOfVictory|J. J. (on Wikipedia)]] 19:57, 4 November 2005 (UTC)

== Decision on Wikiversity? ==

Has there been a decision on whether or not Wikiversity will be an offical project? Just wondering. [[User:Gflores|Gflores]] 21:25, 19 November 2005 (UTC)

While waiting to hear from the [http://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Board_agenda board], I am going ahead with the [http://education.wikicities.com/wiki/Wikiversity Wikiversity Core Courses Initiative]. --[[User:JWSchmidt|JWSurf]] 16:31, 20 November 2005 (UTC)

I have high hopes that the board will approve, as I know at least Anthere is a fan of the project.  If you're interested in adding content, I'd say go ahead and do so.  Even if the answer ends up being no, I promise people will find some way to save the content.  --[[User:Javariel|Gabe Sechan]] 17:40, 21 November 2005 (UTC)

:Here is how to save the content: most of the stuff at Wikiversity are textbook modules. Even the example [[Wikiversity:Forms:Circle]] is a textbook module. I oppose the creation of Wikiversity as a wiki separate from Wikibooks (essay at [[MetaWikipedia:No to Wikiversity]]). --[[User:Kernigh|Kernigh]] 18:03, 9 December 2005 (UTC)
::  Your essay is a joke.  You honestly think books and classes are essentially the same thing.  You gloss over the interaction between professors and students (and students and students) as irrelevant.  It's like calling basketball and soccer essentially the same (except for all of those differences). --[[User:MateoP|MateoP]] 20:42, 10 December 2005 (UTC)

*Alterations to the Wikiversity proposal requested by the Board: [[m:Talk:Wikiversity#Current status|Current status]]. --[[User:JWSchmidt|JWSurf]] 01:48, 11 December 2005 (UTC)

----
In reply to MateoP (''You gloss over the interaction between professors and students (and students and students) as irrelevant.'') - this interaction is '''not''' irrelevant. I do think that the books at Wikibooks and the classes at Wikiversity (which are mostly lectures, list of participants, and external links) are &quot;essentially the same&quot; - why I wrote [[MetaWikipedia:No to Wikiversity]]. If Wikiversity was a forum where users had discussions, then I would believe that Wikiversity was different from Wikibooks. --[[User:Kernigh|Kernigh]] 01:37, 12 December 2005 (UTC)

I would agree with MateoP (though I would phrase it differently.) The problem with so much of the web-based learning is that it IS just a book or lecture put to hardcopy. The concept we need to be directing ourselves is how do we make this interactive. Think about what you gained from college. Maybe the courses were good... maybe the content was good... but you definitely remember the people and networks you formed. That is what we need here to make it work. Not the largest cyber-keg party... but the ability for people to interact, exchange ideas, and form relationships. This ability to interact and exchange ideas will be what sets us apart from the traditional web course... that ability to form an &quot;academic community.&quot;--[[User:Mfinney|Mfinney]] 04:31, 2 January 2006 (UTC)

== Lets not limit ourselves to wikibooks not yet made ==

As much as I love wikibooks, I think we need a more stable base to start this joint. I suggest using any and all open textbooks right now.

The perfect ideal of course, is to use wikibooks in conjunction with wikiversity. But that ideal has a problem in itself. Wikibooks are living books, they are moving targets. The wikiversity will be required to change their lectures and keep up with wikibooks. What if chapter 1 gets split into 2 chapters? Then wikiversity will have lectures for chapter 5 which really are for chapter 6.

Of course, this problem will be corrected through time. Wikibooks probably won't go through major changes after they stabalize. But using an unstable wikibook as a base learning material would be inefficient at best.

I suggest using whatever materials possible to get the wikiversity on the road before working in the ideal. I'd hate for this project to stall. --[[User:Dragontamer|Dragontamer]]

== No to online courses? ==

Does the new recommendations mean that we can't do online courses.  I'm putting together a course here:  [[Interventionism in Latin America During the Cold War: US and USSR]] and want to know if I should stop.  I'm not clear with what their recommendations mean.  If there are no online courses, does this mean that &quot;wikiversity&quot; would basically just be a place for people to come together and research to improve other wiki articles?  If it is &quot;no online courses&quot; could someone direct me to another place where I can hold my course (like the education wiki maybe?)..  Thanks.  --[[User:MateoP|MateoP]] 16:19, 11 December 2005 (UTC)

:I agree with the Board that it does not make sense to try to make '''conventional''' university courses the priority at Wikiversity. I think that the Board is looking for innovative e-learning that takes full advantage of the wiki format. If not conventional courses, then what? One suggestion had been that Wikiversity produce and archive &quot;teaching materials&quot; that could be shared globally. A second suggestion is that Wikiversity could be a learning community where various &quot;learning projects&quot; would exist. In my view, learning in Wikiversity should center around editing wiki documents (webpages). Learning would be through hands-on participation in Wikiversity projects. Initially, Wikiversity projects could center on &quot;services&quot; provided for other existing WikiMedia projects, particularly Wikipedia. Wikiversity could be a place for teaching Wikipedia editors how to find sources and evaluate references to include in Wikipedia articles so that all of the content of Wikipedia becomes verifiable. Currently, there are efforts towards this end within Wikipedia, but they need help. Wikiversity could archive all of the research performed by Wikipedia editors and Wikiversity researchers as they search for reliable sources to support what is said in Wikipedia articles. Only the best sources and conclusions from this Wikiversity background research would be transferred over to actual Wikipedia articles while the bulk of the sources (and probably BIG ARGUMENTS over their relative importance) would remain available at Wikiversity where it could continue be built upon in the future. The advantage for Wikiversity in starting with &quot;service courses&quot; for other wiki projects would be that it would provide a large pool of Wikiversity participants. Once Wikiversity learned how to form and facilitate useful learning communities for other wiki projects such as Wikiversity, then it would naturally expand in other directions starting from its initial foundation of &quot;service courses&quot;. In particular, I think that there will be a place in Wikiversity for the study of topics like [[Interventionism in Latin America During the Cold War: US and USSR]], but there is no reason that such e-learning projects could not start with an effort to make sure that Wikipedia has good coverage of Latin America. Eventually there could be links from Wikipedia articles about Latin America to the Wikiversity project called [[Interventionism in Latin America During the Cold War: US and USSR]] and those links would probably provide the main source of Wikiversity participants for the project. You could add &quot;work to improve Wikipedia articles&quot; to your list of &quot;Ideas or proposed study tasks&quot;. --[[User:JWSchmidt|JWSurf]] 23:09, 11 December 2005 (UTC)
::I'm not interested in teaching people how to find sources.  What i am interested in is teaching and learning about topics [[Interventionism in Latin America During the Cold War: US and USSR|such as this]], and then using what is learned to improve wikimedia articles (i put in my course outline that editing Wikipedia and Wikibook articles would be part of assignments).  So does this fit into where Wikiversity seems to be heading?  Of course I want discussion about the topic to be an essential part of the course, not just jumping into article editing.  --[[User:MateoP|MateoP]] 23:49, 11 December 2005 (UTC)

:If you teach any subject it is a good idea to explaining the sources that you rely upon. If you give someone a fish, you feed them for a day. If you teach someone to fish, you feed them for life. If you do not show someone how to find and evaluate sources, then all you are doing is force feeding them one POV about a topic. Anyhow, the idea of orienting Wikiversity &quot;courses&quot; around existing wiki projects such as Wikipedia is probably what the Board is looking for. See this article about [[m:Wikiversity/Modified project proposal|modifications to the Wikiversity proposal]] for a central place to discuss modifications that will satisfy the Board. --[[User:JWSchmidt|JWSurf]] 21:50, 13 December 2005 (UTC)

== Worldwide Vancouver University ==
Worldwide Vancouver University http://www.WorldwideUniversity.edu
would be glad to collaborate in the Wikiversity concept.  First,
however, Wikipedia needs to remove the slanderous and ignorant
remarks posted about this nearly-four-decades-old non-profit entity.


&lt;small&gt;&amp;mdash;''the preceding comment is by'' [[User:64.59.144.24|64.59.144.24]] ([[User talk:64.59.144.24|talk]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;bull;&amp;nbsp;[[Special:Contributions/64.59.144.24|contribs]]) 00:15, 13 January 2006&lt;/small&gt;

: I don't exactly know what to do about Wikipedia; I don't frequent the site. But when I looked at it, it obviously doesn't follow the &quot;neutral point of view&quot; policy, so I marked it as such. Other than that, I'm unsure what to do. --[[User:Dragontamer|Dragontamer]] 02:21, 13 January 2006 (UTC)

==Just give the textbooks for each class==

I think that the best thing this site could do is to list a bunch of textbooks for each course. For the intro to psychology, you might list The Essentials of Understanding Psychology by Robert Feldman. This is the best way to start Wikiversity.


:If thats all you want, check out [http://ocw.mit.edu/ MIT Open Courseware].  Their lectures, notes, and other materials are spotty, but they always have the book names.  --[[User:Javariel|Gabe Sechan]] 21:13, 27 January 2006 (UTC)

Thanks. The site looks great, but I noticed there was no psychology or art history degrees. Are there any other sites that are similar to MIT open courseware? [[User:Erudite|Erudite]] 18:05, 3 February 2006 (UTC)

I agree with this idea and have an additional suggestion.  I think it would be powerful to have a suggested syllibi for each course that outlines course objectives, topics of study, a suggested timeline, and recommended reading materials (from wikipedia, wikibooks, textbooks, articles, etc.).  For a start, it would allow online learners to skip or supplement the material gathering phase of online research by pointing out good resources and defining terms and ideas of a certain course topic. --[[User:Jcorrales|Jcorrales]] 18:40, 14 May 2006 (UTC)

==Prewritten Proposal to Teachers==
I know that a lot of students wouldn't want to take the time to write up a snippet of information about Wikiversity to send their teachers. Why not make a prewritten &quot;30-seconds-to-read&quot; letter that overviews the project and recommends that he or she write or help create a course? This way, students would be able to just highlight the text, paste it in an email, and send it to their teachers. [[User:Foxjwill|Foxjwill]] 23:11, 19 February 2006 (UTC)
:Great idea!  Do not ask the stacked board for permission, just do it.  You might also challenge the students/teachers to write up their extra credit homework in the appropriately placed course (creating a new course title or section if necessary) and then send the link to the public work to teachers, mentors, parents or peers requesting review, comment or grading.  Of course it would help to have a stable name space and basic policy in place such that we appear to be a going concern when an instructor or peer show up to look the work over.   The rumor that poor first impressions can be killers that are hard to overcome is well documented in various business marketing, management and pop pyschology sources. [[user:lazyquasar]]

== New here at Wikibooks/Wikiversity ==

I was wondering, do you guys have a school for political science, history, etc? [[User:Wikizach|Wikizach]] 17:51, 4 March 2006 (UTC)


:Take a look here: [[Wikiversity:Wikiversity_Schools]]. Look under Social Sciences, you should find them there. Hope this helps! If not, leave a message on my talk page and I can help further.--[[User:Mfinney|Mfinney]] 21:50, 4 March 2006 (UTC)


==Formation of an Advisory Board/Group==
We are developing well as a project, but I see several things beginning to occur:

* We have some definite conflict with the Wikibooks folks and this could be problematic down the road if it continues.

* We need a core group of folks to organize and begin bringing stuff together.

* We need a support structure for those who are new to help them gain momentum.

In the early stages of any project (while this has been going on for awhile) there should be some core group to assist with the development and management of the process. Much like [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WP:EA Esperanza] seems to be a positive influence on Wikipedia, we should look seriously at something similar. Something like that would be a great asset to the development of this project. Just my thoughts... anyone have something similar?--[[User:Mfinney|Mfinney]] 19:10, 9 March 2006 (UTC)

I would love to participate in discussions on this topic, based on my experience with the same concept
[http://tutor-web.info] albeit in a much smaller fashion.  I do not think we can look only at the web pages -
we need to be thinking about the full needs of students and instructors. [[User:Gstefans|Gstefans]]

== Computer Science==
Hello i am french an i try to develop the french computer science département of the wikiversité [[fr:Wikiversité:Département informatique]]. I am looking for some people wanting to finish the books of the english school of computer science. I can not speak english very well but i can give all the contents of the books, with a lot of samples and exercises. Who wants to work with me ? A computer science studient or a cteacher will be wellcomed.[[User:Merrheim|Merrheim]] 20:06, 9 March 2006 (UTC)

== Publicidad para tu web ==

Se les agradece a todos los wikiversitarios, a publicar algún(os) logotipo(s) para los webmasters, para que puedan dar a conocer este proyecto y así vaya creciendo la '''Wikiversidad''', pueden ser banners 468x60 más que todos... Muchas gracias. &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[w:Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[User:201.242.97.41|201.242.97.41]] ([[User talk:201.242.97.41|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/201.242.97.41|contribs]]) {{{2|}}}.&lt;/small&gt;

The preceeding comment was posted as a random page on Wikibooks, but it does bring up an interesting point.  Here is a rough translation (please improve if you speak Spanish natively). --[[User:Robert Horning|Rob Horning]] 01:42, 24 March 2006 (UTC)

To all Wikiversitarians that know anything about the project '''Wikiversity''':  Is is possible to have some 468x60 banners for advertisement?  Thank you very much.

== Naming standards for courses ==

I've been doing some plowing through Wikibooks and I've come across some module titles that are really more Wikiversity course oriented modules rather than a book.  The goal I have is to index all Wikibooks (which is not as easy of a task as I first thought!).  Since these are course outlines rather than a book, I've been leaving these off of the book index.  The distinction isn't exactly clear, but there are some differences.  These are indexed through the various schools of Wikiversity, so the content isn't exactly lost.

If Wikiversity were on its own domain (hint, hint... yeah, I'm working on that too), it wouldn't be a problem either, but for now Wikiversity and Wikibooks are sharing domain space.  I am proposing at least for now that a seperate pseudonamespace like '''Course:''', '''Subject:''', or '''Wikiclass:''' be used for these pages.  Any other thoughts here with regular Wikiversity users?  --[[User:Robert Horning|Rob Horning]] 15:16, 14 April 2006 (UTC)

== Problems with globe-and-crown logo ==

[[Image:Wikiversity-logo-zs.png|right]]
This logo was on the [[Wikiversity]] page, but now [http://en.wikibooks.org/w/index.php?title=Wikiversity&amp;curid=773&amp;diff=429200&amp;oldid=428350 it is not].

I thought of restoring it, but instead I marked it as ''&quot;missing essential source information&quot; at Wikimedia Commons - it appears to be tagged with the wrong license. I am reluctant to restore a wrongly-licensed image to the [[Wikiversity]] page, so I will not. --[[User:Kernigh|Kernigh]] 06:57, 15 April 2006 (UTC)

:I don't think this is necessarily as big of a deal as it is being made out to be.  The originator (aka the person who made the image) is [[User:Zephram Stark]], who has also been a significant contributor to both Wikibooks and Wikiversity.  That his major work is currently up for a VfD right now is certainly not endearing him to Wikibooks at the moment, however.  He has also been quite active on Wikipedia, and indeed brought some of his &quot;enemies&quot; to Wikibooks as well.

:From what I can tell, you are correct that it should be GFDL'd and not just granted to the Wikimedia Foundation, and that is an interesting dilemma for the foundation to consider if they should accept as a major project logo something that has been GFDL'd.  In this case, however, the logo hasn't been formally accepted by participants or anything seriou, just that it is a logo that has been created for the project.  The real solution to this would be to create alternative logos for Wikiversity and try to hold a contest for it.  It would be fun to move on to less serious stuff like trying to decide the logo for Wikiversity.  --[[User:Robert Horning|Rob Horning]] 17:04, 15 April 2006 (UTC)

::That proposed logo and all of my contributions are my gifts to the project. If you find them useful, please use them. If you don't find them useful, I won't take it personally should you choose to delete them. The only issue I have is when someone uses their position or influence to suppress something that could be useful to a majority of other people. There are two editors who are doing that at Wikipedia. One of them has followed me here. His login at Wikipedia is [[w:User:JW1805|JW1805]]. I regret that he is causing trouble here, but I don't know what I can do about it. --[[User:Zephram Stark|Zephram Stark]] 15:50, 19 April 2006 (UTC)

I have updated and clarified the legalities of the licensing issue at Wikipedia commons for [http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Image:Wikiversity-logo-zs.png Wikiversity-logo-zs.png]. Unless there are any other concerns, I will restore the proposed logo to the Module page. --[[User:Zephram Stark|Zephram Stark]] 03:51, 21 April 2006 (UTC)

::[[User:Zephram Stark|Zephram Stark]]'s accusations are neither here nor there.  It appears that this user has already been banned from both [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Zephram_Stark Wikipedia] and [http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Zephram_Stark Wikimedia Commons].  My problem with this logo is that is doesn't seem to have anything to do with Wikiversity.  It looks like some sort of cross between the [[w:UN|UN logo]] and the [http://www-rnks.informatik.tu-cottbus.de/~tweimann/logos/uniform_insignia/1024_USS%20Enterprise%20-%20United%20Earth.jpg United Federation of Planets logo], with Royalist iconography (what on earth does a crown have to do with Wikiversity?)  Are we endorsing the divine right of kings here?  --[[User:M Connell|M Connell]] 20:56, 6 May 2006 (UTC)

:::LMAO. I think you just gave yourself away. I didn't say anything about your &quot;M Connell&quot; login, but you seemed to have taken it personally anyway. If there was any way to assume good faith, I would, but I honestly think you are here merely to cause trouble. I'm going to restore the proposed logo so that people can consider it and hopefully come up with some alternate ideas and we can have a vote. Why don't you propose one, M Connell? --[[User:Zephram Stark|Zephram Stark]] 04:30, 7 May 2006 (UTC)

==Grading and certification==
=== Grading ===
An important part of the traditional classroom experience is grading assignments.  You often don't know how well you're really understanding or not understanding material until you turn in an assignment and get some feedback.  It would seem useful to have a mechanism for confidential submission of assignments, so people can't just copy off the students who finish first.  (For assignments where that sort of thing matters.)  This could be just done by e-mail, or some improvements to the wiki software might enable it.  There's also the question of whether or not grades would be made public.  There are some privacy and also some legal concerns there.  -- [[User:Beland|Beland]] 02:24, 28 July 2005 (UTC)

:We could have it on a Special: page. That way it's like your Watchlist, only you can see the contents.  Whereas email exclusivity has problems, such as losing the email. [[User:Master Thief Garrett|Garrett]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Master Thief Garrett|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 05:25, 29 July 2005 (UTC)

I think tools supporting personal assessment will be critical to success.  Personally I am not much interested in some self appointed authority's opinion of my understanding of the material.  Rather I am interested in the universe's response when I attempt to field some new space related technology or product.  I agree that expert evaluation will become needed and necessary to achieve accreditation (a critical long term goal, I myself and past employers have both placed a premium value on my B.S. in Engineering Physics from an accredited institution, I think we are self delusional if we think people wish to undertake serious study with no assurance that they will ever be able to use the material for personal goals or gain) but I think that over reliance on external evaluation is one of the major pitfalls that has been impacting the quality of educational resources in the U.S.  With external evaluation there is a tendency for students to learn to game the system to get high marks now with good intentions of understanding the material later.  This allows poor students to graduate with high marks and incompetence in critical fields in the U.S.  This has large negative impacts on the student and society as resources are misapplied and wasted and errrors in the field are required to wash out or imprison incompetents who have unintentionally, negligently or fraudulently damaged others.  External grading is necessary but not sufficient to achieve our goal of improving education via the free online elearning strategy. [[User:Lazyquasar|Lazyquasar]] 19:10, 23 November 2005 (UTC)

=== Grading and formats ===

I just saw Wikiversity.  Great concept but we certainly need a grading scheme.  Given a grading scheme
it would not be too hard to define what a degree consists of.  The only problem I can see from the very open
Wikiversity attitude is that I see no difference between a student and a teacher - can a student make up
all the questions and then answer them :-? 

It is very difficult to get  teachers involved in this kind of thing - I've been trying a more modest effort for several years and it is moving much more slowly than I would like.  But surely this is also to some extent a
question of permissible formats:  Can I easily upload all sorts of formats into Wikiversity or do I need
to retype everything in a specified wiki format?  I would think that there are a lot of very well 
structured latex books and slides which could be made available...   Also, I believe that students have
a need to see things on paper so one needs to be able to print everything easily - e.g. an entire course...

Finally, I have found it important to be able to write/enter/upload graphics and quiz questions in the
form of programming code (read fig/xfig, R, gnuplot etc) which automatically generates html, postscript,
pdf, png etc, depending on the required output.  I do not think it is enough to merely look at the content
on web pages.  Can one do this in Wikiversity?

[[User:Gstefans|Gstefans]] 18:56, 17 March 2006 (UTC)

:Wiki format is a limited subset of HTML with a few tools added by users. You can upload text and others will help you standardize the format. A method of standardized testing is something I have been arguing for since before the project began. Wikiversity is nothing more than a name without it. Additional functionality in the core code is required to enable real testing. That could come in one or both of two forms: expanded programming privileges granted to teachers within their specific testing areas, or a standardized testing form that would allow teachers to plug in questions or provide a testing bank of questions for a randomized test. I'm sure you realize that this would not entirely prevent fraud, so no certification could be given based on these tests alone. However, just as in physical universities, tests can be a measure of progress with some safeguards when combined with mid-terms and finals taken at a controlled testing facility. --[[User:Zephram Stark|Zephram Stark]] 17:05, 20 April 2006 (UTC)

===Certification===

Unless a student plans on always working for himself, knowledge of a discipline won't do him any good without proof that he '''''has''''' that knowledge and can put it to good use.  In my opinion, proof should not come from the &quot;good name&quot; of the school, but from some objective measure.

The classes that I have taught for the last twenty years are centered around achieving a quantifiable goal of some practical knowledge upon completion.  The level of knowledge, speed and skill is then demonstrated through third-party testing, available to anyone, whether they take the course or not, to generate an unbiased comparison of the student's abilities compared with those of people working in the industry or graduating from other schools.  Taking a particular class from a particular school is largely irrelevant to whether or not a student is qualified to do the job.  Hence, certification of a particular level of competency should not be tied to a school or a course, but to a demonstrable skill level in an unbiased environment.  --[[User:Zephram Stark|Zephram Stark]] 06:09, 6 November 2005 (UTC)

: Do you need a certification to apply knowledge? While I see this as a great bonus to Wikiversity if a certification could actually happen, I see this as both an unattainable and unnecessary goal. Again, it would be great, but it just seems like it would be too much trouble to get actual certifications. --[[User:Dragontamer|Dragontamer]]

::Now that some time is passed, do you still see it as an unnecessary goal? Without standardized certification, we will not get students. Without students, we have no school. Certification is a huge undertaking, but proof and quantification of learning is a going to be a necessary requirement for almost any student. --[[User:Zephram Stark|Zephram Stark]] 16:51, 20 April 2006 (UTC)

This is going to be a free university.  Accreditation is nearly impossible.  And unnecessary.  Any students who participate in wikiversity would be doing so for their only personal knowledge only.  No, you're wrong when you say knowledge of a discipline will do no good without proof; knowledge is worthy of having for its own sake.  --[[User:MateoP|MateoP]] 20:36, 10 December 2005 (UTC)

: The effort to gain knowledge for its own sake is a commendable endeavour, but it would be useless if people don't trust that the knowledge you have gained is complete and relavent. I would not like to gain knowledge that I was unable to use because no one either believed I had it, or didn't trust it. Wikiversity may not require formal accreditation status, but if Wikiversity can construct a course, and a good way to test their students, the Wikiversity will be able to carry its own academic clout regardless of if its accredited. 

: The accumulation of knowledge is what Wikipedia is about, the application and improvement of that knowledge is what a learning is about. Wikiversity should be able to increase the populations understanding, and in doing that the population can then improve on Wikipedia.  --[[User:Ciaran.mooney|Ciaran Mooney]] 11:41, 11 Feburary 2006 (GMT)

===Testing by Employers===

The instructor developing the course could also create a standardized certification testing method.  One way to keep Certification free and unbiased is to have a potential employer sponsor the testing.  An established firm that would like to hire a person based on a standardized skill level could offer to conduct the testing for that area in order to draw in potential employees and to verify their expertise.  A representative of the established firm would submit a request to the Wikiversity Testing Department for a certification exam and procedures bundle (available online by password).  The representative would sign a non-disclosure form and a promissory agreement to make the names, log-ins, and scores of those desiring certification available to the Wikiversity Testing Department after exams are finished.  Those demonstrating a particular skill level in the exam would have an official certification thumbnail placed on their user:page that leads to a printable version when clicked.  The graphic would include a disclaimer with the name of the established firm that conducted the physical testing.  --[[User:Zephram Stark|Zephram Stark]] 06:09, 6 November 2005 (UTC)

===Examination Institutions===

One problem with online certification is that there is no way to know wich person took the examination. And what materials he/she had at the time of it. That takes out credibility in the certification. One way to avoid this is by use of Examination Institution. The purpose of the institutions would be to exam the student and verify their documents. Some institutions (non profit org, goverment, etc) can do this for free. But others should be allowed to charge a small fee (like $20 per exam). That way they can cover the expenses on the examination (paying a person to give the exam, paper, usage of room, etc.). At the end of the test the result could then be send to a central database that will hold the student record. --[[Ricardo Santos|Ricardo Santos]] March 29, 2006

: I second this proposal.  There is no online way of examination which will retain the integrity of such a certification.  I further       
: propose that no other online assignments' marks be taken into account when grading a candidate, since this would also degrade the 
: integrity of any Wikiversity certification, since there is no way of verifying that the online assignment was indeed handed in by the
: candidate under consideration. --[[User:Huibrecht|Huibrecht]] 15:11, 1 June 2006 (UTC)

== Family Trees ==

It would be a cool feature to begin a massive family tree.

== Abuse ==

I don't know too much about Wikiversity, but I restored the page to a previous version because someone, (non-registered), mutilated it with a bunch of links to beastiality.

== Student ==

How can i become a wikiversity student?

*Look through the course listings. Find a topic that is as close as possible to what you are interested in. Start interacting with people who have similar interests. [[m:Wikiversity/Modified project proposal|Help get the project launched]]. --[[User:JWSchmidt|JWSurf]] 16:22, 24 May 2006 (UTC)

== Wikiversity in Wikibooks ==

I must confess that I am unaware what is happening with the Wikiversity proposal. Whatever the result, however, I understand that textbooks for university students will remain on wikibooks. I therefore think Wikibooks should be ensuring that its own Wikiversity section looks like a textbook repository. This would mean rearranging the Wikiversity portal page, and transferring bits related to the Wikiversity proposal to the Wikibooks: namespace. I don't think this would take too much, nor do I think it would detract from the proposal, whilst it would have the benefit of emphasising that university textbooks are very much part of Wikibooks' offering. Before making this change, I note my ideas here first to allow for comment, [[User:Jguk|Jguk]] 23:04, 2 June 2006 (UTC)

:Eventually, there should be a good deal of cooperation between Wikiversity and Wikibooks. Many Wikiversity participants will be looking for online textbooks. Some Wikiversity participants will engage in scholarly projects that will very useful to the development of online textbooks. What is important is creating ways for constructive interactions between the two projects. It will not be constructive for anyone to patrol Wikiversity in order to make sure that it does not contain anything like a textbook or to patrol Wikibooks and make sure that it does not contain anything that looks like a Wikiversity learning project. --[[User:JWSchmidt|JWSurf]] 18:15, 5 June 2006 (UTC)

I imagine a Wikiversity section will remain in wikibooks and will host university level textbooks. No doubt, assuming a separate Wikiversity project proceeds, there would be links between the wikibooks wikiversity section and wikiversity.org. Are there any objections to changing what we now have on wikibooks, so that the wikiversity section of wikibooks looks like how it will be after a new wikiversity.org project is set up, with the all the non-textbook related content (eg policy discussion pages) moved to the Wikibooks namespace (where other Wikibooks policy is discussed)? [[User:Jguk|Jguk]] 06:41, 6 June 2006 (UTC)

== Some similar concepts ==

* http://www.freecurricula.org/ (PD textbooks! 7 at the moment)
* http://www.theassayer.org/ (seems more like wikisource...not always free)
* http://textbookrevolution.org/ (some are only free-as-in-beer
--[[User:Pfctdayelise|pfctdayelise]] 09:32, 15 June 2006 (UTC)

==  Administrator Needed to Correct Horseshit or Large Error on Front Page ==

*Publish your course notes &lt;/b&gt;(note that we're talking to ''instructors'' here, not their students)&lt;/b&gt;, lesson plans, topical essays, or reference works for others to review, modify or fork.

Either above or under the above I attempted to add a bullet and found the page protected, any admin is requested to add the bullet while any interested can debate with me here why we want &quot;students&quot; to become &quot;participants&quot; at Wikiversity by &quot;participating&quot; in any way they please.  Modifying electronic bytes to improve the product is cheap and easy way to help people learn something and is what Wikiversity is all about.

* Publish your course notes (note that we're talking to ''students'' here, not their instructors), lesson plans, topical essays, or reference works for others to review, modify or fork.

and

*Publish your course notes (note that we're talking to ''participant'' here, not their parasites or naysayers), lesson plans, topical essays, or reference works for others to review, modify or fork.

or simplify the entire bullet list by changing the damaging sabotage in the original bullet to:

&lt;b&gt;* Publish your course notes, lesson plans, topical essays, or reference works for others to review, modify or fork.&lt;/b&gt;

The entire point of Wikiversity is to start with whatever participation we get and evolve towards effective materials and participants.   Participants means however someone wants to use the site. Students, mentors, professors, teachers, cub scout leaders, self improvement clubs, entrepreneurial cliques, whatever.   Discouraging student participation is a very bad idea on the front page.

Thanks Lazyquasar

:Okay, first... calm down. The warning about the page being protected says, &quot;''This page has been locked so that only '''registered users''' can edit it''&quot; (my emphasis). [[User:Lazyquasar|You are a registered user]], so you can edit it if you just log in. Now, secondly: I'm the one who added the phrase &quot;''note that we're talking to ''instructors'' here, not their students''&quot; to the instructions/suggestions. Calling that &quot;sabotage&quot; is a gross exaggeration. My concern was simply that one can easily argue that instructors who develop their own course notes '''hold the copyright to those notes'''. Thus, there may be legal issues involved if students post class notes without their instructor's permission. I have modified the statement to better reflect those concerns. - [[User:Dcljr|dcljr]] 08:01, 17 June 2006 (UTC)

::I have already calmed down as you know if you have checked your discussion page. Now secondly, copyright is exactly the issue.  Perhaps we have a terminology problem.  Obviously handouts or large volumes of verbatim repetition of the instructors materials will requirement their permission as they hold copyright.  The copyright to a student's &quot;course notes&quot; or &quot;notebook&quot; created by them as they assemble paraphrased materials to study from obviously belongs to the student and is well within their rights as copyright holders to publish.  Implying that we do not want participation from students donating their materials for coordination and group study between particpants improving the material as they interact socially to the wiki is diametrically opposed to the consensus or agreement to disagree that emerged during the Wikiversity proprosal development over the last year.  The issue of being a site for &lt;b&gt;educational professionals only&lt;/b&gt; was raised and dismissed in favor of broad participation of any interested in improving local content via the wiki while studying via group interaction or self study of the materials made available via the wiki.   &quot;(students might want to get the permission of their instructors first)&quot; is better than outright patronizing of students but should be relocated to the submittal screen notice if required and corrected to &quot;please do not illegally post copyrighted materials of others, permission to release the copyrighted materials under the FDL is required from the owners of the copyright&quot;.  I believe it has some similar already.  &quot;Personally created student notebooks with short specific quotes and appropriate citations in accordance with fair use provisions of copyright law are materials belonging to the student and may be posted.&quot;   This should be run by our copyright experts and improved and approved if there is concern about people's use or interpretation of &quot;notebook&quot; or &quot;course materials&quot;.  In any future changes please do not imply that some of our partipants interactions are presumed inferior or inappropriate and not welcome.  All participants are welcome to post their own materials for &quot;merciless editing&quot; until an offical coordinated policy says otherwise.  [[user:lazyquasar]]

== Move to Wikibooks namespace ==

The project/discussion pages on Wikiversity are not really pages of textbooks. I therefore intend to start moving these over to the more appropriate Wikibooks namespace - so that project pages starting Wikiversity: will instead start with Wikibooks:Wikiversity/ . I do not intend to move the textbook pages that begin with &quot;Wikiversity&quot;. If anyone has comments before the move, please do so here. Thanks, [[User:Jguk|Jguk]] 09:28, 17 June 2006 (UTC)

:I do not really understand all of the implications of the different namespaces you are refering to above. I have been assured by Mr. Wales that the Board is supportive of getting Wikiversity started soon and by the members of the &quot;activation committee&quot; appointed by the &quot;Special Projects Committee&quot; that action will be forthcoming soon to finalize the initial Wikiversity project scope and wiki assets.  Rather than shuffling the materials at this time it might be advantageous to wait and allow Wikiversity people to transwiki or fork all the appropriate Wikiversity specific materials.   The Wikiversity project really does not need the further confusion of materials shifting around at this time.  Interest has waned dramatically over the last six months as the project has been stalled in limbo and this further confusion could be very detrimental to the new attempts to launch a successful project.  [[User:Lazyquasar|Lazyquasar]] 03:30, 18 June 2006 (UTC)

I am more mindful that the Wikibooks project, which has hosted this proposal, which in strictness it really wasn't obliged to do, should get back to normal and showcase the textbook content within Wikiversity as a full integral part of its own. If we knew a date for a Wikiversity project to start that was near, we could plan around it - but there have been so many delays with Wikiversity, which suggests we should not wait. I also think that having all Wikversity project pages labelled up as Wikibooks:Wikiversity would help with the move - currently some but not all of the pages beginning with Wikiversity: are project pages - identifying the difference should be useful. However, I do think it is time for the Wikibooks project to regularise itself, and that remains the motivation behind this proposed tidy-up, [[User:Jguk|Jguk]] 07:17, 18 June 2006 (UTC)

:I have been treating Wikiversity as a seperate namespace for some time, and I don't know why this was even proposed.  Please don't go moving Wikiversity content elsewhere other than to something tied directly to Wikiversity itself.  If Wikiversity is to remain on Wikibooks (that would require some more work and policy changes) I would hope that it would become a seperate namespace.  For now, please leave the Wikiversity pages in place, especially if they have a Wikiversity prefix.  I find it unfortunate that Wikiversity participants are more comfortable adding content to Meta now than Wikibooks, for what should be project content, like [[meta:Wikiversity community]].  There is obviously a very hostle attitude right now toward Wikiversity participants if content like this is even made on Meta.  --[[User:Robert Horning|Rob Horning]] 14:49, 20 July 2006 (UTC)

::I agree with you, Robert, that the Wikiversity content on Wikibooks should be left alone until it is transwikied (which ''is'' imminent). I'm not sure I agree about the hostility, though - I think the content on Meta is of a different kind to here (planning, policy and process, as opposed to actual educational content). I do feel I should have worked more on content of interest here on Wikibooks - I think I've simply been waiting for the separate domain all this time. Maybe this attitude hasn't helped.. [[User:Cormaggio|Cormaggio]] 16:25, 20 July 2006 (UTC)

== Small Spelling Mistake ==
Just wanted to point out that under the &quot;Some Ideas for Effective Initial Participation&quot; section, the emboldened &quot;edit mercilously&quot; should be spelled &quot;edit mercilessly&quot;.  Just thought I'd point it out, seeing as how it's on the main page and everything. :)

== See comments on blog ==

I've blogged a bit on the missing piece in Wikiversity at http://twofish.wordpress.com/

I lot of my comments are based on what happened in the &quot;beta prototype&quot; for an online university at http://www.gnacademy.org/

The thing that someone (probably Wikiversity) can and should provide is a lot of learning support services.  Academic advising.  Career counselling.  Research help.  Financial aid.

I'm a high school student that wants to be a high-energy particle physicist.  How do I do this?

== University departments are evil.... ==

And I think we need to get rid of them from wikiversity.  University departments exist to allocate budgets and exercise administrative lines of power.  Since we don't have a budget and there is no administrative line of power, there is no need for them here.  The problem with departments is that they draw lines that prevent people from interacting.

[[User:Roadrunner|Roadrunner]] 06:56, 7 August 2006 (UTC)

:Agreed. [[User:Fredrik|Fredrik]] 07:54, 9 August 2006 (UTC)

::I think that we need departments at wikiversity at the same way we need folders in our computer. If I am looking for something I can find it quickly. Why you say that they prevent people from interacting? [[User:Vitalij zad|vitalij]] 08:14, 9 August 2006 (UTC)

I suspect that [[m:Wikiversity:Communities|learning projects]] will be an important type of community group within WIkiversity. We will need many ways to organize and categorize learning groups and help Wikiversity participants find the specific Wikiversity learning communities that match their personal learning goals. A listing of conventional university schhools, departments and courses could be useful to help guide Wikiversity participants to Wikiversity projects and activities. Even if conventional university departments are too restrictive, that does not mean that Wikiversity departments would have to adopt the negative aspects of bricks-and-mortar schools. Wikiversity departments can be fluid and supportive of inter-disciplinary communication......everything is only a hyperlink away. Do we really have to call them &quot;wikidepartments&quot; in order to get people to think in the wiki way? --[[User:JWSchmidt|JWSurf]] 13:41, 9 August 2006 (UTC)

I certainly can't imagine a point where we would be restrictive based on the names of our departments.  There's tons of overlap and certainly we should encourage the overlap in this arena.  And while I agree University departments traditionally discourage this behaviour, I have to agree that [[User:Vitalij zad|vitalij]] is right in that we've got to help people find what they are looking for.  [[User:Atrivedi|Atrivedi]]

== Intro to CG course request for help ==

I've started writting an intro to computer graphics course, but i have realized that i would be duplicating a lot of work. I am basing it on this: [http://math.hws.edu/eck/cs324/ CPSC 324] (a now closed class, with outdated material, i'm only trying to match what it covers.) I think i'm going to change what's already in the course to just use chapters from this offsite manual for the blender sections: [http://www.cdschools.org/54223045235521/blank/browse.asp?A=383&amp;BMDRN=2000&amp;BCOB=0&amp;C=55205 mostly up to date blender manual for classrooms] That just leaves the gimp, YafRay, and OpenGL. Anyone feel like helping to get it complete? (I have no idea on opengl, and little on programming.)--[[User:V2os|V2os]] 05:10, 9 August 2006 (UTC)

== Project launch ==

The following (1-5) was posted by [http://wikimediafoundation.org/wiki/User:Anthere Anthere] to the [http://mail.wikipedia.org/mailman/listinfo/foundation-l Wikimedia Foundation Mailing List] (Tue, 15 Aug 2006 01:03:33):

1) there will be a domain at beta.wikiversity.org, where all new
languages may contribute and start working on translation of guidelines
etc...

2) those languages with at least 10 active participants can request a
separate domain name. As of today, I presume the english language has at
least 10 people interested, so you guys may bug Brion to ask for
en.wikiversity.org. I am not sure if it is the case for any other language.

3) All sites will be flagged &quot;beta&quot; in the same way that wikinews has
been for at least 6 months.

4) During these 6 months, guidelines should be developped, *in
particular* with regards to collaborative research. We would hope that
these guidelines are as much as possible developped on the beta site (in
particular collaborative research), so that all languages share a common
goal and a few common non negociable rules.

5) At the end of these 6 months period, the project will be reviewed, in
particular so that the issue of collaborative research is qualified, and
if possible to define whether the beta stage is over. Reviewal will be
done by Spc.

----

The [http://en.wikiversity.org/wiki/Main_Page English language Wikiversity] is now online. --[[User:JWSchmidt|JWSurf]] 13:33, 15 August 2006 (UTC)


----
We need to get a [[wikiversity:language registration]] page active both here and at the beta.wikiversity.org to assist people with getting their language versions started.  See point two of the project launch message just above.  Anyone with admin priveleges please put the link above on the front page here at wikibooks.   Also a good idea to put links to the various languages and beta on this front page.   Thanks.   lazyquasar  [[User:70.110.37.107|70.110.37.107]] 07:58, 16 August 2006 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>dk1yd0nyzsqu5r5umgte1zmgqdb1l82</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Discrete Mathematics/Introduction</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>764</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1578456</id>
      <parentid>442277</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-07-24T15:52:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>moved [[Talk:Discrete mathematics/Introduction]] to [[Talk:Discrete Mathematics/Introduction]]: Title casing.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Groups are usually considered introductory level, not advanced. Elementary group theory, I mean...

: I think a consolidated and thorough treatment of group theory constitutes it being in the upper level section. However I might rearrange some things. [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 10:43, 21 Aug 2003 (UTC)

-----

Groups are usually considered low level, but that doesn't necessarily mean they should be treated in the introductory part. Nonetheless, Groups probably shouldn't be called complex.

Anyway, what exactly is this introduction about? Is it an introduction 
* to the topic itself, i.e. discrete maths, or 
* to this book, i.e. the subset treated here, or 
* to this Wikibook, i.e. the way it's treated here?

: A bit on the topic, and a bit on the Wikibook.  Reworded intro. [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 07:29, 2 Feb 2004 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>ssciwh2og9q29ni9efzfvkbpbgrm6ob</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Esperanto/Authors</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>767</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2226827</id>
      <parentid>1717882</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-12-03T17:18:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Swfarnsworth</username>
        <id>324928</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Esperanto | ^ Esperanto ^]] | About the book: Authors
----

The [[Esperanto]] textbook was started by [[User:Gabriel Beecham|Gabriel Beecham]].

Other contributors have included:
*[[w:User:LittleDan|LittleDan]] (only a few minor contributions)
*[[User:Chuck SMITH|Chuck SMITH]] (only a few minor contributions and [[Esperanto/Introduction]])
*[[w:User:goodgerster|Ben Goodger]] ([[Esperanto/Appendix/Summary of grammar|Summary of grammar]])
*[[w:User:ThrashedParanoid|ThrashedParanoid]] ([[Esperanto/Word synthesis|Word synthesis]], [[Esperanto/Appendix/Table of word endings|Table of word endings]], [[Esperanto/Appendix/Table of affixes|Table of affixes]], and [[Esperanto/Appendix/False friends|False friends]])
*[[User:DroEsperanto|DroEsperanto]] (A few minor contributions and [[Esperanto/Family|Family]])
*[[User:Swfarnsworth|Steele W. Farnsworth]] (Rewriting chapters for formatting and logical progression)
----
[[Esperanto | ^ Esperanto ^]] | About the book: Authors

[[Category:Esperanto]]</text>
      <sha1>jdva8yaa9pkunh6ogqrqrat84l81j6j</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Gabriel Beecham</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>769</id>
    <revision>
      <id>152906</id>
      <parentid>25772</parentid>
      <timestamp>2004-04-16T01:48:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Gabriel Beecham</username>
        <id>80</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[m:User:Kwekubo|Meta]]

[[en:User:Kwekubo]], [[eo:Vikipediisto:Gabriel BEECHAM]] ...</text>
      <sha1>dogumgowez8d56oxp3ec9uxp8xkpbb5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Esperanto</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>770</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2363303</id>
      <parentid>2360782</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-13T19:53:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Wikiotics</username>
        <id>664384</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Growing beyond the book format */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{WikiProject Languages}} 

== Old issues ==

There are a lot of issue to sort out on this book, before we get going.
*Firstly, we need to choose a transcription system. Should it be Latin-3, Unicode, X-system... you know the rest...
*How can we change the content to be more suitable for an Esperanto book? [[The original version came from the [[Spanish]] module. On that note, see the [[Talk:Spanish]] page.
*Any suggestions for chapters?
*Lastly, lets get writing!
-- [[User:Gabriel Beecham|Gabriel Beecham]] 17:11, 21 Aug 2003 (UTC)

:This wiki is in UTF-8, you can type Unicode straight into it. (Aŭtomata X-konvertado estas starigita ĉe la esperantlingva vikipedio por faciligi la laboron por tiuj, kiuj ne ĝuste agordis sian komputilon por Esperanto, sed ĉi-momente neeblas tiun enŝalti por nura parto de la vikio. Eble iam poste, sed mi havas sufiĉe da laboro kaj restas multe farenda pri lingvoj en la vikisistemo...) --[[User:Brion VIBBER|Brion VIBBER]] 05:40, 26 Sep 2003 (UTC)

:Concerning the chapters, I don't think they are in the best order (and some of them aren't very relevant); for example, ''Traveling'' seems rather... inappropriately placed, seeing as what would usually be covered under that (riding taxis, catching flights, etc.) isn't something that is possible to use Esperanto for...  Anyways, I was thinking that it would be good to stick in a chapter somewhere concerning describing people, places, etc., rather near the beginning, just to give the readers a basic vocabulary, so they feel like they're actually learning something... --[[User:Travisg|travisg]] 00:08, 28 Sep 2004 (UTC)

----
Cxu mi bobe komprenas, ke ni povas komune verki Esperanto-libron, respektive lernolibron? Cxu la x-sistemo ne funkcias en Vikipedio suficxe bone? Mi pensas ke jes. Eble anstataux la libro-titolo &quot;Esperanto&quot; (kiu sonas al mi same
kiel &quot;La cxehxa lingvo&quot;) estas tro largxa temo. Eble ni devus verki plurajn elektronikajn librojn pri Esperanto, ekz. &quot;Esperanto-lernolibro&quot;, &quot;Esperanto-infolibro&quot;, &quot;Esperanto-junularo&quot;, &quot;Esperanto-enciklopedio&quot;(mi pensas nun pri simila verko, kiu estis presita en 30-aj jaroj kaj iam en 1980 represita), &quot;Esperanto-historio&quot;, ... cxu ne?
Vikipediisto:Jan

:Nu jes! Je la unua okulĵeto, ŝajnas al mi ke ĉi tiun paĝaron estas planita kiel lernolibro por anglalingvanoj. Se indas krei apartajn librojn pri specifaj temoj (kaj kompreneble por alilingvanoj), oni certe rajtas tion fari ankaŭ. --[[User:Brion VIBBER|Brion VIBBER]] 05:40, 26 Sep 2003 (UTC)

-----

Mi ne volas kritiki, sed rigardante nur la skeleton de la nuna libro, sxajnas al mi iom tro teda - ege similas al similaj libroj, el kiuj jam ekzistas multegaj, ecx sur rete (kelke da artikoloj, vortlistoj, vojagxo ktp ktp). Kial tiu cxi libro estas pli bona/utila? Cxu cxar gxi estos libera? Eble... tamen mi kredas ke indus pripensi cxu ne E-a lernolibro povus esti organizata en alia kaj pli novpensa maniero. 

(mi ne regule venos cxi tien, se vi volas respondi, povas ankaux retposxti min al shaklev cxe gmx punkto net).

Stian

== Move it over? ==

Esperanto is a different ''kind'' of language, and it serves a different ''function'' compared to natural languages such as Spanish.  This book should '''not''' follow the generic language-learning-book template.  That said, I think that this wiki may be the wrong place to start a &quot;Learn Esperanto&quot; book.  It might work, but perhaps we should use Esperanto in the way it was intended... by making sure that we have a version '''in''' Esperanto to translate to other languages.

There ''is'' an [[eo:Cxefpagxo|Esperanto wikibooks wiki]] but I am apparently the only real [[eo:Speciala:listusers|user]] at the moment.  In a fit of entheusiasm, I've gone and started a book there: '''''[[eo:La Esperanto Komensanta|La Esperanto Komensanta]]'''''.  How's the title?

--[[User:Rick MILLER|Rick MILLER]] 03:40, 7 Aug 2004 (UTC)

::Sorry to nit-pick, but that should be Komen'''''c'''''anta. [[User:128.205.219.145|128.205.219.145]] 23:17, 18 Sep 2004 (UTC)

== Interactive Activities ==

Hey Everyone --

I posted a link ( http://langwidge.com/esperanto.html ) to some activities I had made to the bottom of the wikibooks. If anyone knows of any way to incorporate them into the actual wikibook you totally have my permission to do so -- they've just been sitting on my hard drive unedited for 5 years now -- I couldn't find any way to use Flash in the WikiBook, though, so I just made a link.

~Ravi

btw, wikibooks would support the interactive activities if they were just sound. If anyone wants to try and make something similar as an ogg file, but didn't have the technical resources/skills, write me: ravip(at)mit(dot)edu

== Slang appendix ==

I believe that would be very useful an appendix about how translate &quot;[[w:en:American|American]]&quot; slang to Esperanto.

Dankon

== accusative case ==

In lesson one, you say &quot;the accusative case ... will be covered in the next lesson&quot;, but it isn't.  &amp;mdash;&amp;mdash; [[User:212.139.34.221|212.139.34.221]] 21:29, 28 Jun 2005 (UTC)

Just fixed that. I went into Lesson 1 and put in a section on objects. Though it probably needs some expansion and revision.

[[User:DroEsperanto|DroEsperanto]] 04:34, 10 December 2005 (UTC)

== wordlist? ==

Shouldn't Appendix C and Appendix D be ROOT lists, after all, you can make English, Englishman, English speaker, and English hater all out of the same root. I know the appendix hasn't been made, but before it is begun, shouldn't have a correct title? --[[w:User:ThrashedParanoid|ThrashedParanoid]]
01:18, 30 November 2005 (UTC)

No one else has said anything about what's going on with the two wordlist appendices, but regardless i have started reformatting them. Since the [[Esperanto/Appendix_D|Esperanto-English appendix]] is already populated, i'm starting there. First, i am using templates rather than raw tables - which will make it ''much'' easier to change the styling if necessary, and allow for consistent styling across the whole book. Second, i have changed the style somewhat because the old style had ''way'' too much padding - each entry of the table took up three or four times the vertical space. Third, i have started adding styling to the sections that weren't styled (and were damn near illegible clumps of word soup) and fixed some broken code. i will work my way down the page - it should only take a couple of days - but once it's all done, the whole page will be in a single, regular format which can be easily changed into anything else you like. (Especially by script - just say what you want and i can change the whole list in minutes.) --[[User:Indiana|Indiana]] ([[User talk:Indiana|talk]]) 09:01, 11 September 2009 (UTC)

== Lesson 4! ==

Hura! Lesson 4 is up! Though due to laziness, I have yet to add anything on the affectionate suffixes for male and female, nor have I said anything regarding &quot;bo&quot; or &quot;pra&quot;.
[[User:DroEsperanto|DroEsperanto]] 23:46, 10 December 2005 (UTC)

== Amount of grammar ==

Since Esperanto has a very easy grammar, I don't think we have to introduce it almost all at once. Students get scared away if they have to read through 3 screens full of grammar explanations before they learn how to say anything in a language. When teaching German, French or Russian, it is quite difficult to teach students to say something without having to introduce a lot of grammar at once, particularly in the first lesson, but even that is doable (see my Wikibook [[BLL German]]). In Esperanto, it should be no problem at all to write a lesson introducing e. g. just -as and -o (no -n even at first since the word &quot;Accusative&quot; alone will send students of German or Russian running) and to do so in a natural conversation, for example a round of introductions at a congress. Keep in mind that this Wikibook should probably not look like a textbook used during an Esperanto course. Self-study has different demands on material than classroom study. The most crucial difference is that self-study books have to keep the students' motivation up. As soon as something appears too difficult or too boring, many students will stop studying the course or maybe stop studying the language altogether, since they're not at High School where they have to continue taking the class or write exams and they're not working with a private teacher whom they could ask for additional explanations or who could re-motivate them. 

I believe the ideal structure for an Esperanto course would be:
# Text or Dialogue from a situation the student might find himself in (and yes, asking for the way or the like could be part of it, if you imagine a Pasporta Servo kind of situation of an international Esperanto-speaking visitor and a local speaker)
# Vocabulary
# Grammar
# Exercises for grammar and word usage
# Information about the Esperanto movement
# Maybe a list of additional vocabulary for those students who would like to have more words to use along the same patterns taught in the lesson. E. g. if the lesson teaches how to say that you're from a particular country, you wouldn't want to put in lots and lots of country names in the main vocabulary list of words that the student will absolutely have to know in the next lesson. Instead, you could put them in an optional vocabulary list, which the student can use to look up the name of his country and any country he is particularly interested in. Part of motivation is also the feeling that you aren't taught anything useless, only commonly-used vocabulary and vocabulary highly relevant to your own situation. 

There is a Wikibook about creating good language-teaching Wikibooks, for those interested in more tips for coursebook-writing. And I tried summarising the approach that I found worked best for self-study courses in natural languages in the article [[Bite-sized language lessons]].

[[User:Junesun|Junesun]] 08:54, 22 May 2006 (UTC)

:I believe that this would be a great structure to learn ANY language, not solely Esperanto.&lt;br&gt;I would really appreciate it if someone were to add that 'additional vocabulary', since I just started learning Esperanto (like half an hour ago) and feel like the amount vocabulary is out of sink with the grammar (although all this grammar was still easy enough for me) and would like to learn more words to get into sink again.  --[[User:JorisvS|JorisvS]] 11:22, 4 August 2006 (UTC)
:I've already started the first extra vocabulary list in lesson 1, but I need someone to expand it. --[[User:JorisvS|JorisvS]] 11:34, 5 August 2006 (UTC)
:To address JorisvS point - I need to have a good read of all this.  I take the line below, but you do need some basic bits and pieces to make up sentences with.[[User:Stevebritgimp|Stevebritgimp]] 19:51, 27 December 2006 (UTC)

Personally I disagree on the main point (in the gentlest possible way).  The point of Esperanto is that it has an entirely regular grammar, and so grammar is easy to learn.  If I were teaching Esperanto to a small group of people I would almost immediately talk about, say, the tenses - past and future.  Now if you were learning French in school you wouldn't do tenses until the second year, or at least quite a few weeks or months down the line.  I do very much agree that using the grammatical terms for things (like accusative) while fine on talk, should be avoided in lessons - in fact accusative itself is a mistake by Latin grammarians.  Best use 'object'.

Following on from that I think the classic 'phrasebook' or 'expressions' approach is not ideal for Esperanto, given that it is international and don't have idiom.

A lot to discuss - I wonder if this is something that floats people's boat - Esperanto's great strength is its simplicity and that it illustrates how other languages work.  [[User:Stevebritgimp|Stevebritgimp]] 19:49, 27 December 2006 (UTC)  P.S. Anyone encountered [[w:Michel Thomas]]' approach to teaching languages? [[User:Stevebritgimp|Stevebritgimp]] 19:51, 27 December 2006 (UTC)

== Lesson 10 ==

===''Venturo'' or ''veturo''?===
It says in lesson 10: &lt;br&gt;
ŝip- (ship) + ventur (travel) = ŝip(o)veturo (a journey by ship) &lt;br&gt;
This doesn't look correct. What is there correct translation of 'a journey' in Esperanto?&lt;br&gt;
--[[User:JorisvS|JorisvS]] 15:05, 4 August 2006 (UTC)

== False Friends ==

Oh my gosh!  What happened to the section on False Friends?!  It looks like it was deleted, and right when I was about to learn from it!  Why was it deleted?  What can be done/what should I do?--[[User:Gabriel Koulikov|Gabriel Koulikov]] 20:06, 17 December 2006 (UTC)
== Esperanto Wikiversity course ==
The Wikiversity course is very bare and needs further development. Right now it just has links to the standard e-mail course but not much else. If anyone could help develop it that would be greatly apreciated. The link is here: http://en.wikiversity.org/wiki/Introductory_Esperanto#.5B.5BPortal:Learning_Materials.7CLearning_materials.5D.5D

Thanks

== Add some flare! ==

I was thinking, why not add a welcome page and some nice graphics, similar to [[Spanish]] and [[German]]? I think that a good first impression will make learning from this wikibook easier. [[User:Sandman85048|Sandman85048]] 21:49, 22 September 2007 (UTC)

== Merge introduction ==

The introduction section is in all these tiny little bits.. why not just put them in one page and set up redirects? [[User:Sandman85048|Sandman85048]] 23:02, 22 September 2007 (UTC)

== Translated navigation??? ==

This book is intended to be for English speakers (anything else belongs in other language versions of Wikibooks) who don't know any Esperanto yet and wish to learn it. Hence, we can't have the navigation in Esperanto, because they won't understand it and will leave these pages discouraged from learning Esperanto. Not to mention that with the current translations, Esperanto speakers won't easily understand the items either...
[[User:Junesun|Junesun]] 18:38, 11 October 2007 (UTC)

That's a good idea, my friend. Japanese is difficult enough for me to learn; since I'm now tackling an artificial language, baby steps are necessary here. --[[Special:Contributions/74.130.244.188|74.130.244.188]] ([[User talk:74.130.244.188|talk]]) 21:53, 22 October 2008 (UTC)

== Renaming pages ==

The [[Wikibooks:Manual_of_Style|manual of style]] frowns on naming pages as we have done here. I am going to go through renaming all &quot;lesson&quot; and &quot;appendix&quot; pages properly. All &quot;lesson&quot; pages are going to be renamed from, for example, &lt;tt&gt;Esperanto/Lesson 1&lt;/tt&gt; to &lt;tt&gt;Esperanto/Introducing yourself&lt;/tt&gt; (with English titles like &quot;Introducing yourself&quot; rather than Esperanto ones like &quot;Enkonduko&quot; because this is the English Wikibooks) - and then I will turn &lt;tt&gt;Esperanto/Lesson 1&lt;/tt&gt; into a redirect to &lt;tt&gt;Esperanto/Introducing yourself&lt;/tt&gt;. All &quot;appendix&quot; pages are going to be renamed from, for example, &lt;tt&gt;Esperanto/Appendix A&lt;/tt&gt; to &lt;tt&gt;Esperanto/Appendix/Esperanto alphabet and pronunciation&lt;/tt&gt;, along with a redirect. This is the total list of changes I will make:

* Lessons
*# &lt;tt&gt;Lesson 1&lt;/tt&gt; → &lt;tt&gt;Introducing yourself&lt;/tt&gt;
*# &lt;tt&gt;Lesson 2&lt;/tt&gt; → &lt;tt&gt;Travelling&lt;/tt&gt;
*# &lt;tt&gt;Lesson 3&lt;/tt&gt; → &lt;tt&gt;Recreational activities&lt;/tt&gt;
*# &lt;tt&gt;Lesson 4&lt;/tt&gt; → &lt;tt&gt;Family&lt;/tt&gt;
*# &lt;tt&gt;Lesson 5&lt;/tt&gt; → &lt;tt&gt;School&lt;/tt&gt;
*# &lt;tt&gt;Lesson 6&lt;/tt&gt; → &lt;tt&gt;Shopping&lt;/tt&gt;
*# &lt;tt&gt;Lesson 7&lt;/tt&gt; → &lt;tt&gt;Household&lt;/tt&gt;
*# &lt;tt&gt;Lesson 8&lt;/tt&gt; → &lt;tt&gt;Esperanto culture&lt;/tt&gt;
*# &lt;tt&gt;Lesson 9&lt;/tt&gt; → &lt;tt&gt;World Congress&lt;/tt&gt;
*# &lt;tt&gt;Lesson 10&lt;/tt&gt; → &lt;tt&gt;Word synthesis&lt;/tt&gt;
* Appendices
*# &lt;tt&gt;Appendix A&lt;/tt&gt; → &lt;tt&gt;Appendix/Alphabet and pronunciation&lt;/tt&gt;
*# &lt;tt&gt;Appendix B&lt;/tt&gt; → &lt;tt&gt;Appendix/Solutions to exercises&lt;/tt&gt;
*# &lt;tt&gt;Appendix C&lt;/tt&gt; → &lt;tt&gt;Appendix/English-Esperanto word list&lt;/tt&gt;
*# &lt;tt&gt;Appendix D&lt;/tt&gt; → &lt;tt&gt;Appendix/Esperanto-English word list&lt;/tt&gt;
*# &lt;tt&gt;Appendix E&lt;/tt&gt; → &lt;tt&gt;Appendix/Abbreviations&lt;/tt&gt;
*# &lt;tt&gt;Appendix F&lt;/tt&gt; → &lt;tt&gt;Appendix/Summary of grammar&lt;/tt&gt;
*# &lt;tt&gt;Appendix G&lt;/tt&gt; → &lt;tt&gt;Appendix/Web resources&lt;/tt&gt;
*# &lt;tt&gt;Appendix H&lt;/tt&gt; → &lt;tt&gt;Appendix/Table of correlatives&lt;/tt&gt;
*# &lt;tt&gt;Appendix I&lt;/tt&gt; → &lt;tt&gt;Appendix/Table of word endings&lt;/tt&gt;
*# &lt;tt&gt;Appendix J&lt;/tt&gt; → &lt;tt&gt;Appendix/Table of affixes&lt;/tt&gt;
*# &lt;tt&gt;Appendix K&lt;/tt&gt; → &lt;tt&gt;Appendix/False friends&lt;/tt&gt;
*# &lt;tt&gt;Appendix L&lt;/tt&gt; → &lt;tt&gt;Appendix/Slang&lt;/tt&gt;
*# &lt;tt&gt;Appendix M&lt;/tt&gt; → &lt;tt&gt;Appendix/Common phrases&lt;/tt&gt;

The reasons for this, other than better conformance to the Wikibooks manual of style, should be painfully obvious I think. Lessons and appendices will be easy to add, remove and shuffle around (and clearly some shuffling is needed - why is &quot;World Congress&quot; a lesson? Are we going to be tested on it? &quot;Esperanto culture&quot; and &quot;World Congress&quot; should probably come ''after'' the lessons, after the language is taught and now you're discussing the culture). I'll be making this change sometime in February probably, or maybe March - unless I get a lot of negative feedback before then. --[[User:Indiana|Indiana]] ([[User talk:Indiana|talk]]) 21:08, 1 February 2010 (UTC)
:Sounds like a good idea. --[[User:Yair rand|Yair rand]] ([[User talk:Yair rand|talk]]) 21:15, 1 February 2010 (UTC)

== Move worksheets to Wikiversity? ==

What do people think of the possibility of moving the worksheet-like sections to Wikiversity, and linking to them from within the appropriate section in the Wikibook? For example, we could remove the [[Esperanto/Introducing_yourself#Exercise : Translation|Exercise : Translation]] section from the first lesson, add something like [[v:User:Yair rand/eobooksandbox|this]] to Wikiversity, and link to that from the first lesson. --[[User:Yair rand|Yair rand]] ([[User talk:Yair rand|talk]]) 23:49, 18 February 2010 (UTC)

:I think that's a great idea. Once I finish souping up the appendices, I intend to start on the lessons themselves, and I did intend to trim out the exercises. But if this textbook could have an associated course on Wikiversity, that would be even better. Would you like to talk about a lesson plan? I mean, not right away because I have to finish with the appendices first, but eventually we'll need a plan for the lessons - right now they're organized based on some other language textbook, but that's not really appropriate for Esperanto (when are you ever going to need to buy a plane ticket in Esperanto?). It would be cool if we could figure out a workable lesson plan for the Wikibook, and have exercises and lessons mirrored in Wikiversity, so that while either could stand alone, they work even better together. --[[User:Indiana|Indiana]] ([[User talk:Indiana|talk]]) 18:14, 11 March 2010 (UTC)

== Book layout ==

I have created a [[Esperanto/Manual of style|manual of style]] for this Wikibook (feel free to discuss that [[Talk:Esperanto/Manual of style|there]]). As I mentioned there, I think we need to talk about how to organize the main body of this book (thus far, all of my work has been souping up the [[Esperanto/Appendix|appendices]], which I will continue to do, of course). What should the book's layout be (Are we going to have a preface? A brief grammar intro before the in depth lessons?)? What should the lessons be like (How should grammar elements be introduced, and in what order? Should there be a consistent story to keep readers engaged, or isolated dialogues?)? --[[User:Indiana|Indiana]] ([[User talk:Indiana|talk]]) 03:51, 11 February 2010 (UTC)

==Rewrite==
I'm working on a rewrite of this wikibook, as it has been incomplete for several years. I plan to present topics in this order. Feel free to suggest a different order.

*Lesson 1
**Nouns
**Adjectives
**Adverbs
**Personal and possessive pronouns
**Direct and indirect objects
**Prepositional phrases
*Lesson 2
**Infinitive
**Simple tenses/Active Voice
**Conditional mood
**Imperative mood
**Active and passive participles
**Questions
*Lesson 3
**Correlatives
**Participles as adverbs and nouns
*Lesson 4
**Word building with affixes
**Compound words
**Changing part of speech
*Lesson 5
**Complex tenses formed with participles

{{User:Swfarnsworth/Signature}} 20:01, 3 December 2011 (UTC)

I can only say that I strongly support your idea! --[[User:Leefeni,de Karik|Leefeni,de Karik]] ([[User talk:Leefeni,de Karik|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Leefeni,de Karik|contribs]]) 22:08, 8 December 2011 (UTC)

==Dialogues==

I'm thinking about creating a session only for small talk in Esperanto, and this is the first one I've made. I think you could help with more.

* [[Esperanto/Dialogues/Bus stop]]

--[[User:Leefeni,de Karik|Leefeni,de Karik]] ([[User talk:Leefeni,de Karik|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Leefeni,de Karik|contribs]]) 22:08, 8 December 2011 (UTC)

::I just added a section (in outline form) for Esperanto and electronic communication. This is a place to cover SMS texts, Tweets, and Email as translation exercises&amp;mdash;both into and out of EO. I think it's an excellent place to cover slang various abbreviation.  

I should mention, the bus stop dialogues are good, they should be integrated into the book. [[User:Wikijeff|Wikijeff]] ([[User talk:Wikijeff|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Wikijeff|contribs]]) 01:09, 8 June 2012 (UTC)

== Growing beyond the book format ==

My name is Ian and I'm from a project called Wikiotics, where we build free software tools for language instruction. We are starting to build collections of interactive language lessons that can serve as textbook replacements for students and this we would love for the Esperanto community to be represented.

If there is anyone here who is interested in expanding this content beyond a traditional text-based book format or who would like to incorporate interactive lessons we build based on the outline of this book, just chime in here or contact us at contact AT wikiotics DOT org or in irc at #wikiotics on freenode. 

As example of the kind of new materials you can make with our tools, here are examples our current lesson types:
* Picture choice lesson (http://wikiotics.org/en/Introduction), 
* Re-mixable Podcast (http://wikiotics.org/user/ian/FSI-Mandarin-Module01-Unit01), 
* Text multiple choice lesson (http://wikiotics.org/en/WANY_Hospital_grammar) 
* new Storybook lesson [''coming soon''](http://laurent.dev.wikiotics.net/en/storybook1).

[[User:Wikiotics|Wikiotics]] ([[User talk:Wikiotics|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Wikiotics|contribs]]) 19:53, 13 June 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>ozbe5mgkv46p9nz0r8c2hzm2w3damk2</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>French</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>771</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2486549</id>
      <parentid>2262227</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-02-10T18:41:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Belteshazzar</username>
        <id>333751</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>As long as this template exists, it belongs here</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Former featured book}}
__NOTOC__
{{French/Project|width=95%|showcontents=false|compact=true}}
== Lessons ==
{{:French/Lessons}}

== Texts ==
{{:French/Texts}}

== Further study ==
{{French/Grammar|width=95%|showcontents=false|compact=true}}
{{French/Vocabulary|width=95%|showcontents=false|compact=true}}
{{French/Appendices|width=95%|showcontents=false|compact=true}}

== Information and resources ==
{{Subject box|French language}}
: ''This book has a [[Wikibooks:Collections/French|collection]], a [[:Media:French.pdf|PDF version]], and a [[French/Print version|print version]].''
{{category 1}}
* [[Louisiana French]]
* [[French For Football]]
&lt;noinclude&gt;
{{Subjects|French language}}
{{alphabetical|F}}
{{status|75%}}

[[es:Francés]]
[[de:Französisch]]
[[fr:Français]]
[[it:Francese]]
[[he:צרפתית]]
[[ja:フランス語]]
[[nl:Frans]]
[[pl:Francuski]]
[[pt:Francês]]
[[sv:Franska]]
[[zh:法语]]

[[Category:Books with Public Collections|French]]
[[Category:Books with PDF version|French]]
[[Category:Books with print version|French]]
&lt;/noinclude&gt;</text>
      <sha1>kn9mmkqhg0e3izd4pjgg4c8e1gr4lvi</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>French/Lessons/Introductory/Review</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>772</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2521854</id>
      <parentid>2521853</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-05-06T23:27:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Fort123</username>
        <id>949489</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* V: The days of the week. */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;noinclude&gt;{{French/Lessons/Introductory/Header||||.}}&lt;/noinclude&gt;

==G: The French alphabet==
{| {{French/Table|Grammar|The French Alphabet|L'alphabet français||27}}
|-
!Characters
|Aa||Bb||Cc||Dd||Ee||Ff||Gg||Hh||Ii||Jj||Kk||Ll||Mm
|-
!Pronunciation
|ah||bay||say||day||uh||ehf||zhay||ahsh||ee||zhee||kah||ehl||ehm
|-
!Characters
|Nn||Oo||Pp||Qq||Rr||Ss||Tt||Uu||Vv||Ww||Xx||Yy||Zz
|-
!Pronunciation
| ehn || oh ||pay||kew||ehr||ehs||tay||ew||vay||doo-bluh-vay||eeks||ee-grehk||zehd
|}

In addition, French uses several accents which are worth understanding. These are: à, è, ù, (grave accents) and é (acute accent). A circumflex applies to all vowels: â, ê, î, ô, û. A tréma (French for dieresis) is also applied: ä, ë, ï, ö, ü, ÿ. Two combined letters are used: æ and œ, and a cedilla is used on the c to make it sound like an English s: ç.

==V: Basic phrases==

{| {{French/Table|Vocabulary|Basic Phrases|Les expressions de base||2}}
|bonjour, salut||hello (formal), hi (informal)
|-
|Comment allez-vous ? (formal),&lt;br&gt; Comment vas-tu ? (informal),&lt;br&gt; Comment ça va ? / Ça va ? (informal)|| (lit: How you go/How it goes?)
|-
|ça va (très) bien||I'm doing (very) well (lit. It goes (very) well)
|-
|merci||thank you
|-
|et toi ? et vous ?||and you? (informal) and you? (formal)
|-
|pas mal||not bad
|-
|bien||well
|-
|pas si bien/pas très bien||not so well
|-
|comme ci, comme ça ||so-so
|-
|Désolé(e)||I'm sorry.
|-
|quoi de neuf ?||what's up with you? (lit. what's new)
|-
|pas grand-chose||not much (lit. no big-thing)
|-
|au revoir||bye
|-
|à demain||see you tomorrow (lit. at tomorrow)
|-
|à plus tard||see you later
|-
|Au revoir, à demain.||Bye, see you tomorrow 
|}
{{newpage}}

==V: Numbers==

{| {{French/Table|Vocabulary|Numbers|Les nombres||3}}
|-
| un || 1 || une unité (a unity)
|-
| deux || 2 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| trois || 3 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| quatre || 4 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| cinq || 5 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| six || 6 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| sept || 7 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| huit || 8 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| neuf || 9 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| dix || 10 || une dizaine (one ten)
|-
| onze || 11 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| douze || 12 || une douzaine (one dozen)
|-
| treize || 13 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| quatorze || 14 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| quinze|| 15 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| seize|| 16 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| dix-sept|| 17 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| dix-huit || 18 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| dix-neuf|| 19 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| vingt || 20 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| vingt et un || 21 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| vingt [deux - neuf] || 22-29 || 
|-
| trente || 30 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| trente et un || 31 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| trente [deux - neuf] || 32-39 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| quarante || 40 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| cinquante || 50 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| soixante || 60 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| soixante-dix || 70 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| soixante et onze || 71 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| soixante-[douze - dix-neuf] || 72-79 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| quatre-vingts || 80 || &amp;nbsp;
|- 
| quatre-vingt-un || 81 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| quatre-vingt-[deux - neuf] || 82-89 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| quatre-vingt-dix || 90 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| quatre-vingt-[onze - dix-neuf] || 91-99 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| cent || 100 || une centaine (one hundred)
|-
| [deux - neuf] cents || 200-900 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| deux cent un || 201 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| neuf cent un || 901 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| mille || 1.000 || un millier (one thousand)
|-
| (un) million || 1.000.000 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| (un) milliard || 1.000.000.000 || &amp;nbsp;
|-
| (un) billion || 1.000.000.000.000 || &amp;nbsp;
|}

====Things of note about numbers:====

*For 70-79, it builds upon &quot;soixante&quot; but past that it builds upon a combination of terms for 80-99
*Only the first (21,31,41,51,61 and 71, but not 81 nor 91) have &quot;et un&quot; without a hyphen; but past this it is simply both words consecutively (vingt-six, trente-trois, etc.) with a hyphen in between.
*For 100-199, it looks much like this list already save that &quot;cent&quot; is added before the rest of the number; this continues up to 1000 and onward.

==V: Asking for the day/date/time==
{| {{French/Table|Vocabulary|Asking For The Day, Date, Time|Demander le jour, la date, le temps||4}}
! colspan=4 | Asking for the day.
|-
| 1a ||Aujourd'hui c'est quel jour?||Today is what day?||(''oh-zhur-dewee seh kehl zhoor'')
|-
| 1b ||Aujourd'hui c'est [''jour''].||Today is [''day''].||
|-
| 2a ||Demain c'est quel jour||Tomorrow is what day?||(''duh-ma&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt; seh kehl zhoor'')
|-
| 2b ||Demain c'est [''jour''].||Tomorrow is [''day''].||
|-
! colspan=4 | Asking for the date.
|-
| 3a ||Quelle est la date&lt;br&gt;(aujourd'hui)?||What is the date&lt;br&gt;(today)?||(''kehl eh lah daht'')
|-
| 3b ||C'est le [#] [month].||It's [month] [#].||
|-
! colspan=4 | Asking for the time.
|-
| 4a ||Quelle heure est-il?
| rowspan=2 | What hour/time is it?
| (''kehl ewr eh-teel'')
|-
| 4b ||Il est quelle heure?||(''eel eh kehl ewr'')
|-
| 5 ||Il est [nombre] heure(s).||It is [''number''] hours.||(''eel eh [nombre] ewr'')
|}

==V: Time==

In French, “il est” is used to express the time; though it would literally translate as “he is”, it is actually, in this case, equivalent to “it is” (unpersonal &quot;il&quot;). Unlike in English, it is always important to use “heures” (“hours”) when referring to the time. In English, it is OK to say, “It’s nine,” but this wouldn’t make sense in French.  The French time system traditionally uses a 24 hour scale.  Shorthand for writing times in French follows the format &quot;17h30&quot;, which would represent 5:30PM in English.

{| {{French/Table|Vocabulary|Time|Le temps||2}}
|Quelle heure est-il ?||What time is it?
|-
|Il est une heure.||It is one o’clock.
|-
|Il est trois heures.||It is three o’clock.
|-
|Il est dix heures.||It is ten o’clock.
|-
|Il est midi.||It is noon.
|-
|Il est minuit.||It is midnight.
|-
|Il est quatre heures cinq.||It is five past four.
|-
|Il est quatre heures et quart.||It is a quarter past four.
|-
|Il est quatre heures quinze.||It is four fifteen.
|-
|Il est quatre heures et demie.||It is half past four.
|-
|Il est dix-neuf heures moins le quart.||It is a quarter to seven, or six forty-five.
|-
|Il est quatre heures trente.||It is four thirty.
|-
|Il est cinq heures moins vingt.||It is twenty to five.
|-
|Il est quatre heures quarante.||It is four forty.
|}

==V: The days of the week.==

{| {{French/Table|Vocabulary|The days of the week|Les jours de la semaine|audio=French Vocabulary - The Days of the Week..ogg|columns=4}}
! colspan=1| French || Pronunciation || English || Origin
|-
| lundi || {{fr/IPA|/lœ̃di/|approx=luh&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;-dee}} || Monday || {{French/sec|(Moon)}}
|-
| mardi || {{fr/IPA|/maʁdi/|approx=mahr-dee}} || Tuesday || {{French/sec|(Mars)}}
|-
| mercredi || {{fr/IPA|/mɛʁkʁədi/|approx=mehr-kruh-dee}} || Wednesday || {{French/sec|(Mercury)}}
|-
| jeudi || {{fr/IPA|/ʒødi/|approx=zhur-dee}} || Thursday || {{French/sec|(Jupiter)}}
|-
| vendredi || {{fr/IPA|/vɑ̃dʁədi/|approx=vah&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;-druh-dee}} || Friday || {{French/sec|(Venus)}}
|-
| samedi || {{fr/IPA|/samdi/|approx=sahm-dee}} || Saturday || {{French/sec|(Saturn)}}
|-
| dimanche || {{fr/IPA|/dimɑ̃ʃ/|approx=dee-mah&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;sh}} || Sunday || {{French/sec|(Dies Domini)}}
|}

*The days of the week are not capitalized in French.
*For phrases relating to the day of the week, see [[French/Vocabulary/Travel/Phrases|the phrasebook]].

Notes:
* ''What day is it today?'' is equivalent to ''Quel jour sommes-nous ?''.
* ''Quel jour sommes-nous ?'' can be answered with ''Nous sommes...'', ''C'est...'' or ''On est...'' (last two are less formal).
* ''Nous sommes...'' is not used with ''hier'', ''aujourd’hui'', or ''demain''. ''C'était'' (past) or ''C'est'' (present/future) must be used accordingly.

==V: The months of the year==

{| {{French/Table|Vocabulary|The months of the year|Les mois de l'année|audio=French Vocabulary - The Months of the Year.ogg|columns=3}}
! colspan=1| French || Pron. || English 
|-
| janvier || {{fr/IPA|/ʒɑ̃vje/|approx=zhah&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;-vyay}} || January
|-
| février || {{fr/IPA|/fevʁije/|approx=fay-vree-yay}} || February
|-
| mars || {{fr/IPA|/maʁs/|approx=mahrs}} || March
|-
| avril || {{fr/IPA|/avʁil/|approx=ahv-reel}} || April
|-
| mai || {{fr/IPA|/mɛ/|approx=meh}} || May
|-
| juin || {{fr/IPA|/ʒɥɛ̃/|approx=zhoo-a&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;}} || June
|-
| juillet || {{fr/IPA|/ʒɥijɛ/|approx=zhoo-ee-yeh}} || July
|-
| août || {{fr/IPA|/ut/|/u/|approx=oot/oo}} || August
|-
| septembre || {{fr/IPA|/sɛptɑ̃bʁ/|approx=sehp-tah&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;-br}} || September
|-
| octobre || {{fr/IPA|/ɔktɔbʁ/|approx=ohk-toh-br}} || October
|-
| novembre || {{fr/IPA|/nɔvɑ̃bʁ/|approx=noh-vah&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;-br}} || November
|-
| décembre || {{fr/IPA|/desɑ̃bʁ/|approx=day-sah&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;-br}} || December
|}

==V: Relative date and time==

{| {{French/Table|Vocabulary|Relative Date and Time|Date et heure relatives|columns=2}}
! colspan=2 | Times of Day
|-
|le lever du jour||daybreak&lt;br&gt;lit:the rise of the day
|-
|le lever du soleil||sunrise&lt;br&gt;lit: the rise of the sun
|-
|le soleil levant||rising sun.
|-
|le matin||morning
|-
|...du matin||A.M., lit: of the mornng
|-
|hier matin||yesterday morning
|-
|le midi ||noon, midday
|-
|l'après-midi (m)||afternoon
|-
|le soir||evening, in the evening
|-
|...du soir||P.M. lit: of the evening
|-
|le coucher du soleil||sunset
|-
|la nuit||night
|-
! colspan=2 | Relative Days
|-
|avant-hier||the day before yesterday
|-
|hier||yesterday
|-
|aujourd'hui||today
|-
|ce soir||tonight
|-
|demain||tomorrow
|-
|après-demain||the day after tomorrow
|}

==V: Seasons==

{| {{French/Translations table|Vocabulary|The Seasons|Les Saisons|audio=French Vocabulary - Seasons.ogg}}
| la saison || {{fr/IPA|/la sɛ.zɔ̃/|approx=lah seh-zoh&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;}} || season
|-
| le printemps || {{fr/IPA|/lə pʁɛ̃.tɑ̃/|approx=luh pra&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;-taw&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;|audio=Fr-printemps.ogg}} || Spring
|-
| l'été {{fr/sec|(m)}} || {{fr/IPA|/le.te/|approx=lay-tay}} || Summer
|-
| l'automne {{fr/sec|(m)}} || {{fr/IPA|/lo.tɔn/|approx=loh-tawn}} || Autumn
|-
| l'hiver {{fr/sec|(m)}} || {{fr/IPA|/li.vɛʁ/|approx=lee-vehr}} || Winter
|}
{{newpage}}

== {{French/Section|Dialogue|A conversation between friends|Une conversation entre amis}} ==

{| {{French/Dialogue|includestranslations=true|audio=A conversation between friends.ogg}}
| rowspan=2 | Daniel
| Bonjour Hervé. Comment vas-tu ?
|-
| Hello, Hervé. How are you?
|-
| rowspan=2 | Hervé
| Je vais bien, merci. Et toi ça va ?
|-
| I'm good,{{ref|1|1}} thank you. And you, it goes (fine)?
|-
| rowspan=2 | Daniel
| Ça va bien. Est-ce que{{ref|2|2}} tu viens à mon anniversaire ? J'organise une petite fête.
|-
| It goes well. You're coming to my party? I'm organizing a little party.
|-
| rowspan=2 | Hervé
| C'est quand ?
|-
| When is it?
|-
| rowspan=2 | Daniel
| Le 3 mars à 20h.
|-
| March 3rd at 08:00 PM.
|-
| rowspan=2 | Hervé
| Le 3 mars, entendu. Tu fais ça chez toi{{ref|3|3}} ?
|-
| March 3rd, agreed. You're having it at your place?
|-
| rowspan=2 | Daniel
| Oui c'est chez moi. J'ai invité une vingtaine d'amis. On va danser toute la nuit.
|-
| Yes, it's at my place. I have invited (a set of) twenty friends. We{{ref|4|4}} are going to dance all night.
|-
| rowspan=2 | Hervé
| C'est très gentil de m'inviter, merci. A bientôt.
|-
| It's very nice to invite me, thank you. So long.
|-
| rowspan=2 | Daniel
| A demain, bonne journée.
|-
| Until tomorrow, good day.
|}

{{note|1|1}} ''Bien...'' is an adverb meaning ''well''. Its adjective equivalent is ''bon(ne)'', which means ''good''. Since ''je vais'', meaning ''I go'', uses an action verb,&lt;br&gt;
the adverb ''bien'' is used. In English, I'm good, which uses the linking verb ''am'', is followed by an adjective rather than an adverb.
&lt;p&gt;
{{note|2|2}} ''Est-ce que...'' doesn't mean anything (like the spanish upside down question mark) and is used to start a question.&lt;br&gt;
This can be used in a similar manner to ''do'' in English. Instead of ''You want it?'', one can say ''Do you want it?''
&lt;p&gt;
{{note|3|3}} ''chez...'' is a preposition meaning ''at the house of...''. ''Chez moi'' is used to say ''at my place''. ''Chez [''name'']'' is used to say ''at [''name'''s] place''. 
&lt;p&gt;
{{note|4|4}} ''on...'' can mean ''we'' or ''one''.
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;noinclude&gt;{{French/Lessons/Introductory}}[[Category:French/Lessons/Introductory| Review]]&lt;/noinclude&gt;</text>
      <sha1>inn04db9lsq5mlrjsfwqe9xdiks8kq6</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Esperanto/Appendix/Alphabet and pronunciation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>778</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2594875</id>
      <parentid>2515576</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-12-20T12:02:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>81.62.189.199</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Pronunciation */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">== Alphabet ==

The Esperanto alphabet has 28 letters.

;Uppercase
:A, B, C, Ĉ, D, E, F, G, Ĝ, H, Ĥ, I, J, Ĵ, K, L, M, N, O, P, R, S, Ŝ, T, U, Ŭ, V, Z
;Lowercase
:a, b, c, ĉ, d, e, f, g, ĝ, h, ĥ, i, j, ĵ, k, l, m, n, o, p, r, s, ŝ, t, u, ŭ, v, z
;Names
:a, bo, co, ĉo, do, e, fo, go, ĝo, ho, ĥo, i, jo, ĵo, ko, lo, mo, no, o, po, ro, so, ŝo, to, u, ŭo, vo, zo

Four letters from the English alphabet have been dropped &amp;ndash; '''Q''', '''W''', '''X''' and '''Y''' &amp;ndash; and there are six new accented letters: '''Ĉ''', '''Ĝ''', '''Ĥ''', '''Ĵ''', '''Ŝ''' and '''Ŭ'''.
The first five have an angle-shape accent called a ''circumflex'' ('''^''') over them, whilst the last has an accent rather like the bottom part of a circle, which is called a ''breve'' ('''˘''').

All of the accented letters are unique to Esperanto except for ''ŭo'' ('''Ŭ'''), which also exists in Belarusian, and ''ĝo'' ('''Ĝ'''), which also exists in Aleut.
Some of the accented letters may be used in transcription systems for languages that use non-Latin alphabets.
(For example, ''ŝo'' ('''Ŝ''') is used as the ISO 9:1995 transliteration of the Russian Cyrillic letter ''shcha'' ('''Щ''').)

=== Vowels ===

As in English, five letters are vowels ('''A''', '''E''', '''I''', '''O''', '''U'''), and the rest are consonants.
The letter ''ŭo'' ('''Ŭ''') is a consonant, not a vowel.&lt;!-- Note: maybe add sidebar about semivowels? --&gt;

=== Collation ===

Collation in Esperanto is the same as for English, except that the accented characters are counted as separate characters and collated after their non-accented versions.
Collation is as shown in the table above.

== Pronunciation ==

Each letter in Esperanto has only one pronunciation (allowing for cultural variation), and no letters are silent.
There are six dipthongs (see [[#Dipthongs|the next section]]), but their pronunciation follows logically from their constituent letters, except for being shortened into a single syllable.
This means that Esperanto is pronounced just as it is spelled.

Also, each sound has only one way of being written, so it is very easy to spell Esperanto words you hear.

The technical description for these traits is that Esperanto is ''phonetic'' and ''orthographic''.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!rowspan=&quot;2&quot; |Letter
!rowspan=&quot;2&quot; |[[w:International Phonetic Alphabet|IPA]]
!rowspan=&quot;2&quot; |Sound
!colspan=&quot;3&quot; |Example
!rowspan=&quot;2&quot; |Notes
|-
!Esperanto
!Phonetic
!English
|-
!colspan=&quot;7&quot; |Vowels
|-
|A
|[[w:Open front unrounded vowel|{{IPA|a}}]], [[w:Open back unrounded vowel|{{IPA|ɑ}}]]
|ah, as in f'''a'''ther
|{{lang eo|'''a'''miko}}
|ah-MI-koh
|friend
|
|-
|E
|[[w:Close-mid front unrounded vowel|{{IPA|e}}]], [[w:Open-mid central unrounded vowel|{{IPA|ɜ}}]]
|eh, as in b'''e'''t
|{{lang eo|'''e'''gala}}
|eh-GAH-lah
|equal
|
|-
|I
|[[w:Close front unrounded vowel|{{IPA|i}}]]
|ee, as in m'''e'''
|{{lang eo|'''i'''deo}}
|ee-DEH-oh
|idea
|
|-
|O
|[[w:Close-mid back rounded vowel|{{IPA|o}}]], [[w:Open-mid back rounded vowel|{{IPA|ɔ}}]]
|oh, as in r'''o'''bot
|{{lang eo|'''o'''fta}}
|OH'F-tah
|common
|
|-
|U
|[[w:Close back rounded vowel|{{IPA|u}}]]
|oo, as in b'''oo'''t
|{{lang eo|'''u'''tila}}
|oo-TEE-lah
|useful
|
|-
!colspan=&quot;7&quot; |Consonants
|-
|B
|[[w:Voiced bilabial plosive|{{IPA|b}}]]
|b
|{{lang eo|'''b'''ela}}
|BEH-lah
|beautiful
|
|-
|C
|[[w:Voiceless alveolar affricate|{{IPA|t͡s}}]]
|ts
|{{lang eo|'''c'''elo}}
|TSEH-loh
|goal
|
|-
|Ĉ
|[[w:Voiceless postalveolar affricate|{{IPA|t͡ʃ}}]]
|ch
|{{lang eo|'''ĉ'''ielo}}
|chee-EH-loh
|sky
|
|-
|D
|[[w:Voiced alveolar plosive|{{IPA|d}}]]
|d
|{{lang eo|'''d'''iri}}
|DEE-ree
|to say
|
|-
|F
|[[w:Voiceless labiodental fricative|{{IPA|f}}]]
|f
|{{lang eo|'''f'''acila}}
|fah-TSEE-lah
|easy
|
|-
|G
|[[w:Voiced velar plosive|{{IPA|g}}]]
|hard g as in '''g'''o
|{{lang eo|'''g'''aja}}
|GAH-yah
|cheerful
|
|-
|Ĝ
|[[w:Voiced velar plosive|{{IPA|d͡ʒ}}]]
|j
|{{lang eo|'''ĝ'''usta}}
|JOOS-tah
|correct
|
|-
|H
|[[w:Voiceless glottal fricative|{{IPA|h}}]]
|h
|{{lang eo|'''h'''ela}}
|HEH-lah
|bright
|
|-
|Ĥ
|[[w:Voiceless velar fricative|{{IPA|x}}]]
|ch as in Scottish lo'''ch'''
|{{lang eo|e'''ĥ'''o}}
|E(HKX)-oh
|echo
|Depending on the context, it is sometimes replaced with '''h''' or '''k'''.
|-
|J
|[[w:Palatal approximant|{{IPA|j}}]]
|y
|{{lang eo|'''j'''una}}
|YOO-nah
|young
|
|-
|Ĵ
|[[w:Voiced postalveolar fricative|{{IPA|ʒ}}]]
|zh
|{{lang eo|'''ĵ'''us}}
|ZHOOS
|just, just now
|
|-
|K
|[[w:Voiced velar plosive|{{IPA|k}}]]
|k
|{{lang eo|'''k'''ara}}
|KAH-rah
|dear
|
|-
|L
|[[w:Alveolar lateral approximant|{{lang eo|l}}]]
|l
|{{lang eo|'''l'''onga}}
|LOHN-gah
|long
|
|-
|M
|[[w:Bilabial nasal|{{lang eo|m}}]]
|m
|{{lang eo|'''m'''ano}}
|MAH-noh
|hand
|
|-
|N
|[[w:Alveolar nasal|{{IPA|n}}]]
|n
|{{lang eo|'''n'''ova}}
|NOH-vah
|new
|
|-
|P
|[[w:Voiceless bilabial plosive|{{IPA|p}}]]
|p
|{{lang eo|'''p'''eni}}
|PEH-nee
|to try
|
|-
|R
|[[w:Alveolar tap|{{IPA|r}}]]
|r
|{{lang eo|'''r'''uĝa}}
|ROO-jah
|red
|Roll your tongue, as in Spanish.
|-
|S
|[[w:Voiceless alveolar fricative|{{IPA|s}}]]
|s
|{{lang eo|'''s'''uno}}
|SOO-noh
|sun
|
|-
|Ŝ
|[[w:Voiceless postalveolar fricative|{{IPA|ʃ}}]]
|sh
|{{lang eo|'''ŝ'''ipo}}
|SHEE-poh
|ship
|
|-
|T
|[[w:Voiceless alveolar plosive|{{IPA|t}}]]
|t
|{{lang eo|'''t'''empo}}
|TEHM-poh
|time
|
|-
|Ŭ
|[[w:Labio-velar approximant|{{IPA|w}}]]
|w
|colspan=&quot;3&quot; |
|This letter only appears in diphthongs. In the past it has been used to pronounce &quot;w&quot; in foreign words, but this has fallen out of favour.
|-
|V
|[[w:Voiced labiodental fricative|{{IPA|v}}]]
|v
|{{lang eo|'''v'''eni}}
|VEH-nee
|to come
|
|-
|Z
|[[w:Voiced alveolar fricative|{{IPA|z}}]]
|z
|{{lang eo|'''z'''orgi}}
|ZOHR-gee
|to care
|
|-
!colspan=&quot;7&quot; |Diphthongs
|-
|AJ
|{{IPA|aɪ̯}}
|&quot;aye&quot;
|{{lang eo|k'''aj'''}}
|KYE
|and
|
|-
|AŬ
|{{IPA|aʊ̯}}
|&quot;ow&quot;
|{{lang eo|ĉirk'''aŭ'''}}
|CHEER-cow
|around, approximately
|
|-
|EJ
|{{IPA|eɪ̯}}
|&quot;ey&quot;
|{{lang eo|pl'''ej'''}}
|PLAY
|most
|
|-
|EŬ
|{{IPA|eʊ̯}}
|&quot;euw&quot;
|{{lang eo|'''Eŭ'''ropo}}
|euw-ROH-poh
|Europe
|This is pronounced much like how Elmer Fudd pronounces the &quot;ew&quot; in &quot;vewwy (very)&quot;.
|-
|OJ
|{{IPA|oɪ̯}}
|&quot;oy&quot;
|{{lang eo|lingv'''oj'''}}
|LING-voy
|languages
|
|-
|UJ
|{{IPA|uɪ̯}}
|&quot;oo-ee&quot; as one syllable
|{{lang eo|ĉi'''uj'''}}
|CHEE-(oo'ee)
|all
|
|}

=== Stress ===

The stress on every word is put on the penultimate (second-to-last) syllable.

[[Category:Esperanto/Appendices|{{SUBPAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Alphabets]]</text>
      <sha1>5o7knawpsx46lsnlezbhbh7pnyoxjwa</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Esperanto/Introducing yourself</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>779</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2644889</id>
      <parentid>2601669</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-05-02T17:19:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>166.137.208.30</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Esperanto/nav|1}}
&lt;center&gt;'''Be sure to make use of the [[Esperanto/Appendix/Alphabet and pronunciation|pronunciation appendix]].'''&lt;/center&gt;
==Grammar==
Since Esperanto is a very regular language, all its rules can be applied universally without exceptions. This means Esperanto grammar concepts are much easier to understand than those of natural languages. In this first lesson, we shall examine how to form nouns, adjectives, and the present tense.

===Nouns===
In any language, ''nouns'' are words that designate a person, place, thing, idea, or quality. Some examples of nouns in English are: &quot;house&quot;, &quot;friends&quot;, &quot;cake&quot;, &quot;John&quot;, &quot;France&quot;, and &quot;gardens&quot;.

In Esperanto, all nouns end in '''-o'''. The part of the word that goes before the '''-o''' is known as the ''root''. For example, in the word '''urbo''' (city), '''urb-''' is the root and the '''-o''' makes it a noun.

To make a noun plural, add a '''-j''' to the end, for example '''urboj''' (cities).

Some examples of nouns in Esperanto: {{Esperanto/wt|homo}} (human), {{Esperanto/wt|domo}} (house), {{Esperanto/wt|amikoj}} (friends), {{Esperanto/wt|kuko}} (cake), {{Esperanto/wt|Johano}} (John), {{Esperanto/wt|Francio}} (France) and {{Esperanto/wt|ĝardenoj}} (gardens).

To say ''a'' or ''an'', as in &quot;a town&quot;, just say the noun on its own, e.g. '''urbo''' (town, a town).  There is no indefinite article (&quot;a&quot; or &quot;an&quot;) in Esperanto.

The word for ''the'' is '''la''', e.g. '''la urbo''' (the city). '''La''' never changes for singular or plural.

===Adjectives===
''Adjectives'' are words that describe a noun. Some English examples are: &quot;happy&quot;, &quot;tired&quot;, &quot;beautiful&quot;, &quot;young&quot; and &quot;fresh&quot;.

To change an Esperanto noun into its corresponding adjective, replace the '''-o''' with an '''-a'''. For example, '''urbo''' (town) gives rise to '''urba''' (urban, &quot;relating to a town&quot;). 

Some examples of adjectives in Esperanto: {{bt|wt|feliĉa}} (happy), {{bt|wt|laca}} (tired), {{bt|wt|bela}} (beautiful), {{bt|wt|juna}} (young) and {{bt|wt|freŝa}} (fresh).

In Esperanto, an adjective must &quot;agree in number&quot; with the noun it describes. This means that if the noun is singular, the adjective must also be. If the noun is plural, the adjective must also be, too. Some examples: '''la freŝa kuko''' (the fresh cake), '''la freŝaj kukoj''' (the fresh cakes); '''feliĉa homo''' (a happy person), '''feliĉaj homoj''' (happy people).

The prefix '''mal-''' changes an Esperanto word into its opposite meaning - a feature that greatly reduces the vocabulary. Here are some examples of '''mal-''' words in Esperanto: {{bt|wt|malfeliĉa}} (unhappy), {{bt|wt|mallaca}} (alert, not tired), {{bt|wt|malbela}} (ugly), {{bt|wt|maljuna}} (old) and {{bt|wt|malfreŝa}} (stale).

===Adverbs===
''Adverbs'' are words that describe a verb, an adjective, or another adverb. They indicate manner, place, time or quantity. Some English examples are: &quot;quickly&quot;, &quot;orally&quot;, &quot;at home&quot;, and &quot;in writing&quot;.

To change an Esperanto word into an adverb, replace the usual ending ('''-a''' for adjectives, '''-o''' for nouns, and '''-i''' for verbs) with '''-e'''. The meaning of the base word determines whether it becomes a manner, place, time or quantity adverb.
*'''Manner''' - How something is done, ''&quot;He runs '''quickly'''.&quot;'' ; ''&quot;He submitted it '''in writing'''.&quot;''
*'''Place''' - Where something is done, ''&quot;He runs '''at home'''.&quot;''
*'''Time''' - When something is done, ''&quot;He runs '''on Sunday'''.&quot;''
*'''Quantity''' - ''&quot;He runs '''a lot'''.&quot;''

Some examples of adverbs in Esperanto: {{bt|wt|rapide}} (quickly), {{bt|wt|buŝe}} (orally), {{bt|wt|hejme}} (at home), and {{bt|wt|skribe}} (in writing).

Please note that not all adverbs use this rule, but the overwhelming majority of them do. Once you are introduced to these adverbs, it will be obvious why they are exceptions.

===Personal pronouns===
In Esperanto there are ten personal pronouns. However, you will initially need to only know seven of these pronouns.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!colspan=&quot;2&quot;| Person
!Singular (one person) !!Plural (more than one)
|-
!colspan=&quot;2&quot;| First (the speaker)
|mi (I, me)
|ni (we, us)
|-
!colspan=&quot;2&quot;| Second (the listener)
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;| vi (you, you all)
|-
!rowspan=&quot;3&quot;| Third (somebody else)
! Masculine
| li (he, him)
|rowspan=&quot;3&quot;| ili (they, them)
|-
! Feminine
| ŝi (she, her)
|-
! Neuter
| ĝi (it)
|}

*The other pronouns (&quot;{{bt|wt|oni}}&quot;, &quot;{{bt|wt|si}}&quot;) will be covered later.
*&quot;{{bt|wt|Ci}}&quot;, a pronoun translated &quot;[[wiktionary:thou|thou]]&quot;, is rarely used.
*The third person neuter singular pronoun, &quot;ĝi&quot;, is not exactly the same as the English &quot;it&quot; because it can be used as a gender-neutral pronoun for a living person. For example, &quot;Look at that baby. I can't tell if '''it''' is a boy or a girl.&quot;

===Possessive pronouns===
To turn a personal pronoun into a possessive pronoun (which is an adjective), simply add an '''-a''' to the end.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Esperanto !! English
|-
| mia || my, mine
|-
| via || your, yours
|-
| ŝia || her, hers
|-
| lia || his
|-
| ĝia || its
|-
| nia || our, ours
|-
| ilia || their, theirs
|}

===Verbs - present tense===
The basic form of a verb is called its ''infinitive''. In English, this is the part of the verb that has &quot;to&quot; in front of it, as in the sentence &quot;John likes '''to play''' football&quot;. In Esperanto, the infinitive simply has an '''-i''' after the root, e.g. {{bt|wt|ludo}} (a game), {{bt|wt|ludi}} (to play).

The present tense has three forms in English. For example, one can say either &quot;I kick&quot;, &quot;I am kicking&quot; or &quot;I do kick&quot;; &quot;he laughs&quot;, &quot;he is laughing&quot;, &quot;he does laugh&quot;; &quot;Robert eats the cake&quot;, &quot;Robert is eating the cake&quot;, &quot;Robert does eat cake&quot;. All these forms are represented under one form in Esperanto.

To form the present tense of any Esperanto verb, simply substitute the '''-i''' in the root with '''-as'''. Some examples: '''mi legas''' (I am reading), '''li ridas''' (He is laughing), '''Roberto manĝas la kukon''' (Robert eats the cake).

You will also note that there is no verb conjugation in Esperanto for person. For example, in English you would say &quot;Bob eat'''s'''&quot;, &quot;I eat&quot;, and &quot;She eats&quot;; In Esperanto, you would use the same form of the verb: &quot;Bob manĝas&quot;, &quot;Mi manĝas&quot;, &quot;Ŝi manĝas&quot;.

===Objects and the accusative case===
Like in English, every complete declarative sentence in Esperanto requires at least two parts: a subject and a verb. In the sentence &quot;I ate&quot;, the subject is &quot;I&quot; and the verb is &quot;ate&quot;. A subject is a noun which performs an action. However, in the sentence &quot;I ate spaghetti&quot;, there is a third word: &quot;spaghetti&quot;. The word &quot;spaghetti&quot; in this sentence is what is known as a '''direct object'''. A direct object is a noun which is having an action performed on it. It is being &quot;verb'ed&quot;, so to speak.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Sentence !! Subject !! Verb !! Direct object
|-
| I ate spaghetti. || I || ate || spaghetti
|-
| The cat loves the dog. || the cat || loves || the dog
|-
| Bob punched John. || Bob || punched || John
|-
| Jennifer likes ponies. || Jennifer || likes || ponies
|-
| Frank gave Jane flowers. || Frank || gave || flowers
|}

Take special note of the last sentence. In the first three sentences, the direct object directly followed the verb. However, in the last sentence, the word &quot;Jane&quot; directly follows the verb &quot;gave&quot;. So why isn't Jane the direct object of the sentence? Because Jane is not having an action performed on her by the verb of the sentence, &quot;give&quot;. Frank is not giving Jane, Frank is giving flowers ''to Jane''. Since the flowers are what is being given, the flowers are the direct object.

So what is Jane in this sentence, then? Jane is what is known as an '''indirect object'''. An indirect object is a noun which is neither performing an action nor having an action performed directly upon it, but receiving the action of the verb less directly than the ''direct object'' (hence the name). In Esperanto, the indirect object will always take a preposition. For example, &quot;Frank baked '''Jane''' a cake&quot; becomes &quot;Frank baked a cake '''for Jane'''.&quot;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Sentence !! Subject !! Verb !! Direct object !! Indirect object
|-
| Frank gave Jane flowers || Frank || gave || flowers || (to) Jane
|-
| Mary wrote Susan a letter. || Mary || wrote || a letter || (for) Susan
|-
| Harry read Dr. Phillips the message. || Harry || read || the message || (to) Dr. Phillips
|-
| The war veteran tells schoolchildren his stories. || the war veteran || tells || his stories || (to) schoolchildren
|-
| The U.S. Constitution grants Americans Freedom of Speech. || the U.S. Constitution || grants || Freedom of Speech || (to) Americans
|}

In English, the order of the words in a sentence determine whether a noun is a subject, a direct object, or an indirect object. In English, the order is either &quot;subject, verb, direct object&quot; or &quot;subject, verb, indirect object, direct object&quot;. Esperanto, however, is more flexible. In order to make a direct object in Esperanto, one simply adds the letter &quot;n&quot; to the noun (if the noun is plural, the &quot;n&quot; is added after the &quot;j&quot;).

Therefore, in Esperanto, subjects, verbs, and direct objects can be put in any order! All of the following sentences, which mean &quot;the apple loves the banana&quot; are grammatically correct in Esperanto.
*La pomo amas la bananon.
*La pomo la bananon amas.
*Amas la pomo la bananon.
*Amas la bananon la pomo.
*La bananon la pomo amas.
*La bananon amas la pomo.

==Conversation - Introducing yourself==
{{Only in print|The translation of this dialogue is included at the end of the page for correcting your mistakes, if any.}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable collapsible&quot; align=&quot;right&quot;
!colspan=&quot;2&quot;|Vocabulary
|-
! Esperanto !! English
|-
| saluton || hello, hi
|-
| mia || my, mine
|-
| nomo || name
|-
| estas || am, are, is
|-
| kaj || and
|-
| via || your, yours
|-
| de || from, of
|-
| kie || where
|-
| venas || come, comes
|-
| en || in, at
|-
| Novjorko || New York
|-
| Usono || USA
|-
| Parizo || Paris
|-
| Francio || France
|-
| feliĉa || happy
|-
| amiko || friend
|-
| kuko || cake
|}

Two people - Jean and Frank - meet for the first time:
*''Frank'': Saluton! Mia nomo estas Frank. Kaj via?
*''Jean'': Saluton! Mi estas Jean. De kie vi venas?
*''Frank'': Mi venas de Novjorko, en Usono. Kaj vi?
*''Jean'': Mi venas de Parizo, en Francio.

{| class=&quot;wikitable collapsible collapsed noprint&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;
! Show translation
|-
|Two people - Jean and Frank - meet for the first time:
*''Frank'': Hello ! My name is Frank. And yours?
*''Jean'': Hi ! I am Jean. From where do you come? (Where do you come from?)
*''Frank'': I come from New York, in the U.S.A. And you?
*''Jean'': I come from Paris, in France.
|}

===Exercise: Translation===
{{Only in print|The translation of this dialogue is included at the end of the page for correcting your mistakes, if any.}}
#Translate the following Esperanto dialogue into English:
##*''Jonah'': Saluton! Mi estas Jonah. 
##*''Kelly'': Saluton, Jonah. Mi estas Kelly. Mi venas de Parizo, en Francio. Kaj vi?
##*''Jonah'': Mi venas de Novjorko. 
#Translate the sentences into Esperanto:
##The happy friends are Julie and Kelly.
##The beautiful cake is stale!
##He is sad.
#Translate the sentences into English:
##La ĝardenoj belaj estas malnovaj.
##Mia domo estas en la urbo.
##Iliaj domoj estas belaj.

{| class=&quot;wikitable collapsible collapsed noprint&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;
!Show answers
|-
|
#Translate the following Esperanto dialogue into English:
##*''Jonah'': Hello! I am Jonah.
##*''Kelly'': Hello, Jonah. I am Kelly. I come from Paris, in France. And you?
##*''Jonah'': I come from New York.
#Translate the sentences into Esperanto:
##La feliĉaj amikoj estas Julie kaj Kelly.
##La bela kuko estas malfreŝa!
##Li estas malfeliĉa.
#Translate the sentences into English:
##The beautiful gardens are old.
##My house is in the city.
##Their houses are beautiful.
|}

==Vocabulary==
===Phrases===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Esperanto !! English
|-
| &quot;Mia nomo estas...&quot; || &quot;My name is...&quot;
|-
| &quot;Mi estas...&quot; || &quot;I am...&quot;
|-
| &quot;Mi venas de...&quot; || &quot;I'm from...&quot; (&quot;I come from...&quot;)
|}

===Words===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Esperanto !! English
|-
| ami || to love
|-
| saluton || hello, hi
|-
| nomo || name
|-
| estas || am, are, is
|-
| kaj || and
|-
| de || of, from
|-
| kie || where
|-
| venas || come, comes
|-
| Novjorko || New York
|-
| Usono || USA
|-
| Parizo || Paris
|-
| Francio || France
|-
| mi || I, me
|-
| vi || you
|-
| li || he, him
|-
| ŝi || she, her
|-
| ĝi || it
|-
| ni || we, us
|-
| ili || they, them
|-
| mia || my, mine
|-
| via || your, yours
|-
| lia || his
|-
| ŝia || her, hers
|-
| ĝia || its, his/her, his/hers
|-
| nia || our, ours
|-
| ilia || their, theirs
|}

==What You Need to Know==
*All nouns in Esperanto end in &quot;-o&quot;
*All adjectives in Esperanto end in &quot;-a&quot;
*Most adverbs in Esperanto end in &quot;-e&quot;
*Personal pronouns are used to refer to people or things.
*To change a personal pronoun into a possessive pronoun, add &quot;-a&quot;.
*The infinitive form of verbs in Esperanto ends in &quot;-i&quot;.
*To change verbs to be in the present tense, remove the &quot;-i&quot; and add &quot;-as&quot;.
*Plurals end in &quot;-j&quot;.

==Extra vocabulary==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Esperanto !! English
|- 
| Germanio || Germany
|- 
| Britio || Britain
|- 
| Alĝerio || Algeria
|- 
| Hispanio || Spain
|- 
| Nederlando ||the Netherlands
|- 
| Italio || Italy
|- 
| Grekio || Greece
|- 
| Rusio || Russia
|- 
| Polio || Poland
|- 
| Belgio || Belgium
|- 
| Skandinavio || Scandinavia
|}              

{{Only in print|1=
==Translation Key==
===Frank and Jean===
*''Frank'': Hello! My name is Frank. And yours?
*''Jean'': Hi! I am Jean. From where do you come? (Where do you come from?)
*''Frank'': I come from New York, in the U.S.A. And you?
*''Jean'': I come from Paris, in France.

===Exercise: Translation===
#Translate the following Esperanto dialogue into English:
##*''Jonah'': Hello! I am Jonah.
##*''Kelly'': Hello, Jonah. I am Kelly. I come from Paris, in France. And you?
##*''Jonah'': I come from New York.
#Translate the sentences into Esperanto:
##La feliĉaj amikoj estas Julie kaj Kelly.
##La bela kuko estas malfreŝa!
##Li estas malfeliĉa.
#Translate the sentences into English:
##The beautiful gardens are old.
##My house is in the city.
##Their houses are beautiful.
}}

-----
{{Esperanto/nav|1}}</text>
      <sha1>ndf6sivpv7awntkv56d2hioiz2galnv</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Spanish/Dictionary</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>781</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1377545</id>
      <parentid>1377544</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-01-12T17:36:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>201.198.5.182</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Diccionarios Español-Ingles y Inglés-Español */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Diccionarios Español-Ingles y Inglés-Español==
*[[Wiktionary:Wiktionary:Spanish index|Wiktionary Spanish index]] (not much content yet, but together we can build it up)
*[http://education.yahoo.com/reference/dict_en_es/ Yahoo Spanish dictionary]
*[http://www.online-dictionary.biz/english/spanish Spanish dictionary]
*[http://www.diccionarios.com/ Diccionarios.com] (very limited translations per day)
*[http://www.wordreference.com/ Wordreference.com]
*[http://www.spanish-translator-services.com/dictionaries/ English Spanish Dictionaries]
*[http://www.wordmagicsoft.com/dictionary/tools/index.php Word Magic English Spanish Dictionary]
[[Category:Spanish]]</text>
      <sha1>lflvwuruq7655u3q5t6xgcix1zhy9c9</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:French/Lessons/Introductory/Review</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>782</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1867168</id>
      <parentid>1864526</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-06-28T23:13:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>replaced: {{WikiProject Languages}} → {{WikiProject Languages|french=yes}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{WikiProject Languages|french=yes}} 

Instead of ''Quelles sont les nouvelles ?'' I'd say ''Quoi de neuf ?'', which is more idiomatic. [[User:Dhum Dhum|Dhum Dhum]] 20:36, 22 Aug 2003 (UTC)
&lt;BR&gt;How to play the OGG audio file? I found that neither windows media play nor realone can play it.--[[User:21st centry fox|21st centry fox]]
:Winamp, for example
[[User:João Jerónimo|João Jerónimo]] 15:48, 8 Aug 2004 (UTC)

== The French Alphabet ==

Wouldn't it make more sense to simply say 'The French alphabet has the same letters as the English alphabet'? Given that the article is written in English, it seems pedantic to list the same characters the lesson is being written with.

:Well, it makes sense to show the alphabet since the pronunciation is different and this is what is highlighted. However, it is already part of the [[French/Lessons/Alphabet|Reading French]] Section, which makes it unnecessary to duplicate in this first lesson. --[[User:Jazz|Jazz]] 12:13, 2 August 2005 (UTC)

===W===
regarding the pronunciation of W, is there perhaps a better way of representing it other than the current dubl-vay. If I didn't know better, I feel I might read it as dubble-vay rather than the correct doob-le-vay. In fact, that seems to be an adequate way of communicating it, but I've neglected from changing it myself as I'm unaware if this is perhaps the standard form of communicating the sound and we're merely stuck with it as the norm. - &lt;strike&gt;Chris [[User:81.76.50.9|81.76.50.9]] 13:44, 23 January 2006 (UTC)&lt;/strike&gt; [[User:Chris|Chris]] 13:49, 23 January 2006 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>2icoq9xyhf9oktwxjrg648ia8cewot6</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>