<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>Myers-Briggs Type Indicator/Further reading</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4773</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2693605</id>
      <parentid>2593704</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-22T16:18:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Rotlink</username>
        <id>761486</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>fixing dead links</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{PersonalityTypeTOC}}

==In print==

* '''It Takes All Types: The Guide for Finding a Job, Changing Careers, and Understanding Yourself at Work''' by John J. Arnopp ISBN 1410760227
* '''Type Talk''' by Janet M. Thuesen and Otto Kroeger ISBN 0440507049
* '''Do What You Are: Discover the Perfect Career for You Through the Secrets of Personality Type''' by Paul D. Tieger and Barbara Barron-Tieger ISBN 0316880655
* '''Gifts Differing: Understanding Personality Type''' by Isabel Briggs Myers and Peter B. Myers ISBN 089106074X
* '''The Art of Speed Reading People''' by Paul D. Tieger and Barbara Barron-Tieger ISBN 0316845183
* '''YOU: Being More Effective In Your MBTI(R) Type''' by Roger R. Pearman, Michael M. Lombardo, and Robert W. Eichinger ISBN 0974589284
* '''I'm Not Crazy I'm Just Not You: The Real Meaning of the Sixteen Personality Types''' by Roger R. Pearman and Sarah C. Albritton. ISBN 0891060960

==On the web==

* [http://www.aptcentral.org/ The Association For Psychological Type]
* [http://www.systemsthinker.com/interests/mind/ptypes.shtml Howard's Personality Types Page]
* [http://keirsey.com/ Keirsey Temperament and Character Web Site]
* [http://greenlightwiki.com/lenore-exegesis The Lenore Thomson exegesis wiki: all about understanding a version of the psychological theory that inspired the Myers-Briggs test.]
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20010423054354/http://members.ozemail.com.au/~alchymia/library/history.html An MBTI History]
* [http://myersbriggs.org/ MyersBriggs.org]
* [http://www.humanmetrics.com/cgi-win/JTypes2.asp Online test based on Jung - Myers-Briggs typology]
* [http://www.typetango.com/help.php#1 What is personality theory?]

[[Category:Myers-Briggs Type Indicator]]</text>
      <sha1>s4193fuqkybs0r4f0dq0kv2tfsbsk5h</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Myers-Briggs Type Indicator/ISTJ</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4775</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1798961</id>
      <parentid>1791771</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-05-18T18:00:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>198.146.43.212</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Famous ISTJs */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{PersonalityTypeTOC}}

The Introverted Sensor Thinker Judger is a traditionally masculine personality type, detached, unexpressive, concrete, and not given to speculation.

==Famous ISTJs==
George H.W. Bush,
Harry Truman,
George Washington

==Working with an ISTJ==
ISTJ's are detail people.
You will mostly find them in technical service industries, including medical fields, accounting, police work, engineering, office managers, and so forth. 
They are keen sensors of their environments; tastes, smells, noise levels. They often prefer a quiet work environment, where they can concentrate and focus on the task at hand. They work slowly and methodically, and don't like to be rushed. They can be focused on keeping structure in order and feel most comfortable when everyone is doing what they are supposed to be doing. ISTJ's value their personal privacy, and like to remain professional. Due to their discreet and reserved nature, others may see them as snobbish or uptight. Often times they remain anonymous for achievements they have accomplished. They may be upset with people who don't follow the rules, honor their promises, or follow through, but may not say so publicly. Traits they may value among fellow coworkers are loyalty, friendliness, and a strong work ethic. They are usually willing to lend their help to others in need if they have time.

==ISTJs in relationships==

==Web links==

* [http://www.typetango.com/istj-personality.php ISTJ Profiles and Famous ISTJs on TypeTango]

[[Category:Myers-Briggs Type Indicator]]</text>
      <sha1>kkc6tekmm16o5452ybboibrxpimukm2</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Myers-Briggs Type Indicator/ENFP</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4777</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2710171</id>
      <parentid>2710152</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-05T04:24:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2600:1004:B015:4AC4:FD13:BC48:8B90:6C8B</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* ENFPs in relationships */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{PersonalityTypeTOC}}

ENFPs are outgoing and talkative types who often have many diverse friends. They are naturally irreverent, curious, good with words, creative, and even a bit artsy. They favor abstraction over detail and tend to flit from one activity to the next, deriving more pleasure from starting projects than from finishing them.

==ENFPs at work==

ENFPs are sponges of knowledge. Curiously collecting information about life's experiences as fodder for their own stories, they live their lives much like a dramatic character in a movie, delighting in finding irony and drama in life situations wherever they go. They interpret the data they gather from people and the world in the form of inner meanings, relationships, and possibilities, often recounting their ideas to people though conversation. They love to spread the word!
ENFPs, [[../NF/]]s, are interested in many different things and this often leads them in multiple directions, therefore they are known for changing jobs and even careers frequently. ENFPs prefer to make work fun and have been known to put off work when there is a chance to have fun. ENFPs prefer environments which have little administrative or detailed work. Delegation to reliable support staff is important for success. ENFPs seek out jobs not confined by strict schedules and mundane tasks. According to Keirsey, the &quot;Idealists&quot; want to make the world a better place to live by helping others and are on a search for their &quot;true self&quot;. Integrity, ideals, beliefs, and values matter to ENFPs. ENFP's practice and dream about being the best at what ever they seek to achieve. They want to KNOW everything!

ENFPs generally have the following traits:

    * Project-oriented
    * Bright and capable
    * Warmly, genuinely interested in people; great people skills
    * Extremely intuitive and perceptive about people
    * Able to relate to people on their own level
    * Service-oriented; likely to put the needs of others above their own
    * Future-oriented
    * Dislike performing routine tasks
    * Need approval and appreciation from others
    * Cooperative and friendly
    * Creative and energetic
    * Well-developed verbal and written communication skills
    * Natural leaders, but do not like to control people
    * Resist being controlled by others
    * Can work logically and rationally - use their intuition to understand the goal and work backwards towards it
    * Usually able to grasp difficult concepts and theories 
(from http://www.personalitypage.com/html/ENFP_car.html)

Common careers for ENFPs are those which allow flexibility and spontaneity while serving others. This includes teaching, general practice of medicine, medical research, religious fields, entrepreneurship, missionary work, social work, community development, creative arts, acting, broadcasting, consulting, coaching, corporate training, public relations, counseling, advertising, and marketing. They enjoy working for themselves and creating new ideas to help people. The perfect job for an ENFP is one where they would give out useful information to others and they would receive several hundred dollars per hour for that service.

==ENFPs in relationships==

'''Strengths'''

ENFPs are energized by being around people. ENFPs take their relationships very seriously. ENFPs seek and demand authenticity and depth in their personal relationships, and will put forth a lot of effort into making things work out. ENFPs are generally warm, considerate, affirming, nurturing, and highly invested in the health of the relationship. ENFPs have excellent interpersonal skills, and are able to inspire and motivate others to be the best that they can be. ENFPs are generally highly valued for their genuine warmth and high ideals.

ENFPs want to help, to be liked, and to be admired by other people on both an individual and a humanitarian level. ENFPs hold up their end of relationships, sometimes being victimized by less caring individuals.

'''Weaknesses'''

ENFPs are well aware of their weaknesses, often being their own harshest critic; they may sarcastically put themselves down before others do, because secretly they may expect to be humiliated.
Often the ENFP is reluctant to share intimate feelings unless in the company of deeply trusted relationships. Despite being extroverts, ENFPs require a great deal of alone time to center themselves. ENFPs are strongly influenced by the opinions of others. ENFPs can exhibit preoccupation in their relationships, sometimes putting &quot;all their eggs in one basket&quot; and can tend to hyper focus on the other individual, in attempts to &quot;fix&quot; the other person or pull out their &quot;real&quot; emotions, transforming them into the perfect person. ENFPs may feel very anxious and preoccupied if the other partner is silent, non expressive, or withdrawn when coping with stress, instead of talking through things. This can deeply hurt them. There often appears to be a silent pull of ENFPs to the wishes of authority figures, parents, and friends which may cause a dilemma as to loyalties and decision making. Although energetic and effervescent, the ENFP can sometimes be smothering in their enthusiasm. They do not understand why someone would not be charmed by their enthusiastic display of affection and quirky jokes, because most people find them entertaining and refreshing.
They may try too hard to be what others want them to be, play the role of actor and entertainer, and feel in danger of losing touch with their true authentic selves when they don't receive appreciation and feedback for who they really are.
ENFPs are often seen as disorganized, having a short attention span, takes on too many tasks at once, lacks structure, and all over the place.

==How to Behave Toward an ENFP==

Give ENFPs the freedom to be flexible. Realize that churning through possibilities inspires their minds and get their creative juices flowing. Don't bog the ENFP down with too many details, especially on any subject not known to be of deep interest to him or her. Involve the ENFP in the process and try to keep things fun.
When communicating with ENFPs you will find that many like to talk. Do not hesitate to interrupt and state your opinion. ENFPs enjoy speculating about ideas. They enjoy others who engage them in conversation, contribute their ideas and keep it moving in a positive direction. Overall ENFPs appreciate honesty in others, they want to know how people really feel. ENFPs are easily influenced by what other people say. It may not appear that they are listening when they are talking to you, but soon after the conversation ends they often ponder what the other person has said and incorporate those ideas into their own thinking to use the knowledge for the future.

The main points to remember, ENFPs: &lt;br&gt;
1) Want to help and please the people they are working with, so give them frequent feedback.&lt;br&gt;
2) Like to hear from their significant others that they are loved and valued, (and are willing and eager to return the favor,) so let them know what you appreciate about them. &lt;br&gt;
3) Prefer happy and upbeat relationships, nevertheless, when conflict occurs, they usually want to engage in a dialog to work it out.&lt;br&gt;
4) Are one of the most freedom orientated personality types. Give them room to have some adventures on their own.&lt;br&gt;
5) May have a difficult time staying focused and following things through to completion. Let them know clearly what your deadlines are. ENFPs want to please other people, so let them know how important it is to you and why it is important to you.&lt;br&gt;
6) Prefer a participative and collegial atmosphere in which employees are included in the decision making.

==Web links==

* [http://tech.groups.yahoo.com/group/enfp_haven/ ENFP Yahoo! group]
* [http://www.typelogic.com/enfp.html ENFP on TypeLogic]
* [http://www.personalitypage.com/ENFP.html ENFP on PersonalityPage] and [http://www.personalitypage.com/ENFP_car.html ENFP careers]
* [http://www.typetango.com/enfp-personality.php ENFP Profiles and Famous ENFPs on TypeTango]
{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>crvtpapg13ywz13un5qrf1ab25o1y9k</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Ilyanep</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>4778</id>
    <revision>
      <id>228066</id>
      <parentid>156466</parentid>
      <timestamp>2005-09-04T15:51:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>67.184.97.46</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">I'm a user/sysop/bureaucrat on Wikipedia, see my [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Ilyanep Userpage].

NOTE!!! Use my Wikipedia Talk page, because I won't be checking this one!</text>
      <sha1>teadlpea0h2pup5sevb8kyc173jwgff</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:Ilyanep</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>4779</id>
    <revision>
      <id>156467</id>
      <timestamp>2004-02-20T00:49:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ilyanep</username>
        <id>615</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Use my [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User_talk:Ilyanep Wikipedia talk page] please...</text>
      <sha1>t9d4xuzpuiukydf9z92yiow7rsq0lof</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Myers-Briggs Type Indicator/NF</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4780</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520886</id>
      <parentid>443705</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-07-13T17:55:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">----
= NF (The iNtuitive Feeler) =
NFs are categorized as ''' idealists ''' and share the traits of dominant ''' iNtuitive ''' and ''' Feeling ''' traits. They include the [[../ENFJ/]], [[../ENFP/]], [[../INFJ/]], and [[../INFP/]].

The iNtuitive side of the NF makes him or her more inclined towards the abstract and the future as opposed to the concrete present. The Feeler preference means he makes decisions based on his personal values more than on cold analytical data.

[[Category:Myers-Briggs Type Indicator]]</text>
      <sha1>2bmcgdclzmypkf5vs9d65j2btdjd17f</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Myers-Briggs Type Indicator/Introversion</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4781</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1159241</id>
      <parentid>520882</parentid>
      <timestamp>2008-04-07T23:38:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>67.160.243.250</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{PersonalityTypeTOC}}

'''Introverts''' are rested and energized by solitude, and are very effective in solitary pursuits. An introvert is a person who prefers to process thoughts internally. Introverts tend to think before they speak. The word is also used informally to refer to somebody who prefers solitary activities to social ones, which is more of a behavioural than cognitive definition. Introverts tend to be seen as quiet and reserved, which is often confused with a lack of confidence by louder, more extroverted people. They often perform well in analytical roles that require intelligence or logic, but place less emphasis on social interactions and &quot;people skills&quot;.

[[Category:Myers-Briggs Type Indicator]]</text>
      <sha1>ekv54fhek9bp0lmdxsn0iw176yjs6li</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Myers-Briggs Type Indicator/Extraversion</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4782</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520865</id>
      <parentid>443602</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-07-13T17:51:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{PersonalityTypeTOC}}

'''Extraverts''' are energized by interacting with other people. They can often appear to be outgoing and may be effective in pursuits that involve interacting with other people. Extraverts tend to be sensation-seeking, spontaneous, and gregarious. They may enjoy crowds, noise, and stimulation.

In a conversation, an extravert will tend to talk faster and louder than an introvert and to interrupt more frequently.

[[Category:Myers-Briggs Type Indicator]]</text>
      <sha1>lbz6mnbbk3h35ar1uz92vf5wlwcil8u</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Myers-Briggs Type Indicator/Sensing</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4783</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520889</id>
      <parentid>443607</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-07-13T17:55:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{PersonalityTypeTOC}}

'''Sensors''' want, trust, and remember facts, and usually describe themselves as &quot;practical&quot;. For a Sensor, intuition is untrustworthy, and might seem like mental static. Sensation, as a perceiving mode of consciousness, focuses on heightening reality. Guardians share the combination SJ, while Artisans share the combination SP.

[[Category:Myers-Briggs Type Indicator]]</text>
      <sha1>kndn1b26ysb19q9gwx1vo6472ozn1bv</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Myers-Briggs Type Indicator/Intuitive</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4784</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520884</id>
      <parentid>443609</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-07-13T17:55:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{PersonalityTypeTOC}}

'''Intuitives''' prefer metaphor, analogy, and logic, and tend to reason from first principles and hunches. While Sensors pride themselves on living in the real world, Intuitives pride themselves on seeing possibilities. This can cause conflict. Intuition, as a perceiving mode of consciousness, filters experience through the unconscious mind. Intuition focuses on possibilities rather than realities. Idealists share the combination NF, while Rationals share the combination NT.

[[Category:Myers-Briggs Type Indicator]]</text>
      <sha1>dd0hi56c95beos4o2xe6ellspe9rvc7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Myers-Briggs Type Indicator/Thinking</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4785</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520877</id>
      <parentid>443611</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-07-13T17:54:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{PersonalityTypeTOC}}

'''Thinkers''' use impersonal means of reasoning: logic and verifiable experience.

[[Category:Myers-Briggs Type Indicator]]</text>
      <sha1>a2lucp0k6uejn0fq8gl0gdiv6pssthj</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Myers-Briggs Type Indicator/Feeling</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4786</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520866</id>
      <parentid>443613</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-07-13T17:51:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{PersonalityTypeTOC}}

'''Feelers''' prefer personal reasoning: value judgements and emotions. Thinkers often find Feelers muddle-headed. Feelers often find Thinkers cold and inhuman.

[[Category:Myers-Briggs Type Indicator]]</text>
      <sha1>ag83a67zj3rzuumwiq3h2rjc5e79lb0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Myers-Briggs Type Indicator/Judging</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4787</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520885</id>
      <parentid>443615</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-07-13T17:55:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{PersonalityTypeTOC}}

'''Judgers''' prefer to come to decisions and move on. They can feel betrayed if a decision is &quot;reopened&quot;. They are prone to hastiness, but get things done.

[[Category:Myers-Briggs Type Indicator]]</text>
      <sha1>79xdpfb8kctj4cq80qcbzksd0hwhawr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Myers-Briggs Type Indicator/Perceiving</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4788</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520887</id>
      <parentid>443617</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-07-13T17:55:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{PersonalityTypeTOC}}

'''Perceivers''' prefer to leave their options open to perceive new possibilities and processes as long as possible. They tend to mourn opportunities lost to premature decisions. They are prone to analysis paralysis, but rarely make permanent mistakes.

[[Category:Myers-Briggs Type Indicator]]</text>
      <sha1>ff7x27d1mkhcwrgf2z3677sfu658nvk</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Abstract Algebra/Hypercomplex numbers</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4790</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2280946</id>
      <parentid>1598940</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-03-06T02:32:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>140.247.40.217</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Quaternions */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Hypercomplex numbers are numbers that use the square root of -1 to create more than 1 extra dimension.

The most basic Hypercomplex number is the one used most often in vector mathematics, the Quaternion, which consists of 4 dimensions.   Higher dimensions are diagrammed by adding more roots to negative 1 in a predefined relationship.

==Quaternions==

A Quaternion consists of four dimensions, one real and the other 3 imaginary.  The imaginary dimensions are represented as ''i'', ''j'' and ''k''.  Each imaginary dimension is a square root of -1 and thus it is not on the normal number line.  In practice, the ''i'', ''j'' and ''k'' are all orthogonal to each other and to the real numbers.  As such, they only intersect at the origin (0,0''i'', 0''j'', 0''k'').

The basic form of a quaternion is:
*&lt;math&gt;q = a + bi + cj + dk&lt;/math&gt;

where a, b, c and d are real number coefficients. 

For a quaternion the relationship between ''i'', ''j'' and ''k'' is defined in this simple rule:
*&lt;math&gt;i^2 = j^2 = k^2 = i \times j \times k = -1&lt;/math&gt;

From this follows:
*&lt;math&gt;i \times j = k&lt;/math&gt;, &lt;math&gt;j \times i = -k&lt;/math&gt;
*&lt;math&gt;j \times k = i&lt;/math&gt;, &lt;math&gt;k \times j = -i&lt;/math&gt;
*&lt;math&gt;k \times i = j&lt;/math&gt;, &lt;math&gt;i \times k = -j&lt;/math&gt;

As you may have noticed, multiplication is not commutative in hyperdimensional mathematics.

They can also be represented as a 1 by 4 matrix in the form


{| border=&quot;1&quot;
! real
! ''i''
! ''j''
! ''k''
|-
| width=&quot;20&quot; | 1 || width=&quot;20&quot; | 1 || width=&quot;20&quot; | 1
| width=&quot;20&quot; | 1
|}

...

...

The quaternion is a 4 dimensional number, but it can be used to diagram three dimensional vectors and can be used to turn them without the use of calculus.

see also: [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quaternion Wikipedia's Article on Quaternion]

==Octonion==

8-dimensional.  See: [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Octonion Wikipedia's Article on Octonion]

==Sedenions==
16-dimensional.  See: [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sedenion Wikipedia's Article on Sedenion]

{{Subject|Abstract Algebra}}</text>
      <sha1>2chcp2n39lizwc5g4r88uv8pm4vzyen</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Vanicat</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>4798</id>
    <revision>
      <id>156482</id>
      <timestamp>2004-02-20T13:05:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Traroth</username>
        <id>178</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Bienvenu !</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Bienvenu, Vanicat. Ceci est ta page personnelle.</text>
      <sha1>tu5q6tr9mmww14i6lbgerdzc7cu9d3y</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:Vanicat</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>4799</id>
    <revision>
      <id>156483</id>
      <timestamp>2004-02-20T13:06:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Traroth</username>
        <id>178</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Objective Caml</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Bienvenu sur Wikibooks, et merci pour les contributions sur Objective Caml. [[User:Traroth|Traroth]] 13:06, 20 Feb 2004 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>d8f72657hhxr8iuqck9vwu7yse3c1wj</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Myers-Briggs Type Indicator/ISFJ</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4800</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2238059</id>
      <parentid>1254096</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-12-18T04:47:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>188.221.11.15</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* How to deal with an ISFJ */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{PersonalityTypeTOC}}

==ISFJs at work==

==ISFJs in relationships==

==How to deal with an ISFJ==

ISFJ's with a persistent guiding hand behind them can learn to like anything.
They often feel faint when bitten.

==Web links==

* [http://www.typelogic.com/isfj.html ISFJ on TypeLogic]
* [http://www.personalitypage.com/ISFJ.html ISFJ on PersonalityPage] and [http://www.personalitypage.com/ISFJ_car.html ISFJ careers]
* [http://www.typetango.com/isfj-personality.php ISFJ Profiles and Famous ISFJs on TypeTango]
* [http://www.personalitydesk.com/isfj-type-description.php ISFJ Profile on PersonalityDesk]

[[Category:Myers-Briggs Type Indicator]]</text>
      <sha1>jkv713qgpfrwmvxn88a8lmbszkhnym4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Myers-Briggs Type Indicator/INTJ</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4801</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2713794</id>
      <parentid>2689909</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-15T10:07:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>14.139.156.167</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Fictional Characters */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{PersonalityTypeTOC}}

==Famous INTJs==

===Entertainment===
* Dan Aykroyd, actor (Blues Brothers)
* Raymond Burr, actor (Perry Mason, Ironsides)
* Chevy Chase, actor (Cornelius Crane) (Fletch)
* Phil Donahue, television talk show host
* Greg Gumbel, television sportscaster
* Veronica Hamel, actress (Hill Street Blues)
* Peter Jennings, television newscaster
* Joan Lunden, television talk show host
* Trent Reznor, founder of Nine Inch Nails
* Pernell Roberts, actor (Bonanza)
* Elyse Sewell, fashion model, reality TV star
* Maria Owens Shriver, television newscaster

===Politicians and Leaders===
* Susan B. Anthony, suffragist
* Chester A. Arthur, US President
* William F. Buckley, Jr., Conservative political advocate
* Augustus Caesar (Gaius Julius Caesar Octavianus), Roman Emperor
* Calvin Coolidge, US President
* Michael Dukakis, Governor (D-MA), 1988 U.S. Dem. pres. nominee
* Hannibal, Carthaginian military leader
* Charles Everett Koop, former U.S. surgeon general
* Julia Gillard, Prime Minister of Australia
* Charles Rangel, US Representative (D-NY)
* Samantha Power, former advisor to President Obama
* Maximilien Robespierre, French Revolution leader
* Woodrow Wilson, US President

===Athletes===
* Arthur Ashe, tennis champion
* Orel Leonard Hershiser, IV, major league baseball pitcher
* Edwin Moses, U.S. olympian (hurdles)
* Martina Navratilova, tennis champion
* Ivan Lendl, tennis champion
* Tom Landry, Dallas Cowboys head coach for 29 seasons

===Literature===
* Isaac Asimov, sci-fi writer (I, Robot)
* Jane Austen, author (Pride and Prejudice)
* Philip K. Dick, sci-fi writer (The Man in the High Castle)
* C. S. Lewis, author (The Chronicles of Narnia)
* Josephine Tey (Elizabeth Mackintosh), mystery writer (Brat Farrar)
* Anton Chekhov, Russian writer, dramatist

===Fictional Characters===
* Dr. Nicholas Rush (Stargate Universe)
* Mr. Darcy (Pride and Prejudice)
* Elphaba Thropp (Gregory Maguire's Wicked)
* Hannibal Lecter (Silence of the Lambs)
* Professor Moriarty (Sherlock Holmes' nemesis)
* Paul von Oberstein (Legend of the Galactic Heroes)
* Ensign Ro (Star Trek--the Next Generation)
* George Smiley, John le Carre's master spy
* Clarice Starling (Silence of the Lambs)
* Emperor Palpatine (Star Wars)
* Lord Voldemort (Harry Potter)  
* Severus Snape (Harry Potter) 
* some versions of the Doctor (Doctor Who)
* Daniel Plainview (There Will Be Blood)
* Raistlin Majere (Dragonlance Legends)
* Number Six (The Prisoner)
* Maleficent (Sleeping Beauty)
* Elizabeth Hawke (Wicked Science)
* Andrew Ryan (Bioshock)
* GLaDOS (Portal)
* Walter White (Breaking Bad)
* Gus Fring (Breaking Bad)
* Peter Wiggin (Ender's Game)
* Artemis Fowl (Artemis Fowl)
* Nico Robin (One Piece)
* Lex Luthor (Smallville)
* Nora Gainesborough (True Blood)
* Gabriel Tosh (Starcraft II: Wings of Liberty)
* Abathur (Starcraft II: Heart of the Swarm)
* Rodion Romanovich Raskolnikov (Crime and Punishment)
* Gregory House(House M.D.)

===Others===
* Azzedine Alaïa, couturier
* William J. Bennett, 'drug czar'
* Ben Bernanke, Chairman of US Federal Reserve
* Fischer Black, economist
* Niels Bohr, physicist
* Bobby Fischer, chess prodigy
* Stephen Hawking, physicist
* Christopher Hitchens, polemicist
* John Maynard Keynes, economist
* Lise Meitner, physicist
* Ludwig von Mises, economist
* Sir Isaac Newton, physicist, mathematician
* Nikola Tesla, inventor, engineer
* Adam Worth, &quot;Napoleon of Crime&quot;, Master Criminal, &quot;The Eye&quot;

==Web links==

* [http://www.typelogic.com/intj.html INTJ on TypeLogic]
* [http://www.personalitypage.com/INTJ.html INTJ on PersonalityPage] and [http://www.personalitypage.com/INTJ_car.html careers]
* [http://www.systemsthinker.com/interests/mind/ptypes.shtml Personality Types Page Written by an INTJ]
* [http://www.typetango.com/intj-personality.php INTJ Profiles and Famous INTJs on TypeTango]
* [http://www.INTJ.org General information for INTJs]
* [http://www.cognitiveprocesses.com Jung's Cognitive Processes explained]
* [http://intjforum.com/ INTJ Discussion Forum]
* [http://intjcentral.com/manual1 The Compleat Idiot's Guide to the INTJ]
* [http://www.personalitydesk.com/intj-type-description.php INTJ Profile on PersonalityDesk]

[[Category:Myers-Briggs Type Indicator]]</text>
      <sha1>qujly1oao0ryirpax8c1wixerbm6xbb</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Myers-Briggs Type Indicator/INFJ</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4802</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2564910</id>
      <parentid>1254384</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-10-10T20:19:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>124.198.202.140</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* How to deal with an INFJ */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{PersonalityTypeTOC}}

==INFJs at work==

==INFJs in relationships==

==How to deal with an INFJ==
Be honest.  Don't try and manipulate them, they will see through it and never trust you again.  INFJ's have an uncanny ability to read people's emotions and they tend to take others emotions into themselves.  They easily make connections between things by matching up pieces of conversations and visual memories and can appear to be psychic because of this.

==Web links==

* [http://www.typelogic.com/infj.html INFJ on TypeLogic]
* [http://www.personalitypage.com/INFJ.html INFJ on PersonalityPage] and [http://www.personalitypage.com/INFJ_car.html careers]
* [http://www.typetango.com/infj-personality.php INFJ Profiles and Famous INFJs on TypeTango]
* [http://www.personalitydesk.com/infj-type-description.php INFJ Profile on PersonalityDesk]

[[Category:Myers-Briggs Type Indicator]]</text>
      <sha1>nrv67xd0qeoa0tuflhd79rtqwum1sdb</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>