<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>Bicycles/Maintenance and Repair/Cleaning parts</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3639</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2012126</id>
      <parentid>2012116</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-01-05T01:41:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Thereen</username>
        <id>44896</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>adding nav</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{bicycles}}
'''Cleaning parts''' can be done with a cleaning solution of some kind, and/or with a rag or stiff brush.
A couple of notes about cleaning products:
*Solvents must be thoroughly cleaned off parts that are to be re-lubricated. Residual solvent will have a solvent effect on the replacement lubricant.
*Even a bio-degradable solvent will have whatever substance it removed mixed in with it after use, and thus must be treated according to both the laws applicable to the solvent itself and the dissolved substances.
== Power Washer ==
Using a power washer is an option in some situations, but care must be taken not to displace lubricant from parts. A high pressure stream of water is capable of displacing the grease from a bearing surface, including from sealed bearings, which are not designed to be lubricated by the user. Some very powerful power washers can also take the paint off of a bike. As such it is not recommended to clean a bike with a power washer because it is very hard to dry the water and replace the grease.

==Cleaning and lubricating a bicycle chain==

Cleaning and lubricating your chain is one of the simplest and most important things to do to keep your bike in good working order.  It is also an activity that draws intense debate with many people insisting that their way is the &quot;Right&quot; way to do it.  The short story is, the cleaner and better lubricated your chain is the longer the entire drivetrain (the chain and gears) will last, but no drive-train lasts forever.  It is worth spending time taking care of your drivetrain, it's not worth obsessing about.

You need:
*Lubricant, 
*A couple Rags
*Old toothbrush

The choice of lubricant is important.  '''DO NOT''' use WD40* as it is too thin and will evaporate leaving nothing to lubricate the chain.  Use special bike chain lube found at any bike store.  Some lubricants are formulated for wet conditions, others for dry.  The difference is the viscosity.  A dry lube used in wet conditions will require more frequent applications, a wet lube used in dry conditions will gather dirt, and require more frequent cleaning.

Prior to lubricating, clean the chain as well as possible.  Usually a chain cleaning tool, or a toothbrush is sufficient. [[Bicycles/Maintenance and Repair/Chains/Removing a Bicycle Chain|Remove the chain]] from the bicycle and soak it in a solvent such as a cycle degreaser. Hang up chain to dry off.  Paraffin will also work, but is unpleasant and unhealthy to work with environmentally hazardous, and flammable; as such it is not recommended.

Dirt is what causes a chain to wear out, so keeping your chain as clean as possible extends its life, and the life of the entire drivetrain.  

Apply the lubricant on the chain non-pressurized drip type lubes are recommended as are more accurate, and waste less lube than spray lubricants.

Put a rag behind the chain so that the lube does not contaminate the tires or other parts of the bike. Rotate the pedals to move the chain and lubricate the whole length.  Wipe the chain with the rag to remove the excessive lubricant, as this just gathers dirt and does not help lubricate the chain.

[[Category:Bicycles]]</text>
      <sha1>tv1kynerjm1te8tt1jtyqt08ys7c568</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Caesar Salad</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>3640</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2680272</id>
      <parentid>2419763</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-07-10T18:31:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Austncorp</username>
        <id>1540792</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Added images cat. Suppressed TOC.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[File:CaesarSalad3.jpg|thumb|A Caesar salad variation topped with grilled chicken.]]
__NOTOC__
{{recipe}} | [[Cookbook:California cuisine|California cuisine]] | [[Cookbook:Salad Recipes|Salad]]

The '''Caesar salad''' is a traditional salad served in American restaurants, often prepared table side. It is referred to by some as the &quot;king&quot; of salads. 

Its origin is largely credited to Italian immigrant Caesar Cardini, a restaurateur and chef in Tijuana, Baja California del Norte, Mexico.  Cardini reportedly tossed the first such salad table side at his restaurant on July 4, 1924.

== Ingredients ==
* 1 head Romaine lettuce, roughly chopped&lt;ref group=&quot;N&quot;&gt;Contrary to popular belief, chopping the lettuce will '''''not''''' cause the edges to brown. If we were using a more delicate leaf, say radicchio, then we would tear it, but we're using Romaine, which isn't that delicate.&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1/4 cup (about 50ml) extra-virgin olive oil, divided
* 2 [[Cookbook:Soft Boiled Eggs|soft-boiled eggs]] 
* Heavy pinch of sea salt. Don't use table salt, or else you're not making Caesar salad.
* Freshly ground black pepper
* Drizzle red wine vinegar
* 3 shots Worcestershire sauce
* Garlic croûtons (below)

== Procedure==
#Drizzle lettuce with 2 tbsp extra-virgin olive oil. Toss to coat.
#Add salt and pepper. Toss to coat.
#Add vinegar and toss to coat.
#Drizzle Worcestershire sauce over lettuce. Toss to coat.
#Crack eggs over salad. Toss to coat.
#Top with garlic croûtons and serve.

== Notes ==
&lt;references group=&quot;N&quot;/&gt;

== Garlic Croûtons ==
===Ingredients===
* 1 stale loaf Italian bread, cut into 2-inch (5cm) cubes
* 1/4 cup (about 50ml) olive oil
* 2 tsp garlic powder
* 1/2 tsp salt
* 1/2 tsp black pepper

===Procedure===
#Place cubes on a greased baking sheet and bake at 400°F (200°C)until thoroughly dried.
#Heat olive oil over medium heat. Add seasonings and combine with oil. Add bread cubes and toss to coat.
#Cook until crisp. Remove and set aside until needed. 

{{Wikipedia|Caesar salad}}
{{Commonscat|Caesar salad}}
[[Category:Californian recipes]]
[[Category:Salad recipes]]
[[Category:Recipes_with_metric_units|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Recipes with images]]</text>
      <sha1>78xfnqljqw2nf7pais4njyhjhxcc4cu</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>German/Concepts Basic</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3641</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1709450</id>
      <parentid>509888</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-01-31T19:26:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>fixed links/category</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;small&gt; &lt;&lt; [[German/Introduction|Vorwort]] |&lt;/small&gt; '''Lektion N''' &lt;small&gt;| [[German/Concept Advanced|Lektion NA]] &gt;&gt; &lt;/small&gt;
----

===Richtig oder falsch?===

1 a Wir müssen gehen. So wir haben keine Zeit.
 
1 b Wir müssen gehen. Deshalb haben wir keine Zeit.

2 a Wenn wir haben Stress, machen wir oft Fehler.

2 b Wenn wir Stress haben, machen wir oft Fehler.

3 a Ich mag Leute nicht, die zu spät kommen.

3 b Ich mag Leute nicht, die kommen zu spät.
 

Richtig sind:
1 b, 2 b, 3 a,

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>asa3der1wjnxl60plrzr5j72wfnkstn</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>German/Concept Advanced</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3642</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2066174</id>
      <parentid>1709725</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-03-06T04:44:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Avicennasis</username>
        <id>314063</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WP:AWB/T|Typo fixing]], typos fixed: everthing → everything using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;small&gt;&lt;&lt; [[German/Concepts_Basic|Lektion N]] |&lt;/small&gt; '''Lektion NA''' &lt;/small&gt;
----
''Contributed to Lesson 1A, but concept not really introduced until Lesson 5'':


 Beispiel an          ''können'' (can)    ''gehen'' (go)     ''sein'' (to be)
 pronoun              verb I (irreg?) verb II        verb III (irregular)
 Basicform            können          gehen          sein
 ich                  kann            gehe           bin
 du                   kannst          gehst          bist
 er/sie/es            kann            geht           ist
 wir                  können          gehen          sind
 ihr                  könnt           geht           seid
 sie                  können          gehen          sind
 Sie (formal)         können          gehen          sind

As you can see, any verb uses the same declination for wir, sie and Sie.
Also, er/sie/es uses the same declination for all three genders.
NOTE: Moved to Lesson 6


----
''Used this story for [[German/Level III/Markus Studiert]] since it nicely followed your other Markus conversation. But I could not match ''holt'' or ''holt aus'' to any verb. Can you help? '' -- holt is from holen, holt aus is from ausholen, which has another meaning, but &quot;holen&quot; is meant here in the sense of &quot;fetching a book out of the shelf&quot; (trying to match the German sentence literally)

Markus ist in der Universität. Er trinkt dort einen Kaffee und ißt ein Brötchen. Danach geht er in die Bibliothek. Er sucht ein Buch über Biochemie. Er '''holt das Buch aus''' dem Regal und setzt sich an einen Tisch. Nach einer Stunde geht er in den Hof und raucht eine Zigarette. Danach geht er an den Tisch zurück. Er denkt: &quot;Wenigstens eine Stunde...&quot; und stellt das Buch wieder in das Regal. Heute ist nicht sein Tag.
----
''There are already lessons completed for some of these points. However, it might be that the stories or conversations need to made easier to read in those lessons.''
 
What should be explained here?
* Genders
* Articles: der, die das, ein, eine, ein.
* Nominativ, Dativ and Akkusativ. (We could live without Genitiv for a while)
* Daklinations with articles. 
* Keep everything in singular.

''Note that the book layout is such that the Advanced lessons add to the basic lesson (1A furthers something taught in 1), but 1A cannot be the place where anything basic is introduced, as the berginning student should not even visit Lesson 1A until later''.


Just wondering, but isn't this very limited for Advanced Level? I would like like some help for the Wirtschaftsdeutsch Prüfung but this isn't going to help me.
:This page is meant to be a place for contributors to put proposed lessons. Unsure what you were looking for? - [[User:Marshman|Marsh]] 01:39, 14 Oct 2004 (UTC)

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>jbgxu6gmx2a5tzoif12gonzx9h5k9i0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Wanttomoveapage</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>3644</id>
    <revision>
      <id>155529</id>
      <timestamp>2004-01-06T19:28:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Wanttomoveapage</username>
        <id>426</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">password: Wanttomoveapage</text>
      <sha1>rz6744sa4botpza8vk0bui6xea0h251</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Bourne Shell Scripting</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3645</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2669431</id>
      <parentid>2578003</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-06-03T22:46:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>63.235.131.194</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External References */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Hi there! Welcome to this Wikibook on the wonderful world of Bourne Shell Scripting!

This book will cover the practical aspects of using and interacting with the Bourne Shell, the root of all shells in use in the [[en:Unix|Unix]] world. That includes interacting with the shell on a day-to-day basis for the purposes of operating the computer in normal tasks, as well as grouping together commands in files (scripts) which can be run over and over again. Since it's not practical to talk about the Bourne Shell in complete isolation, this will also mean some short jaunts into the wondrous world of Unix; not far, just enough to understand what is going on and be able to make full use of the shell's very wide capabilities.

There are also some things this book '''won't''' do for you. This book is not an in-depth tutorial on any kind of programming theory -- you won't learn the finer points of program construction and derivation or the mathematical backings of program development here. This book also won't teach you about [[en:Linux|Linux]] or any other type of Unix or Unix itself or any other operating system any more than is necessary to teach you how to use the shell. Nothing to be found here about [[en:Apache|Apache]], joe, [[Learning the vi Editor|vi]], or any other specific program. Nor will we cover firewalls and networking.

We ''will'' cover the Bourne Shell, beginning with the basic functionality and capabilities as they existed in the initial release, through to the added functionality specified by the international POSIX standard POSIX 1003.1 for this shell. We will have to give you ''some'' programming knowledge, but we hope that everyone will readily understand the few simple concepts we explain.

Having said that, the authors hope you will find this book a valuable resource for learning to use the shell and for using the shell on a regular basis. And that you might even have some fun along the way.
&lt;noinclude&gt;
== Chapters ==
{{Print version|/Print Version}}
{{PDF version|Bourne Shell Scripting|File size: 690kB}}
* [[/Comparing Shells/]] ''The Bourne Shell versus other shells (or: why the Bourne Shell?)'' {{stage short|100%|October 11, 2005}}
* [[/Running Commands/]] ''How to execute commands in the Bourne Shell'' {{stage short|100%|October 11, 2005}}
* [[/Environment/]] ''The Bourne Shell environment (and how it relates to multiprocessing)'' {{stage short|100%|May 05, 2010}}
* [[/Variable Expansion/]] ''Embedding values of parameters'' {{stage short|100%|April 24, 2010}}
* [[/Control flow/]] ''Programming in Bourne Shell (getting actual work done)'' {{stage short|100%|April 18, 2010}}
* [[/Files and streams/]] ''The (standard) ins and (standard) outs of what to do with your pipe...'' {{stage short|100%|October 11, 2005}}
* [[/Modularization/]] ''Programming in blocks -- and having them interact'' {{stage short|100%|April 20, 2010}}
* [[/Debugging and signal handling/]] ''Shell settings and debugging'' {{stage short|100%|April 26, 2010}}
* [[/Appendix A: Command Reference/]] ''An overview of all the built-in commands of the Bourne Shell'' {{stage short|100%|April 27, 2010}}
* [[/Appendix B: Environment reference/]] ''An overview of all the standard environment variables of the Bourne Shell'' {{stage short|100%|April 28, 2010}}
* [[/Appendix C: Quick Reference/]] ''Quick examples to refresh your memory'' {{stage short|100%|May 12, 2010}}
* [[/Appendix D: Cookbook/]] {{stage short|100%|May 12, 2010}}&lt;/noinclude&gt;

== Authors ==
# [[User:BenTels|BenTels]], started the book
# [[User:Kernigh|Kernigh]], added [[/Substitution/]] and [[/Loops/]] chapters
# Quick reference was originally by Greg Goebel and was from http://www.vectorsite.net/tsshell.html (was public domain licensed) and was partly wikified by [[w:user:unforgettableid|unforgettableid]].
# Other and anonymous contributors

== External References ==

* [http://pubs.opengroup.org/onlinepubs/9699919799/ IEEE Std 1003.1, 2013 Edition] - The 2013 Edition of IEEE/POSIX standard 1003.1
* [http://steve-parker.org/sh/bourne.shtml An Introduction to the Unix Shell] - HTML format republication of Steve Bourne's original tutorial for the Bourne Shell. 
* [http://www.injunea.demon.co.uk/pages/page201.htm UNIX Shell Script Tutorials &amp; Reference]
* '''Beginner'''
** [http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Bash-Prog-Intro-HOWTO.html BASH Programming - Introduction HOWTO ]
** [http://bash.cyberciti.biz/guide/Main_Page Linux Shell Scripting Tutorial - A Beginners handbook ]
* '''Advanced scripting guide'''
** [http://tldp.org/LDP/abs/html/index.html Advanced Bash-Scripting Guide]
* '''Print'''
** UNIX IN A NUTSHELL: A Desktop Quick Reference for System V &amp; Solaris 2.0 (2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; edition)&lt;br/&gt;Daniel Gilly et al.&lt;br/&gt;August 1994&lt;br/&gt;ISBN 1-56592-001-5
&lt;noinclude&gt;

{{subjects|computer programming languages}}
{{Subjects|Scripting languages|UNIX}}
{{alphabetical|B}}
{{status|100%}}
&lt;/noinclude&gt;

[[Category:Shell Programming]]

[[cs:Skriptování v Bourne shellu]]</text>
      <sha1>bh689lnhwkt1989ofwypj9rju4telo0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Creative Writing/Comics</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3646</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2097299</id>
      <parentid>1636870</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-05-19T17:33:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>90.142.167.182</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Chapter 6: Show and Tell */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">This is a summary of Scott McCloud's  &quot;Understanding Comics&quot;.

== Chapter 1: Setting the Record Straight ==

Comics is a [[w:medium|medium]], not a [[w:genre|genre]].

In one of the few previous books discussing [[w:comic book|comics]] as a medium, [[w:Will Eisner|Will Eisner]]'s ''[[w:Comics and Sequential Art|Comics and Sequential Art]]'', comics is defined, unexpectedly, as Sequential Art.  Here McCloud expands and formalizes that definition (in a rare panel that reduces neatly to pure text):  &quot;'''com.ics''' (kom'iks) '''n.''' plural in form, used with a singular verb. '''1.''' Juxtaposed pictoral and other images in deliberate sequence, intended to convey information and/or to produce an aesthetic response in the viewer.&quot;

The definition is dense (in the book it is developed over several pages, with McCloud's cartoon [[w:avatar|avatar]] taking questions from an audience), but to quote another part of the chapter&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The secret is not in what the definition says but what it ''doesn't'' say! || 

For example, our definition says nothing about superheroes or funny animals.  Nothing about fantasy/science fiction or reader age.  No genres are listed in our definition, no types of subject matter, no styles of prose or poetry. || 

Nothing is said about paper and ink.  No printing process is mentioned.  Printing ''itself'' isn't even specified!&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;  Nothing is said about technical pens or bristol board or Windsor &amp; Newton Finest Sable Series 7 Number 2 Brushes!&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;  No materials are ruled out by our definition.  No tools are prohibited. || 

There is no mention of black lines and flat colored ink.  No calls for exaggerated anatomy or for representational art of any kind.  No schools of art are banished by our definition, no philosophies, no movements, no ways of seeing are out of bounds!&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Like text, comics can be used in uncountable ways; unlike text, its potential has until recently been tragically squandered.

=== Footnotes ===

# In quoting without pictures, a lot has to be left out (here I've denoted frame breaks with || ).  One of the joys of this book, and one of many reasons it has to be in comics, is that the phenomena talked about in the text are often played out in the art (to oversimplify a complex and interdependent relationship).  Some simple examples: later in the book, in the middle of  the explanation of the effects of the ''non sequitor'' panel transition, the narrative is interrupted by a panel containing only a fork.  In Chapter 2, after explaining Magritte's [[w:The Treachery of Images|The Treachery of Images]], the McCloud-[[w:avatar|avatar]] asks, &quot;Do you hear what I'm saying?  If you do, have your ears checked, because no one said a word.&quot;  In an example closer to home (if somewhat more diffuse), the quote directly following the sentence to which this is footnoted describes comics freed from the constraints of adolescent power fantasies, and lo and behold, the very comics describing this are themselves free of that mold.  McCloud points out, later, that one of the advantages of comics as a medium is the ease with which text and subtext can spar, as in [[w:Art Spiegelman|Art Spiegelman]]'s ''[[Maus]]'', where the Jews are drawn as mice and the Nazis as cats.
# In the discussion that led up to this passage, McCloud pointed out out that under his definition, artifacts like [[w:Trajan's Column|Trajan's Column]] would be comics, and traced the medium's development into the current century, highlighting notables like [[w:William Hogarth|William Hogarth]]'s [[w:A Harlot's Progress|A Harlot's Progress]], [[w:Max Ernst|Max Ernst]]'s [[w:A Week of Kindness|A Week of Kindness]], and the works of [[w:Rodolphe Topffer|Rodolphe Topffer]], [[w:Lynd Ward|Lynd Ward]], and [[w:Frans Masereel|Frans Masereel]], all of which are traditionally considered non-Comics.
# Indeed, McCloud now proudly uses a tablet and [[w:Photoshop|Photoshop]], and publishes many of his comics on [http://www.scottmccloud.com his website].
# Two footnotes in one:
#* On the other hand, McCloud points out that his definition excludes single panel works like [[w:Family Circus|Family Circus]] and [[w:the Far Side|the Far Side]].
#* These issues are further explored in ''[[w:Reinventing Comics|Reinventing Comics]]'', which focuses on the possibilities the internet creates.

== Chapter 2: The Vocabulary of Comics ==

Comics are built out of icons -- &quot;For the purposes of this chapter, I'm using the word [[w:icon|icon]] to mean any image used to represent a person, place, thing or idea.&quot;  Letters and words are completely abstract icons, bearing no physical resemblance to their ideas; pictures have varying levels of abstraction, from the photograph of a face, full of color and shading, an ink copy of photons taken in through a shutter, to '''=D'''

That [[w:smiley|smiley]], that :-) , that set of dots and lines that looks like a face to us only because our brains contain a lot of face-seeing hardware (after all, no one sees eyes in solitary colons, noses in solitary dashes), is a [[w:cartoon|cartoon]].  Cartoons focus our attention -- through simplification, by eliminating superfluous features, they amplify the features that remain -- but, McCloud explains, that is not the entirety of their drawing power:

&lt;blockquote&gt;When two people interact, they usually look directly at one another, seeing their partner's features in vivid detail. || Each one also sustains a constant awareness of his or her own face, but ''this'' mind-picture is not nearly so vivid; just a sketchy arrangement...a sense of shape...a sense of ''general placement''. || Something as simple and basic as a cartoon. || Thus, when you look at a photo or a realistic drawing of a face, you see it as the face of another. || But when you enter the world of the ''cartoon'', you see ''yourself''. ... The cartoon is a vacuum into which our identity and awareness are pulled, || an empty shell that we inhabit which enables us to travel into another realm.  We don't just observe the cartoon, we ''become'' it!&lt;/blockquote&gt;

(McCloud goes on to discuss how varying levels of iconism and realism are used in comics to achieve various effects -- for example, a sword might be drawn as a few quick lines in one panel, to symbolize its connectedness with the iconic character holding it (just as the car one drives becomes, to an extent, an extension of the self), and drawn as detailed and photorealistic in the next panel, as the character gazes down at its strange engravings, to symbolize its mystery, its otherness, to allow the reader to see it, rather than be it.)

The spectrum as described thus far:

real face --&gt; photograph of a face --&gt; realistic drawing --&gt; cartoony drawing --&gt; smiley

The photograph requires little cognition; it is received as pure visual input.  The smiley requires an effort, if an unconscious one, a piecing together of the abstract lines.  Continuing the spectrum to the right, McCloud argues, we arrive at the word '''FACE''' -- bold and distinct, with relatively few letters, reminiscent of prehistoric times, when words and pictures were one -- then at a more detailed description (&quot;Two eyes, one nose, one mouth&quot; is the example given), then at still higher levels of abstraction ([[w:Keats|&quot;Thy youth's proud livery, as gazed on now...&quot;]]).

reality --&gt; photo --&gt; [[w:Batman|Batman]] --&gt; [[w:Charlie Brown|Charlie Brown]] --&gt; =D --&gt; '''FACE''' --&gt; Two eyes, one nose, one mouth --&gt; ''Thy youth's proud livery, as gazed on now...''

&lt;blockquote&gt;Our need for a unified ''language'' of comics sends us toward the center where words and pictures are like one side of the same coin! || But our need for ''sophistication'' in comics seems to lead us outwards, where words and pictures are most separate.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In addition to iconic abstraction, there exists abstraction of the more traditional sense, the abstraction of [[w:abstract art|abstract art]].  Thus, the spectrum becomes a pyramid:


  The [[w:Picture Plane|Picture Plane]]/[[w:Art Object|Art Object]]
                 /\\
                / [[w:Piet Mondrian|.]]\ \
               /  [[w:Jackson Pollock|.]] \  \
              /      [[w:dada|\]]   \
             /  [[w:Pablo Picasso|.]]     \    \
            / [[w:Vincent van Gogh|.]]        \   [[w:John Keats|.]]|
           [[w:Claude Monet|/]]        [[w:Matisse|.]]   \  / [[w:language|language]]
          [[w:Ansel Adams|/]][[w:Michelangelo|.]]             \/
 [[w:reality|reality]]


The pyramid has limitations, of course (Where do [[w:The Treachery Of Images|The Treachery Of Images]] and [[w:Fountain|Fountain]] fall?  Does the horizontal axis along the verbal edge dictate how the words are displayed on the page or how they describe things?) but it is a cool little invention.

== Chapter 3: Blood in the Gutter ==


&lt;pre&gt; ^_^   -_^ &lt;/pre&gt;

As part of normal life, everyone learns to assume certain things (or so one assumes) -- that the world doesn't disappear when you're not looking, for example, that the house across the street has furniture and interior walls.  &quot;As infants, we're unable to commit that act of faith.  If we can't see it, hear it, smell it, taste it or touch it, it isn't there!  The game &quot;Peek-A-Boo&quot; plays on this idea.  Gradually, we learn that even though the sight of mommy comes and goes, mommy remains. || This phenomenon of observing the parts and perceiving the whole has a name.  It's called [[w:closure|closure]].&quot;

You performed closure when you saw the lines at the top of this section as two [[w:anime|anime]] smilies; more to the point of the chapter, you performed closure when you saw the two smileys as a single ''winking'' smiley.  &quot;See that space between the panels?  That's what comics aficionados have named &quot;the gutter!&quot;  And despite its unceremonious title, the gutter plays host to much of the magic and mystery that are at the very heart of comics...If visual iconography is the [[w:semantics|vocabulary]] of comics, closure is its [[w:syntax|grammar]].&quot;

Of course, other media make use of closure as well -- in movies, our minds effortlessly connect each frame to those preceding and following it -- but comics requires conscious (or semiconscious), high-level closure between every frame.  McCloud has categorized panel-to-panel transitions into six classes:

; 1. '''Moment-to-moment''' : The same subject is displayed in adjacent instants, like a movie running jerkily on a slow computer. Very little closure is required.
; 2. '''Action-to-action''' : The focus remains on a single subject, but this time, two separate, consecutive actions are displayed (for example, the first panel might contain a car speeding along, the 2nd the car smashing into a tree).&lt;/dd&gt;
; 3. '''Subject-to-subject''' : Both panels are within the same scene or idea, but each portrays a different subject.  (&quot;John: What more could go wrong? || Catherine: Well, at least Jerry never called! || Telephone: ''Rring'' &quot;)&lt;/dd&gt;
; 4. '''Scene-to-Scene''' : Just what it sounds like: great leaps in time or space.  (&quot;Detective: He can't outrun us forever. || Image of darkened house with caption: Ten years later...&quot;)  Lots o' closure -- deductive reasoning, even -- is often required to link the panels into a single narrative.&lt;/dd&gt;
; 5. '''Aspect to aspect''' : &quot;Bypasses time for the most part and sets a wandering eye on different aspects of a place, mood, or idea.&quot;&lt;/dd&gt;
; 6. '''Non-Sequitur''' : Panels with no logical relationship.  (McCloud argues, though, that any panels placed side by side will inevitably generate the impression of some sort of relationship in the reader's mind.  &quot;--alchemy at work in the space between panels which can help us find meaning or resonance in even the most jarring of combinations.&quot;

(The transition at the top of this section, iconic and decontextualized as it is, manages to fall into two separate categories, Moment-to-moment and Action-to-action.)

Looking at how often each panel transition is used in a particular comic can reveal some interesting things.  [[w:Jack Kirby|Jack Kirby]]'s pioneering style, as invoked in a [[w:Fantastic Four|Fantastic Four]] comic from [[w:1966|1966]], breaks down as follows: 65% action-to-action (type 2), 20% subject-to-subject (type 3), 15% scene-to-scene (type 4); the remaining transitions are unused.  Here's the bar graph McCloud makes of the data:


    |'''1'''|'''2'''|'''3'''|'''4'''|'''5'''|'''6'''|
    | | | | | | |
 90%| | | | | | |
    | | | | | | |
    | |'''.'''| | | | |
    | |'''M'''| | | | |
 50%| |'''M'''| | | | |
    | |'''M'''| | | | |
    | |'''M'''| | | | |
    | |'''M'''|'''M'''|'''.'''| | |
 10%| |'''M'''|'''M'''|'''M'''| | |

As it turns out, almost every American comic -- regardless of storytelling style, regardless of genre (with a few experimental exceptions like [[w:Art Spiegelman|Art Spiegelman]]'s early work) -- charts similarly, from issue 1 of [[w:X-Men|X-Men]] to [[w:Heartbreak Soup|Heartbreak Soup]] to [[w:Betty and Veronica|Betty and Veronica]] to [[w:Naughty Bits|Naughty Bits]] to [[w:Frank in the River|Frank in the River]] to [[w:A Contract With God|A Contract With God]] to [[Maus (graphic novel)|Maus]] to [[w:Donald Duck|Donald Duck]].  A similar survey of European comics ([[w:Squeak the Mouse|Squeak the Mouse]], [[w:Asterix|Asterix]], [[w:Welcome to Alflolol|Welcome to Alflolol]], [[w:The Long Tomorrow|The Long Tomorrow]], [[w:Manhattan|Manhattan]], [[w:Clik!|Clik!]], [[w:The Black Island|The Black Island]], [[w:The Clock Strikes|The Clock Strikes]]) yields similar results.

But here's a popular mainstream Japanese comic from [[w:Osamu Tezuka|Osamu Tezuka]]:

    |'''1'''|'''2'''|'''3'''|'''4'''|'''5'''|'''6'''|
    | | | | | | |
 90%| | | | | | |
    | | | | | | |
    | | | | | | |
    | | | | | | |
 50%| | | | | | |
    | |'''M'''| | | | |
    | |'''M'''|'''M'''| | | |
    | |'''M'''|'''M'''| |'''L'''| |
 10%|'''L'''|'''M'''|'''M'''|'''M'''|'''M'''| |

In [[w:Japan|Japan]], where comics developed mostly in isolation following [[w:World War II|World War II]], where they are often published in gigantic anthologies rather than tiny magazines (lessening the premium on space and thus the emphasis on concise, action-oriented transitions 2-4) the charts look quite different.  More important still, eastern culture has bequeathed an emphasis on [[w:holism|holism]] and contemplation (aspect-to-aspect works well for setting a mood), an emphasis on the power of intervals -- of silence in a song, of [[w:negative space|negative space]] in a painting.

In comics this means a renewed emphasis on the power of closure, on the strange alchemy that occurs in the gutter.  The effect is to spark the imagination, to engage every one of the five senses, rather than simply sight.  (Sadly, replicating McCloud's demonstration of this in [[w:ASCII art|ASCII art]] is prohibitively difficult.)

&lt;blockquote&gt;The comics creator asks us to join in a silent dance of the seen and unseen.  The visible and invisible. || This dance is unique to comics.  No other artform gives so much to its audience while asking so much from them as well. || This is why I think it's a mistake to see comics as a mere hybrid of graphic arts and prose fiction.  What happens between these panels is a kind of magic only comics can create.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

== Chapter 4: Time Frames ==

We've been trained to see a picture as a snapshot, as a single moment in time, but any student of visual physiology can tell you that the vast majority of information is taken in by a small area at the center of the field of vision; our eyes compensate for this porthole effect by darting continually around and our brains compensate by maintaining the illusion of detailed [[w:peripheral vision|peripheral vision]] (for a demonstration, try reading this sentence while keeping your eyes fixed on one of its component words).  Much [[w:modern art|modern art]] acknowledges this ([[wikipedia:Cubism|Cubism]], for example, incorporates many perspectives into one image), and so do many comics.  McCloud's example is a long panel containing several chatting family members; reading from left to right, the conversation takes maybe 15 seconds to unfold, and the expression and pose of each person matches the moment his or her particular statement is made -- &quot;one panel, containing several panels&quot;.

To some extent, then, space in comics translates into time; as your eyes cross the page they also pass through the seconds (or the hours, or the years) and while a frame generally denotes a particular moment (in addition to serving other purposes beyond the scope of this entry), ''moment'' is a slippery thing that in practice can be any length at all; in determining a more specific time period, the reader relies heavily on context, on a page's particular content, and, especially, on the sounds portrayed in the text, which we have not been conditioned to think of as having a duration of zero.

(Here there is a quick digression about direction. What would happen if instead of reading solely left-to-right, a comic was made into a labyrinth wherein at every intersection the reader could choose which direction the story takes?  What would happen if a comic was circular, its end connecting to its beginning?)

And then there's motion.  It can, of course, be portrayed through the frame transitions described in chapter 3, but shortly after the era of [[w:futurism|futurism]] had ended, shortly after the invention of the [[w:motion picture|motion picture]], comics invented the [[w:motion line|motion line]], which lies &quot;somewhere between the futurists' ''dynamic'' movement and [[w:Duchamp|Duchamp]]'s diagrammatic ''concept'' of movement.&quot;  Over a period of decades, motion lines evolved from &quot;wild, messy, almost desperate attempts to chart the paths of moving objects through space&quot; to something &quot;more refined and stylized, even ''diagrammatic''&quot;, then, eventually, &quot;became ''so'' stylized as to almost have a life and physical presence all their own!&quot;

&lt;blockquote&gt;I've been trying to figure out what makes comics tick for years and I'm still amazed at the strangeness of it all. || But no matter how bizarre the workings of time in comics is -- || -- the face it presents to the reader -- || -- is one of simple normalcy. || Or the illusion of it, anyway. || It all depends on your frame of mind.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

== Chapter 5: Living in Line ==

This chapter relies very heavily on visual examples, so is difficult to summarize here.

== Chapter 6: Show and Tell ==

In the beginning, pictures and words were two sides of the same coin.  In school, at show-and-tell, you show, and you tell, interchangeably -- &quot;This is my robot...it's got one of ''these'' things&quot;; in picture books, simple words combine similarly with images.  As we grow up, we learn to separate ''show'' and ''tell'' from each other -- we paint pictures without words, and read books without pictures.

A similar progression can be traced through history.  In cave paintings, the people shown were iconic, symbol-esqe, almost like letters, as were the flat, bright [[w:The Bull Fight|images of]] the early [[w:ancient Greece|Greek]]s and [[w:Crete|Crete]]ans and the line-drawings of ancient [[w:Egypt|Egypt]]; early written language, likewise, was full of the descendants of those cave paintings, [[w:pictograph|letters that were pictures]].  Words and images were side by side, at the lower-left vertex of McCloud's great pyramid.

Over the course of the next few thousand years, they diverged.  Letters sacrificed visual representation for writing ease (and, later, printing ease) and pictures grew richer and more complex until looking at them was more like looking at reality than at thoughts.

[[Category:{{FULLBOOKNAME}}|{{FULLCHAPTERNAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>jpnd6nt7ji6p5m5or7sfmsqwcudjosy</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook talk:Policy/Recipe template</title>
    <ns>103</ns>
    <id>3650</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2364576</id>
      <parentid>2364572</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-16T13:12:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kri</username>
        <id>162760</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Named sections collectively</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">== &gt;&gt;Unnamed sections as of July 2012&lt;&lt; ==

I think this page should be moved out of the main namespace, but am unsure if it should go to Cookbook: or Wikibooks:.  It's definatly a cookbook item, but it's not intended to be seen by the regular user, only by contributers.  Any opinions? [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] 02:02, 7 Jan 2004 (UTC)
:That makes sense to me. [[User:Kellen|Kellen]] Jan 7 (how do i do a timestamp?!) 2005
----
I think it would be fine to have some categorical information to each recipe (and ingredient) so that a special search can be applied. I'm thinking about things like seasonal and geographical information or classification like vegetarian, vegan and so on. Even better would be to also have things like preparation time and calories available as search terms. A visitor could then for example search for vegetarian italian dishes under 30 min prep. or similar. I think for that to work we would need a specially programmed search module and I have no clue about the MediaWiki workings in that respect... The jewel on the crown would be if you can search by ingredients: 'hmm.. I have carrots, potatoes and chicken [and hopefully some other basic ingredients]. what will I have tonight?' Any Ideas about that? --[[User:Elkmann|Elkmann]] 23:43, 19 Sep 2004 (UTC)
:Not sure about the search idea (which I think would be good, but I'm not a developer), but if you click the &quot;what links here&quot; link on the side of the page from [[Cookbook:Carrot]] you end up at [http://en.wikibooks.org/w/wiki.phtml?title=Special:Whatlinkshere&amp;target=Cookbook%3ACarrot this page] which lists all the recipes that link back to the carrot page, which I think is an important reason to wikify each ingredient. [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] 20:29, 20 Sep 2004 (UTC)

:Search needs to be low-maintenence. Tagging recipes is troublesome, especially if the absense of a tag implies a meaning which is opposite to having the tag. (are all recipes ''not'' tagged as vegan known to be non-vegan, or should they appear as unknowns at the bottom of a search for vegan stuff?) I see two ways to make searching work.
:#Make it Google-like, with a synonym database generated from the redirects.
:#Make it like a music referral service. As you rate recipes, recipes become sorted according to the ratings of people with similar taste in food. This was developed for music so that a heavy metal fan would not get suggestions for country music, etc. The idea should work well for recipes.
:[[User:AlbertCahalan|AlbertCahalan]] 01:32, 4 May 2005 (UTC)

::I put in a request at bugzilla that the new search function in use at wikipedia be turned on for the sister projects.  If you want the developers to listen to us, please vote [http://bugzilla.wikimedia.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1917 here]. [[User:Gentgeen|Gentgeen]] 05:23, 4 May 2005 (UTC)

----
Why are optional ingredients to be listed separately from the main list? It seems as if variations in cooking method or main ingredients (say, oranges for lemons) would make sense as a separate section at the end, but that optional ingredients (say coconut on top of a cake) should be listed in the main ingredients list. Opinions? [[User:Kellen|Kellen]] Jan 7 2005

:Agreed. In some cases, I mark an ingredient as &quot;(optional)&quot;. In other cases, I list optional ingredients in a second list immediately after the first list. I don't think it is good to get terribly formal about this sort of thing; the proper answer really depends on the recipe. Some recipes do well with multiple ingredient lists, breaking things up as &quot;filling&quot; and &quot;crust&quot; or similar. [[User:AlbertCahalan|AlbertCahalan]] 06:35, 4 Feb 2005 (UTC)


:If its only one or two I tend to simply use &quot;(optional)&quot; but for more than that I add a line break and start a ne w list marked optional directly below the first list. While it is useful to have multiple lists they should all be together for clarity. If you're reading a recipe to confirm which ingredients you'll need you need to have them all together so that you don't accidentally miss one. Introducing ingrediants into the text of a recipe that aren't invited in the main Ingredients section is a major pet peeve for me. [[User:The Grimm Ripper|Grimm]] 23:43, 16 Apr 2005 (UTC)

== people put recipes in the template! ==

Twice now, people have put recipes ''into'' the template. Perhaps they ought to be saved elsewhere:

 03:17, 25 Apr 2005
 04:51, 9 Apr 2005

For the future though... how shall we clue people in?

*I've added a note about it to the top. It might be as well to add it to the end as well. [[User:The Grimm Ripper|Grimm]]

One might want to fish those recipes out of the page history. [[User:AlbertCahalan|AlbertCahalan]] 05:39, 1 May 2005 (UTC)

 04:51,  9 Apr 2005   68.190.244.102  Chicken Taco???
 03:17, 25 Apr 2005   68.9.128.107    Salad w/ Lemon-oil Dressing
 20:43, 30 Apr 2005   68.50.62.31     Pickled Bologna

==Template==
Hello, on the Dutch wikibooks, we've created a new skin for the template:
*One for recipes with picture: [[nl:Sjabloon:Receptmetafbeelding]], [[nl:Kookboek:Berchemse_boterkoekjes|example]]
*One for recipes without picture: [[nl:Sjabloon:Recept]], [[nl:Kookboek:Arretjescake|example]].&lt;br /&gt;
[[User:Firefox|Firefox]] 10:26, 2 May 2005 (UTC)

:: This is excellent, thanks! We'll probably use something like it! [[User:68.15.29.44|68.15.29.44]] 04:31, 20 Jun 2005 (UTC)

==Recipes In Progress==
Given the open source spirit of &quot;release early, release often&quot;, I think that the cookbook would benefit from a template indicating that a recipe is a &quot;Recipe In Progress&quot; (RIP). This would indicate that a given article contains a recipe being created or adapted and should be discussed for possible improvements on the talk page. This way, original recipes that need to be further developed or new recipes that need to be tweaked can be clearly marked as such. Hopefully, this will lead to some testing by the community and at the end, a solid recipe will emerge. It might also be helpful if the template indicates that the recipe should be used at a reader's own risk. [[User:Yonkeltron|Yonkeltron]] 13:03, 16 March 2006 (UTC)

== Serves ?? ==

may be each recipe should show how many people it serves
and if its a side serving or full meal

And Perhaps a Variants list for the base article
for eg for Macaroni and Cheese there's an article called Macaroni and Cheese
and with in that page is a list of the different Variants of the recipe and a short Description:
Over Baked: Cooked In the oven for Great Taste takes 1 hour
Simple: Super quick Takes 10 minutes
Stove Top: cook in a pot takes 20-25 minutes

== Weight &amp; Volume ==

The recipe template recommends use of volumes rather than weights on the grounds that many kitchens do not have scales. In Europe most kitchens do have scales, and a cheap kitchen scale need cost only a few dollars - high accuracy is not necessary.

Outside North America it is far less common to perceive a &quot;cup&quot; as a known volume (8 fl.oz.) and rather to see it as &quot;whatever cup I have close to hand&quot; which may vary by more than 5:2. Furthermore the physical state of an ingredient can cause its density to vary by 3:2 or even more - a cup of white flour can easily be as little as 100 gm or as much as 150 gm. For consistency and repeatability of recipes it is far better to use weight for solid ingredients and volume only for liquids.

I have not found a volume/weight conversion table for different ingredients - is there one?

== Shouldn't be classified as a recipe ==

This page is classified as a recipe, which it should not be. —[[User:Kri|Kri]] ([[User talk:Kri|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Kri|contribs]]) 13:09, 16 June 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>dnmtooqs107yazcyyzishtjd5k26itc</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:US History</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>3651</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2675703</id>
      <parentid>2674618</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-06-22T11:58:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pittsburgh Poet</username>
        <id>1449338</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* A personal bugbear: &quot;this resulted&quot; */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">== The great Re-edit of 2008 ==
It has been reorganized and re-edited in Nov 2008 to better meet the content and organization that the college board has defined for a course in AP U.S. History. The content of the book was carefully chosen for NPOV, significance and interest. We are very interested in the success of the book and any feedback and improvments would be greatly appreciated.

I look forward towards any and all discussion on the content and organization of the book, which we (Geoff Plourde) feel needs to be as close to the college board listed topics as possible.--[[User:JoliePA|JoliePA]] ([[User talk:JoliePA|talk]]) 15:48, 29 October 2008 (UTC)

==ARCHIVE==
(such significant changes to the organization that the following comments may no longer be relevant)

some one can change the rev. box to only one purple box its not 50% yet
and the pdf is out of date

I agree that the chapters are a little short, but I think I can help to expand many of them, especially if this is going to be based off of the AP US History course--I have the 11th and 12th editions of '''The American Pageant''', a rather widely used textbook on the subject of AP US History--what are the legal restraints on using that textbook as a reference for the creation of this wikibook? --[[user:Mance|Mance]]

----

http://www.collegeboard.com/prod_downloads/ap/students/ushistory/ap_cd_ushistory.pdf contains a course description that runs to 33 &quot;chapters&quot; of topics.  As this text book is going to be, at least initially, based on the College Board's Advanced Placement course, perhaps it should reasonably closely follow the course outline's topics.  Since the the contents of this book ends at 1960 but the course outline goes up to today, I have added a few suggested chapters for others to expand on. [[User:210.86.34.179|210.86.34.179]] 09:59, 7 Jan 2004 (UTC)

----

I don't think that the title of Chapter 26, ''Another Bush, September 11, Iraq again, and Terror (2001-2004)''; it seems somewhat pejorative.  It somewhat diminishes Bush (43) as the continuation of the Bush (41), and his presidency (43's) is very different from his father's.  Iraq ''again'', also seems POV.  (Emphasis added, b/c that's how I think most people will read it.)  That said, the rest of the outline seems great.  I look forward to contributing to this wikibook.--[[User:Mcornelius|Mcornelius]] 00:38, 24 Sep 2004 (UTC)


-----

== chapter titles ==

It seems as if I've heard the chapter titles from another source.  Are they original?--[[User:64.254.129.161|64.254.129.161]] 06:13, 14 Feb 2005 (UTC)
:they appear to be so!--[[Special:Contributions/165.138.245.1|165.138.245.1]] ([[User talk:165.138.245.1|talk]]) 16:06, 1 November 2008 (UTC)
::Absolutely!  in keeping with the required topics of the College board I'm trying to keep the discussion limited to content normally covered in the AP history test.  the content might be 'spiced up' but lets keep the organization ruthlessly specific to there requirements, no matter how interesting or uninteresting you think it might be for the text book.  --[[User:JoliePA|JoliePA]] ([[User talk:JoliePA|talk]]) 16:06, 5 November 2008 (UTC)

== Broken link ==

(First link is broken. Know what it should link to? Change it.) -[[User:Hyperlink|Hyperlink]]
: I clicked on the links, but they all seem to work with my browser. Could you be more specific, which was the broken link? --[[User:Andreas Ipp|Andreas]] 09:45, 29 Mar 2005 (UTC)
:: I was referring to [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/WikiWiki]. First link in the second grouping of links, the one regarding wikirelated things.--[[User:Hyperlink|Hyperlink]] 21:08, 29 Mar 2005 (UTC)
::: It should obviously refer to http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wiki . I corrected the link. --[[User:Andreas Ipp|Andreas]] 10:37, 30 Mar 2005 (UTC)

----
My teacher gave me a packet of keywords to study before taking the test, and it really helped.  Hope no one minds me adding it here.&lt;br&gt;[[User:Cnelson|Cnelson]] 20:06, 15 May 2005 (UTC)

== an observation.... ==

Is it just me, or are these chapters a little on the short side? If this is intended to be used for AP History, the chapters need to have quite a bit more detail. I don't mean to diminish all the work that has been done so far, but for this book to compete with commercial college textbooks it has to go into the same depth of detail.

== Room for Improvement? == 
In the spirit of contstructive criticism I offer the following.

I was surfing through this section and delved into the subsection on the U.S. Civil War. My comments would be that the articles are rather &quot;thin&quot; and make little use of existing articles in Wikipedia.

I'll contribute when I can, but thought that I would point out that it might be possible to save much writing and rewriting by referencing already extant articles. I'll be adding links as I notice them to Wikipedia and other sources as I think that hypertexting is one of the more efficient ways of developing such a project.

I'd also suggest that if this is to serve as a functional textbook there should be certain additions:

* Tests (even for the casual reader, a self test at the tend of the section is a useful tool to verify comprehension)
* Bibliographies and/or a &quot;Recommended Reading&quot;.
* This suggestion is a bit farther out, if sites don't exist for opinions and exploring &quot;What If?&quot; (every historian's favorite game) some facility should be developed to that end. Nothing encourages comprehension of history better than considering the possibilities if things had gone differently.
* Some determination for a target age group, unless we're settled on the first listed recommended test subjects.

For my part, where and when I can, I will be adding and working on some of these sections. My intent unless I hear otherwise will be to copyedit for the most part and to not duplicate what could be found in the articles and sites linked to from the pages.

[[User:Erraunt|erraunt]] 18:28, 4 October 2005 (UTC)
:Linking may help, but this wouldn't be a book if it was a big list of links. You should, in my opinion, be able to print this out and use it like a textbook (for the most part).Also, &quot;What ifs&quot; can be highly debatable, and they aren't really history. If used, they should be limited  [[User:Ericruud|Ericruud]] 03:03, 20 December 2006 (UTC)


It is a &quot;text book&quot; which are not suppose to go into great detail.  What my be helpful hyperlinks to wiki pages that would go into greater detail.

== Blue words in the PDF ==
Since the PDF book is directly copied and pasted from the text here, some of the words in the PDF appear blue as if they would still be linked to something, and the compiler of the PDF hasn't bothered to unlink them, it seems. Please someone unlink the words that appear blue in the PDF, they serve no purpose and are a distraction. --[[User:84.239.157.217|84.239.157.217]] 14:50, 19 August 2006 (UTC)

== Adding Questions ==

If no one objects, I can add several review questions at the end of each chapter to reinforce the material (as suggested by &quot;erraunt&quot; in October of last year). Not too many, maybe somewhere between three to six, maybe seven. Note that this will only apply to &quot;completed chapters&quot;.

[[User:Ccny930|Ccny930]] 19:02, 28 October 2006
== midnite judges== 
we need to include it and become more detaild!

see me at my page if u know anything but don't know where to put it[[User:TrackMonkey|TrackMonkey]] 23:04, 3 November 2006 (UTC)

== room ==

Is this how long the book should be? This is about as long as the colonial chapters in my (AP) US book.. 
[[User:Ericruud|Ericruud]] 03:03, 20 December 2006 (UTC)

== Secession, secession, secession... ==

Why are there three chapters on secession and the Confederacy (&quot;States' Rights&quot;, &quot;Intro to Secession&quot;, &quot;Farewell to the Star Spangled Banner&quot;)? Shouldn't we just consolidate them into one chapter? Or add them into &quot;The Civil War&quot;?

--[[User:Ccny930|Ccny930]] 23:33, 20 December 2006 (UTC)

:The Civil War chapter itself is too long, so consolidation of all four would result in quite a load for quite a few browsers. I have merged (with [[User:Webaware]]'s help) the &quot;Intro&quot; and &quot;Farewell&quot; chapters. The &quot;States' Rights&quot; chapter might also be better merged in as well, but there are other issues to be dealt with beforehand. [[User:Neoptolemus|'''Νεοπτόλεμος''']] ( [[User talk:Neoptolemus|talk]] &amp;#124; [[Special:Emailuser/Neoptolemus|email]] &amp;#124; [[Special:Contributions/Neoptolemus|contribs]] ) 23:30, 11 March 2008 (UTC)

== New chapter ==

I apologize for not mentioning it earlier, but I've added a new chapter about exploration (&quot;European Exploration and the New World&quot;) after realizing that there was no content dealing with this topic. If anyone is interested (or still paying attention to this wikibook), please feel free to add any relevant content. Thanks!

--[[User:Ccny930|Ccny930]] 19:19, 23 January 2007 (UTC)

==Failures of traditional histories==
After briefly reading through a few portions of this Wikibook, I've come to fear that it may repeat some of the failures of traditional histories. That is, it seems to favor the same sectors of society that the average high school textbook does. I would highly recommend that the editors of this book check out Howard Zinn's ''[[w:A People's History of the United States|A People's History of the United States]]'', which will provide a lot of facts that will help this book rise above the mediocrity of standard issue history textbooks. If this is going to be a truly unbiased book, then it's going to have to cover not only presidents and their history, but also the histories of black people, Native Americans, women, laborers, radicals, and other people usually ignored by traditional histories. -- [[User talk:LGagnon|LGagnon]] 06:26, 6 August 2007 (UTC)
:Be bold!  [[User:Jade Knight|Jade Knight]] ([[User talk:Jade Knight|talk]]) 21:03, 14 October 2008 (UTC)
==If you enjoy this==
If you enjoy this novel, check out [[The Big Unit]]
:That book got deleted as it was 100% blatant copyright violations or plagiarism. &amp;nbsp;'''&amp;mdash;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Mike.lifeguard|&lt;b style=&quot;color:#309;&quot;&gt;Mike.lifeguard&lt;/b&gt;]]'''&amp;nbsp;&amp;#124;&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Mike.lifeguard|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#309;&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 17:13, 9 November 2008 (UTC)

== The Great(er) Re-edit of 2009 ==

Hello, all!

As you can see, I have yet to sign up.  I have been cordially invited to, and likely will.  Problem is, I am a horrible procrastinator. :)

In the re-edit, I am working on a massive overhaul and reorganization to make the book flow more coherantly and fill it with content more complete.  Don't get me wrong, some sections are more complete than others, and my main intent is to fill the void as necessary.  The more complete sections (such as the Civil War, save for a few specific major battles) will stay pretty much as they are, of course.

--[[Special:Contributions/132.56.180.7|132.56.180.7]] ([[User talk:132.56.180.7|talk]]) 17:39, 27 May 2009 (UTC)

*P.S. -- I should note, this is my work IP, shared by perhaps hundreds of other people.  My main IP has also been used in the editing of this article.  I suppose this is just another great reason to sign up ASAP!... after lunch, that is...

--[[Special:Contributions/132.56.180.7|132.56.180.7]] ([[User talk:132.56.180.7|talk]]) 17:41, 27 May 2009 (UTC)

== Flow ==

Hey y'all, 

Did a little reorganizing to get the book to flow better. You can now click through from the cover to the middle of the book! Unfortunately its now 6 am so i didn't finish.

[[User:aozeba|aozeba]]

== Anyone want to give me an orientation? ==
I'm starting work on a separate U.S. History textbook project for a nonprofit working on Open Educational Resources. The philosophy is slightly different, with each chapter consisting of a collection of primary and secondary documents--so it's not really duplicating your work. I was thinking of using some of the text from your book (or Wikipedia articles) as secondary sources.  It would (in theory) provide some contextualizing, synthetic elements that the primary sources lack, but also be held up not as an infallible source, but as one of many possible accounts, which students would be invited to read critically. Anyway, I'd be interested to talk with someone who knows this project well and can tell me about which parts are going to be developed enough for that kind of use, or whether I should just go to the Wikipedia article. FWIW, I'm a doctoral student in education at Stanford, working on this project for http://www.ck12.org, and know my way around the wiki world fairly well, but not WikiBooks in particular. Please reply to me here or drop me a message, if you'd be up for a phone call. Thanks. --[[User:Rmlucas|Rmlucas]] ([[User talk:Rmlucas|talk]]) 05:13, 13 June 2009 (UTC)

== Orphans ==
*[[US History/New Nation]] 
*[[US History/Indian Tribes]]
*[[US History/Friction Between States]]
*[[US History/Secession]]
*[[US History/Early Colonial Period]]
*[[US History/States Rights]]

are orphaned.  Please link them from the contents or mark them for deletion. -- [[User:Adrignola|Adrignola]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Adrignola|talk]] [[Special:Contributions/Adrignola|contribs]]&lt;/sup&gt; 04:29, 7 February 2010 (UTC)

== New Sweden ==

New Sweden should be included in the colonial section. They founded Philadelphia and Wilmington, cooperated with the native Americans, and lasted over 30 years until the colony was bought by the Dutch. We should also include sections on the founding of Florida and more on the French coming into America.--[[User:Stidmatt|Stidmatt]] ([[User talk:Stidmatt|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Stidmatt|contribs]]) 00:28, 15 August 2011 (UTC)

== finish 2002 to present era ==

could anybody finish the latest era in us history, it would be a huge favor.

== Seems to be missing ==
Among other things USA and China. USA and Japan. USA and Israel. USA war with Spain.  --[[User:Panic2k4|Panic]] ([[User talk:Panic2k4|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Panic2k4|contribs]]) 05:18, 29 January 2012 (UTC)

== Organization ==

Hey, I've noticed that there have been sections on education, women's history, and demographics added to some chapters, in many cases being integrated poorly.  I also noticed that we have an orphaned article dealing with native American tribes, and very little coverage on the Industrial Revolution prior to the American Civil War.  Therefore, I propose the following topical histories, each to be listed in a separate section of the table of contents entitled &quot;Topical histories&quot;:

*[[US History/Women's History]]
*[[US History/History of Education in America]]
*[[US History/Demographic History]]
*[[US History/Industrial Revolution]]
*[[US History/Native American History]]

Thoughts? [[User:Purplebackpack89|Purplebackpack89]] ([[User talk:Purplebackpack89|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Purplebackpack89|contribs]]) 22:08, 2 June 2012 (UTC)
:I would add [[US History/Crime]] to that list, if there is enough material on that subject which doesn't fit well elsewhere. [[User:Belteshazzar|Belteshazzar]] ([[User talk:Belteshazzar|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Belteshazzar|contribs]]) 04:18, 3 June 2012 (UTC)
::Go for it [[User:Purplebackpack89|Purplebackpack89]] ([[User talk:Purplebackpack89|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Purplebackpack89|contribs]]) 13:57, 3 June 2012 (UTC)

== US History removed from Wikibooks Featured Books ==

This book is no longer a Featured Book.  The discussion which ended in the removal of this status can be found at [[Wikibooks:Featured_books]].  --[[User:Xania|ЗAНИA]] [[Image:Flag_of_Estonia.svg|15px]][[User talk:Xania|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]] 23:08, 14 January 2013 (UTC)

== Second Great Awakening ==

I see nowhere this is covered in the current text. Where may I put it? [[User:Pittsburgh Poet|Pittsburgh Poet]] ([[User talk:Pittsburgh Poet|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Pittsburgh Poet|contribs]]) 23:06, 17 May 2014 (UTC)
LATER: Never mind. :( [[User:Pittsburgh Poet|Pittsburgh Poet]] ([[User talk:Pittsburgh Poet|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Pittsburgh Poet|contribs]]) 23:38, 17 May 2014 (UTC)

== Request for deletion: the orphan chapter US History/Vikings ==

Erik the Red and Leif Erikson are discussed in the section on European history. Erik's other children, and Snorri Sturluson, seem irrelevant. [[User:Pittsburgh Poet|Pittsburgh Poet]] ([[User talk:Pittsburgh Poet|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Pittsburgh Poet|contribs]]) 11:03, 30 May 2014 (UTC)

Now deleted. [[User:Pittsburgh Poet|Pittsburgh Poet]] ([[User talk:Pittsburgh Poet|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Pittsburgh Poet|contribs]]) 12:54, 14 June 2014 (UTC)

== Flow, two ==

There are problems with the big, complicated subject of American History being organized into a Wikibook. There is no current way of seeing subheadings within chapters. You cannot tell, for example, from looking at a chapter in the table of contents that it has a certain important development within it (e.g., public education, a Supreme Court decision, an advocate for a disadvantaged minority). What is more, there is no current way of linking subheadings within chapters. You could not see, for example, that the continual expansion of technology is a continuing theme in our history. More simply, you cannot see that an account of one presidential election occurs *twice* in succeeding chapters, creating redundancy &amp; confusion. This seems to negate an important advantage of the Internet, though paper books also have ways of indicating these themes. 

I am looking at other Wikibooks to see how they have solved these problems. What works? I could use advice. [[User:Pittsburgh Poet|Pittsburgh Poet]] ([[User talk:Pittsburgh Poet|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Pittsburgh Poet|contribs]]) 11:44, 18 June 2014 (UTC)

== A personal bugbear: &quot;this resulted&quot; ==

No matter what one's view of history -- &quot;Great Man&quot; theory, economic forces, or movement causation -- try to show how one action affects another. There are too many phrases like &quot;this resulted,&quot; with nothing showing *how* something grew from something else. What is the relationship between the Second Great Revival and the Temperance crusade? If one is quoting a source (as I do too seldom), try to show the relationship in the quote. [[User:Pittsburgh Poet|Pittsburgh Poet]] ([[User talk:Pittsburgh Poet|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Pittsburgh Poet|contribs]]) 11:58, 22 June 2014 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>ju69cdvo4rcf7hcn9ucev97qagcgy2u</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Modern Physics/Waves in Spacetime</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3652</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1526415</id>
      <parentid>1090138</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-06-09T23:56:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>recat</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{AspecrTOC}}
== Applications of Special Relativity ==

In this chapter we continue the study of special relativity by applying the ideas developed in the previous chapter to the study of waves. 

First, we shall show how to describe waves in the context of spacetime. We then see how waves which have no preferred reference frame (such as that of a medium supporting them) are constrained by special relativity to have a dispersion relation of a particular form. This dispersion relation turns out to be that of the relativistic matter waves of quantum mechanics. 

Second, we shall investigate the Doppler shift phenomenon, in which the frequency of a wave takes on different values in different coordinate systems. 

Third, we shall show how to add velocities in a relativistically consistent manner. This will also prove useful when we come to discuss particle behaviour in special relativity.

A new mathematical idea will be presented in the context of relativistic waves, namely the spacetime vector or four-vector. Writing the laws of physics totally in terms of relativistic scalars and four-vectors ensures that they will be valid in all inertial reference frames.

=== Waves in Spacetime ===

Waves in Spacetime

We now look at the characteristics of waves in spacetime. Recall that a wave in one space dimension can be represented by

&lt;math&gt;A(x,t) = A_0 \sin(kx- \omega t) \,&lt;/math&gt;

where &lt;math&gt;A_0&lt;/math&gt; is the (constant) amplitude of the wave, &lt;math&gt;k&lt;/math&gt; is the wavenumber, and &lt;math&gt;\omega&lt;/math&gt; is the angular frequency, and that the quantity &lt;math&gt;\phi = kx - \omega t&lt;/math&gt; is called the &lt;i&gt;phase&lt;/i&gt; of the wave. For a wave in three space dimensions, the wave is represented in a similar way,

&lt;math&gt;A(\mathbf{x},t) = A_0 \sin(\mathbf{k}\cdot\mathbf{x}- \omega t) &lt;/math&gt;	

where &lt;math&gt;\mathbf{x}&lt;/math&gt; is now the position vector and &lt;math&gt;\mathbf{k}&lt;/math&gt; is the wave vector. The magnitude of the wave vector, &lt;math&gt;|\mathbf{k}| = k&lt;/math&gt; is just the wavenumber of the wave and the direction of this vector indicates the direction the wave is moving. The phase of the wave in this case is &lt;math&gt;\phi = \mathbf{k}\cdot\mathbf{x} - \omega t&lt;/math&gt;.

&lt;div style=&quot;float:right;margin:0 0 1em 1em;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;
[[image:Introductory_Physics_fig_5.1.png|Figure 5.1: Sketch of wave fronts for a wave in spacetime.]]&lt;br&gt;'''Figure 5.1''': Sketch of wave fronts for a wave in spacetime. The large arrow is the associated wave four-vector, which has slope &lt;math&gt;\omega /ck&lt;/math&gt;. The slope of the wave fronts is the inverse, &lt;math&gt;ck/ \omega&lt;/math&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;

In the one-dimensional case &lt;math&gt;\phi = kx - \omega t&lt;/math&gt;. A wave front has constant phase &lt;math&gt;\phi&lt;/math&gt;, so solving this equation for &lt;math&gt;t&lt;/math&gt; and multiplying by &lt;math&gt;c&lt;/math&gt;, the speed of light in a vacuum, gives us an equation for the world line of a wave front: 

&lt;math&gt;ct = \frac{ckx}{\omega}-\frac{c\phi}{\omega}=\frac{ck}{u_p}-\frac{c\phi}{\omega} \quad \mbox{(wave front).}&lt;/math&gt;

The slope of the world line in a spacetime diagram is the coefficient of &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt;, or &lt;math&gt;c/u_p&lt;/math&gt;, where &lt;math&gt;u_p = \omega/k&lt;/math&gt; is the phase speed.

[[Category:{{FULLBOOKNAME}}|{{FULLCHAPTERNAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>bzetjx97xn423vx3fnxmxa88envq5s6</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Introductory Physics fig 5.1.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>3653</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1526414</id>
      <parentid>904398</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-06-09T23:55:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>+category</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Sketch of wave fronts for a wave in spacetime.

==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}

[[Category:Special Relativity]]</text>
      <sha1>9xb8xc2obh17tzqmgiuj1s7jzba5as8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Dutch/Lesson 2</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3663</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2530356</id>
      <parentid>2031732</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-05-30T11:08:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>91.199.6.246</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Grammatica 2-2 Adjectives, demonstratives and articles */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;center&gt;
&lt;big&gt;&lt;big&gt;&lt;big&gt;Les 2 ~ Lesson 2&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/big&gt;

&lt;big&gt;Onbekenden en vrienden ~ Strangers and Friends&lt;/big&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
{| align=center cellspacing=10 class=PrettyTextBox style=&quot;background-color: rgb(249, 249, 249); -moz-border-radius: 1em; margin-bottom: 1em;&quot;
| • '''Simple conversations II'''
|-
| • '''Grammar: Introduction to Verbs '''
|-
| • '''Grammar: Adjectives, demonstratives and articles'''
|-
| • '''Syntax: Question and negation'''
|-
|}
----
&lt;small&gt;&lt;&lt; [[Dutch/Lesson 1|Les 1]] |&lt;/small&gt; '''Les 2''' &lt;small&gt;| [[Dutch/Lesson 3|Les 3]] &gt;&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
----
==Gesprek 2-1==

#First push the button to simply listen to the following conversation.
#Then study the text to find out what the meaning is. If necessary, hover your mouse over a {{C|word|and see an instant translation}} if you don't know it. Once you think you understand the conversation open the dropdown below to see the full translation.
#Finally listen to the conversation again and see how much you understand. First with eyes open to see the text. Then do it with eyes closed.
#If there are parts you do not understand when listening, go back to step 2.

[[Image:Nl-Dutch-gesprek-2-1.ogg|40px|noicon]]

:''Standish'': {{C|Goedemorgen|good morning}} {{C|meneer|sir, mister}}. {{C|Hoe|How}} {{C|gaat|goes}} {{C|het|it}} {{C|met|with}} {{C|u|you (polite)}}?
:''Jansen'': Goedemorgen. {{C|Goed|goed}}. {{C|Hoe|How}} {{C|heet|are called}} u?
:''Standish'': {{C|Ik|I}} {{C|heet|am called}} Standish. Robert Standish. {{C|En|and}} u? {{C|Wat|What}} is {{C|uw|your}} {{C|naam|name}}?
:''Jansen'': U heet Robert? {{C|Wat|how, what}} {{C|toevallig|coincidental}}! Ik heet {{C|ook|also}} Robert. Robert Jansen.
:''Standish'': {{C|Inderdaad|Indeed}} toevallig! Wij heten {{C|allebei|both}} Robert. {{C|Weet|know}} u {{C|hoe|how}} {{C|die|that}} {{C|mevrouw|lady}} {{C|daar|there}} {{C|heet|is called}}?
:''Jansen'': {{C|Ik geloof|I believe}} {{C|dat|that}} {{C|zij|she}} Alice {{C|heet|is called}}.
:''Standish'': Gelooft u dat {{C|of|or}} bent u {{C|zeker|certain}} {{C|ervan|thereof, of it}}?
:''Jansen'': {{C|Vrij|rather}} {{C|zeker|certain}}. Ze heet Alice Koopman.
{{Dutch/Translation|gesprek 2-1
|
:''Standish'': Good morning sir. How are you?
:''Jansen'': Goed morning. Fine. What is your name?
:''Standish'': I'm called Standish. Robert Standish. And you? What is your name?
:''Jansen'': Is your name Robert? What a coincidence! My name is Robert as well. Robert Jansen.
:''Standish'': A coincidence indeed! We are both called Robert. Do you know what that lady there is called?
:''Jansen'': I believe that her name is Alice.
:''Standish'': Do you believe that or are you sure of it?
:''Jansen'': Pretty sure. Her name is Alice Koopman.
}}
{{Dutch/Exercise|waar of niet waar
|
Study the above text and answer the following questions with
:Dit is waar - (this is true)
:Dit is niet waar - (this is not true)
# Meneer Standish heet Charles
# Meneer Standish en meneer Jansen heten allebei Robert
# Dit is erg toevallig
# Meneer Standish {{C|ziet|sees}} een mevrouw {{C|staan|stand, standing}}
# Meneer Standish gelooft dat zij Heleen heet.
# Standish en Jansen zijn {{C|goede|good}} {{C|vrienden|friends}}. {{C|Zij|They}} {{C|zeggen|say}} jij en jou {{C|tegen|to}} {{C|elkaar|each other}}.
|
# Meneer Standish heet Charles - niet waar. Hij heet Robert.
# Meneer Standish en meneer Jansen heten allebei Robert - waar
# Dit is erg toevallig - waar
# Meneer Standish ziet een mevrouw staan - waar
# Meneer Standish gelooft dat zij Heleen heet - niet waar. 
# Standish en Jansen zijn goede vrienden. Zij zeggen jij en jou tegen elkaar - niet waar. Zij zeggen 'u'.
}}

==Pronunciation drill 2-1. Hoe heet u?==
{{Dutch/Exercise|Your turn to say something
|
The little sentence &quot;Hoe heet u?&quot; literally means: ''What are you called?'' and is usually translated as: ''What's your name?''. It presents some serious pronunciation problems particularly for American speakers, because it contains three unfamiliar sounds. There are two difficult vowels, the [u] of &quot;hoe&quot; and the [y] of &quot;u&quot;. They are hard because the American &quot;u&quot; is much less rounded than either and also more or less intermediary between the two in tongue position. 
:'''Lips''': Both Dutch vowels are ''strongly rounded'', the lips are held as in blowing a kiss. 
:'''Tongue''': For the [y] the tongue is pushed forward to produced a little cup just behind the teeth, for the [u] it is pulled back to form a cup in the throat area.

In addition the Dutch &quot;h&quot; is a bit different, because it is generally ''voiced'' [ɦ]

Listen to the recording and try to reproduce the sounds:
*{{audio|Nl-Dutch-hoeheetu-drill.ogg|Hoe heet u?}}

|
:If you are French, Turkish or German the two vowels [u]/[y] are a piece of cake, but not the [ɦ].
:If you are Hispanic, Italian or Russian the [u] is easy, but not [y] and [ɦ].
:If you speak Arabic only the [y] should be a problem.

Depending on your background you may have to revisit this to get your ears, lips and tongue used to it all.
}}
==Grammatica 2-1 ~ Introduction to Verbs==
A '''[[Wikipedia:en:Verb|verb]]''' (in Dutch: ''werkwoord'') is that part of speech that describes an action. Verbs come in an almost bewildering array of tenses, moods, voices and aspects, and there are several major types: intransitive, transitive, ditransitive, and ergative verbs.  

Fortunately, the Dutch verb is not too different from the English one, although it does have a few more forms.

  I &lt;u&gt;am called&lt;/u&gt; Standish                      ''Ik &lt;u&gt;heet&lt;/u&gt; Standish'' 
  What &lt;u&gt;are&lt;/u&gt; you &lt;u&gt;called&lt;/u&gt; (named)?              ''Hoe &lt;u&gt;heet&lt;/u&gt; u?'' 
  ...that she &lt;u&gt;is named (called)&lt;/u&gt; 'Alice'     ''...dat ze 'Alice' &lt;u&gt;heet&lt;/u&gt;''
  We &lt;u&gt;are&lt;/u&gt; both &lt;u&gt;called&lt;/u&gt; Robert                 ''Wij &lt;u&gt;heten&lt;/u&gt; allebei Robert''
 
The Dutch verb ''heten'' can best be translated as &quot;to be named&quot; or &quot;to be called&quot; and we see two forms of it here
# a singular one: ''heet'' used with ''ik'',''u'',''ze'' 
# a plural one ''heten'' used for ''wij'' (as well the other plural persons).

Actually there are usually three forms. This can be seen from:

  I believe                                         Ik geloof
  do you believe?                                   geloof'''t''' u?

In the case of ''heten'' the extra '''''-t''''' does not get added because the stem already ends in a ''-t''.

In a [[Dutch/Lesson 5|later lesson]] we will revisit the verb forms associated with each person.

The irregular verb ''to be''-''zijn'' has a few more forms in both languages.

==Gesprek 2-2 ~ De Engelsman==
[[Image:Nl-Dutch-gesprek-2-2.ogg|40px|noicon]]
:Meneer Standish, een Engelsman, {{C|gaat|goes}} {{C|naar|to}} de {{C|boekhouding|bookkeeping, administration}}.
* ''Meneer Standish'': Goedemorgen. {{C|Bent|Are}} {{C|u|you}} mevrouw Koopman?
* ''Mevrouw Nieman'': Nee. {{C|Zij|She}} is het {{C|meisje|girl}} {{C|daar|there}}. Ik ben mevrouw Nieman. En u? {{C|Hoe heet u|What is your name}}?
* ''Meneer Standish'': Ik heet Standish.
* ''Mevrouw Nieman'': {{C|Aangenaam|Pleasant}} {{C|kennis te maken|to make acquintance}}. Bent u {{C|Nederlander|Dutchman}}?
* ''Meneer Standish'': Nee, ik ben een Engelsman. 
* ''Mevrouw Nieman'': {{C|Echt waar|really}}? Dat is {{C|erg|very}} interessant. Kunt u mij {{C|verstaan|understand}}?
* ''Meneer Standish'': {{C|Ja|Yes}}. {{C|Als|If}} u {{C|een beetje|a little}} {{C|langzamer|more slowly}} {{C|spreekt|speak}}.
* ''Mevrouw Nieman'': Goed zo! {{C|Mag|May}} ik u {{C|mijn|my}} collega {{C|voorstellen|introduce, present}}, mevrouw Koopman?
* ''Meneer Standish'': {{C|Jazeker|certainly}}!

{{Dutch/Translation|Gesprek 2-2|
:Mr. Standish, an Englishman goes to the administration department.

* ''Mr. Standish'': Good morning. Are you Mrs. Koopman?
* ''Mrs. Nieman'': No, she is the girl over there. I am Mrs. Nieman. And you? What is your name?
*  ''Mr. Standish'': Standish is my name. (lit.: I'm called Standish)
* ''Mrs. Nieman'': Glad to meet you. Are you a Dutchman?
* ''Mr. Standish'': No, I am an Englishman
* ''Mrs. Nieman'': Really? That is very interesting. Can you understand me?
* ''Mr. Standish'': Yes, If you speak a bit more slowly.
* ''Mrs. Nieman'':  All right. May I introduce my colleague, Mrs. Koopman.
* ''Mr. Standish'': Certainly!
}}
==Vocabulary drill 2-1==
{{Dutch/Exercise|Some common phrases
|
Here are a few very common expressions.&lt;br&gt;
Listen to this drill, repeat in the pauses and say the Dutch phrase when told to.
[[Image:nl-Dutch-ch2-vocabulary-drill.ogg|40px|noicon]]
|
:What is your name? - ''Hoe heet je?''
:What time is it? - ''Hoe laat is het?''
:Good morning - ''Goedemorgen''
:Please - ''Alstublieft''
:You are welcome - ''Graag gedaan''
:Thank you - ''Dank u wel''
}}
==Grammatica 2-2 ~ Inversion in questions and negations==

You may have wondered about the order of the words in

: ik geloof dat ze Alice '''''heet'''''.

Even though Dutch verbs are not so much more complicated than English ones, word order is. In fact it is quite a bit more complicated than in English. For the moment let's just leave the above sentence for what it is and start with questions.

===Questions===

A question sentence in Dutch simply '''''reverses''''' the order of subject and verb. 

Recall: ''&lt;font color=blue&gt;U&lt;/font&gt; &lt;font color=green&gt;heet&lt;/font&gt; meneer Standish'' ('You are named Mr. Standish). 

It became: ''Hoe &lt;font color=green&gt;heet&lt;/font&gt; &lt;font color=blue&gt;u&lt;/font&gt;?'' as a question

The normal word order of &lt;font color=blue&gt;subject (''u'' or &quot;you&quot;)&lt;/font&gt; then &lt;font color=green&gt;verb (''heten'')&lt;/font&gt; is ''reversed'' and, in this case, an interrogative (''hoe'' or &quot;how&quot;) added. 

Additional examples:
{|
|-
| ''Hoe &lt;font color=green&gt;gaat&lt;/font&gt; &lt;font color=blue&gt;het&lt;/font&gt; met u?'' ||↔|| ''&lt;font color=blue&gt;Het&lt;/font&gt; &lt;font color=green&gt;gaat&lt;/font&gt; goed met u''  
|-
| ''&lt;font color=green&gt;Bent&lt;/font&gt; &lt;font color=blue&gt;u&lt;/font&gt; mevrouw Koopman?''||↔|| ''&lt;font color=blue&gt;U&lt;/font&gt; &lt;font color=green&gt;bent&lt;/font&gt; mevrouw Koopman'' 
|-
| ''&lt;font color=green&gt;Bent&lt;/font&gt; &lt;font color=blue&gt;u&lt;/font&gt; Nederlander?'' ||↔|| ''&lt;font color=blue&gt;U&lt;/font&gt; &lt;font color=green&gt;bent&lt;/font&gt; Nederlander'' (&quot;You are Dutch&quot;).
|-
| ''&lt;font color=green&gt;Verstaat&lt;/font&gt; &lt;font color=blue&gt;u&lt;/font&gt; mij?''||↔||''&lt;font color=blue&gt;U&lt;/font&gt; &lt;font color=green&gt;verstaat&lt;/font&gt; mij'' (&quot;You understand me&quot;).
|-
| ''&lt;font color=green&gt;Gelooft &lt;font color=blue&gt;u&lt;/font&gt;?''||↔|| ''&lt;font color=blue&gt;Ik&lt;/font&gt; &lt;font color=green&gt;geloof''
|-
|[[Image:Nl-Dutch-grammatica-2-2.ogg|40px|noicon]]
|}
English does the same thing when using the verb ''to be'':

: I am - are you?
: ik ben - bent u?

Dutch does '''''not''''' use the auxiliary ''to do'' as English requires in most other cases:

: ik weet  -  weet u?
: I know   -  do you know? (instead of &quot;know you?&quot;)

===Negations===

The negative is formed by simply adding ''niet'' at the end:

:Ik versta u       -  I understand you
:Ik versta u niet  -  I do not understand you

Again, Dutch does ''not'' use the auxiliary ''to do''. (In fact using it sounds very foreign.)

Even a negative question does not use ''to do'':

:Verstaat u mij niet? - Don't you understand me?

{{Dutch/Exercise|questions and negations
|
Turn the following statements into questions and translate:
# U gelooft de man niet 
# De man ziet een vrouw
# U verstaat Nederlands
# Het meisje daar is Anne
# U hoort beneden mensen 
|
#Gelooft u de man niet? - Don't you believe the man?
#Ziet de man de vrouw? - Does the man see the woman?
#Verstaat u Nederlands? - Do you understand Dutch?
# Is het meisje daar Anne? - Is the girl there Anne?
# Hoort U beneden mensen? - Do you hear people downstairs?
}}

==Gesprek 2-3 ~ Het nieuwe meisje==
In this conversation, the parties are close friends.
* ''Karel'': Heleen, {{C|wie|who}} is dat {{C|nieuwe|new}} {{C|meisje|girl}}? Die brunette {{C|daar|there}}. 
* ''Heleen'': Ik {{C|geloof|believe}} dat ze Karolien heet. 
* ''Karel'': Ze is {{C|erg|very}} {{C|mooi|pretty, beautiful}}.
* ''Heleen'': Ze is {{C|leuk|cute}}, als je kleine meisjes met {{C|lange|long}} {{C|zwarte|black}} {{C|haren|hair}} {{C|leuk vindt|leuk vinden:fancy}}.
* ''Karel'': Ja. Ik ben {{C|gek|crazy}} op dat haar. Wat een {{C|mooie meid|babe}}!
* ''Heleen'': {{C|Karel toch|Shame on you}}!

{{Dutch/Translation|Gesprek 2-3|
*''Charley'': Helen, who is that new girl? That brunette there
*''Helen'': I believe her name is Caroline
*''Charley'': She is very beautiful
*''Helen'': She is cute, if you like little girls  with long black hair
*''Charley'': Yeah, I love that hair. What a beauty!
*''Helen'': But Charley! (Shame on you)
}}

==Grammatica 2-2 Adjectives, demonstratives and articles==
===Gender===
Where English uses the '''demonstrative pronoun''' ''that'', Dutch uses either ''dat'' or ''die'', recall:

:''dat'' nieuwe meisje. ''Die'' brunette. - ''that'' new girl, ''that'' brunette

Similarly, where English uses the '''article''' ''the'', Dutch has two possibilities: ''de'' or ''het'', recall:

:''de'' boekhouding, ''het'' meisje. - ''the'' administration, ''the'' girl

We will revisit this phenomenon (gender) in the next lesson more extensively. There is a bit of a problem with it in Dutch.

For the moment it is enough to realize that there are two kinds of words, 
:ones that take ''de'' and ''die''
:ones that take ''het'' and ''dat''

Both articles and demonstrative pronouns are a special kind of '''adjectives''': words that are added to make the meaning of another word more precise, like ''new'', ''small'' or ''exciting''

{{Dutch/Exercise|die en dat
|
Replace the articles by the correct demonstratives ''die'' or ''dat'' and translate (might have to guess a bit):
# Het huis  (house) is van het nieuwe meisje
# De huizen zijn erg groot.
# De boekhouding is niet in orde
# De brunette heeft lang haar.
# Ik weet het telefoonnummer niet.
# Weet jij wie de vrouw is?
|
# Dat huis is van dat nieuwe meisje - That house belongs to that new girl
# Die huizen zijn erg groot. - Those houses are very big
# Die boekhouding is niet in orde - The administration is not in order
# Die brunette heeft lang haar. - That brunette has long hair
# Ik weet dat telefoonnummer niet. - I do not know that telephone number
# Weet jij wie die vrouw is? Do you know who that woman is?
}}

===Inflection===
Recall that some adjectives in the dialogue ended in '''''-e''''' (mooi''e'' meid), sometimes they did  not (is erg mooi).

Adjectives can be used in two ways: in front of a noun and after a verb like ''is'' (a copula).  In English the adjective remains the same regardless:

:The house is '''red''' (copula + adjective)
:The '''red''' car (adjective + noun)

Behind a copula (as ''predicate'') this is true in Dutch as well:

:Ik ben gek (I am crazy)
:Ze is mooi (She is pretty)
:De auto is rood (The car is red)

But in Dutch they are ''inflected'' if they occur in front of a noun (as ''attribute''). Compare:

:de rode auto - the red car
:een rode auto - a red car
:de rode auto's - the red cars
:rode auto's  - red cars

Neuter words are the ones that carry the definite article ''het'' and the demonstrative ''dat''. They are a bit different (Again: we will revisit them in the next lesson.)

:het rode huis
:een '''rood''' huis - a red house
:de rode huizen
:rode huizen

As you see the adjective is not inflected after the indefinite article ''een''.

This also holds if there is no article:

:met groot gemak - with great ease (het gemak: neuter)

'''But''':

:in hoge nood - in desparate need (de nood)

Thus, apart from the indefinite neuter an attributive adjective is usually inflected with '''''-e'''''.

There are a few exceptions, compare e.g.:

:de man - the man
:een grote man  - a big man
:een groot man - a great man

{{Dutch/Exercise|inflection
|
Put the adjectives in parentheses in the correct form
# Dit is een (groot) boekhouding
# Deze haren zijn (lang)
# Dit (groot) huis is (hoog)
# Weet jij wie die (mooi) auto heeft?
# Dit is een (klein) meisje
|
# Dit is een grote boekhouding
# Deze haren zijn lang
# Dit grote huis is hoog
# Weet jij wie die mooie auto heeft?
# Dit is een klein meisje
}}

===Making nouns out of adjectives===
Adjectives can be turned into nouns, by assuming their inflected form:

:Dat is een grote  
::That is a big one
:Dat is een kleine
::That is a small one
:Die lange heeft mijn fiets gestolen
::That tall guy has stolen my bike

Notice that Dutch does not use 'one' in such cases.

There are a number of adjectives that can be turned into nouns by adding '''''-te'''''.  They all carry '''de'''. In English the corresponding suffix is '''''-th''''':

:wijd – wijdte (wide - width)
:lang – lengte (long, tall - length)
:groot – grootte (big - size)
:breed – breedte (broad - breadth) 
:eng – engte (narrow - narrowness)
:zwaar – zwaarte (heavy - heaviness)
:heet – hitte (hot - heat)
:warm – warmte (warm - warmth)
:zwak – zwakte (weak - weakness)
:sterk – sterkte (strong - strength)
:droog – droogte (dry - drought)
:hoog – hoogte (high - height)
:menig – menigte (many - crowd)
:duur – duurte (expensive - dearth) &lt;!-- en ja dat woord bestaat echt in het Engels) --&gt;
:gewoon – gewoonte (usual - habit)

More about nouns in the next lesson.

{{Dutch/Exercise|adjectives,word order
|
Translate into Dutch:
#She has red hair
# How is she doing?
#She has a small black car
# The length is not very great
#How tall is she?
#The red houses are nice
#Don't you believe that?
#The heat is very great
# Do you know who that heavy man is? 
|
#She has red hair
#:Zij heeft rood haar
# How is she doing?
#:Hoe gaat het met haar?
#She has a small black car
#:Ze heeft een kleine zwarte auto
# The length is not very great
#:De lengte is niet erg groot
#How tall is she?
#:Hoe lang is ze?
#The red houses are nice
#:De rode huizen zijn mooi
#Don't you believe that?
#: Geloof je dat niet?
#The heat is very great
#: De hitte is erg groot
# Do you know who that heavy man is? 
#: Weet jij wie die zware man is?
}}

==Woordenlijst 2==
{|class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left; float:left; clear:right; margin: 0.5em 0 0 0; border-style: solid; border: 1px solid #AAAAAA; border-right-width: 1px; border-bottom-width: 1px; border-collapse: collapse; font-size: 100%;&quot;
! Dutch word!!audio file!!English translation
|-
| de brunette      ||   ||        brunette
|- 
| de Engelsman     ||   ||        Englishman
|-
| het haar, de haren||{{audio|nl-haar.ogg|haar}}  ||        hair(s)
|-
| het meisje, de meisjes||{{audio|nl-meisje.ogg|meisje}}||      girl, girls
|-
| de collega       ||{{audio|nl-collega.ogg|collega}}||           colleague
|-
| Mag ik...voorstellen? ||{{audio|nl-mag ik voorstellen.ogg|mag ik voorstellen?}}||      May I introduce...?
|-
| Jazeker                 ||{{audio|nl-jazeker.ogg|jazeker}}||  yes, indeed
|-
| Aangenaam&lt;br&gt; kennis te maken ||{{audio|nl-aangenaam.ogg|aangenaam}}&lt;br&gt;{{audio|nl-kennismaken.ogg|kennismaken}} ||Pleased to meet you
|-
| Goed zo!            ||{{audio|nl-goedzo.ogg|goedzo}}      ||  That's nice!
|-
| gek zijn (op)             ||{{audio|nl-gek.ogg|gek}}&lt;br&gt;{{audio|nl-zijn.ogg|zijn}}||  to be crazy (about) 
|-
| verstaan                  ||{{audio|nl-verstaan.ogg|verstaan}}||  to understand
|-
|   verstaat u?             ||  ||  do you understand?
|-
| geloven                   || {{audio|nl-geloven.ogg|geloven}}|| to believe
|-
|   ik geloof               ||   || I believe
|-
| heten                     ||{{audio|nl-heten.ogg|heten}}||  to name, call (a name)
|-
|   ze heet                  ||  || she is called
|-
|praten                    ||{{audio|nl-praten.ogg|praten}}||  to speak, to talk
|-
|  u praat                 ||   || you speak
|-
|voorstellen               ||{{audio|nl-voorstellen.ogg|voorstellen}}||  to introduce
|-
|leuk vinden               ||{{audio|nl-leuk.ogg|leuk}}&lt;br&gt;{{audio|nl-vinden.ogg|vinden}}||  to like
|-
|  als je ... leuk vindt    ||  || if you like ...
|-
| Nederlands             ||{{audio|nl-Nederlands.ogg|Nederlands}} ||      Dutch
|-
| het (neuter)             ||{{audio|nl-het.ogg|het}} ||    the
|-
| de (m/f)                ||{{audio|nl-de.ogg|de}} ||     the
|-
| dat (neuter)            ||{{audio|nl-dat.ogg|dat}} ||     that
|-
| die (m/f)               ||{{audio|nl-die.ogg|die}} ||     that
|-
| daar                   ||{{audio|nl-daar.ogg|daar}} ||      there
|-
| daarginds              ||{{audio|nl-daarginds.ogg|daarginds}} ||      over there
|-
| daarachter            ||{{audio|nl-daarachter.ogg|daarachter}} ||       over there 
|-
| een                  ||{{audio|nl-een.ogg|een}} ||        a, an
|-
| een beetje            ||{{audio|nl-beetje.ogg|beetje}} ||       somewhat, a bit
|-
| haar                  ||{{audio|nl-haar.ogg|haar}} ||       her
|-
| interessant          ||{{audio|nl-interessant.ogg|interessant}} ||        interesting
|-
| leuk                ||{{audio|nl-leuk.ogg|leuk}} ||         cute
|-
| kort, korte         ||{{audio|nl-kort.ogg|kort}} ||         short
|-
| lang, lange        ||{{audio|nl-lang.ogg|lang}} ||          long
|-
| langzaam          ||{{audio|nl-langzaam.ogg|langzaam}} ||           slow
|-
| langzamer         ||{{audio|nl-langzamer.ogg|langzamer}} ||           slower
|-
| mijn              ||{{audio|nl-mijn.ogg|mijn}} ||           my
|-
| mij               ||{{audio|nl-mij.ogg|mij}} ||           me
|-
| mooi               ||{{audio|nl-mooi.ogg|mooi}} ||          beautiful
|-
| naar               ||{{audio|nl-naar.ogg|naar}} ||          to
|-
| nieuw, nieuwe      ||{{audio|nl-nieuw.ogg|nieuw}} ||          new
|-
| zwart, zwarte     ||{{audio|nl-zwart.ogg|zwart}} ||           black
|-
| zij               ||{{audio|nl-zij.ogg|zij}} ||           she
|-
| u           ||{{audio|nl-u.ogg|u}} ||                 you
|-
| als   ||{{audio|nl-als.ogg|als}} ||                       if
|-
| wie?   ||{{audio|nl-wie.ogg|wie}} ||                      who? 
|}
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot;&gt;

{{Dutch/Exercise|Additional vocabulary
|
Go to the [[Dutch/Vocabulary/Animals]] to learn the most important animals in the Dutch language. Once you know them all, do the self test to make sure you really do know them.
|
}}





&lt;small&gt;[[Dutch/Alfabet|Pronunciation Guide]] &gt;&gt; &lt;/small&gt;

:* [[Dutch/Lesson 2A|Advanced Lesson 2]] &gt;&gt;

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>jy8sur491pbatf21ddp17bw7ijijavy</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:German/Concepts Basic</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>3664</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1867382</id>
      <parentid>1864632</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-06-28T23:25:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>replaced: {{WikiProject Languages}} → {{WikiProject Languages|german=yes}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{WikiProject Languages|german=yes}} 

Hansm - I like the conversation you developed. It should replace the difficult one I had in Lesson 1 (1-2). Otherwise, the lesson material is similar to the existing, with the exception of discussing verbs.  That can be started here, but I was holding off because so much material (vocab, pronouns, wortd order) needs inclusion.  I can try putting the verb intro up front, or just delay one lesson (to your 0.2 for example) - [[User:Marshman|Marsh]] 17:26, 7 Jan 2004 (UTC)

Marsh - what I have done here was just to show up my ideas. Yes, you are right, there is much more to be explained as I thought on the first view. Anyway, I think verb forms are more important than polite and familar forms, aytually, this are special verb forms. Integrate it in your lesson as you like. I know, it's not easy at all. Btw, you see, my English always needs corrections and my grammatical knowlage about German is more intuition than knowing, althought I'm quite sure about it. But It's realy hard for me to give grammatical rules since I don't need them myself. -- [[User:Hansm|Hansm]] 19:30, 7 Jan 2004 (UTC)

=== Testing Questions ===
I do like this idea of having testing questions, developed here by [[User:217.24.226.196|217.24.226.196]] - [[User:Marshman|Marsh]] 17:38, 28 Feb 2004 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>iu3n59a9fe65nuokjq3mvzy9xocabdj</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Bourne Shell Scripting/Comparing Shells</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3666</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2713027</id>
      <parentid>2255254</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-13T20:46:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>207.81.46.117</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Why Bourne Shell */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Almost all books like this one have a section on (or very similar to) &quot;why you should use the shell/program flavor/language/etc. discussed in this book and not any of the others that perform the same tasks in a slightly different way&quot;. It seems to be pretty well mandatory.

However, this book will not do that. We'll talk a bit about &quot;why Bourne Shell&quot; of course. But you'll soon see that doesn't preclude other shells at all. And there's no good reason not to use another shell either, as we will explain a little further down.

==Bourne shell and other Unix command shells==

There are many Unix command shells available today. Bourne Shell is just one drop in a very large ocean. How do all these shells relate? Do they do the same things? Is one better than the other? Let's take a look at what makes a shell and what that means for all the different shells out there.

===How it all got started...===

The Unix operating system has had a unique outlook on the world ever since it was created back in the 1970s. It stands apart from most other operating systems in that its focus has always been towards ''power users'': people who want to squeeze every drop of performance out of their system and have the technical knowledge to do so. Unix was designed to be programmed and modified to the desires of the user. At its core, Unix does not have a user interface; instead it is comprised of a stable OS kernel and a versatile C library. If you're not trying to do actual hard-core programming but rather are trying to do day-to-day tasks (or even just want to put a little program together quickly), pure Unix is a tremendous pain in the backside.

In other words, it was clear from the start that a tool would be needed that would allow a user to make use of the functions offered him by the coding library and kernel without actually doing serious programming work. A tool in other words that could pass small commands on to the lower-level system quickly and easily. Without the need for a compiler or other fancy editor, but with the ability to tap into the enormous power of the underlying system. Stephen Bourne set himself to the task and came up with what he called a ''shell'': a small, on-the-fly compiler that could take one command at a time, translate it into the sequence of bits understood by the machine and have that command carried out. We now call this type of program an [[wiktionary:interpreter|interpreter]], but at the time, the term &quot;shell&quot; was much more common (since it was a shell over the underlying system for the user). Stephen's shell was slim, fast, and though a bit unwieldy at times, its power is still the envy of many current operating system command-line interfaces today. Since it was designed by Stephen Bourne, this shell is called the Bourne Shell. The executable is simply called ''sh'' and use of this shell in scripting is still so ubiquitous, there isn't a Unix-based system on this earth that doesn't offer a shell whose executable can be reached under the name sh.

===...And how it ended up===

Of course, everyone's a critic. The Bourne Shell saw tremendous use (indeed, it still does) and as a result, it became the de facto standard among Unix shells. But all sorts of people almost immediately (as well as with use) wanted new features in the shell, or a more familiar way of expressing commands, or something else. Many people built new shells that they felt continued where Bourne Shell ended. Some were completely compatible with Bourne Shell, others were less so. Some became famous, others flopped. But pretty much all of them look fondly upon Bourne Shell, the shell they call &quot;Dad...&quot;

A number of these shells can be run in sh-like mode, to more closely emulate that very first sh, though most people tend just to run their shells in the default mode, which provides more power than the minimum sh.

===It's Bourne Shell, but not as we know it....===

So there are a lot of shells around but you can find Bourne Shell everywhere, right? Good old ''sh'', just sitting there faithfully until the end of time....

Well, no, not really. Most of the sh exectuables out there nowadays aren't really the Bourne Shell anymore. Through a bit of Unix magic called a link (which allows one file to masquerade as another) the sh executable you find on any Unix system is likely actually to be one of the shells that is based on the Bourne shell. One of the most frequently used shells nowadays (with the ascent of free and open-source operating systems like Linux and FreeBSD) is a heavily extended form of the Bourne Shell produced by the Free Software Foundation, called [[w:Bash (Unix shell)|Bash]]. Bash hasn't forgotten its roots, though: it stands for the '''B'''ourne '''A'''gain '''SH'''ell.

Another example of a descendant shell standing in for its ancestor is the Korn Shell (ksh). Also an extension shell, it is completely compatible with sh -- it simply adds some features. Much the same is true for zsh.

Finally, a slightly different category is formed by the C Shell (csh) and its descendant tcsh. These shells do break compatibility to some extent, using different syntax for many commands. Systems that use these shells as standard shells often provide a real Bourne Shell executable to run generic Bourne Shell scripts.

Having read the above, you will understand why this book doesn't have to convince you to use Bourne Shell instead of any other shell: in most cases, there's no noticeable difference. Bourne Shell and its legacy have become so ingrained in the heart and soul of the Unix environment that you are using Bourne Shell when you are using practically any shell available to you.

==Why Bourne Shell== 

So only one real question remains: now that you find yourself on your own, cozy slice of a Unix system, with your own shell and all its capabilities, is there any real reason to use Bourne Shell rather than using the whole range of your shell's capabilities?

Well, it depends. Probably, there isn't. For the most part of course, you ''are'' using Bourne Shell by using the whole potential of your shell -- your shell is probably ''that'' similar to the Bourne Shell. But there is one thing you might want to keep in mind: someday, you might want to write a script that you might want to pass around to other people. Of course you can write your script using the full range of options that your shell offers you; but then it might not work on another machine with another shell. This is where the role of Bourne Shell as the Latin of Unix command shells comes in -- and also where it is useful to know how to write scripts targeted specifically at the Bourne Shell. If you write your scripts for the Bourne Shell and nothing but the Bourne Shell, chances are far better than equal that your script will run straight out of the mail attachment (don't tell me you're still using boxes to ship things -- come on, get with the program) on any command shell out there.

&lt;noinclude&gt;
{{auto navigation|Running Commands}}
[[Category:{{FULLBOOKNAME}}|{{FULLCHAPTERNAME}}]]
&lt;/noinclude&gt;</text>
      <sha1>1xbbrxxbgode03jui5jp7rzlt1yugvl</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>German/Level III/Markus Studiert</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3675</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1709736</id>
      <parentid>1709684</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-02-01T02:49:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Übersetzung 1-2 */ fixed link</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{German/Level III/Header}}
----
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;big&gt;&lt;big&gt;Lektion Eins für Fortgeschrittene&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/big&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

== Geschichte 1-3 ~ ''Markus studiert'' ==
:&lt;big&gt;Markus ist in der Universität. Er trinkt dort einen Kaffee und isst ein Brötchen. Danach geht er in die Bibliothek. Er sucht ein Buch über Biochemie. Er holt das Buch aus dem Regal und setzt sich an einen Tisch. Nach einer Stunde geht er in den Hof und raucht eine Zigarette. Danach geht er an den Tisch zurück. Er denkt: &quot;Wenigstens eine Stunde...&quot; und stellt das Buch wieder in das Regal.&lt;/big&gt;

This short story (''Geschichte'') is told in the 3rd person (see Grammatik 1-3). Note how this is apparent from both the pronoun (''Er'' or &quot;he&quot;) and verb forms.

== Vokabeln 1-3 ==
 die Biblio'''thek'''           library
 die Biochemie            biochemistry
 das Brötchen             roll, biscuit
 das Buch                 book
 der Fortgeschrittene     advancer
   die Fortgeschrittenen  advancers (pl.)
 die Geschichte           story
 der Hof                  courtyard; also court
 der Kaffee               coffee
 die Stunde               hour
 der Tisch                table
 das Regal                shelf
 die Zigarette            cigarette

 denken                   think                     (Er denkt = He thinks)
 essen                    eat                       (Er isst = He eats)
 holen                    fetch, get                (Er holt = He gets/fetches)
 rauchen                  smoke (a cigarette)       (Er raucht = He smokes)
 sich setzen              sit (oneself) down        (Er setzt sich = He sits)
 stellen                  place                     (Er stellt = He places)
 suchen                   seek, search for          (Er sucht = He looks for)
 trinken                  drink                     (Er trinkt = He drinks)

 aus                      out
 danach                   afterwards
 dort                     there
 in                       in
 nach                     after
 über                     about
 wenigstens               at least, at any rate
 wieder                   again
:* &lt;small&gt;[[German/Appendices/Alphabet|Pronunciation Guide]] &gt;&gt; &lt;/small&gt;
----

== Grammatik 1-3 ~ Personal Pronouns ==
As in English, '''personal pronouns''' exist in three grammatical persons, each with singular and plural number. In Gespräch 1-1 and 1-2, you see only the singular versions. The table here gives also the plural (nominative case only):
&lt;ul&gt;

{|
|-
| '''''ich''''' || &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; I 
| &amp;nbsp; ||    &amp;ndash; 1st person, singular
|-
| '''''du''''' ||  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; you 
|
 ||  &amp;ndash; 2nd person, singular 
|-
| '''''er''''' ||  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; he 
|
| &amp;ndash; 3rd person musculine, singular
|-
| '''''sie''''' ||  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; she 
|
| &amp;ndash; 3rd person feminine, singular 
|-
| '''''es'''''&lt;p&gt; ||  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; it&lt;p&gt;
|
| &amp;ndash; 3rd person neuter, singular&lt;p&gt;
|-
| '''''wir''''' ||  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; we 
|
 ||  &amp;ndash; 1st person, plural 
|-
| '''''ihr''''' ||  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; you 
|
 ||  &amp;ndash; 2nd person, plural 
|-
| '''''sie''''' ||  &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; they 
|
 ||  &amp;ndash; 3rd person, plural 
|-
| '''''Sie'''''
| &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; you ('''formal''') 
|
| &amp;ndash; 2nd person, plural and singular, always declined plural 
|}
&lt;/ul&gt;
----

== Grammatik 1-3 ~ Incomplete Sentences ==
What are we to make of short, incomplete sentences such as that in Gespräch 1-1: 'Und dir?'?  This translates as: 'And for you?'.  In English and German it is not always necessary to express every part of a sentence, especially in conversation where the words left out are easily understood by both or all parties.  Walk up to a stranger and say 'And you?' and a possible response is a hostile 'Out of my face, fool'.  But in the conversation between Heinrich and Karl, Heinrich knows that Karl is really meaning: ''Und &lt;u&gt;wie geht es&lt;/u&gt; dir?'', with that part underlined left out of the conversational statement.  Note especially that the pronoun 'you' retains its case&amp;mdash;its relation to the missing verb from the implied sentence&amp;mdash;distinctive in German (that is, ''dir'' instead of ''du'') but not so in English (the form &quot;you&quot; covers both cases).
----

== &lt;font color=&quot;SaddleBrown&quot;&gt;Übersetzung 1-2&lt;/font&gt; ==
Although these sentences involve many grammatical concepts that have not been covered, each can be written in German by referring to the example sentences and vocabularies in Lessons 1 and  1A.  Using a piece of paper and pencil, translate each of these sentences into German:
# Hello Mark! Do you have a cigarette?
# Are you studying German?
# Catherine drinks coffee at a table.
# The students study at the library.
# He eats cheese and sausage in the courtyard.
# She looks for a book about biology.
# Mark goes back to the University.
# Mark removes the book from the shelf and places it on the table.

:* [[../Answers|Antworten]] &gt;</text>
      <sha1>djwmk7pcgedy5oim5oz0ccx1el7n7ke</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Jdoms</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>3678</id>
    <revision>
      <id>155552</id>
      <parentid>24840</parentid>
      <timestamp>2004-04-09T21:34:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>213.224.208.49</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">i'm jdoms and that's all ya need to know 'bout me :-).</text>
      <sha1>9mvkwjyrkrs9eos94a1twblahcltrge</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:German/Lesson 7</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>3679</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1867405</id>
      <parentid>1864655</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-06-28T23:26:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>replaced: {{WikiProject Languages}} → {{WikiProject Languages|german=yes}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{WikiProject Languages|german=yes}} 

It's actually -zig not -ßig. The only number where it's -ßig is dreißig. Everywhere else, -zig.</text>
      <sha1>89epcim0psqfkowsjfr933mmudl27i3</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Dutch/Alfabet</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3680</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2657724</id>
      <parentid>2657722</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-05-19T10:22:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>93.96.99.28</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* The Dutch &quot;r&quot; */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;small&gt;^ [[../Lesson 1|Les 1]] ^&lt;/small&gt;
----
&lt;big&gt;&lt;big&gt;Appendix 1 ~ &lt;/big&gt;Alphabet and Pronunciation Guide&lt;/big&gt;

== Het alfabet ~ The alphabet ==

The Dutch alphabet, like English, consists of 26 basic letters. However, there are also a number of letter combinations. The following table includes a listing of all these letters and a guide to their pronunciation.  As in English, letter sounds can differ depending upon where within a word the letter occurs.  The first pronunciation given below (second column) is that in English of the letter (or combination) itself. Reading down this column and pronouncing the &quot;English&quot; words will recite the alphabet ''in het Nederlands'' (in Dutch). Note that letter order is exactly the same as in English, but pronunciation is not for many of the letters. 

{{Audio|Dutch_alphabet.OGG|listen}}

SAMPA-orthography: see [[Wikipedia:en:SAMPA|SAMPA]]
&lt;pre&gt;
A  (ah)   Long 'a' in French 'bateau', but longer (SAMPA /a:/); short 'a' as in 'arm' (/A/)
B  (bay)  Pronounced like 'p' when at the end of a word
C  (say)  Like 's' preceding i, e and y; like 'k' preceding a, o, u and consonants
D  (day)  Pronounced like 't' when at the end of a word
E  (ay)   Long 'e' as 'a' in 'late' (/e:/); short 'e' as 'e' in 'pet' (/E/)
F  (ef)
G  (khay) 'g' as 'ch' in Scottish 'loch' or the composer 'Bach', but voiced (/G/)
H  (hah)  Usually voiced.
I  (ee)   Long 'i' as 'e' in 'seen' (ee) (/i:/); short 'i' as 'i' in 'pit' (/I/)
J  (yay)  Pronounced like 'y' as in 'yes'
K  (kah)  No aspiration
L  (el)   Thinner than in English
M  (em)
N  (en)   
O  (oh)   Long 'o' as 'o' in 'open' (oh; /o:/); short 'o' as 'aw' in British English 'law' (/O/)
P  (pay)  No aspiration
Q  (kuuh)
R  (err)  trilled (see below)
S  (ess)  
T  (tay)  No aspiration
U  (uuh)  Long 'u' as 'u' in French 'du' (/y:/); short 'u' somewhat like 'i' in 'bird' (/Y/)
V  (vay)  
W  (way)  for Holland: between upper teeth and lower lip (not between lips) / for Flanders (Belgium): between the lips
X  (iks)
Y or IJ (eh-ee). Y only in loans, IJ is a diphthong and considered two letters.
Z  (zet)  
&lt;/pre&gt;

'''combined letters'''

&lt;pre&gt;
aa
ee
oo
uu
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
au
ei
eu
ie
ij
oe
ou
ui
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
ch
ng
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;!-- '''Audio''': [[media:Alphabet.ogg|OGG]] (114KB) ~ ''Das Alphabet'' oder ''Das ABC''--&gt;

&lt;small&gt;&lt;&lt; [[Dutch|Contents Page]]&lt;/small&gt;
----

== Nederlandse uitspraak ~ Dutch Pronunciation Guide ==

=== Klinkers ===

Dutch has quite a few vowels (13). To be well understood by a native speaker it is imperative to master them, which can be quite challenge for native speakers of languages that rely more on their many consonants such as Russian. One general observation is that they are always pronounced as ''pure'' (or only slightly diphthongized) vowels as in French, never drawled or 'chewed upon' as in many varieties of English. 

Most vowels occur in pairs that are traditionally indicated by the terms '''short''' and '''long'''. Unfortunately, this nomenclature is rather misleading because the difference is not a matter of length, but rather a difference in the position of the tongue root ('''lax''' vs. '''tense''').

{| border=1 rules=all  margin-left:1em; margin-bottom:0.5em; width:25em; border:#99B3FF solid 1px;border-color:#99B3FF;&quot; id=toc
|-
| width=33%| vowel {{Audio|Dutch_pronunciation_klinkers.OGG|listen}}
| width=33%| 'short' (lax)
| width=33%| 'long' (tense)
|-
| width=33%| a - - stal - staal
| width=33%|/{{IPA|ɑ}}/ as in squat, father
| width=33%|/a/ as in broad US 'my God!' (Gaad) or Fr. bâteau
|-
| width=33%|e - - bed - beet
| width=33%|/{{IPA|ɛ}}/ as in bell
| width=33%|/e/ as in bait
|-
| width=33%|i  - - bit - biet
| width=33%|/{{IPA|ɪ}}/ as in bit
| width=33%|/i/ as in beet
|-
| width=33%|o - -  bot  - boot
| width=33%|/{{IPA|ɔ}}/  as in paw or UK Potter 
| width=33%|/o/ as in boat
|-
| width=33%|u - - put - kluut
| width=33%|/{{IPA|ɵ}}/ more rounded than subtle
| width=33%|/y/ as in French tu
|-
| width=33%|oe - - koet
| width=33%|/u/ as oo, but rounded
|-
| width=33%|eu - -  deuk
| colspan= 2 width=33%|/ø/ as German Möwe
|-
|}


In addition there is a neutral vowel that occurs in almost all unstressed syllables, the schwa /{{IPA|ə}}/ as is does more or less in English as well. It is spelled with an 'e', so that this letter has three meanings: the above two in stressed syllables, the schwa in unstressed ones.

Notice the value of the letter 'u' in Dutch. As in French it denotes the /y/ sound. Thus, in German it corresponds to ü. It is relatively rare in Dutch because most words that used to have it have shifted it to the diphthong ''ui''. It occurs mostly at the end of words like ''u'', ''nu'' or in front of a w or r: ''ruw'', ''stuur''.

::Trick: If you can whistle: whistle a high note, freeze your mouth in the position it is in and sing. You'll produce a /y/-sound. The trick is to have the tongue far in the front of the mouth and the lips rounded.

The spelling 'oe' for /u/ is a real Dutch oddity. Most languages use 'u' as German and Latin. (French uses 'ou', English often used 'oo', although it does have words like ''shoe''). The Dutch /u/ sound is strongly rounded and dark with the tongue pretty far retracted back in the mouth. (American 'oo' sounds tend to be intermediary between /u/ and /y/ )

There is a systematic way in the spelling to indicate which of the two varieties is intended. An open syllable has the 'long' one, a closed one -ending in one or more consonants- has the 'short' one.

:na  /na/
:nat /{{IPA|nɑt}}/

If a conflict arises, either the vowel or the consonant is doubled:

:za'''a'''k - zaken  both have /a/ (business - businesses)
:zak  - zak'''k'''en both have /{{IPA|ɑ}}/ (bag- bags)
{{Audio|Dutch_pronunciation_zak.OGG|listen}}

Notice how the formation of the plural necessitates a good mastery of this principle. The vowels oe and eu do not exhibit the dual quality of the other vowels. 

The case of the letter i is a bit special. There has been a double ii in the past but to avoid confusion with a hand-written u it was replaced by -ij. Afterwards the long /i:/ sound it represented became a diphthong /{{IPA|ɛi}}/ (although many dialects retain /i/). To write the long /i/ sound Dutch mostly uses -ie.

As said above, the distinction 'short'-'long' has little to do with pure length, because the change from open to closed is much more important. There is an exception. In front of -r the long vowel may indeed just be the same vowel held a bit longer:

:bord : /{{IPA|bɔrt}}/
:boord: /{{IPA|bɔːrt}}/

In front of -r there are a few other oddities:

:''keel'' - /kel/
:''keer'' - /{{IPA|kɪːr}}/

:''keus'' - /køs/
:''keur'' - /kœːr/

===Diphthongs===

:ei and ij are both /ɛi/ compare English ''feisty''
:au and ou are both /au/ as in English ''now''
:ui is /ʌy/ needs to be learned by ear, it is a bit like in French l'oeil.
:aai is /ai/ 
:ooi is /oi/
:ieu is /iu/ or /iy/
:eeu is /eu/
:uw is /yu/

Diphthongs like /ɔi/ (as in English ''toy'') or /ɑi/ (as in English ''my'') are not used in the standard language. In various dialects they do occur and producing them is often frowned upon. They are considered 'lower class' in many circles.

In unstressed syllables like the suffix -lijk the ij represents a schwa.

=== Medeklinkers ===

Most consonants in Dutch are pronounced more or less the same way as in English but there are a number of notable exceptions. First of all a number of phonemes that English has are simply missing in Dutch. Phonemes are sounds that suffice in marking one word as different from the other.

===Missing phonemes===

:/θ/ : ''th'' as in  ''th''ing.
:/ð/ : ''th'' as in ''th''at.
:/g/ : ''g'' as in ''g''ood. (but it does occur as an allophone of '''k''' before '''d''', for example in ''za'''k'''doek'')

Please avoid these sounds when speaking Dutch.

===The g, ch and sch problem===

The spelling sch- can be rather confusing for people familiar with some German. In German it is used to write the /ʃ/ sound, where English uses sh-. In Dutch the sch- combination also occurs quite frequently but is pronounced rather differently. In most cases it presents a combination of s+ch where the latter is the voiceless velar fricative /x/ as heard in German ''Bach'' or Scottish ''loch''.

:schip : /{{IPA|sxɪp}}/ 

In older versions of the orthography (prior to 1947) the combination -sch represented a simple /s/ sound in final position. The guttural ch at the end had gone mute. (Originally it represented a k- sound as it still does in some dialects and in Frisian). The final -sch spelling is still used for one rather common ending: -isch and also in numerous geographical names as they have never been altered in spelling:

:chaotisch:  /{{IPA|xa'otis}}/ (not: /{{IPA|xa'otiʃ}}/
:'s-Hertogenbosch : /{{IPA|sɛrtoɣən'bɔs}}/ , (not: /{{IPA|ʃɛr'togənboʃ}}/ )
{{Audio|Dutch_pronunciation_sch_g.OGG|listen}}

In principle Dutch has both a voiceless and a voiced velar fricative and the letter 'g' represents the voiced one and the combination 'ch' the voiceless one. However, the number of words where this creates a phonemic distinction is very small:

logen /{{IPA|'loɣən}}/  contrasts with:  loochen  /{{IPA|'loxən}}/

It depends on the region whether this distinction is actually made in the spoken language. Around Amsterdam it would not be, further south the phoneme 'g' is often pronounced as a voiced palatal fricative, so that the difference becomes more pronounced.

Worldwide, the voiced /ɣ/ sound is pretty rare. It only occurs in a few languages like Arabic and Gaelic. As many native speakers do not use it either, it is recommended not to bother about it and 
use the voiceless /x/ for both, unless your mother tongue happens to have the difference.

===The Dutch &quot;r&quot;===

Another, similar, problem for English-speaking learners is the Dutch &quot;r&quot;.  Essentially there are two, both of which were historically trilled.  The first, alveaolar [r], is the trilled &quot;r&quot; also used in Spanish, produced with the tip of the tongue against the alveolar ridge. This sound was standard only a few decades ago and is still used by some speakers. However it is gradually replaced by a voiced velar or uvular trill [R], which is also used in many dialects of German; it is also similar to the French &quot;r&quot;, but is voiced and articulated somewhat further forward (it is less &quot;throaty&quot;).  Starting from the Dutch &quot;g&quot; (/ɣ/) described above - a voiced velar fricative, the tongue is lowered and relaxed, thereby allowing the back of the tongue to trill against the soft palate (the velum) or of the uvula against the back of the tongue.

Both the alveolar and the uvular /r/ sounds are often not trilled when spoken by native speakers; the alveolar [r] is more often a light tap, while the uvular [R] can turn into a fricative or approximant. This also presents a considerable challenge for those unaccustomed to the sound when they are confronted with words like ''groot'' (&quot;big&quot;). The first two sounds tend to blend to one lengthy velar/uvular /x:ot/ or /ɣ:ot/, which may cause confusion with words like ''rood'' (red) and  ''goot'' (gutter).  

A third type of /r/ currently making inroads into Dutch is ''Gooise R'', named after the Gooi area in the Netherlands, where Dutch television is produced (Hilversum) and this speech feature is popularly thought to have originated. This concerns an approximant sound, not unlike American /r/ in words such as ''bar'', without trilling or friction.

===Voiceless consonants===

: p represents /p/, but unlike in English it is never aspirated.
: ''poot'' /pot/, ''kaap'' /kap/
: f represents /f/ as in English
: ''fuut'' /fyt/, ''schaaf'' /sxaf/
: t represents /t/ a true dental. Unlike UK-English it is not aspirated and unlike US-English it does not become a /d/ in the middle of a word.
: ''toe'' /tu/, ''beter'' /'betər/
: s represents /s/, in few case it can be a /z/ sound but much less frequently so than in German:
: ''samen'': /'samən/
::but:
:organisatie:  /ɔrɣani''''z'''atsi/  

The latter word also contains an exception on the rule that t represents /t/. In the ending -tie (corresponding to -tion) it is pronounced as a quick /ts/ combination.

:k represents /k/. again it is never aspirated as often happens in English or German.
:''kop'' /kɔp/ , ''kraak'' /krak/
In contrast to English it is not silent in combinations like kn-: ''knie''' /kni/

:ch represents /x/ as discussed above, except in recent English loans. This phoneme is quite common.
:''schraag'' /sxrax/, ''schichtig'' /sxɪxtəx/

===Devoicing and assimilation===

As in German, but unlike English all consonants at the ends of words are devoiced (''..at the ents off worts are devoist...''). You may hear that phenomenon when people speak English with a strong Dutch accent.
:zaad: /za'''t'''/
Assimilation with the previous word often devoices the consonant in initial position as well:
:het zaad: /t'''s'''at/

The neutral article ''het'' is often reduced to a prefixed t-sound in the spoken language and occasionally rendered as such in the written language as: 't. Het zaad -&gt; 't zaad.

Notice however that both the /z/ and the /d/ reappear in the plural:

:de zaden: /də 'za'''d'''ən/

Contrary to d, the letters v and z are not used in the final position in such cases:

: de vaas - de vazen:  /də vas - də 'vazən/
: de graaf - de graven /də ɣraf - də 'ɣravən/

===Voiced consonants===

Apart from the devoicing effects Dutch has the following voiced consonants:

:b represents /b/ as in English
:''baas'' /bas/
:v represents /v/ as in English, although its voicing is less emphatic
:''bevel'' /bə'vɛl/
:d represents /d/ as in English
:''dader'' /'dadər/
:z represents /z/ as in English
:ziezo! /'zizo/
:g represents /ɣ/ not /g/ as in English (see above)
:gegraven /ɣəɣravən/, ''gracht'' /ɣrɑxt/

Around Amsterdam the tendency to devoice is so strong that /v/ /ɣ/ and /z/ are seldom heard. People use /f/, /x/ and /s/ instead.

===Liquids, nasals etc.===

:m represents /m/ as in English
:''mooi'' /moi/
:w represents /ʋ/ much like in German, it is a ''labiodental'' approximant, not a bilabial one. Bring your upper teeth close to your lower lip and produce sound without breath. Put otherwise: produce a v-sound without breath. Speakers from e.g. Surinam often do use the bilabial version.
:''water'' /ʋatər/
In initial wr- (''wraak'' /vrak/ or /ʋrak/) w tends to sound more like /v/. It is not silent as in English.

In ''erwt'' /ɛrt/ (pea) the w is silent for most speakers

:n represents /n/ as in English
:''nonnetje'' /'nɔnət&lt;sup&gt;j&lt;/sup&gt;ə/ (/'nɔnəcə/)

Many plurals (including the plural forms of the verb) have an ending -en. For many speakers this is pronounced as /-ə/ and the final n is dropped, but this is not true for all. It depends strongly on the region of the speech area you are in. Around Amsterdam it is certainly  /-ə/, but in Groningen or in West-Flanders it is a syllabic /-n/ instead.

:ng /ŋ/ as in English sing, never /ŋg/ as in finger (the latter uses a /g/ that Dutch does not have). It does not occur in initial position, much like in English. 
:''vinger'' /vɪŋər/

Even in loans the /ŋg/ tends to be avoided: tango : /'tɑnɣo/ or /'tɑŋɣo/

:nk /ŋk/ as in English sink (This involves a /k/ sound that Dutch does have)

:j represents a /j/ sound, which in English usually written as ''y''. The English j as in Jack is virtually unknown.

:jacht: /jɑxt/, borrowed into English as: yacht.

In combination with i it forms a diphthong: ij. Although this is a two letter combination, both letters get capitalized at the beginning of a sentence: ijs -&gt; IJs (ice). /ɛis/.
The suffix -je that forms the rather ubiquitous diminutives tends to palatellize the previous consonants or even fuse to a palatal stop all together in rapid speech.
:''blaadje'' /'blat&lt;sup&gt;j&lt;/sup&gt;ə/ (/'blacə/ 

:y is not a native Dutch letter but it occurs in loans where it is pronounced /i/ or /j/.

:l represents an /l/ that is neither velarized (dark) as most English l's are, nor is it the slender variety as in German, French (or Irish). It is neutral and in between.
:''lila'' /'lila/

:r can represent a variety of sounds. A rolled 'r' /r/ was more or less the norm, but is heard less and less. A variety of uvular forms is taking its place. Retroflex ones (as in US English) sound distinctly foreign.

:h represents /ɦ/ a ''voiced'' version of the h-sound commonly heard in English and German. It only occurs in initial position of a syllable.
:''behang'' /bə'ɦɑŋ/, ''herfst'' /ɦɛrfst/

:the glottal stop ` is not rendered in the ortography, unless by a trema, e.g. in naäpen /na`apən/. 

It is much less used than in German, e.g. theater: /te'jatər/ rather than /te`atər/.

=== Syllable Stress ===

Stress is not represented in the spelling as such but often an educated guess can be made. Dutch is like English and German (and unlike French) a typical stress language. One syllable tends to get all the attention. It is at the same time loud, long and high in pitch and it never has a schwa ə. Instead it has a full vowel or a diphthong. Unstressed syllables tend to be short, low, soft and usually have a schwa, although there are exceptions.

Because the schwa is written as a ''e'' in the orthography it is often quite clear where the stress falls in a word:

: verlaten : /vər'&lt;u&gt;la&lt;/u&gt;tən/ has only one non-schwa syllable &lt;u&gt;la&lt;/u&gt; and sure enough that is where the stress goes. 

Unfortunately for the non-native speaker the letter e is also used for other purposes.

:verleden : /vər'&lt;u&gt;le&lt;/u&gt;dən/

And, to make it any more difficult for the non-native speaker:

:december : /d&lt;u&gt;e&lt;/u&gt;'s&lt;u&gt;ɛ&lt;/u&gt;mb&lt;u&gt;ə&lt;/u&gt;r/

It's a word which has three e's, all different pronounced.

The middle -e represent a full /e/ sound (as the ai in bait), but that is only clear for a native speaker. But with a bit of knowledge of grammar it will be clear that /led/ is the root of a verb (lijden actually) and that ver- is a prefix and -en the suffix. In general, the root of a verb (or noun) will get the stress in Dutch.

Of course there are exceptions, a good example are the separable and non-separable verbs.

Some words and names can have rather surprising stress patterns:

:Veluwe is /'&lt;u&gt;ve&lt;/u&gt;lyə/ for example.

===Capitalization===

The rules for capitalization in Dutch are similar to those in English. Capitalization occurs at the beginning of a sentence. ''Eigennamen''  (proper names, e.g., of persons, organisations, countries etc.) are capitalized, but ''soortnamen'' (generic names) are not.

As mentioned above, when a word beginning with '''ij''' has to be capitalized, both letters become capitals, e.g. '''IJ'''sselmeer.

&lt;small&gt;&lt;&lt; [[Dutch|Contents Page]]&lt;/small&gt;

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>6nqcs6whkdshuiandtwzmjgk3wjhnay</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>XML - Managing Data Exchange/A single entity</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3681</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2716841</id>
      <parentid>2680384</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-23T09:40:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>81.65.54.24</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Schema reference */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{XML-MDE | prev=Introduction to XML|next=Basic data structures}}
----

{|cellspacing=10 cellpadding=10 border=5
|-
|'''Learning objectives'''


* introduce XML documents, schemas, and stylesheets
* describe and create an XML document
* describe and create an XML schema
* describe and create an XML stylesheet
|-
|}



=Introduction=

In this chapter, we start to practice working with XML using XML documents, schemas, and stylesheets.  An XML document organizes data and information in a structured, hierarchical format.  An XML schema provides standards and rules for the structure of a given XML document.  An XML schema also enables data transfer.  An XSL (XML stylesheet) allows unique presentations of the material found within an XML document.

In the first chapter, ''Introduction to XML'', you learned what XML is, why it is useful, and how it is used. So, now you want to create your very own XML documents. In this chapter, we will show you the basic components used to create an XML document. This chapter is the foundation for all subsequent chapters--it is a little lengthy, but don't be intimidated. We will take you through the fundamentals of XML documents.


This chapter is divided into three parts:
* XML Document
* XML Schema
* XML Stylesheets (XSL)


As you learned in the previous chapter, the XML Schema and Stylesheet are essentially specialized XML Documents. Within each of these three parts we will examine the layout and components required to create the document. There are links at the end of the XML document, schema, and stylesheet sections that show you how to create the documents using an XML editor. At the bottom of the page there is a link to Exercises for this chapter and a link to the Answers.  

The first thing you will need before starting to create XML documents is a problem--something you want to solve by using XML to store and share data or information. You need some entity you can collect information about and then access in a variety of formats. So, we created one for you.

To develop an XML document and schema, start with a data model depicting the reality of the actual data that is exchanged. Once a high fidelity model has been created, the data model can be readily converted to an XML document and schema. In this chapter, we start with a very simple situation and in successive chapters extend the complexity to teach you more features of XML.

Our starting point is a single entity, CITY, which is shown in the following figure. While our focus is on this single entity, to map CITY to an XML schema, we need to have an entity that contains CITY. In this case, we have created TOURGUIDE. Think of a TOURGUIDE as containing many cities, and in this case TOURGUIDE has no attributes nor an identifier. It is just a container for data about cities.


'''Exhibit 1: Data model - Tourguide'''
[[File:Data Model - Tourguide.png|none|]]
:::&lt;!--  Commented out because image was deleted: [[Image:xmldmcity.png|Single Entity - City]] --&gt;
:::&lt;!--  Update - added replacement image - contact me if necessary regarding this - User:MHCABI 02 JUL 2009 --&gt;


=XML document=

An XML document is a file containing XML code and syntax.  XML documents have an .xml file extension.

We will examine the features &amp; components of the XML document.


* Prologue (XML Declaration)
* Elements
* Attributes
* Rules to follow
* Well-formed &amp; Valid XML documents


Below is a sample XML document using our TourGuide model.  We will refer to it as we describe the parts of an XML document.

'''Exhibit 2: XML document for city entity'''

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot;&gt;
  &lt;?xml version=&quot;1.0&quot; encoding=&quot;UTF-8&quot;?&gt;
  &lt;tourGuide xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation='city.xsd'&gt;
    &lt;city&gt;
        &lt;cityName&gt;Belmopan&lt;/cityName&gt;
        &lt;adminUnit&gt;Cayo&lt;/adminUnit&gt;
        &lt;country&gt;Belize&lt;/country&gt;
        &lt;population&gt;11100&lt;/population&gt;
        &lt;area&gt;5&lt;/area&gt;
        &lt;elevation&gt;130&lt;/elevation&gt;
        &lt;longitude&gt;88.44&lt;/longitude&gt;
        &lt;latitude&gt;17.27&lt;/latitude&gt;
        &lt;description&gt;Belmopan is the capital of Belize&lt;/description&gt;
        &lt;history&gt;Belmopan was established following the devastation of the
           former capital, Belize City, by Hurricane Hattie in 1965. High 
           ground and open space influenced the choice and ground-breaking 
           began in 1966.  By 1970 most government offices and operations had 
           already moved to the new location.
        &lt;/history&gt;
    &lt;/city&gt;
    &lt;city&gt;
        &lt;cityName&gt;Kuala Lumpur&lt;/cityName&gt;
        &lt;adminUnit&gt;Selangor&lt;/adminUnit&gt;
        &lt;country&gt;Malaysia&lt;/country&gt;
        &lt;population&gt;1448600&lt;/population&gt;
        &lt;area&gt;243&lt;/area&gt;
        &lt;elevation&gt;111&lt;/elevation&gt;
        &lt;longitude&gt;101.71&lt;/longitude&gt;
        &lt;latitude&gt;3.16&lt;/latitude&gt;
        &lt;description&gt;Kuala Lumpur is the capital of Malaysia and the largest 
            city in the nation&lt;/description&gt;
        &lt;history&gt;The city was founded in 1857 by Chinese tin miners and  
            preceded Klang.  In 1880 the British government transferred their 
            headquarters from Klang to Kuala Lumpur, and in 1896 it became the 
            capital of Malaysia. 
        &lt;/history&gt;
    &lt;/city&gt;
    &lt;city&gt;
        &lt;cityName&gt;Winnipeg&lt;/cityName&gt;
        &lt;adminUnit&gt;St. Boniface&lt;/adminUnit&gt;
        &lt;country&gt;Canada&lt;/country&gt;
        &lt;population&gt;618512&lt;/population&gt;
        &lt;area&gt;124&lt;/area&gt;
        &lt;elevation&gt;40&lt;/elevation&gt;
        &lt;longitude&gt;97.14&lt;/longitude&gt;
        &lt;latitude&gt;49.54&lt;/latitude&gt;
        &lt;description&gt;Winnipeg has two seasons. Winter and Construction.&lt;/description&gt;
        &lt;history&gt;The city was founded by people at the forks (Fort Garry)
         trading in pelts with the Hudson Bay Company. Ironically, 
         The Bay was bought by America.
        &lt;/history&gt;
    &lt;/city&gt;
  &lt;/tourGuide&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

==Prologue (XML declaration)==
The XML document starts off with the prologue.  The prologue informs both a reader and the computer of certain specifications that make the document XML compliant.  The first line is the XML declaration (and the only line in this basic XML document).

'''Exhibit 3: XML document - prologue'''
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot;&gt;
     &lt;?xml version=&quot;1.0&quot; encoding=&quot;UTF-8&quot;?&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

'''xml''' &amp;nbsp; = &amp;nbsp; this is an XML document&lt;br /&gt;
'''version=&quot;1.0&quot;''' &amp;nbsp; = &amp;nbsp; the XML version (XML 1.0 is the W3C-recommended version)&lt;br /&gt;
'''encoding=&quot;UTF-8&quot;''' &amp;nbsp; = &amp;nbsp; the character encoding used in the document - UTF 8 corresponds to 8-bit encoded Unicode characters (i.e. the standard way to encode international documents) - [http://www.unicode.org/ Unicode] provides a unique number for every character.&lt;br /&gt;
Another potential attribute of the XML declaration:&lt;br /&gt;
'''standalone=&quot;yes&quot;''' &amp;nbsp; = &amp;nbsp; the dependency of the document ('yes' indicates that the document does not require another document to complete content)

==Elements==

The majority of what you see in the XML document consists of XML '''elements'''. Elements are identified by their '''tags''' that '''open''' with &lt; or &lt;/ and '''close''' with &gt; or /&gt;. The '''start tag''' looks like this: &lt;element attribute=&quot;value&quot;&gt;, with a left angle bracket (&lt;) followed by the '''element type name''', optional '''attributes''', and finally a right angle bracket (&gt;). The '''end tag''' looks like this: &lt;/element&gt;, similar to the start tag, but with a slash (/) between the left angle bracket and the element type name, and no attributes.

When there's nothing between a start tag and an end tag, XML allows you to combine them into an '''empty element tag''', which can include everything a start tag can: &lt;img src=&quot;Belize.gif&quot; /&gt;. This one tag must be closed with a slash and right angle bracket (/&gt;), so that it can be distinguished from a start tag.

The XML document is designed around a major theme, an umbrella concept covering all other items and subjects; this theme is analyzed to determine its component parts, creating categories and subcategories.  The major theme and its component parts are described by elements. In our sample XML document, 'tourGuide' is the major theme; 'city' is a category; 'population' is a subcategory of 'city'; and the hierarchy may be carried even further: 'males' and 'females' could be subcategories of 'population'. Elements follow several rules of syntax that will be described in the Rules to Follow section.


We left out the attributes within the &lt;tourGuide&gt; start tag &amp;mdash; that part will be explained in the XML Schema section.

'''Exhibit 4: Elements of the city entity XML document'''
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot;&gt;
  &lt;tourGuide&gt;
    &lt;city&gt;
        &lt;cityName&gt;Belmopan&lt;/cityName&gt;
        &lt;adminUnit&gt;Cayo&lt;/adminUnit&gt;
        &lt;country&gt;Belize&lt;/country&gt;
        &lt;population&gt;11100&lt;/population&gt;
        &lt;area&gt;5&lt;/area&gt;
        &lt;elevation&gt;130&lt;/elevation&gt;
        &lt;longitude&gt;88.44&lt;/longitude&gt;
        &lt;latitude&gt;17.27&lt;/latitude&gt;
        &lt;description&gt;Belmopan is the capital of Belize&lt;/description&gt;
        &lt;history&gt;Belmopan was established following the devastation of the
           former capital, Belize City, by Hurricane Hattie in 1965. High 
           ground and open space influenced the choice and ground-breaking 
           began in 1966.  By 1970 most government offices and operations had 
           already moved to the new location.
        &lt;/history&gt;
    &lt;/city&gt;
  &lt;/tourGuide&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;


===Element hierarchy===

* '''root element'''&amp;nbsp; - &amp;nbsp; This is the XML document's major theme element. Every document must have exactly one and only one root element. All other elements are contained within this one root element. The root element follows the XML declaration. In our example, &lt;tourGuide&gt; is the root element.

* '''parent element'''&amp;nbsp; - &amp;nbsp; This is any element that contains other elements, the child elements. In our example, &lt;city&gt; is a parent element.

* '''child element'''&amp;nbsp; - &amp;nbsp; This is any element that is contained within another element, the parent element. In our example, &lt;population&gt; is a child element of &lt;city&gt;.

* '''sibling element'''&amp;nbsp; - &amp;nbsp; These are elements that share the same parent element. In our example, &lt;cityName&gt;, &lt;adminUnit&gt;, &lt;country&gt;, &lt;population&gt;, &lt;area&gt;, &lt;elevation&gt;, &lt;longitude&gt;, &lt;latitude&gt;, &lt;description&gt;, and &lt;history&gt; are all sibling elements.

&lt;br&gt;

==Attributes==

Attributes aid in modifying the content of a given element by providing additional or required information.  They are contained within the element's opening tag.  In our sample XML document code we could have taken advantage of attributes to specify the unit of measure used to determine the area and the elevation (it could be feet, yards, meters, kilometers, etc.); in this case, we could have called the attribute 'measureUnit' and defined it within the opening tag of 'area' and 'elevation'.


        &lt;adminUnit '''class=&quot;state&quot;'''&gt;Cayo&lt;/adminUnit&gt;

        &lt;adminUnit '''class=&quot;region&quot;'''&gt;Selangor&lt;/adminUnit&gt;


The above attribute example can also be written as:


1. using child elements
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot;&gt;
     &lt;adminUnit&gt;
          &lt;class&gt;state&lt;/class&gt;
          &lt;name&gt;Cayo&lt;/name&gt;
     &lt;/adminUnit&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot;&gt;
     &lt;adminUnit&gt;
          &lt;class&gt;region&lt;/class&gt;
          &lt;name&gt;Selangor&lt;/name&gt;
     &lt;/adminUnit&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

2. using an empty element

     &lt;adminUnit class=&quot;state&quot; name=&quot;Cayo&quot; /&gt;

     &lt;adminUnit class=&quot;region&quot; name=&quot;Selangor&quot; /&gt;



Attributes can be used to:

* provide more information that is not defined in the data
* define a characteristic of the element (size, color, style)
* ensure the inclusion of information about an element in all instances

Attributes can, however, be a bit more difficult to manipulate and they have some constraints.  Consider using a child element if you need more freedom.



==Rules to follow==
These rules are designed to aid the computer reading your XML document.

* The first line of an XML document must be the XML declaration (the prologue). 

* The main theme of the XML document is established in the root element and all other elements must be contained within the opening and closing tags of this root element.

* Every element must have an opening tag and a closing tag - '''no exceptions''' &lt;br&gt;
(e.g. &lt;element&gt;data stuff&lt;/element&gt;).

* Tags must be nested in a particular order 
=&gt; the parent element's opening and closing tags must contain all of its child elements' tags; in this way, you close first the tag that was opened last:
 &lt;parentElement&gt;
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;childElement1&gt;data&lt;/childElement1&gt;
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;childElement2&gt;
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;subChildElementA&gt;data&lt;/subChildElementA&gt;
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;subChildElementB&gt;data&lt;/subChildElementB&gt;
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/childElement2&gt;
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;childElement3&gt;data&lt;/childElement3&gt;
 &lt;/parentElement&gt;

* Attribute values should have quotation marks around them and no spaces.

* Empty tags or empty elements must have a space and a slash (/) at the end of the tag.

* Comments in the XML language begin with &lt;nowiki&gt;&quot;&lt;!--&quot; and end with &quot;--&gt;&quot;&lt;/nowiki&gt;.


===XML Element Naming Convention===

Any name can be used but the idea is to make names meaningful to those who might read the document.

* XML elements may only start with either a letter or an underscore character.

* The name must not start with the string &quot;xml&quot; which is reserved for the XML specification.

* The name may not contain spaces.

* The &quot;:&quot; should not be used in element names because it is reserved to be used for namespaces (This will be covered in more detail in a later chapter).

* The name may contain a mixture of letters, numbers, or other characters.


XML documents often have a corresponding database. The database will contain fields which correspond to elements in the XML document. A good practice is to use the naming rules of your database for the elements in the XML documents.

==DTD (Document Type Definition) Validation - Simple Example==
====Simple Internal DTD====
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot;&gt;
 &lt;?xml version=&quot;1.0&quot;?&gt;
 &lt;!DOCTYPE cdCollection [
    &lt;!ELEMENT cdCollection (cd)&gt;
    &lt;!ELEMENT cd (title, artist, year)&gt;
    &lt;!ELEMENT title (#PCDATA)&gt;
    &lt;!ELEMENT artist (#PCDATA)&gt;
    &lt;!ELEMENT year (#PCDATA)&gt;
 ]&gt;
 &lt;cdCollection&gt;
  &lt;cd&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Dark Side of the Moon&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;artist&gt;Pink Floyd&lt;/artist&gt;
    &lt;year&gt;1973&lt;/year&gt;
  &lt;/cd&gt;
 &lt;/cdCollection&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

Every element that will be used MUST be included in the DTD. Don’t forget to include the root element, even though you have already specified it at the beginning of the DTD. You must specify it again, in an &lt;!ELEMENT&gt; tag. 
&lt;!ELEMENT cdCollection (cd)&gt; The root element, &lt;cdCollection&gt;, contains all the other elements of the document, but only one direct child element: &lt;cd&gt;. Therefore, you need to specify the child element (only direct child elements need to be specified) in the parentheses. 
&lt;!ELEMENT cd (title, artist, year)&gt; With this line, we define the &lt;cd&gt; element. Note that this element contains the child elements &lt;title&gt;, &lt;artist&gt;, and &lt;year&gt;. These are spelled out in a particular order. This order must be followed when creating the XML document. If you change the order of the elements (with this particular DTD), the document won’t validate.
&lt;!ELEMENT title (#PCDATA)&gt; The remaining three tags, &lt;title&gt;, &lt;artist&gt;, and &lt;year&gt; don’t actually contain other tags. They do however contain some text that needs to be parsed. You may remember from an earlier lecture that this data is called Parsed Character Data, or #PCDATA. Therefore, #PCDATA is specified in the parentheses. 
So this simple DTD outlines exactly what you see here in the XML file. Nothing can be added or taken away, as long as we stick to this DTD. The only thing you can change is the #PCDATA text part between the tags.

====Adding complexity====
There may be times when you will want to put more than just character data, or more than just child elements into a particular element. This is referred to as mixed content. For example, let’s say you want to be able to put character data OR a child element, such as the &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt; tag into a &lt;description&gt; element:

  &lt;!ELEMENT description (#PCDATA | b | i )*&gt;

This particular arrangement allows us to use PCDATA, the &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt; tag, or the &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt; tag all at once. One particular caveat though, is that if you are going to mix PCDATA and other elements, the grouping must be followed by the asterisk (*) suffix. This declaration allows us to now add the following to the XML document (after defining the individual elements of course)

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot;&gt;
  &lt;cd&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Love. Angel. Music. Baby&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;artist&gt;Gwen Stefani&lt;/artist&gt;
    &lt;year&gt;2004&lt;/year&gt;
    &lt;genre&gt;pop&lt;/genre&gt;
    &lt;description&gt;
      This is a great album from former  
      &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;i&gt;No Doubt&lt;/i&gt; singer &lt;b&gt;Gwen Stephani&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/nowiki&gt;
    &lt;/description&gt;
  &lt;/cd&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

With attributes this is done a little differently than with elements. Please see following example:

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot;&gt;
  &lt;cd remaster_date=”1992”&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Dark Side of the Moon&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;artist&gt;Pink Floyd&lt;/artist&gt;
    &lt;year&gt;1973&lt;/year&gt;
  &lt;/cd&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

In order for this to validate, it must be specified in the DTD. Attribute content models are specified with:

  &lt;!ATTLIST element_name attribute_name attribute_type default_value&gt;

Let’s use this to validate our CD example: 

  &lt;!ATTLIST cd remaster_date CDATA #IMPLIED&gt;

====Choices====

  &lt;ATTLIST person gender (male|female) “female”&gt;

====Grouping Attributes for an Element====
If a particular element is to have many different attributes, group them together like so:

 &lt;!ATTLIST car horn CDATA #REQUIRED
              seats CDATA #REQUIRED
      steeringwheel CDATA #REQUIRED
              price CDATA #IMPLIED&gt;

==== Adding STATIC validation, for items that must have a certain value ====

 &lt;!ATTLIST classList   classNumber CDATA #IMPLIED
                       building (UWINNIPEG_DCE|UWINNIPEG_MAIN) &quot;UWINNIPEG_MAIN&quot;
                       originalDeveloper CDATA #FIXED &quot;Khal Shariff&quot;&gt;

====Suffixes====
So what happens with our last example with the CD collection, when we want to add more CDs? With the current DTD, we cannot add any more CDs without getting an error. Try it and see. 
When you specify a child element (or elements) the way we did, only one of each child element can be used. Not very suitable for a CD collection is it? 
We can use something called suffixes to add functionality to the &lt;!ELEMENT&gt; tag.
Suffixes are added to the end of the specified child element(s). There are 3 main suffixes that can be used:

* ( No suffix ): Only 1 child can be used.
* ( + ): One or more elements can be used.
* ( * ): Zero or more elements can be used.
* ( ? ): Zero or one element may be used.

====  Validating for multiple children with a DTD ====

So in the case of our CD collection XML file, we can add more CDs to the list by adding a + suffix:
 &lt;!ELEMENT cd_collection(cd+)&gt;

==== Using more internal formatting tags ====

Bold tags, B's for example are also defined in the DTD as elements, that are optional like thus:

 &lt;ELEMENT notes (#PCDATA | b | i)*&gt;
    &lt;!ELEMENT b (#PCDATA)*&gt;
    &lt;!ELEMENT i (#PCDATA)*&gt;
 ]&gt;
_______________
 &lt;classList classNumber=&quot;303&quot; building=&quot;UWINNIPEG_DCE&quot; originalDeveloper=&quot;Khal Shariff&quot;&gt;
  &lt;student&gt;
    &lt;firstName&gt;Kenneth
    &lt;/firstName&gt;
    &lt;lastName&gt;Branaugh
    &lt;/lastName&gt;
    &lt;studentNumber&gt;
    &lt;/studentNumber&gt;
    &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;notes&gt;&lt;b&gt;Excellent &lt;/b&gt;, Kenneth is doing well.&lt;/nowiki&gt;
    &lt;/notes&gt;
 etc

{| width=&quot;100%&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|- style=&quot;horizontal-align:wraptext;&quot;
| style=&quot;background-color:lightyellow&quot; |

= Case Study on BMEcat =


One of the first major national projects for the use of XML as a B2B exchange format was initiated by the federal association for material management, purchasing and logistics (BME) in cooperation with leading German companies, e.g. Bayer, BMW, SAP and Siemens. They all created a standard for the exchange of product catalogues. This project was named [http://www.bmecat.org/English/index.asp? BMEcat]. The result of this initiative is a DTD collection for the description of product catalogues and related transactions (new catalogue, updating of product data and updating of prices). 

Companies operating in the electronic commerce (suppliers, purchasing companies and market places) exchange increasingly large amounts of data. They quickly reach their limits here by the variety of data exchange formats. The BMEcat solution creates a basis for a straightforward transfer of catalogue data from various data formats. This lays the foundation to bringing forward the goods traffic through the Internet in Germany. The use of the BMEcat reduces the costs for all parties as standard interfaces can be used. 

The XML-based standard BMEcat was successfully implemented in many projects. Nowadays a variety of companies applies BMEcat and use it for the exchange of their product catalogs in this established standard.



'''A BMEcat catalogue (Version 1.2) consists of the following main elements:'''

'''CATALOG''' 
This element contains the essential information of a shopping catalog, e.g. language version and validity. BMEcat expects exactly one language per catalog.

'''SUPPLIER''' 
This element includes identification and address of the catalog suppliers. BMEcat expects exactly one supplier per catalog.

'''BUYER''' 
This element contains the name and address of the catalogue recipient. BMEcat expects no more than one recipient per catalog.

'''AGREEMENT''' 
This element contains one or more framework agreement IDs associated with the appropriate validity period. BMEcat expects all prices of a catalogue belonging to the contract mentioned above.

'''CLASSIFICATION SYSTEM''' 
This element allows the full transfer of one or more classification systems, including feature definitions and key words.

'''CATALOG GROUP SYSTEM''' 
This element originates from version 1.0. It is mainly used for the transfer of tree-structures which facilitate the navigation of a user in the target system (Browser).

'''ARTICLE''' (since 2005 PRODUCT) 
This element represents a product. It contains a set of standard attributes. 

'''ARTICLE PRICE''' (since 2005 PRODUCT PRICE) 
This element represents a price. The support of different pricing models is very powerful in comparison with other exchange formats. Season prices, country prices, different currencies and different validity periods, etc. will be supported. 

'''ARTICLE FEATURE''' (since 2005 PRODUCT FEATURE) 
This element allows the transfer of characteristic values. You can either record predefined group characteristics or individual product characteristics. 

'''VARIANT''' 
This element allows listing of product variants, without having to duplicate them. However, the variations of BMEcat  only apply to individual changes in value, leading to a change of Article ID. Otherwise there can’t exist any dependences on other attributes (especially at prices). 

'''MIME''' 
This element includes any number of additional documents such as product images, data sheets, or websites. 

'''ARTICLE REFERENCE''' (since 2005 REFERENCE PRODUCT) 
This element allows cross-referencing between articles within a catalogue as well as between catalogues. These references may used restrictedly for mapping product bundles. 

'''USER DEFINED EXTENSION''' 
This element enables transportation of data at the outside the BMEcat standards. The transmitter and receiver have to be coordinated.

You can find a typical BMEcat file [http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/BMECat here.]
|}

====ONLINE Validator====
http://www.stg.brown.edu/service/xmlvalid/

==Well-formed and valid XML==

'''Well-formed XML'''&amp;nbsp; - &amp;nbsp;An XML document that correctly abides by the rules of XML syntax.

'''Valid XML'''&amp;nbsp; - &amp;nbsp;An XML document that adheres to the rules of an XML schema (which we will discuss shortly).  To be valid an XML document must first be well-formed.


A Valid XML Document must be Well-formed.  But, a Well-formed XML Document might not be valid - in other words, a well-formed XML document, that meets the criteria for XML syntax, might not meet the criteria for the XML schema, and will therefore be invalid.

For example, think of the situation where your XML document contains the following (for this schema):

   &lt;city&gt;
     &lt;cityName&gt;Boston&lt;/cityName&gt;
     &lt;country&gt;United States&lt;/country&gt;
     &lt;adminUnit&gt;Massachusetts&lt;/adminUnit&gt;
   :
   :
   :
   &lt;/city&gt;

Notice that the elements do not appear in the correct sequence according to the schema (cityName, adminUnit, country). The XML document can be validated (using validation software) against its declared schema – the validation software would then catch the out of sequence error.

----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
===Using an XML Editor===

Check chapter [[../XML Editor/]] for instructions on how to start an XML editor.
Once you have followed the steps to get started you can copy the code in the sample XML document and paste it into the XML editor.  Then check your results.  Is the XML document well-formed?  Is the XML document valid? (you will need to have copied and pasted the schema in order to validate - we will look at schemas next)
----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------

=XML schema=

An XML schema is an XML document.  XML schemas have an .xsd file extension.

An XML schema is used to govern the structure and content of an XML document by providing a template for XML documents to follow in order to be valid.  It is a guide for how to structure your XML document as well as indicating your XML document's components (elements and attributes - and their relationships).  An XML editor will examine an XML document to ensure that it conforms to the specifications of the XML schema it is written against - to ensure it is valid.

XML schemas engender confidence in data transfer.  With schemas, the receiver of data can feel confident that the data conforms to expectations.  The sender and the receiver have a mutual understanding of what the data represent.

Because an XML schema is an XML document, you use the same language - standard XML markup syntax - with elements and attributes specific to schemas.


A schema defines:

* the structure of the document
* the elements
* the attributes
* the child elements
* the number of child elements
* the order of elements
* the names and contents of all elements 
* the data type for each element 

For more detailed information on XML schemas and reference lists of: Common XML Schema Primitive Data Types, Summary of XML Schema Elements, Schema Restrictions and Facets for data types, and Instance Document Attributes, click on this wikibook link =&gt; http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/XML_Schema



==Schema reference==

This is the part of the XML Document that references an XML Schema:

'''Exhibit 5: XML document's schema reference'''
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot;&gt;
  &lt;tourGuide
      xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
      xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation='city.xsd'&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

This is the part we left out when we described the root element in the basic XML document from the previous section.  The additional attributes of the root element &lt;tourGuide&gt; reference the XML schema (it is the schemaLocation attribute).

'''xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' ''' &amp;nbsp;-&amp;nbsp; references the W3C Schema-instance namespace&lt;br /&gt;
'''xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation='city.xsd' ''' &amp;nbsp;-&amp;nbsp; references the XML schema document (city.xsd)

==Schema document==

Below is a sample XML schema using our TourGuide model. We will refer to it as we describe the parts of an XML schema.

'''Exhibit 6: XML schema document for city entity'''
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot;&gt;
  &lt;?xml version=&quot;1.0&quot; encoding=&quot;UTF-8&quot;?&gt;
  &lt;xsd:schema xmlns:xsd=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema&quot;
   elementFormDefault=&quot;unqualified&quot;&gt;  
    &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;tourGuide&quot;&gt;
        &lt;xsd:complexType&gt;
            &lt;xsd:sequence&gt;
                &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;city&quot; type=&quot;cityDetails&quot; minOccurs = &quot;1&quot; maxOccurs=&quot;unbounded&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;/xsd:sequence&gt;
        &lt;/xsd:complexType&gt;
     &lt;/xsd:element&gt;
     &lt;xsd:complexType name=&quot;cityDetails&quot;&gt;
        &lt;xsd:sequence&gt; 
             &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;cityName&quot; type=&quot;xsd:string&quot;/&gt;
             &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;adminUnit&quot; type=&quot;xsd:string&quot;/&gt;
             &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;country&quot; type=&quot;xsd:string&quot;/&gt;
             &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;population&quot; type=&quot;xsd:integer&quot;/&gt;
             &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;area&quot; type=&quot;xsd:integer&quot;/&gt;
             &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;elevation&quot; type=&quot;xsd:integer&quot;/&gt;
             &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;longitude&quot; type=&quot;xsd:decimal&quot;/&gt;
             &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;latitude&quot; type=&quot;xsd:decimal&quot;/&gt;
             &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;description&quot; type=&quot;xsd:string&quot;/&gt;
             &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;history&quot; type=&quot;xsd:string&quot;/&gt;
         &lt;/xsd:sequence&gt;
     &lt;/xsd:complexType&gt;
  &lt;/xsd:schema&gt;
  &lt;!--
    Note: Latitude and Longitude are decimal data types.
    The conversion is from the usual form (e.g., 50º 17' 35&quot;)
    to a decimal by using the formula degrees+min/60+secs/3600.
  --&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;



===Prolog===

Remember that the XML schema is essentially an XML document and therefore must begin with the prolog, which in the case of a schema includes:

* the XML declaration
* the schema element declaration
&lt;br&gt;
The XML declaration:
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot;&gt;
  &lt;?xml version=&quot;1.0&quot; encoding=&quot;UTF-8&quot;?&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

The schema element declaration:
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot;&gt;
&lt;xsd:schema xmlns:xsd=&quot;&lt;nowiki&gt;http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema&lt;/nowiki&gt;&quot; elementFormDefault=&quot;unqualified&quot;&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

The '''schema element''' is similar to a root element - it contains all other elements in the schema.  

Attributes of the schema element include:

'''xmlns''' &amp;nbsp;-&amp;nbsp; XML NameSpace - the URL for the site that describes the XML elements and data types used in the schema.  

You can find more about namespaces here =&gt; [[../Namespace/]].

'''xmlns:xsd''' &amp;nbsp;-&amp;nbsp; All the elements and attributes with the 'xsd' prefix adhere to the vocabulary designated in the given namespace.

'''elementFormDefault''' &amp;nbsp;-&amp;nbsp; elements from the target namespace are either required or not required to be qualified with the namespace prefix.  This is mostly useful when more than one namespace is referenced.  In this case, 'elementFormDefault' must be ''qualified'', because you must indicate which namespace you are using for each element.  If you are referencing only one namespace, then 'elementFormDefault' can be ''unqualified''.  Perhaps, using ''qualified'' as the default is most prudent, this way you do not accidentally forget to indicate which namespace you are referencing.

===Element declarations===
Define the elements in the schema.

Include:

* the element name
* the element data type (optional)

Basic element declaration format: &lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot; enclose=&quot;none&quot;&gt;&lt;xsd:element name=&quot;name&quot; type=&quot;type&quot;&gt;&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

====Simple type====
declares elements that:

* do NOT have Child Elements
* do NOT have Attributes

example: &lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot; enclose=&quot;none&quot;&gt;&lt;xsd:element name=&quot;cityName&quot; type=&quot;xsd:string&quot; /&gt;&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

'''Default Value'''

If an element is not assigned a value then the default value is assigned.

example: &lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot; enclose=&quot;none&quot;&gt;&lt;xsd:element name=&quot;description&quot; type=&quot;xsd:string&quot; default=&quot;really cool place to visit!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

'''Fixed Value'''

An attribute that is defined as fixed must be empty or contained the specified fixed value.  No other values are allowed.

example: &lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot; enclose=&quot;none&quot;&gt;&lt;xsd:element name=&quot;description&quot; type=&quot;xsd:string&quot; '''fixed=&quot;you must visit this place - it is awesome!&quot;''' /&gt;&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

====Complex type====
declares elements that:

* can have Child Elements
* can have Attributes

examples:

'''1.'''  The root element 'tourGuide' contains a child element 'city'.  This is shown here:

'''''Nameless complex type'''''
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot;&gt;
     &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;tourGuide&quot;&gt;
        &lt;xsd:complexType&gt;
            &lt;xsd:sequence&gt;
                &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;city&quot; type=&quot;cityDetails&quot; minOccurs = &quot;1&quot; maxOccurs=&quot;unbounded&quot; /&gt;
            &lt;/xsd:sequence&gt;
        &lt;/xsd:complexType&gt;
     &lt;/xsd:element&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

'''Occurrence Indicators''': 

* ''minOccurs'' = the minimum number of times an element can occur (here it is 1 time) 
* ''maxOccurs'' = the maximum number of times an element can occur (here it is an unlimited number of times, 'unbounded')



'''2.'''  The parent element 'city' contains many child elements: 'cityName', 'adminUnit', 'country', 
'population', etc.  Why does this complex element set not start with the line: &lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot; enclose=&quot;none&quot;&gt;&lt;xsd:element name=&quot;city&quot; type=&quot;cityDetails&quot;&gt;&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;?  The element 'city' was already defined above within the complex element 'tourGuide' and it was given the type, 'cityDetails'.  This data type, 'cityDetails', is utilized here in identifying the sequence of child elements for the parent element 'city'.

'''''Named Complex Type''''' - and therefore can be reused in other parts of the schema
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot;&gt;
   &lt;xsd:complexType name=&quot;cityDetails&quot;&gt;
        &lt;xsd:sequence&gt;
             &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;cityName&quot; type=&quot;xsd:string&quot;/&gt;
             &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;adminUnit&quot; type=&quot;xsd:string&quot;/&gt;
             &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;country&quot; type=&quot;xsd:string&quot;/&gt;
             &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;population&quot; type=&quot;xsd:integer&quot;/&gt;
             &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;area&quot; type=&quot;xsd:integer&quot;/&gt;
             &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;elevation&quot; type=&quot;xsd:integer&quot;/&gt;
             &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;longitude&quot; type=&quot;xsd:decimal&quot;/&gt;
             &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;latitude&quot; type=&quot;xsd:decimal&quot;/&gt;
             &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;description&quot; type=&quot;xsd:string&quot;/&gt;
             &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;history&quot; type=&quot;xsd:string&quot;/&gt;
         &lt;/xsd:sequence&gt;
   &lt;/xsd:complexType&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

The '''&lt;xsd:sequence&gt;''' tag indicates that the child elements must appear in the order, the sequence, specified here.  

Compare the sample XML Schema and the sample XML Document - try to observe patterns in the code and how  the XML Schema sets up the XML Document.


'''3.''' Elements that have attributes are also designated as complex type.

a. this XML Document line: &lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot; enclose=&quot;none&quot;&gt;&lt;adminUnit class=&quot;state&quot; name=&quot;Cayo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
would be defined in the XML Schema as: 
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot;&gt;
     &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;adminUnit&quot;&gt;
          &lt;xsd:complexType&gt;
               &lt;xsd:attribute name=&quot;class&quot; type=&quot;xsd:string&quot; /&gt;
               &lt;xsd:attribute name=&quot;name&quot; type=&quot;xsd:string&quot; /&gt;
          &lt;/xsd:complexType&gt;
     &lt;/xsd:element&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
b. this XML Document line: &lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot; enclose=&quot;none&quot;&gt;&lt;adminUnit class=&quot;state&quot;&gt;Cayo&lt;/adminUnit&gt;&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
would be defined in the XML Schema as:
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot;&gt;
     &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;adminUnit&quot;&gt;
          &lt;xsd:complexType&gt;
               &lt;xsd:simpleContent&gt;
             		&lt;xsd:extension base=&quot;xsd:string&quot;&gt;
                                &lt;xsd:attribute name=&quot;class&quot; type=&quot;xsd:string&quot; /&gt;
                        &lt;/xsd:extension&gt;
	       &lt;/xsd:simpleContent&gt;
          &lt;/xsd:complexType&gt;
     &lt;/xsd:element&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

===Attribute declarations===

Attribute declarations are used in complex type definitions.  We saw some attribute declarations in the third example of the Complex Type Element. 
 
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot;&gt;&lt;xsd:attribute name=&quot;class&quot; type=&quot;xsd:string&quot; /&gt;&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;



===Data type declarations===

These are contained within element and attribute declarations as: ''' type=&quot; &quot; '''.

Common XML Schema Data Types

XML schema has a lot of built-in data types. The most common types are:

{| cellpadding=&quot;10&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
|string ||a string of characters
|-
|decimal ||a decimal number 
|-
|integer ||an integer
|-
|boolean ||the values true or false or 1 or 0 
|-
|date ||a date, the date pattern can be specified such as YYYY-MM-DD 
|-
|time ||a time of day, the time pattern can be specified such as HH:MM:SS 
|-
|dateTime ||a date and time combination
|-
|anyURI ||if the element will contain a URL
|}


For an entire list of built-in simple data types see http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-2/#built-in-datatypes


----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
Using an XML Editor =&gt; [[../XML Editor/]]

This link will take you to instructions on how to start an XML editor. Once you have followed the steps to get started you can copy the code in the sample XML schema document and paste it into the XML editor. Then check your results. Is the XML schema well-formed? Is the XML schema valid?
----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------

=XML stylesheet (XSL)=

An XML Stylesheet is an XML Document.  XML Stylesheets have an .xsl file extension.

The eXtensible Stylesheet Language (XSL) provides a means to transform and format the contents of an XML document for display.  Since an XML document does not contain tags a browser understands, such as HTML tags, browsers cannot present the data without a stylesheet that contains the presentation information.  By separating the data and the presentation logic, XSL allows people to view the data according to their different needs and preferences.

The XSL Transformation Language (XSLT) is used to  transform an XML document from one form to another, such as creating an HTML document to be viewed in a browser. An XSLT stylesheet consists of a set of formatting instructions that dictate how the contents of an XML document will be displayed in a browser, with much the same effect as Cascading Stylesheets (CSS) do for HTML.  Multiple views of the same data can be created using different stylesheets. The output of a stylesheet is not restricted to a browser. 


During the transformation process, XSLT analyzes the XML document and converts it into a '''node tree''' – a hierarchical representation of the entire XML document.  Each node represents a piece of the XML document, such as an element, attribute or some text content.  The XSL stylesheet contains predefined “templates” that contain instructions on what to do with the nodes.   XSLT will use the match attribute to relate XML element nodes to the templates, and transform them into the resulting document. 

'''Exhibit 7: XML stylesheet document for city entity'''
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot;&gt;
&lt;?xml version=&quot;1.0&quot; encoding=&quot;UTF-8&quot;?&gt;
&lt;xsl:stylesheet version=&quot;1.0&quot; xmlns:xsl=&quot;http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform&quot;&gt;
    &lt;xsl:output method=&quot;html&quot;/&gt; 
    &lt;xsl:template match=&quot;/&quot;&gt;
        &lt;html&gt;
            &lt;head&gt;
                &lt;title&gt;Tour Guide&lt;/title&gt;
            &lt;/head&gt;
            &lt;body&gt;
                &lt;h2&gt;Cities&lt;/h2&gt;
                &lt;xsl:apply-templates select=&quot;tourGuide&quot;/&gt;
            &lt;/body&gt;
        &lt;/html&gt;
    &lt;/xsl:template&gt;
    &lt;xsl:template match=&quot;tourGuide&quot;&gt;
        &lt;xsl:for-each select=&quot;city&quot;&gt;
            &lt;br/&gt;&lt;xsl:value-of select=&quot;continentName&quot;/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
            &lt;xsl:value-of select=&quot;cityName&quot;/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
            &lt;xsl:text&gt;Population: &lt;/xsl:text&gt;
            &lt;xsl:value-of select='format-number(population, &quot;##,###,###&quot;)'/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
            &lt;xsl:value-of select=&quot;country&quot;/&gt;
            &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;/xsl:for-each&gt;     
    &lt;/xsl:template&gt;
&lt;/xsl:stylesheet&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;


The output of the city.xsl stylesheet in Table 2-3 will look like the 
following:
{{Side note|
'''Cities'''

Europe&lt;br/&gt;
Madrid&lt;br/&gt;
Population: 3,128,600&lt;br/&gt;
Spain

Asia&lt;br/&gt;
Shanghai&lt;br/&gt;
Population: 18,880,000&lt;br/&gt;
China}}


You will notice that the stylesheet consists of HTML to inform the media tool (a web browser) of the presentation design.  If you do not already know HTML this may seem a little confusing.  Online resources such as the W3Schools tutorials can help with the basic understanding you will need =&gt;(http://www.w3schools.com/html/default.asp).  

Incorporated within the HTML is the XML that supplies the data, the information, contained within our XML document.  The XML of the stylesheet indicates what information will be displayed and how.  So, the HTML constructs a display and the XML plugs in values within that display.  '''XSL is the tool that transforms the information into presentational form, but at the same time keeps the meaning of the data.'''

{| width=&quot;100%&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|- style=&quot;horizontal-align:wraptext;&quot;
| style=&quot;background-color:lightyellow&quot; |
&lt;big&gt;'''XML at Bertelsmann - a case study'''&lt;/big&gt;

The German Bertelsmann Inc. is a privately owned media conglomerate operating in 56 countries. It has interests in such businesses as TV broadcast (RTL), magazine (Gruner &amp; Jahr), books (Random House) etc. In 2005 its 89 000 employees generated 18 billion € of revenue.
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
A major concern of such a diversified business is utilizing synergies. Management needs to make sure the Random House employees don´t spend time and money figuring out what RTL TV journalists already have come up with.
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Thus knowledge management based on IT promises huge time savings. Consequently Bertelsmann in 2002 started a project called BeCom.
BeCom´s purpose was to enable the different Bertelsmann businesses to use the same data for their different media applications.
XML is crucial in this project, because it allows for separating data (document) from presentation (style sheet). Thus data can both be examined statistically and be modified to fit different media like TV and newspapers.
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Statistical XML data management for example enables employees to benefit from CBR (Case Based Reasoning). [[wikipedia:Case_based_reasoning|CBR]] allows a Bertelsmann employee who searches for specific content to profit from previous search findings of other Bertelsmann employees, thus gaining info which is much more contextual than isolated research results only.
Besides XML data management, Bertelsmann TV and Book units can apply this optimized data in their specific media using a variety of lay-out applications like 3B2 or QuarkXPress.
|}


==Prolog==
*  the XML declaration;
*  the stylesheet declaration;
*  the namespace declaration;
*  the output document format.

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot;&gt;
 &lt;?xml version=&quot;1.0&quot; encoding=&quot;UTF-8&quot;?&gt;
 &lt;xsl:stylesheet version=&quot;1.0&quot; xmlns:xsl=&quot;http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform&quot;&gt;
   &lt;xsl:output method=&quot;html&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;



'''The XML declaration'''

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot;&gt;
 &lt;?xml version=&quot;1.0&quot; encoding=&quot;UTF-8&quot;?&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;


'''The stylesheet &amp; namespace declarations'''
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot;&gt;
     &lt;xsl:stylesheet version=&quot;1.0&quot; xmlns:xsl=&quot;&lt;nowiki&gt;http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform&lt;/nowiki&gt;&quot;&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
* identifies the document as an XSL style sheet;
* identifies the version number;
* refers to the W3C XSL namespace - the URL for the site that describes the XML elements and data types used in the schema.  You can find more about namespaces here =&gt; [[../Namespace/]].  Every time the xsl: prefix is used it references the given namespace.


'''The output document format'''
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot;&gt;
      &lt;xsl:output method=&quot;html&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
This element designates the format of the output document and must be a child element of &lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot; enclose=&quot;none&quot;&gt;&lt;xsl:stylesheet&gt;&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

==Templates==

The '''&lt;xsl:template&gt;''' element is used to create templates that describe how to display elements and their content.  Above, in the XSL introduction, we mentioned that XSL breaks up the XML document into nodes and works on individual nodes.  This is done with templates.  Each template within an XSL describes a single node.  To identify which node a given template is describing, use the 'match' attribute.  The value given to the 'match' attribute is called a '''pattern'''.  Remember:   ('''node tree''' – a hierarchical representation of the entire XML document.  Each node represents a piece of the XML document, such as an element, attribute or some text content).  Wherever there is branching in the node tree, there is a node.  &lt;xsl:template&gt; defines the start of a template and contains rules to apply when a specified node is matched.


'''the match attribute'''

    &lt;xsl:template match=&quot;/&quot;&gt;

This template match attribute associates the XML document root (/), the whole branch of the XML source document, with the HTML document root.  Contained within this template element is the typical HTML markup found at the beginning of any HTML document.  This HTML is written to the output.  The XSL looks for the root match and then outputs the HTML, which the browser understands.

    &lt;xsl:template match=&quot;tourGuide&quot;&gt;
This template match attribute associates the element 'tourGuide' with the display rules described within this element.



==Elements==

Elements specific to XSL:

{| border=3 cellpadding=5
|align=&quot;center&quot;|'''XSL Element'''
|align=&quot;center&quot;|'''Meaning'''
|-
|colspan=&quot;2&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; |(from our sample XSL)
|-
!&lt;xsl:text&gt;
|Prints the actual text found between this element's tags
|-
!&lt;xsl:value-of&gt;
|This element is used with a 'select' attribute to look up the value of the node selected and plug it into the output.
|-
!&lt;xsl:for-each&gt;
|This element is used with a 'select' attribute to handle elements that repeat by looping through all the nodes in the selected node set.
|-
!&lt;xsl:apply-templates&gt;
|This element will apply a template to a node or nodes.  If it uses a 'select' attribute then the template will be applied only to the selected child node(s) and can specify the order of child nodes.  If no 'select' attribute is used then the template will be applied to the current node and all its child nodes as well as text nodes.
|}

For more XSL elements =&gt; http://www.w3schools.com/xsl/xsl_w3celementref.asp .

==Language-Specific Validation and Transformation Methods==

===PHP Methods of XML Dom Validation===
Using the DOM [[DocumentObjectModel]] to validate XML and with a DTD [[DocumentTypeDeclaration]] and the PHP language on a server and more
http://wiki.cc/php/Dom_validation

===Browser Methods===

Place this line of code in your .xml document after the XML declaration (prologue).
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;XML&quot;&gt;
 &lt;?xml-stylesheet type=&quot;text/xsl&quot; href=&quot;tourGuide.xsl&quot;?&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

===PHP XML Production ===
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;PHP&quot;&gt;
 &lt;?php
 $xmlData = &quot;&quot;;
 mysql_connect('localhost','root','')
 or die('Failed to connect to the DBMS');
 // make connection to database
 mysql_select_db('issd')
 or die('Failed to open the requested database');
 $result = mysql_query('SELECT * from students') or die('Query to like get the records failed');
 if (mysql_num_rows($result)&lt;1){
    die ('');
 }
 $xmlString = &quot;&lt;classlist&gt;\n&quot;;
 $xmlString .= &quot;\t&lt;student&gt;&quot;;
 while ($row = mysql_fetch_array($result)) {
         $xmlString .=  &quot;
          \t&lt;firstName&gt;
              &quot;.$row['firstName'].&quot;
           &lt;/firstName&gt;\n
            \t&lt;lastName&gt;
              &quot;.$row['lastName'].&quot;
          \t&lt;/lastName&gt;\n&quot;;         
      }
 $xmlString .= &quot;&lt;/student&gt;\n&quot;;
 $xmlString .= &quot;&lt;/classlist&gt;&quot;;
 echo $xmlString;
 $myFile = &quot;classList.xml&quot;; //any file
 $fh = fopen($myFile, 'w') or die(&quot;can't open file&quot;); //create filehandler
 fwrite($fh, $xmlString); //write the data into the file
 fclose($fh); //ALL DONE!
 ?&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

===PHP Methods of XSLT Transformation===

This one is good for PHP5 and wampserver (latest). Please ensure that *xsl* is NOT commented out in
the php.ini file.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;PHP&quot;&gt;
 &lt;?php
 // Load the XML source
 $xml = new DOMDocument;
 $xml-&gt;load('tourguide.xml');
 $xsl = new DOMDocument;
 $xsl-&gt;load('tourguide.xsl');
 // Configure the transformer
 $proc = new XSLTProcessor;
 $proc-&gt;importStyleSheet($xsl); // attach the xsl rules
 echo $proc-&gt;transformToXML($xml);
 ?&gt; 
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;


Example 1, Using within PHP itself (use phpInfo() function to check XSLT extension; enable if needed)
This example might produce XHTML. Please note it could produce anything defined by the XSL.
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;PHP&quot;&gt;
 &lt;?php
 $xhtmlOutput = xslt_create();
 $args = array();
 $params = array('foo' =&gt; 'bar');
 $theResult = xslt_process(
                         $xhtmlOutput,
                         'theContentSource.xml',
                         'theTransformationSource.xsl',
                         null,
                         $args,
                         $params
                        );
 xslt_free($xhtmlOutput); // free that memory
 // echo theResult or save it to a file or continue processing (perhaps instructions)
 ?&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
Example 2:
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;PHP&quot;&gt;
 &lt;?php
 if (PHP_VERSION &gt;= 5) {
   // Emulate the old xslt library functions
   function xslt_create() {
       return new XsltProcessor();
   }
   function xslt_process($xsltproc,
                         $xml_arg,
                         $xsl_arg,
                          $xslcontainer = null,
                         $args = null,
                         $params = null) {
       // Start with preparing the arguments
       $xml_arg = str_replace('arg:', '', $xml_arg);
       $xsl_arg = str_replace('arg:', '', $xsl_arg);
       // Create instances of the DomDocument class
       $xml = new DomDocument;
       $xsl = new DomDocument;
       // Load the xml document and the xsl template
       $xml-&gt;loadXML($args[$xml_arg]);
       $xsl-&gt;loadXML($args[$xsl_arg]);
       // Load the xsl template
       $xsltproc-&gt;importStyleSheet($xsl);
       // Set parameters when defined
       if ($params) {
           foreach ($params as $param =&gt; $value) {
               $xsltproc-&gt;setParameter(&quot;&quot;, $param, $value);
           }
       }
       // Start the transformation
       $processed = $xsltproc-&gt;transformToXML($xml);
       // Put the result in a file when specified
       if ($xslcontainer) {
           return @file_put_contents($xslcontainer, $processed);
       } else {
           return $processed;
       }
   }
   function xslt_free($xsltproc) {
       unset($xsltproc);
   }
 }
 $arguments = array(
   '/_xml' =&gt; file_get_contents(&quot;xml_files/201945.xml&quot;),
   '/_xsl' =&gt; file_get_contents(&quot;xml_files/convertToSql_new2.xsl&quot;)
 );
 $xsltproc = xslt_create();
 $html = xslt_process(
   $xsltproc,
   'arg:/_xml',
   'arg:/_xsl',
   null,
   $arguments
 );
 xslt_free($xsltproc);
 print $html;
 ?&gt;
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

===PHP file writing code===
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang=&quot;PHP&quot;&gt;
 $myFile = &quot;testFile.xml&quot;; //any file
 $fh = fopen($myFile, 'w') or die(&quot;can't open file&quot;); //create filehandler
 $stringData = &quot;&lt;foo&gt;\n\t&lt;bar&gt;\n\thello\n&quot;; // get a string ready to write
 fwrite($fh, $stringData); //write the data into the file
 $stringData2 = &quot;\t&lt;/bar&gt;\n&lt;/foo&gt;&quot;;
 fwrite($fh, $stringData2); //write more data into the file
 fclose($fh); //ALL DONE!
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

==XML Colors==  

For use in your stylesheet: these colors can be used for both background and font

http://www.w3schools.com/html/html_colors.asp

http://www.w3schools.com/html/html_colorsfull.asp

http://www.w3schools.com/html/html_colornames.asp

-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
Using an XML Editor =&gt; [[../XML Editor/]]

This link will take you to instructions on how to start an XML editor. Once you have followed the steps to get started you can copy the code in the sample XML stylesheet document and paste it into the XML editor. Then check your results. Is the XML stylesheet well-formed?
-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------

=XML at Thomas Cook - a case study=

{| width=&quot;100%&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|- style=&quot;horizontal-align:wraptext;&quot;
| style=&quot;background-color:lightyellow&quot; |
As the leading travel company and most widely recognized brands in the world, Thomas Cook works across the travel value chain - airlines, hotels, tour operators, travel and incoming agencies, providing its customers with the right product in all market segments across the globe. Employing over 11,000 staff, the Group has 33 tour operators, around 3,600 travel agencies, a fleet of 80 aircraft and a workforce numbering some 26,000. Thomas Cook operates throughout a network of 616 locations in Europe and overseas. The company is now the second largest travel group in Europe and the third largest in the world.

As Thomas Cook sells other companies´ products, ranging from packaged holidays to car hires, it needs to regularly change its online brochure. Before Thomas Cook started using XML, it put information into HTML format, and would take upto six weeks to get an online brochure up and running online. XML helps do this job in about three days. This helps provide all of Thomas Cook´s current and potential customers and its various agencies in different geographical locations with updated information, instead of having to wait six weeks for new information to be released.
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
XML allows Thomas Cook to put content information into a single database, which can be re-used as many times as required.
&quot;We did not want to keep having to re-do the same content, we wanted the ability to switch it on immediately,&quot; said Gwyn Williams, who is content manager at Thomascook.com. &quot;This has brought internal benefits such as being able to re-deploy staff into more value added areas.&quot; Thomascook.com currently holds 65,000 pages of brochure and travel guide information and an online magazine in XML format.
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Thomas Cook started using XML at a relatively early stage. As Thomas Cook has a large database, the early use of XML will stand it in good stead. At some point, the databases will have to be incorporated into XML, and it is reported that XML databases are quicker than conventional databases, giving Thomas Cook a slight competitive advantage against those who do not use XML.
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Thomas Cook has found that this can lead to substantial cost reductions as well as consistency of information across all channels. By implementing a central content management system to facilitate brochure production and web publications, they have centralized the production, maintenance and distribution of content across their brands and channels.
|}

=Summary=

{| style=&quot;background: linen; border: 1px solid black; padding: 1em; width: 100%;&quot;
|-
|From the previous chapter ''Introduction to XML'', you have learned the need for data exchange and the usefulness of XML in data exchange.  In this chapter, you have learned more about the three major XML files: the XML document, the XML schema, and the XML stylesheet.  You learned the correct documentation required for each type of file.  You learned basic rules of syntax applicable for all XML documents.  You learned how to integrate the three types of XML documents.  And you learned the definition and distinction between a ''well-formed'' document and a ''valid'' document.  By following the ''XML Editor'' links, you were able to see the results of the sample code and learn how to use an XML Editor.

Below are Exercises and Answers for further practice.  Good Luck!
|-
|}



=[[/Definitions/]]=

 XML
 SGML
 Dan Connelly
 RSS
 XML Declaration
 parent
 child
 sibling
 element
 attribute

 *Well-formed XML

 PCDATA

=[[/Exercises/]]=

Exercise 1. 

a)Using &quot;tourguide&quot; above as a good example, create an XML document whose root is &quot;classlist&quot; . This CLASSLIST is created from a starting point of single entity, STUDENT. Any number of students contain elements: firstname, lastname, emailaddress.

=[[/Answers/]]=

[[Category:{{FULLBOOKNAME}}|{{FULLCHAPTERNAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>p7f1pswatq87e0dxo45l8vrx4jnzfmc</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Puzzles/How do you ... ?/Crossing the Bridge</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3682</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2452740</id>
      <parentid>1302062</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-12-03T22:37:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>59.162.23.73</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Puzzles]] | [[Puzzles/How do you ... ?|How do you...?]] | Crossing the Bridge 
----

'''Crossing the Bridge'''

A man that weighs 98 pounds exactly is carrying 3 weights each weighing 1 pound exactly.  He must cross a bridge that has a weight limit of exactly 100 pounds

How does he cross the bridge with the weights?


'''[[Puzzles/How do you ... ?/Crossing the Bridge/Solution|Solution]]'''

1. Carry one weight at a time?&lt;BR&gt;
2. Throw the weights over.&lt;BR&gt;
3. Get some one lighter to carry them over.&lt;BR&gt;
4. Try to cross and hope the bridge does not collapse.&lt;BR&gt;
5. Find a different route across?&lt;BR&gt;
6. Go on a diet?&lt;BR&gt;
7. Juggle?&lt;BR&gt;
8. Roll the weights across&lt;BR&gt;
9. wear away some of the weights by rubbing them against a rock, or break them or something&lt;BR&gt;
10. FedEx them to the other side :P &lt;BR&gt;
11. Pray &lt;BR&gt;
12. Build a new bridge &lt;BR&gt;
13. Build a small boat and placing the weights on it, drag it across the river with a rope (if there's no river, use helium balloons :P) &lt;BR&gt;
14. Tie the weights to a long rope, cross the bridge and drag the weights from the other side &lt;BR&gt;

[[Category:Puzzles]]</text>
      <sha1>59u99nwapyct8pje36kl47vsdgfro3c</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>