<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Waves/Superposition</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>410</id>
    <revision>
      <id>551249</id>
      <parentid>152567</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-08-07T17:47:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[Talk:Modern Physics:Superposition]] moved to [[Talk:Waves/Superposition]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Re superposition: How do 2 material waves actually pass through each other? Considering water waves, the energy transmits because water molecules receive kinetic and potential energy, and then pass it to other molecules.  Right?  But at an interference point there is no net movement of the material, no change of either kinetic or potential energy.  So if the molecules' momentums are unchanged, how can they pass the tendency to change on? Or, is interference just an average effect, some molecules having momentum in one direction while a balanced number have momentum in the opposite direction?

Its just an average affect --[[User:Flonejek|flonejek]] 23:22, 27 Feb 2004 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>48yx4dq2t0vd6lkonkwlz69wyhbvpb5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Spanish/Lesson 1</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>412</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1867695</id>
      <parentid>1865617</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-06-28T23:39:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>replaced: {{WikiProject Languages}} → {{WikiProject Languages|spanish=yes}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{WikiProject Languages|spanish=yes}} 

==Error==
I believe that I found an error. In the second dialogue of the first lesson, there is an accent missing over the first o in cómo. I have changed...

Señora Pérez: 	Me llamo Ana Pérez. ¿Y usted? ¿Como se llama?

to

Señora Pérez: 	Me llamo Ana Pérez. ¿Y usted? ¿Cómo se llama?

If I have erred, just let me know and I'll change it back, or someone else can. -- [[User:Phreq|Phreq]] 02:57, 3 August 2005 (UTC)&lt;br&gt;
----

The first dialogue is losing control.  We have an audio file listed that does not match the dialogue.  We have acquired three new audio files that only cover three specific lines in the dialogue (and seem to be of poor quality - it could be my software, but the volume on the three files is really low and the sound quality seems low).

I suggest that the three mini files be removed (because downloading three separate files is inconvenient) and that the errant dialogue be replaced by one that matches the existing dialogue.  -- [[User:FyreWolfe|FyreWolfe]] 03:54, 26 Nov 2004 (UTC)

:Hello, I uploaded these 3 audio files in Commons. They are the first ones I recorded so it is quite possible that their quality could be improved. Honestly I tell you that it was my mistake to record them because I didn't realize that there was another audio file with the whole dialogue recorded. About their volume, i thought that their quality were good enough to be uploaded but i didn't realised that my loudspeakers are very powerful. Therefore, i wouldn´t mind and i'll understand if it's decided to erase the audio files I created, I'll try to do it better next time :), but then we have to ask for it in Commons. --[[User:Javier Carro|Javier Carro]] 08:27, 26 Nov 2004 (UTC)


----

Hey this looks great, I'm a Spanish speaker and especially excited to see this textbook started .. -- [[Karl Wick]]

The sound files that are now on the web pages are spoken by Mariela, a friend
of mine who founded a SpanishForForeigners group at yahoo. She is currently
having some trouble with her internet connection and asked me to upload the
files for her. -- [[User:ThomasStrohmann|Thomas Strohmann]]

:I was reading the lesson and I think some of the phrases sound somewhat funny: &quot;¿Cómo se llama usted?&quot; (lit. How are you called?) and &quot;¿Hay algo nuevo para contar?&quot; (Is there anything new to say?). I think no native spanish speaker speaks like that. In the question: &quot;¿Cómo se llama usted?&quot; the word &quot;usted&quot; is redundant, because the context already implies it. I think it's better to remove the word and to explain to the reader the use of the verb conjugation to establish the context. As for the question &quot;¿Hay algo nuevo para contar?&quot;, even when it is completely valid spanish, it's simply never used in the real world. Actually, spanish speaking persons rarely ask questions like that. Some &quot;more natural&quot; alternatives are &quot;¿Qué ha pasado?&quot; or even better, &quot;¿Qué hay de nuevo?&quot; or &quot;¿Cómo te va?&quot;.

:Other instances of redundance are: &quot;¿Y tú, cómo estás?&quot;: &quot;¿Y tú?&quot; is enough. &quot;¿Y usted, cómo se llama?&quot;: &quot;¿Y usted?&quot; will do.

: OASO (Octavio Salguero)

:OASO, I've made the changes you suggested. Thanks so much for all the useful comments (since I'm just starting to learn Spanish I'm not yet confident in writing well stylistically). [[User:ThomasStrohmann | Thomas Strohmann]]

:Perhaps including a note that 'hasta' literally translates to 'until', making it easier later on when it is given other uses in normal conversation.
----
Hello. I think there are to much information for a newbie. I suggest to split the lesson into two parts ''Lesson 1, A'' and ''Lesson 1, B''. Then, there would be in ''lesson 1, A'' : Dialogue 1, vocab of dialogue 1, pronouns seen in lesson 1. 

There is also a lot of information on verbs. I suggest to introduce ''ser, estar'' in lesson 2 or later, beacause it is a complicated topic.

The verbe ''cantar'' has been introduced in lesson 1. I suggest to add examples of sentences with ''-ar'' verbes in lesson 1, B. ''Trabajar'', ''hablar'' seems to be verbs that newbies use soon.

What do you think about my comments ? --[[User:Youssefsan|Oualmakran Youssef]] 14:30, 24 Apr 2004 (UTC)

:I think your comments make a lot of sense. Please take the initiative and do what you suggest and if it gets all messed up (which I don't think will happen) I'll help straighten things up. Some of those simple &quot;-ar&quot; verbs make much more sense to introduce first and we don't want to overwhelm anyone with too much information to bite off in one piece .. - [[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

----
I just noticed the audio file doesn't correspond exactly with the written text in example dialog one.  Should the text be changed? [[User:Lbs6380|Lbs6380]] 18:14, 12 May 2004 (UTC)

== audio files. ==

What should I use to listen to the audio files? Neither real player nor window media player seem to work.

Any suggestions on what to use in the Mac world?  I have tried Quicktime, RealPlayer, iTunes, and MPlayer OS X--this last one produces something really garbled and static-y sounding but is the only thing close to sounding like speech.
===Answer===
I manged to listen to the audio files ending in .ogg with Goldwave, a free program, but it is not really designed for that - Goldwave is really a sound file editing and recording program, and the text files sound a little too funny and a bit fast.  Maybe someone else can tell us what program is supposed to work with .ogg -  and where to get a free version of it...
Yes, I can tell you: Winamp will do (free download for Windows). Found while looking at the possibillities of .ogg files (linux)

== Vowel pronounciation ==

Why are there two tables for vowel pronounciation?  I think both are really confusing.  For example: E=&quot;Eh&quot; as in &quot;Day&quot;.  I know what you mean but it would be better to use a vowel between two consonants such as in the word &quot;bed&quot;.

In the second set of vowel examples we have &quot;A&quot; = A in &quot;father&quot;.  It just isn't.  I don't know anyone who pronounces &quot;que pasa?&quot; using the &quot;a&quot; from father.  It's more like the &quot;a&quot; from &quot;dad&quot; or &quot;fat&quot;.  Shouldn't we use IPA to be clear? Or just use better examples from the English?

[[User:82.213.248.138|82.213.248.138]] 17:27, 7 November 2005 (UTC) El Choco

OK, I have rewritten the Vowel Pronounciations as I suggested above and also moved the section to underneath the Consonant Pronounciation because it makes more sense there.  I have moved the section on &quot;Diacrital use over the vowel u&quot; to be with the other pronounciation changes of u.

I also extended the stress rules so they are correct. 

[[User:82.213.248.138|82.213.248.138]] 21:02, 7 November 2005 (UTC) El Choco

== Consonant pronunciation ==

Why do the vowel and semivowel sections have IPA, but the consonant section only the vague approximations?   Isn't |j| pronounced /x/ (at least in some dialects?), not really /h/ (&quot;like the h in hotel&quot;)?  Or should it say in which dialects |j| is /x/ and which dialects have /h/? --[[User:Jim Henry|Jim Henry]] 23:05, 12 August 2006 (UTC)

== ¿Cómo te llamas? ==

I believe that it is also correct in certain places to say &quot;¿Qué es tu nombre?&quot; instead of &quot;¿Cómo te llamas?&quot;. If I am right, would somebody like to put this in somewhere? --[[User:222.153.151.94|222.153.151.94]] 08:33, 22 December 2005 (UTC)

I don't know if they really use it some places, but it wouldn't be &quot;¿Qué es tu nombre?&quot;. It'll be &quot;¿Cuál es tu nombre?&quot;
([[User:200.126.201.17|200.126.201.17]] 05:30, 25 February 2006 (UTC))

== Semi-Vowels ==
Here in Argentina, we don't pronounce Oyo with the &quot;y&quot; as in &quot;yet&quot;, we do it like a &quot;sh&quot; as in &quot;shake&quot;. So maybe there could be a better example, like &quot;rey&quot;, that it is pronounced the same everywhere (with the y as in &quot;yet&quot;).
([[User:200.126.201.17|200.126.201.17]] 05:38, 25 February 2006 (UTC))

== Side to side ==

Maybe the words in spanish (for the people talking examples) should have the english version right next to it, for better translation. I would do this, but I'm trying to learn spanish.</text>
      <sha1>a40u5wmcfzyf5arzuuamyftpsg0pa35</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Lojban</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>413</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2256915</id>
      <parentid>2256876</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-01-25T20:19:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Recent Runes</username>
        <id>66908</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rejected the last text change (by [[Special:Contributions/167.128.19.234|167.128.19.234]]) and restored revision 2052128 by Iketsi</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">''This is currently a pre-draft textbook. Therefore some information is inaccurate.''

Coi! This book will help you learn Lojban.

==New Table Of Contents==

===Kickstarting an understanding of the basics===

# [[/Place structure/]] teaches you how to read Lojban dictionary definitions
#* [[/Practicing vocabulary with Anki/]] guides you in using software for memorising words
#* [[/Look up words with makfa/]] on the IRC chat or the command line
# [[/Simple sentences with pronouns/]] will have you speak Lojban in no time!
# [[/Using words as adjectives/]] by adding them together
# [[/Forming nouns using articles/]] and you can say almost anything
# [[/Changing the order of a place structure/]] so you ''can'' say anything

==Old Table Of Contents==

#[[/Introduction to Lojban/]]
##[[/Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis/]]
##[[/Culturally neutral/]]
##[[/Unambiguous grammar/]]
##[[/Phonetic spelling/]]
##[[/Logical language/]]
#[[/Introduction to Lojban grammar/]]
#[[/Sounds and alphabet/]]
#[[/cmene/]]
#[[/Vocatives/]]
#[[/Attitudinals/]]
#[[/Bridi/]]
#[[/Selbri/]]
#[[/Tanru/]]
#[[/Sumti/]]
#[[/How to learn vocabulary/]]
#[[/Anaphora/]]
##[[/Acronyms/]]
##[[/Pro-sumti/]]
##[[/Pro-bridi/]]
###[[/Anaphora/Subscription|Anaphora Subscription]]
#[[/Rafsi/]]
##[[/Rafsi/Great Rafsi Reallocation (1993)|Great Rafsi Reallocation (GRR) (1993)]]
##[[/Rafsi/Prior to Reallocation (1993)|Rafsi list prior to GRR (1993)]]
#[[/Lujvo/]]
#[[/Abstractions/]]
#[[/Sumti tcita/]]
#[[/Connectives/]]
#[[/Tenses/]]
#[[/Negation/]]
#[[/Letterals/]]
#[[/Mathematics/]]
##[[/mekso/]]
##[[/Numbers/]]
#[[/Times and dates/]]
##[[/Times/]]
##[[/Dates/]]
#[[/Colours|Colors]]
#[[/Commands/]]
#[[/Elidable terminator/]]
#[[/Cause and effect/]]
#[[/Discursives/]]
#[[/Erasure/]]
#[[/Measurements/]]
#[[/By standard/]]
#[[/Foods and beverages/]]
#[[/Plants/]]
#[[/Animals/]]
#[[/Body parts/]]
#[[/Emotions/]]
#[[/Clothes/]]
#[[/Rooms of the house/]]
#[[/Directions/]]
#[[/Le ninmu cu te dunda le ninmu le gerku/]]
#[[/Fu'ivla/]]
#[[/Vocabulary 1/]]
#[[/Vocabulary 2/]]

Appendices
#[[/Vocabulary/]]
#[[/Glossary/]]
#[[/Recordings/]]
#[[/Other resources/]]

{{Subjects|Constructed languages}}
{{alphabetical|L}}
{{status|25%}}

[[ja:ロジバン]]
[[pl:Lożban]]</text>
      <sha1>4z1bvna7ytp2j059oykzm49tu6vdysc</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Lojban</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>414</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1866670</id>
      <parentid>971944</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-06-28T22:42:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Adding {{WikiProject Languages}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{WikiProject Languages}} 

== In regards to vocabulary ==

I believe that we should not only give words and definitions, but demonstrate these words in a conversational context. For example, in the food and beverages unit, in addition to the basic vocabulary aspect, we could also provide commonly used phrases such as &quot;I would like to book a reservation at your restaurant&quot;, &quot;Enjoy your meal&quot;, &quot;What would you like to order?&quot; etc. It's the only way people will learn how to actually apply Lojban to conversational speaking.

Secondly, I believe that we should add more units to the textbook. I suggest the topics Celebrations, Shopping, Medical (doctor and veterinary), Entertainment and Interests, Relationships (family, friends, fiancees), School, Work, etc. What is your opinion? fe'o --[[User:Jboprelinomu|Jboprelinomu]] 13:07, 15 October 2005 (UTC)

:Yes, I agree. The wikibook like it is now is quite unreadable, which doesn't aid in learning the language (or ANY language for that matter). [[nl:Gebruiker:JorisvS|JorisvS]]

----

[[Colors]] and similar aren't distinct enough to serve as module titles. --[[User:Maveric149|mav]]

----
Cool ! A Lojban textbook ! Keep up the good work man and dont let the naysayers get you down. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]] 03:21 4 Aug 2003 (UTC)


----
Would it be better to add the Lojban draft textbook (http://lojban.org/publications/draft_textbook.html ) to Wikibooks and work with it instead of starting from scratch?


This is legal only if the link you gave is in the public domain or under the GFDL or GFDL-compatible license. I couldn't find anything saying so. The language definition is in the public domain. --[[User:Ellmist|Ellmist]] 05:32, 2 Apr 2004 (UTC)

== Lojban For Beginners ==

Could we just copy [http://www.tlg.uci.edu/~opoudjis/lojbanbrochure/lessons/book1.html this] over? It's under a Creative Commons Attribution 2.5 License. That means it's OK to use, right? - [[User:Talkie Toaster|Talkie Toaster]] 17:52, 18 September 2007 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>rt9ooj9uqogjo004w89ykdae7htl0py</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Lojban/Sounds and alphabet</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>415</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2384348</id>
      <parentid>2383546</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-07-26T20:59:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JackPotte</username>
        <id>99248</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Lojban has a 24-letter alphabet (23 of which come from the Roman alphabet):&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
' a b c d e f g i j k l m n o p r s t u v x y z&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
And two special symbols:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
, .&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
This includes most of the traditional English alphabet except for three letters:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
h q w&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Lojban has a [[w:phonetic spelling|phonetic spelling]] and audio-visual isomorphism, meaning that each letter has exactly one sound and each sound has exactly one letter.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
{| border=&quot;1&quot; 
|-
!Letter !! SAMPA IPA	!! Description
|-
| '     || [h] 
| Unvoiced glottal spirant, as in ''h''at
|-
| ,     || ---          
| Syllable separator
|-
| .     || [/]
| Glottal stop or a pause, as in 'uh oh'
|-
| a     || [a], [A]	
| Open vowel, as in f''a''ther, NOT as in h''a''t
|-
| b     || [b] 
| Voiced bilabial stop, as in ''b''agel
|-
| c     || [S], [s`]
| Unvoiced coronal sibilant, as in ''sh''ark
|-
| d     || [d]
| Voiced dental/alveolar stop, as in ''d''esk
|-
| e     || [E], [e]
| Front mid vowel, as in b''e''t, NOT as in b''ee''p
|-
| f     || [f], [p\]
| Unvoiced labial fricative, as in ''f''at
|-
| g     || [g]
| Voiced velar stop, as in ''g''reat, NOT as in ''G''eorge
|-
| i     || [i]
| Front close vowel, as in mach''i''ne, NOT as in ''i''gloo
|-
| j     || [Z], [z`]
| Voiced coronal sibilant, as in mea''s''ure, NOT as in ''j''ustice
|-
| k     || [k]	
| Unvoiced velar stop, as in ''k''ill
|-
| l     || [l], [l=]
| Voiced lateral approximant (may be syllabic), as in ''l''ake
|-
| m     || [m], [m=]	
| Voiced bilabial nasal (may be syllabic), as in ''m''aybe
|-
| n     || [n], [n=], [N], [N=]
| Voiced dental or velar nasal (may be syllabic), as in ''n''eck
|-
| o     || [o], [O]
| Back mid vowel, as in ''o''pen, NOT as in ''o''pera
|-
| p     || [p]	
| Unvoiced bilabial stop, as in ''p''epper
|-
| r     || [r], [4], [r\], [R\], [r=], [4=], [r\=], [R\=]
| Rhotic sound, as in ''r''iver
|-
| s     || [s]	
| Unvoiced alveolar sibilant, as in ''s''nake
|-
| t     || [t]	
| Unvoiced dental/alveolar stop, as in ''t''arp
|-
| u     || [u]	
| Back close vowel, as in m''oo''n, NOT as in c''u''p
|-
| v     || [v], [B] 
| Voiced labial fricative, as in ''v''ast
|-
| x     || [x]	
| Unvoiced velar fricative, as in German Ba''ch'' and Spanish ''J''ose and Arabic ''Kh''aled, NOT as in ba''k''e and bo''x''
|-
| y      || [@]	
| Central mid vowel, schwa, as in s''y''ringe, NOT as in ''y''ellow
|-
| z      || [z]
| Voiced alveolar sibilant, as in oo''z''e
|}

' only appears in Lojban words between vowels. &quot;,&quot; only appears in Lojban names. Lojbanists can optionally not include the &quot;.&quot; in their writing. The stress is on a word's penultimate syllable. The exception is that a syllable whose nucleus is a 'y' cannot be stressed; in that case, stress the syllable immediately preceding it. Names may indicate different from penultimate stress by capitalizing the entire stressed syllable or the vowel of the stressed syllable. Some Lojbanists have unofficially proposed other characters to mark stress like &quot;^&quot;.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Lojban has eleven diphthongs written by composed vowels. The following transliterations are assuming that the reader has an American English accent.&lt;br&gt;
{| border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
| ai ||        As in h''igh''
|-
| au ||        As in h''ow''
|-
| ei ||        As in h''ey''
|-
| oi ||        As in b''oy''
|-
| ia ||        As in ''ya''cht
|-
| ie ||        As in ''ye''s
|-
| ii ||        As in ''yea''r and ''ye''
|-
| io ||        As in ''yo''gurt
|-
| iu ||        Like ''you''
|-
| ua ||        As in ''waah!'' and French q''uoi''
|-
| ue ||        As in q''ue''stion
|-
| uo ||        As in q''uo''te
|-
| ui ||        Like ''we'' and French ''oui''
|-
| uu ||        As in ''wo''mb
|}

A pair of adjacent vowels which are capable of forming a diphthong ''will'' form a diphthong unless a comma is placed between them. That is the purpose of the comma in Lojban; to act as a separator between syllables whenever necessary for pronunciation purposes. (It is not for pausing between words or phrases like in English.)

To make pronouncing some words easier, you may put unwritten '''buffer vowels''' in your speech between consonants. Any non-Lojban vowel can act as a buffer vowel, but i as in h''i''t has the most popularity. For example, you could pronounce (but not write) a buffer vowel between the &quot;s&quot; and &quot;f&quot; of &quot;sfani&quot;.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
==Exercises==
:&lt;h3&gt;Pronounce&lt;/h3&gt;
:Pronounce the word given.
# .i
# .a
# .e
# .a
# .o
# .u
# .e'i
# lu'a
# se'inai
# gu'onai
# diklo
# tumla
# tunlo
# stasu
# kabri
# vitke
# pandi
# ransu
# tercakyjme
# backemselrerkru
# seljinru
# penydjuxa'a
# vokygenkantu
# xagmaubi'o
# xacysantyse'u
# finprxipoglosu
# smacrkobaiu
# samcrkasava
&lt;h3&gt;Write/Stress&lt;/h3&gt;
:Write down each Lojbanized name, stressing the first syllable. Pronounce the name with the original and initial (afterwards) stress.
# la geibri,el.&lt;br&gt;
# la keitlen.&lt;br&gt;
# la rabert.&lt;br&gt;
# la xeilis.&lt;br&gt;
# la no,as.&lt;br&gt;
# la destenis.&lt;br&gt;
# la keileb.&lt;br&gt;
# la tamas.&lt;br&gt;
# la kateren.&lt;br&gt;
# la djorden.&lt;br&gt;
# la necol.&lt;br&gt;
# la xanter.&lt;br&gt;
# la .alecsendras.&lt;br&gt;
# la kameren.&lt;br&gt;
# la mari,as.&lt;br&gt;
# la kail.&lt;br&gt;
# la savenas.
&lt;h3&gt;Answer&lt;/h3&gt;
:Answer each question completely.
# How many letters does Lojban's alphabet have, not including special symbols?
# How many symbols does Lojban's alphabet have, including special symbols?
# Which three letters of the English alphabet does the Lojban alphabet not have?
# Where do apostrophes (') appear in Lojban text?
# Which of the following are correct Lojban diphthongs: uo, oa, ii, io, oi, ee, ea, ui
# What does &quot;buffer vowel&quot; mean?
&lt;h3&gt;True or False&lt;/h3&gt;
:Answer 'true' or 'false'.
# Each Lojban letter corresponds to exactly one sound.
# The period (.) is a required part of the Lojban orthography.
# Lojban names have antepenultimate stress by default.

==Answers to exercises==
&lt;h3&gt;Pronounce&lt;/h3&gt;
:No recording of pronunciation available.
&lt;h3&gt;Write/Stress&lt;/h3&gt;
# la GEIBri,el.
# la KEITlen
# la RABert.
# la XEILis
# la NO,as.
# la DESTenis.
# la KEILeb.
# la TAMas
# la KATeren.
# la DJORden.
# la NECol.
# la XANter.
# la .ALecendras.
# la KAMeren.
# la MARi,as.
# la kail. (No capitalization needed with only one syllable.)
# la SAVenas.
&lt;h3&gt;Answer&lt;/h3&gt;
# Twenty-four (24) letters.
# Twenty-six (26) symbols.
# h, q, and w.
# Apostrophes (') only appear in Lojban words between vowels.
# uo, ii, io, oi, and ui.
# &quot;Buffer vowel&quot; means unwritten, spoken vowel in a consonant cluster to aid pronunciation.
&lt;h3&gt;True or False&lt;/h3&gt;
# True
# False
# False

[[Category:Lojban]]
[[Category:Alphabets]]</text>
      <sha1>2nx0zoirvbgw9g8epc3pkz08bqaaaep</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Lojban/Cmene</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>417</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1444281</id>
      <parentid>562379</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-03-16T14:11:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>158.59.246.191</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Added IPA</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">In Lojban names are called ''cmene'' (pronouced shmen-eh, IPA /ʃme.ne/), and are transliterated to use only Lojban sounds. In Lobjan all words end in a vowel, and so to avoid any possible confusion all cmene end in a consonant; if a transliterated name would end in a vowel, it is usual to add an s to the end. All cmene are followed by a full stop, so confusion to where the name stops and the next word starts it avoided; for this reason, any names beginning in a vowel have a full stop in front of them. To indicate an accent somewhere other than the second-to-last syllable, the entire syllable to be accented must be capitalised. A comma should be used to stop two vowels next to each other that should not be pronouced as a dipthong. All names must have the word 'la', meaning 'the', placed before them. A few examples are below:

{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!English!!Lojban
|-
|New York||nu,IORK (in some accents ni,IORK)
|-
|Cynthia||sinti,a (pronounced SEEN-tee-ah)
|-
|Daniel||daniyl (DAHN-yuhl)
|}

== Exercises ==
=== English names to Cmene ===
Translate these names to Lojban cmene.
# Jacob
# Emily
# Michael
# Madison
# Joshua
# Hannah
# Matthew
# Emma
# Ethan
# Alexis
# Joseph
# Ashley
# Andrew
# Abigail
# Christopher
# Sarah
# Daniel
# Samantha
# Nicholas
# Olivia
=== Cmene to English names ===
Translate these Lojban cmene to English names.
# la .ueliem.
# la .ilezabet.
# la .entonis.
# la .alesas.
# la deived.
# la laren.
# la tailer.
# la .ezabelas.
# la .alekzander.
# la greis.
# la rai,en.
# la djeseka.
# la djan.
# la brianas.
# la djeimz.
# la teiler.
# la zekeris.
# la keilas.
# la brendan.
# la .ennas.

== Answers to Exercises ==
No one pronouciation of a name is the right one, so use common sense whe deciding if you got these right or not.
=== English names to Cmene ===
# la djeikeb.
# la .emelis.
# la maikel.
# la medesen.
# la djaciu,as.
# la xennas.
# la ma'ius.
# la .emas.
# la .i'an.
# la .alekses.
# la djosef.
# la .aclis.
# la .endrus.
# la .ebegeil.
# la krestofer.
# la seiras.
# la daniel.
# la samentas.
# la nekoles.
# la .olevias.

=== Cmene to English names ===
# William
# Elizabeth
# Anthony
# Alyssa
# David
# Lauren
# Tyler
# Isabella
# Alexander
# Grace
# Ryan
# Jessica
# John
# Brianna
# James
# Taylor
# Zachary
# Kayla
# Brandon
# Anna

[[Category:Lojban]]</text>
      <sha1>834bcs2a727gyqcseby2o2anxnw47b5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Ellmist</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>418</id>
    <revision>
      <id>152575</id>
      <timestamp>2003-08-04T02:40:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ellmist</username>
        <id>26</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>See [[w:User:Ellmist]].</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">See [[w:User:Ellmist]].</text>
      <sha1>pwi2bffvtdpsnbzn1hopygv7v48lv3o</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:Ellmist</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>419</id>
    <revision>
      <id>152576</id>
      <timestamp>2003-08-04T02:40:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ellmist</username>
        <id>26</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>See [[w:User talk:Ellmist]].</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">See [[w:User talk:Ellmist]].</text>
      <sha1>mtdius9dk1bkt1f8q31bs6fejbmhlj6</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Merphant</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>421</id>
    <revision>
      <id>152577</id>
      <timestamp>2003-08-04T07:29:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Merphant</username>
        <id>49</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">See [[en:User:Merphant]]</text>
      <sha1>tgzs9tncjh8zpf5lmt7uk4h00i5ev17</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Spanish/Lesson 4</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>423</id>
    <revision>
      <id>620963</id>
      <parentid>616017</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-10-21T22:13:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Guanaco</username>
        <id>1043</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>fix</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Spanish}}

==Stem Changing Verbs==

In Spanish, some verbs change their stems when they are conjugated. These verbs are known as ''stem-changing verbs''. Many of these verbs are important and often used. There are three different types of stem changing verbs in Spanish:

&lt;center&gt;
{| style=&quot;background-color: #FFDEAD; border: solid 1px #bfffbf; padding: 0.2em; width: 90%;&quot; valign=top
|[[Image:Spain_flag_300.png|left|26px|Spanish Flag]]&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 110%&quot;&gt;'''Cambios de los Verbos'''&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;''Los verbos''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
|-
|
{| style=&quot;width: 100%; text-align: left&quot; 
| colspan=2 | &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 92%&quot;&gt;&lt;center&gt;Types of Stem-Changing Verbs&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
|-
|&lt;div style=&quot;font-size: 95%; font-weight: bold; line-height: 105%&quot;&gt;e → ie&lt;br&gt;
e → i&lt;br&gt;
o → ue&lt;/span&gt;
|}
|}
&lt;/center&gt;

The stem changes for all conjugations, excepting '''nosotros/as''' and '''vosotros/as'''. The endings are the same as for regular verbs ('''-o''' for '''yo''', '''-as/-es''' for '''tú''', ...). 

&lt;br&gt;&lt;big&gt; '''Entender'''&lt;/big&gt;&lt;br&gt;To Understand

{| style=&quot;width: 400px;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; cellpadding=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | I understand
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;100&quot; | yo ent'''ie'''nd
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | '''o'''
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | You understand
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | tú ent'''ie'''nd
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | '''es'''
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | He understands&lt;br&gt;
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | él ent'''ie'''nd
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;e&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot;width=&quot;134&quot; | She understands&lt;br&gt;
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | ella ent'''ie'''nd
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;e&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | You understand&lt;br&gt;
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | Usted ent'''ie'''nd
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;e&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | We understand
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | nosotros entend&lt;br&gt;
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;emos&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | You (pl.) understand
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | vosotros entend&lt;br&gt;
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;eis&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | They understand&lt;br&gt;
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | ellos ent'''ie'''nd
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;en&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | You (pl form) understand&lt;br&gt;
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | Ustedes ent'''ie'''nd
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;en&lt;/b&gt;
|}

Note that the stem change is done for the second 'e' (not the first one) - in general the stem always changes for the last vowel before the '''-ar/-er/-ir''' ending.

'''Example''': pedir (e-&gt;i) ''to ask for, to order''

&lt;big&gt; '''Pedir'''&lt;/big&gt;&lt;br&gt;To Ask For, Order

{| style=&quot;width: 400px;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; cellpadding=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | I ask for
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | yo p'''i'''d
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;o&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | You ask for
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | tú p'''i'''d
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;es&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | He asks for&lt;br&gt;
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | él p'''i'''d
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;e&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | She asks for&lt;br&gt;
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | ella p'''i'''d
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;e&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | You (form) ask for&lt;br&gt;
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; |  Usted p'''i'''d
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;e&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | We ask for
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | nosotros ped&lt;br&gt;
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;imos&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | You (plural) ask for
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | vosotros ped&lt;br&gt;
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;ís&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | They ask for&lt;br&gt;
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | ellos p'''i'''d
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;en&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | You (pl form) ask for&lt;br&gt;
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | Ustedes p'''i'''d
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;en&lt;/b&gt;
|}

Note: all '''e-&gt;i''' stem changing verbs are '''-ir''' verbs.


&lt;big&gt; '''Dormir'''&lt;/big&gt;&lt;br&gt;To Sleep

{| style=&quot;width: 400px;&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; cellpadding=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | I sleep
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | yo d'''ue'''rm
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;o&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | You sleep
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | tú d'''ue'''rm
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;es&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | He sleeps&lt;br&gt;
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | él d'''ue'''rm
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;e&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | She sleeps&lt;br&gt;
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | ella d'''ue'''rm
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;e&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | You (formal) sleep&lt;br&gt;
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | Usted d'''ue'''rm
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;e&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | We sleep
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | nosotros dorm&lt;br&gt;
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;imos&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | You (plural) sleep
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | vosotros dorm&lt;br&gt;
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;ís&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | They sleep&lt;br&gt;
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | ellos d'''ue'''rm
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;en&lt;/b&gt;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#edfded&quot; width=&quot;134&quot; | You (plural formal) sleep&lt;br&gt;
| align=&quot;right&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#f6f9f7&quot; width=&quot;87&quot; | Ustedes d'''ue'''rm
| bgcolor=&quot;#dfe0e0&quot; width=&quot;33&quot; | &lt;b&gt;en&lt;/b&gt;
|}

Here is a list of some other common stem changing verbs:

{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!e -&gt; ie
!e -&gt; i
!o -&gt; ue
|-
|cerrar ''(to close)''
|competir ''(to compete)''
|almorzar ''(to eat lunch)''
|-
|comenzar ''(to begin)''
|conseguir ''(to get, obtain)''
|costar ''(to cost)''
|-
|defender ''(to defend)''
|pedir ''(to ask for, order)''
|encontrar ''(to find)''
|-
|empezar ''(to start, begin)''
|reir ''(to laugh)''
|morir ''(to die)''
|-
|mentir ''(to lie)''
|repetir ''(to repeat)''
|mostrar ''(to show)''
|-
|pensar ''(to think)''
|seguir ''(to follow, continue)''
|mover  ''(to move)''
|-
|perder ''(to lose)''
|servir ''(to serve)''
|recordar ''(to remember)''
|-
|preferir ''(to prefer)''
|sonreír ''(to smile)''
|volver ''(to return)''
|}

'''Exercise''': [[Spanish/Exercises/Stem Changing Verbs|Stem Changing Verbs]]

==Present Participle==

The present participle in Spanish is used either for continuous tenses (with ''estar'', e.g. ''I am running.'') and can also be used as an adjective. The Spanish present participle corresponds to the English '''-ing''' form of the verb.To form the present participle for regular '''-ar''' verbs, add '''-ando''' to the stem. For '''-er''' and '''-ir''' verbs add '''-iendo''':

&lt;center&gt;
{| style=&quot;background-color: #FFDEAD; border: solid 1px #bfffbf; padding: 0.2em; width: 90%;&quot; valign=top
|[[Image:Spain_flag_300.png|left|26px|Spanish Flag]]&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 110%&quot;&gt;'''El Participio Presente'''&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;''Los Verbos''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
|-
|
{| style=&quot;width: 100%; text-align: left&quot; 
| colspan=2 | &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 92%&quot;&gt;&lt;center&gt;-ing&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
|-
|&lt;div style=&quot;font-size: 95%; font-weight: bold; line-height: 105%&quot;&gt;hablar →  hablando&lt;br&gt;
comer →  comiendo&lt;br&gt;
vivir →  viviendo&lt;/span&gt;
|&lt;div style=&quot;font-size: 95%; line-height: 105%&quot;&gt;speaking&lt;br&gt;
eating&lt;br&gt;
living&lt;/span&gt;
|}
|}
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
However, not all present participles are that regular. Some verbs add a &quot;y,&quot; or change the spelling, to adhere to Spanish orthography (spelling) rules. Here is a list of some common verbs that have an irregular present participle:

&lt;center&gt;
{| style=&quot;background-color: #FFDEAD; border: solid 1px #bfffbf; padding: 0.2em; width: 90%;&quot; valign=top
|[[Image:Spain_flag_300.png|left|26px|Spanish Flag]]&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 110%&quot;&gt;'''Participios Irregulares'''&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;''Los Verbos''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
|-
|
{| style=&quot;width: 100%; text-align: left&quot; 
| colspan=2 | &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 92%&quot;&gt;&lt;center&gt;-ing&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
|-
|&lt;div style=&quot;font-size: 95%; font-weight: bold; line-height: 105%&quot;&gt;caer&lt;br&gt;
decir&lt;br&gt;
dormir&lt;br&gt;
ir&lt;br&gt;
leer&lt;br&gt;
oir&lt;br&gt;
pedir&lt;br&gt;
repetir&lt;br&gt;
reír&lt;br&gt;
seguir&lt;br&gt;
traer&lt;/span&gt;
|&lt;div style=&quot;font-size: 95%; line-height: 105%&quot;&gt;cayendo&lt;br&gt;
diciendo&lt;br&gt;
durmiendo&lt;br&gt;
yendo&lt;br&gt;
leyendo&lt;br&gt;
oyendo&lt;br&gt;
pidiendo&lt;br&gt;
repitiendo&lt;br&gt;
riendo&lt;br&gt;
siguiendo&lt;br&gt;
trayendo&lt;/span&gt;
|}
|}
&lt;/center&gt;

==Present Progressive==

Like in English, the Spanish present progressive is used to describe an ''action in progress''.
It is formed by conjugating the verb '''estar''' and then adding the present participle:

&lt;center&gt;
{| style=&quot;background-color: #FFDEAD; border: solid 1px #7FFFD4; padding: 0.2em; width: 90%;&quot; valign=top
|[[Image:Spain_flag_300.png|left|26px|Spanish Flag]]&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 110%&quot;&gt;'''El Presente Progresivo'''&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;''Los Verbos''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
|-
|
{| style=&quot;width: 100%; text-align: left&quot; 
| colspan=2 | &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 92%&quot;&gt;&lt;center&gt;Talking about actions occurring right now&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
|-
|&lt;div style=&quot;font-size: 95%; font-weight: bold; line-height: 105%&quot;&gt;Yo estoy hablando&lt;br&gt;
Tú estás hablando&lt;br&gt;
Él/ella/usted está hablando&lt;br&gt;
Nosotros estamos hablando&lt;br&gt;
Vosotros estáis hablando&lt;br&gt;
Ellos/ellas/ustedes están hablando&lt;/span&gt;
|&lt;div style=&quot;font-size: 95%; line-height: 105%&quot;&gt;I am talking&lt;br&gt;
You are talking&lt;br&gt;
He/She/You is/are talking&lt;br&gt;
We are talking&lt;br&gt;
You are talking&lt;br&gt;
They/You are talking&lt;/span&gt;
|}
|}
&lt;/center&gt;

==Vocabulary==

&lt;center&gt;
{| style=&quot;background-color: #f2fff2; border: solid 1px #bfffbf; padding: 0.2em; width: 90%;&quot; valign=top
|[[Image:Spain_flag_300.png|left|26px|Spanish Flag]]&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 110%&quot;&gt;'''El Vocabulario'''  &lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;''La Familia''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
|-
|
{| style=&quot;width: 100%; text-align: left&quot; 
| colspan=2 | &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 92%&quot;&gt;&lt;center&gt;Vocabulary for the family&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
|-
|&lt;div style=&quot;font-size: 95%; font-weight: bold; line-height: 105%&quot;&gt;los padres&lt;br&gt;
el padre, papá&lt;br&gt;
la madre, mamá&lt;br&gt;
los hijos&lt;br&gt;
el hijo&lt;br&gt;
la hija&lt;br&gt;
los hermanos&lt;br&gt;
el hermano&lt;br&gt;
la hermana&lt;br&gt;
los abuelos&lt;br&gt;
el abuelo&lt;br&gt;
la abuela&lt;br&gt;
los nietos&lt;br&gt;
el nieto&lt;br&gt;
la nieta&lt;br&gt;
los tíos&lt;br&gt;
el tío&lt;br&gt;
la tía&lt;br&gt;
los sobrinos&lt;br&gt;
el sobrino&lt;br&gt;
la sobrina&lt;br&gt;
los primos&lt;br&gt;
el primo&lt;br&gt;
la prima&lt;br&gt;
los cónyuges, marido y mujer&lt;br&gt;
el esposo, el marido&lt;br&gt;
la esposa, la mujer&lt;br&gt;
los suegros&lt;br&gt;
la suegra, la nuera&lt;br&gt;
el suegro, el yerno&lt;br&gt;
los cuñados&lt;br&gt;
el cuñado&lt;br&gt;
la cuñada&lt;br&gt;
los consuegros&lt;br&gt;
el consuegro&lt;br&gt;
la consuegra&lt;/span&gt;
|&lt;div style=&quot;font-size: 95%;
line-height:105%&quot;&gt;parents&lt;br&gt;
father&lt;br&gt;
mother&lt;br&gt;
children&lt;br&gt;
son&lt;br&gt;
daughter&lt;br&gt;
siblings&lt;br&gt;
brother&lt;br&gt;
sister&lt;br&gt;
grandparents&lt;br&gt;
grandfather&lt;br&gt;
grandmother&lt;br&gt;
grandchildren&lt;br&gt;
grandson&lt;br&gt;
granddaughter&lt;br&gt;
uncles and aunts&lt;br&gt;
uncle&lt;br&gt;
aunt&lt;br&gt;
nephews and nieces&lt;br&gt;
nephew&lt;br&gt;
niece&lt;br&gt;
cousins&lt;br&gt;
cousin (male)&lt;br&gt;
cousin (female)&lt;br&gt;
spouses&lt;br&gt;
husband&lt;br&gt;
wife&lt;br&gt;
parents-in-law&lt;br&gt;
mother-in-law&lt;br&gt;
father-in-law&lt;br&gt;
siblings-in-law&lt;br&gt;
brother-in-law&lt;br&gt;
sister-in-law&lt;br&gt;
your child's parents-in-law&lt;br&gt;
your child's father-in-law&lt;br&gt;
your child's mother-in-law&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
|}
|}
&lt;/center&gt;

{{Spanish}}

[[Category:Spanish]]</text>
      <sha1>oqy94mcqm8nizfvxh90ng41y63evljo</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Spanish/Lesson 3</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>424</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2465782</id>
      <parentid>1686060</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-12-20T13:50:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>75.74.15.62</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Regular Verbs */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Spanish}}
----

== Text ==

Here are a couple of sentences and short dialogs about people planning/doing leisure activities. Besides the new vocabulary you should also have a look at how the verbs are conjugated depending on the subject of the sentence.

{{Spanish Dialogue|1=Los Verbos|2=Maria '''viaja''' a México&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
''Luis'': ¿Qué '''hacen''' por la noche?&lt;br&gt;''Ana y Carmen'': Nosotras '''bailamos''' en la fiesta.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;''Raúl'': ¿Qué '''haces''' mañana?&lt;br&gt;''Carlos'': Mañana '''practico''' al tenis.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Marco '''mira''' la televisión porque hace mal tiempo.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Pedro y Mario '''toman''' unos refrescos.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Rosalía '''escribe''' a sus padres los domingos.}}

As you may see, each verb is bolded. These verbs are ''conjugated'', that is, changed by the person(s) to which they are referring. Notice that subject pronouns are ''not'' necessary.
=== Vocabulary for text ===
{{Spanish Vocab|1=Viajar|2=Travelling|3=
viajar&lt;br&gt;
hacer&lt;br&gt;
la noche&lt;br&gt;
bailar&lt;br&gt;
la fiesta&lt;br&gt;
mañana&lt;br&gt;
practicar&lt;br&gt;
mirar&lt;br&gt;
porque&lt;br&gt;
buen tiempo&lt;br&gt;
mal tiempo&lt;br&gt;
tomar&lt;br&gt;
beber&lt;br&gt;
el refresco&lt;br&gt;
el domingo&lt;br&gt;
escribir&lt;br&gt;
los padres|
4=to travel&lt;br&gt;
to do, to make&lt;br&gt;
night&lt;br&gt;
to dance&lt;br&gt;
party&lt;br&gt;
tomorrow&lt;br&gt;
to practice&lt;br&gt;
to watch, to look at&lt;br&gt;
because&lt;br&gt;
nice weather&lt;br&gt;
bad weather&lt;br&gt;
to take, to drink&lt;br&gt;
to drink&lt;br&gt;
soda, soft drink&lt;br&gt;
Sunday&lt;br&gt;
to write&lt;br&gt;
parents}}

===Regular Verbs===

Spanish has three different types of regular verbs: '''-ar''', '''-er''', and '''-ir''' verbs. The subject pronoun is not necessary and in conversational Spanish it is only used for emphasis. For this lesson, we will omit it. One can still use pronouns, however. The conjugation pattern is the
following:

{{Spanish Grammar|1=El presente regular|2=
&lt;table border=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;&lt;tr style=&quot;background: #F0F0FF&quot;&gt;
&lt;td width=&quot;15%&quot;&gt;'''Person'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&quot;15%&quot;&gt;'''-ar&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&quot;15%&quot;&gt;'''-er'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&quot;15%&quot;&gt;'''-ir'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;''Infinitive''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;''hablar''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;''comer''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;''vivir''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;small&gt;English&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;small&gt;to talk&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;small&gt;to eat&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;small&gt;to live&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;'''1'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;habl'''o'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;com'''o'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;viv'''o'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;'''2'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;habl'''as'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;com'''es'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;viv'''es'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;'''3'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;habl'''a'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;com'''e'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;viv'''e'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;'''4'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;habl'''amos'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;com'''emos'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;viv'''imos'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;'''5'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;habl'''áis'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;com'''éis'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;viv'''ís'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;'''6'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;habl'''an'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;com'''en'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;viv'''en'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
}}
&lt;/br&gt;

As one can see, the endings for each person are different. This is similar to other Romance languages, such as Portuguese and Italian (the notable exception is French). This is the reason why we may omit the pronouns while we speak. Remember that sometimes it is best to clarify whether él, ella, or usted is speaking, because they share the same form. However, the context of the rest of the sentence sometimes clarifies this. There are a few steps involved with conjugating a verb. Here are the steps involved:
# Take the ending off of the infinitive. This is either an -ar, -er, or -ir.
# Without the -ar, -er, or -ir, the verb is in its ''base'' form.
# Add the appropriate ending to the base of the verb.

Notice that there are only two differences between the conjugations of -er and -ir verbs. The ''nosotros'' (4) and ''vosotros'' (5) forms are the only differences. Those forms have an &quot;i&quot; in the stem instead of an &quot;e.&quot; 

'''Exercise''': [[Spanish/Exercises/Regular Verbs|Regular Verbs]]

===&quot;G&quot; Verbs===
The verb ''hacer'' means to do or to make. Hacer is irregular in the first person singular form ''(I)'' of the present tense only. The irregular form is '''hago'''. Hacer is one of the many verbs in Spanish which add a &quot;g&quot; in the first person singular of the verb. This is the present indicative of the verb '''hacer'''.
{{Spanish Grammar|1=El verbo hacer|2=
&lt;table border=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;&lt;tr style=&quot;background: #F0F0FF&quot;&gt;
&lt;td width=&quot;50%&quot;&gt;'''Person'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width=&quot;50%&quot;&gt;'''Verb form'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;'''1'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ha'''g'''o&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;'''2'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;haces&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;'''3'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;hace&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;'''4'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;hacemos&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;'''5'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;haceis&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;'''6'''&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;hacen&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
}}

Note that the verb '''hacer''' is translated as ''to do'' and ''to make'' when
referring to activities. But it can also be used to talk
about some weather conditions:

{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!El Tiempo
!The Weather
|-
|Hace buen tiempo.
|The weather is good.
|-
|Hace mal tiempo.
|The weather is bad.
|-
|Hace frío. (also: Está frío)
|It's cold.
|-
|Hace fresco.
|It's chilly.
|-
|Hace calor.
|It's hot.
|-
|Hace sol.
|It's sunny.
|-
|Hace nublado.
|It's cloudy.
|-
|Hace viento.
|It's windy.
|}

But:

{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!El Tiempo
!The Weather
|-
|Está fresco.
|It's chilly.
|-
|Está caluroso.
|It's hot.
|-
|Hay sol/está soleado.
|It's sunny.
|-
|Hay nubes/está nublado.
|It's cloudy.
|-
|Hay viento/está ventoso.
|It's windy.
|}

When speaking about the weather using '''hacer''', the Ud. form (third singular form) is always used.

== El vocabulario (Vocabulary) - Los días (Days) ==

&lt;table border=&quot;0&quot; cellpadding=&quot;2&quot;
 cellspacing=&quot;2&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td colspan=&quot;1&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot;
 align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#EEDC82&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Los dias de la semana&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;center&quot;
 bgcolor=&quot;#EEDC82&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Monday&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;center&quot;
 bgcolor=&quot;#EEDC82&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Tuesday&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;center&quot;
 bgcolor=&quot;#EEDC82&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Wednesday&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;center&quot;
 bgcolor=&quot;#EEDC82&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Thursday&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;center&quot;
 bgcolor=&quot;#EEDC82&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Friday&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;center&quot;
 bgcolor=&quot;#EEDC82&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Saturday&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;center&quot;
 bgcolor=&quot;#EEDC82&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Sunday&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;center&quot;
 bgcolor=&quot;#EEDC82&quot;&gt;el lunes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;center&quot;
 bgcolor=&quot;#EEDC82&quot;&gt;el martes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;center&quot;
 bgcolor=&quot;#EEDC82&quot;&gt;el miércoles&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;center&quot;
 bgcolor=&quot;#EEDC82&quot;&gt;el jueves&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;center&quot;
 bgcolor=&quot;#EEDC82&quot;&gt;el viernes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;center&quot;
 bgcolor=&quot;#EEDC82&quot;&gt;el sábado&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td align=&quot;center&quot;
 bgcolor=&quot;#EEDC82&quot;&gt;el domingo&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;


'''Audio''': [[media:The_days_of_the_week.ogg|OGG]] (157KB)

*The Spanish week begins on Monday (el lunes), unlike the English week (which begins on Sunday/el domingo).

----

==Una fiesta==

[[File:Una fiesta.jpg]]

Una fiesta entre amigos. Nosotros bailamos y lo pasamos bien en el jardín de esta casa.&lt;br&gt;
''A party among friends. We dance and enjoy ourselves in the patio (garden) of this house.''

----
{{Spanish}}

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>oxu9fe6d1yii5ye2ai9qmemun0310y5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:Eating for Health</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>426</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2700924</id>
      <parentid>2700909</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-09-17T12:00:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/Christine hany|Christine hany]] ([[User talk:Christine hany|talk]]) to last version by QuiteUnusual</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{diet}}

==Basics==
A healthful diet brings many benefits. It can help one avoid cancer and heart disease, control weight, and avoid diabetes. A healthful diet can also have effects on mood.

In choosing a healthful diet, you must start with two important concepts:
*Your diet choice is no good if you don't think you can follow it long-term.
*Your diet choice doesn't make up for smoking, lack of exercise, or any other bad habit; however, a healthful diet is a critical ingredient for a healthy body and you will enjoy many benefits from making good eating decisions.

==Examples and suggestions regarding diet==
Not everyone is trying to lose weight, but as an example, suppose that you are. Suppose that you eat a delicious treat. Would you consider yourself a failure? You shouldn't!  Allowing thoughts of failure may only give you an excuse to give up on healthy eating.

If you are trying to lose  weight, cutting down the treats and making sure you eat plenty of vegetables may help.  Beyond diet, losing weight depends on your activity level.  If your calorie intake (food) exceeds your calorie output (activity) your body will store the excess calories as fat.  Weight loss requires your calorie intake to be lower than your calorie output, though neither should be done in the extreme.

Choose a different attitude.  Don't think of healthy eating as a &quot;diet&quot;. Think of healthy eating as balanced eating. Healthy eating is a lifestyle and one that you should enjoy.  You will have difficulty eating well if you don't like the food.   Get yourself in the habit of making good dietary choices by trying different foods as well as different ways to prepare them to find healthy foods that appeal to you.

One last thought, eating healthily does not mean starving yourself!  If you are hungry, eat.  Just be smart about what you take in.  Reach for apples or [[Cookbook:Celery|celery]] over candy bars or chips.  You don't need to feel like you have to cut out completely the occasional treat &amp;mdash; just keep it that: occasional.

==Non-diet concerns==
Diet is hardly your main problem if you won't exercise. As with following a good diet, exercise is best if you can work it into your daily schedule. For example, you might choose to live on the top floor of an apartment building without an elevator. You might choose to walk to work instead of driving.

==Balance==
Humans function best on a diet consisting mainly of [[Cookbook:Vegetable|vegetables]], and a protein source that could be [[Cookbook:Meat|meat]], [[Cookbook:Nut|nuts]] or [[Cookbook:Legume|legumes]]. Fresh leafy green vegetables are most important, but it is also necessary to eat yellow vegetables frequently. Starches ([[Cookbook:Bread|bread]], [[Cookbook:Grits|grits]], [[Cookbook:Pasta|pasta]], [[Cookbook:Potato|potatoes]], etc.) are often both tasty and low-cost. Starches with whole grains are best, as white flours, other modified grains and potatoes have high [[w:Glycemic_index|glycemic indexes]], which can promote [[w:Diabetes|diabetes]] and cause a build up of gas in the digestive tract. You can do very well by planning meals as small servings of meat or meat alternatives with heaping piles of vegetables, and a reasonable serving of some carbohydrate. Add [[Cookbook:Fat|fat and oil]] as needed for energy, rather than using sugar for this purpose. Add [[Cookbook:Herbs and Spices|herbs and spices]] for taste; increased taste can lead to earlier feelings of satiation.

==Specific tips==

===Vegetables===
For many vegetables it is a good method to lightly [[Cookbook:Steaming|steam]] them. While cooking can destroy nutrients, it also makes nutrients more available for the body. Some people think that uncooked vegetables contain the risk to spread disease from frequently-ill farm workers, manure, and animal contamination, but thorough washing of the vegetables before their uncooked use avoids this risk. [[Cookbook:Boiling|Boiling]] will leach nutrients out of the vegetables, so you should avoid it. If you do not have a proper [[Cookbook:Steamer|steamer]], try placing a metal [[Cookbook:Colander|colander]] into a large lidded pot holding a half inch of water.

Many of the best-tasting vegetables are commonly hated because they are typically overcooked.
[[Cookbook:Broccoli|Broccoli]], [[Cookbook:Brussels Sprout|Brussels sprouts]], [[Cookbook:Asparagus|asparagus]], [[Cookbook:Cabbage|cabbage]], [[Cookbook:Spinach|spinach]], and [[Cookbook:Bean Sprouts|bean sprouts]] are all tasty when fresh and not overcooked. Broccoli is particularly versatile, tasty, nutritious, but relatively short-lived. Don't forget to try more unusual vegetables, such as [[Cookbook:Okra|okra]] (cooked with tomatoes) and [[Cookbook:Bok Choy|bok choy]]. Variety is good for you.

Try serving your green vegetables with [[Cookbook:Lemon Juice|lemon juice]] instead of creamy sauces. Lemon juice is particularly good with broccoli and spinach. You might prefer [[Cookbook:Vinegar|vinegar]] with cabbage.

[[Cookbook:Lettuce|Lettuce]] is very high in nutrients and tastes very good.. While green vegetables are most important, don't forget the yellow vegetables ([[Cookbook:Squash|squash]], [[Cookbook:Carrot|carrot]], [[Cookbook:Sweet Potato|sweet potato]]) and [[Cookbook:Tomato|tomatoes]].

===Meat, including eggs and fish===
In general, meat needs to be cooked to at least medium rare for safety. One exception is domestic poultry such as chicken and turkey. [[Cookbook:Pork|Pork]] can be cooked to 145° for medium rare, contrary to popular belief. [[Cookbook:Microwaving|Microwaving]] meat is generally bad, because dangerous bacteria can survive in any cold spots that remain.

It is particularly important to avoid browning nitrite-cured meat such as [[Cookbook:Ham|ham]] or [[Cookbook:Corned Beef|corned beef]] because the added nitrates and nitrites react during browning to make things much worse.

In place of salt on meat, try some [[Cookbook:Herbs and Spices|herbs and spices]]. For example, a [[Cookbook:Pork|pork]] roast goes well with [[Cookbook:Rosemary|rosemary]]. [[Cookbook:Chicken|Chicken]] goes well with [[Cookbook:Sage|sage]], [[Cookbook:Rosemary|rosemary]], and [[Cookbook:Thyme|thyme]]. For a more [[Cookbook:East Asian cuisines|Asian]] flavor, use [[Cookbook:Ginger|ginger]] and [[Cookbook:Soy Sauce|soy sauce]].

You might enjoy your meat with [[Cookbook:Teriyaki Sauce|teriyaki]], [[Cookbook:Barbecue Sauce|barbecue]], or [[Cookbook:Sweet and Sour|sweet and sour]] sauce. These [[Cookbook:Sauces|sauces]] are somewhat high in [[Cookbook:Sugar|sugar]], but the good taste may save you from far worse dietary choices.

A technique to remove excess fat from shredded or ground meats after frying is to remove the meat to a metal [[Cookbook:Colander|colander]], and rinse with hot water. This is especially important when cooking such meats ahead of time to prepare for freezing - otherwise the fat solidifies on the meat when it freezes, and can sometimes cause unpleasant odors and tastes. Another method is to float the fat with cold water or broth, then refrigerate to solidify the fat.

For [[Cookbook:Fish|fish]], try cooking it with some ground [[Cookbook:Spices and herbs|herbs and spices]]. Also, try serving it plain or with [[Cookbook:Lemon Juice|lemon juice]]. You won't need to cover up a &quot;fishy&quot; (bacterial) smell if you buy fresh fish and use it quickly; fresh fish does not have an odor. If the fish is whole, fresh fish will have clear eyes.

[[Cookbook:Egg|Egg]] whites are generally more healthy than egg yolks.{{citation needed}} In most recipes, you can use 2 egg whites to replace 1 whole egg.

Try flavoring your [[Cookbook:Scrambled Eggs|scrambled eggs]] with chopped [[Cookbook:Olive|black olives]] instead of [[Cookbook:Bacon|bacon]] bits.

===Oil and Fat===
For general use, [[Cookbook:Canola Oil|canola oil]] (low erucic acid rapeseed oil) is a good choice.
Fancy grades of [[Cookbook:Olive Oil|olive oil]] can be better, but they are easy to overheat because they have low [[Cookbook:Smoke Point|smoke points]]. When oil is overheated, harmful chemicals end up both in the food and in the air. (use olive oil on your salad, and canola oil for frying)

As a general rule, it is more healthful to choose liquid oils over solid fats. It is currently suspected that the ''trans-'' fats (partially hydrogenated oils) are least desirable; these are found in most [[Cookbook:Margarine|margarine]] and [[Cookbook:Shortening|shortening]]. Shortening without ''trans-'' fats is now available, made from a mixture of unhydrogenated oil and '''fully''' hydrogenated oil.

===Milk===
People with European ancestry usually handle [[Cookbook:Milk|milk]] well. Milk is a valuable nutritious food, providing vitamins and essential fats to those who can properly digest it. Fermenting milk to make products such as [[Cookbook:Cheese|cheese]], [[Cookbook:Yogurt|yoghurt]], and [[Cookbook:Kefir|kefir]], increases the digestibility and available nutrition of milk.

Some people have trouble digesting the lactose in milk, and find that many dairy products cause flatulence or loose bowels. Milk can be treated to reduce lactose by fermenting it or by adding an enzyme. Look for strong (aged) [[Cookbook:Cheese|cheeses]] and Lactaid if you have this problem. 

In addition, some people have intolerance to the proteins in milk, [[w:Casein|casein]] and [[w:Whey|whey]]. Casein intolerance is frequently seen in people with both [[w:Coeliac disease|coeliac disease]] and dairy intolerance. Whey intolerance is less common. In these instances, removing lactose will not help, and cheeses are particularly bad foods for people with casein intolerance because the casein in milk is concentrated in the cheese.

If you choose to avoid milk, you will need an alternate source of calcium. [[Cookbook:Anchovy|Anchovies]] and canned [[Cookbook:Salmon|salmon]] are good sources. You may also need an alternate source of vitamin D, which is added to milk in some countries. This is particularly important if you are a dark-skinned person who does not receive lots of exposure to bright sunlight; the human body normally relies on ultraviolet light to produce vitamin D. Several milk substitutes are available, typically based on [[Cookbook:Soy Milk|soy]], [[Cookbook:Rice|rice]], or [[Cookbook:Oats|oats]]. These can be used to some extent in cooking as well as for drinking, and variants with vitamins and calcium content equivalent to milk are available.

===Salt===
For [[Cookbook:Salt|salt]] added at the table, consider using flaked salt. It's the same stuff, but it tastes stronger (so you use less) because it dissolves faster.

When cooking, you can reduce salt by 20% to 45% without giving up taste by adding a small amount of [[Cookbook:MSG|MSG]]. Consider doing this with [[Cookbook:Meat|meat]], [[Cookbook:Soup|soups]], [[Cookbook:Egg|eggs]], [[Cookbook:Stir-fry|stir-fry]], [[Cookbook:Fried Rice|fried rice]], and anything else you might consider to be a &quot;savory&quot; dish. (MSG contains far less sodium than table salt does)

See above for specific tips for meat and vegetable salt reduction.

===Flour-based foods and fiber===
[[Cookbook:Whole Wheat|Whole wheat]] [[Cookbook:Flour|flour]] provides [[Cookbook:Fiber|dietary fiber]], which helps to clean you out. Whole wheat flour also has more protein than plain white flour. In most recipes, you can replace half of the plain white flour with whole wheat flour. The more whole wheat you use, the less the result will rise. You might add some extra leavening agent ([[Cookbook:Yeast|yeast]], [[Cookbook:Baking Powder|baking powder]], etc.) to make up for this. Many recipes are specifically designed for 100% whole wheat flour, including [[Cookbook:Pancake|pancakes]] and [[Cookbook:Raisin Oatmeal Muffins|raisin oatmeal muffins]].

When making batter for [[Cookbook:Deep Fat Frying|deep-fat frying]], try using [[Cookbook:Cornmeal|cornmeal]] in place of some of the plain white flour.

Instead of white [[Cookbook:Rice|rice]], choose brown rice. This gives you extra flavor, fiber, and nutrients.</text>
      <sha1>r2so27v12rqko7ve17jf9dt9o1kd99z</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Lojban/Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>427</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2231960</id>
      <parentid>2175933</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-12-08T09:09:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>79.40.142.158</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">The Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis (SWH) is a hypothesis in linguistics, stating that there are notable differences in thought patterns of speakers of different languages, and that the way people's brains function is strongly affected by their native languages. It's a very controversial theory, championed by linguist Edward Sapir and his student Benjamin Whorf.

First discussed by Sapir in 1929, the hypothesis became popular in the 1950s following posthumous publication of Whorf's writings on the subject. In 1955, Dr. James Cooke Brown created the Loglan language (which led to the offshoot Lojban) in order to test the hypothesis. After vigorous attack from followers of Noam Chomsky in the following decades, the hypothesis is now only believed by linguists with a grain of salt; that thought processes are somewhat affected by language, but that differences aren't that notable.

Central to the Sapir-Whorf hypothesis is the idea of linguistic relativity: distinctions of meaning between related terms in a language are often arbitrary and particular to that language. Sapir and Whorf took this one step further by arguing that a person's whole world view is determined by the vocabulary and syntax available in his or her language.

The extreme (&quot;Weltanschauung&quot;) version of this idea, that all mental function is constrained by language, can be disproved through personal experience: people in every language occasionally struggle to express their exact thoughts, feeling constrained by the language. It's common to say or write something, only to correct one's self or further clarify meaning, especially to someone being explained to. These show that ideas are not merely words, because one can imagine something without being able to express it in words.

The opposite extreme - that language does not influence thought at all - is also widely considered to be false. For example, it has been shown in studies that people's discrimination of similar colors can be influenced by their vocabulary for distinguishing said colors. Another study showed that deaf children of hearing parents are more likely to fail on some cognitive tasks unrelated to hearing, while deaf children of deaf parents succeed, due to parents being able to more extensively communicate. Computer programmers who know different programming languages often see the same problem in completely different ways.

The Neuro-Linguistic Programming (NLP) analysis of the problem is direct: most people do notable thinking by talking to themselves and by imagining images and other sensory phantasms. To the extent that people think by talking to themselves, they are limited by their vocabulary and the structure of their language and linguistic habits. (However it should also be noted that everyone have idiolects, mental language patterns individual to them.)

John Grinder, a founder of NLP, was a linguistics professor who perhaps unconsciously combined the ideas of Chomsky with the Sapir-Whorf hypothesis. A seminal NLP insight came from a challenge he gave to his students: coin a neologism to describe an idea for which you have no words. Student Robert Dilts gave an example by coining a word for the way people stare into space when they are thinking, and for the different directions they stare. These new words enabled users to describe patterns in the ways people stare into space, which led directly to NLP results — as notable a validation of the weak hypothesis as one could ask.

Lojban is thus designed to test the Sapir-Whorf hypothesis, by attempting to expand the speakers' minds and express thoughts as conveniently as possible to see if there's any notable effects in the speakers' thought patterns/worldview. The only complication with this is that the third factor - the speakers all wanting to learn Lojban, an obscure language - could skew the results somewhat, but the only way to fix that is to get more Lojban speakers.

==External links==
*[[w:Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis|Wikipedia: Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis]]

----
''This article was originally taken from [[w:Wikipedia|Wikipedia]] and is licensed under the [[w:GNU FDL|GNU FDL]]. Update as needed.''

[[Category:Lojban]]</text>
      <sha1>4xy693ni1a376yij93r9qvarl28wuhw</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Lojban/Introduction to Lojban</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>428</id>
    <revision>
      <id>933539</id>
      <parentid>927662</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-07-31T05:04:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Furrykef</username>
        <id>1003</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Lojban Grammar */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">== Loglan ==

Beginning about 1955, Dr. James Cooke Brown began work on '''Loglan''', a constructed language designed for linguistic research, particularly investigation of the [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sapir-Whorf_hypothesis Sapir-Whorf hypothesis].  The object was to make a language so powerfully expressive for logic and calculation that people learning it would become measurably smarter if the hypothesis was true.

He intended it to be as culturally neutral as possible, logically and linguistically powerful, incorporating all known expressive features of any language (e.g., compounded location tenses), metaphysically parsimonious (e.g., you are not required to express any feature of reality, as you are in English time-tenses of verbs), and totally regular and unambiguous.  He even used maximally stable phonemes.

The formal grammar was disambiguated mechanically (at first).

The language's grammar is based on predicate logic (the name Loglan is short for &quot;logical language&quot;), which also makes it particularly suitable for human-computer communication, an application that led Robert Heinlein to mention the language in his novel [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Moon_Is_a_Harsh_Mistress The Moon is a Harsh Mistress].

Dr. Brown founded The Loglan Institute to develop the language and other applications of it.  He always considered the language a research project that was never complete, so although he released many papers about its design he never &quot;released&quot; it to become a usable language.  A group of his followers later formed The Logical Language Group to create the language '''Lojban''' along the same principles, but with the intention to make it freely available and encourage its use as a real language.  This latter group has a small but active community of speakers.

Loglan allows very strange speech, because one can say things that are simply not meaningful.  For example, you can literally say that john, a person, is a short word.  Or one can directly and precisely say any of the 22 possible meanings of the English phrase &quot;a pretty little girls school.&quot;

In natural languages, the ambiguity of the grammar hides these odd meanings; but in Loglan they are all available and add expressive freedom to the language.  This feature is so pronounced that people fluent in Loglan say impossible things as a sort of joke -- a type of humour simply not supported by the linguistic machinery of natural languages.

The oddest, most difficult thing for a speaker of an Indo-european language like English is that Loglan has no distinction between nouns or verbs, objects, direct objects, indirect objects, possessive forms or tenses.  There are only predicates, with places for variables: for example, ''botso'': X buys item Y from seller P for price Q.  There are prefixes to reorder predicates; for example, price would be ''botso'' with a little word to make price the first variable.  With different reorderings, one speaks of buyer, bought-thing, or seller.

Tenses for time, location, actor, type of action, etc. are provided by &quot;little words&quot; which are optional.  Predicates compound, so a predicate can fit in the variable of another predicate.  Every feature of the language has standard, regular forms for acting in compounds.  For example, time-travel tenses are available trivially in Loglan (I did X from time Y to P in time Q.) using compounding forms normally used for location tenses.

After long use of Loglan, the world gains a sort of timeless, objectless, actorless flavor.  Time words and location words fall away except when needed to make a point, usually with emotional emphasis.  It is rather easy to avoid blame for responsibilities in Loglan, and scheduling may be creatively ambiguous because the tenses are optional.

The language is designed so that the patterns of phonemes always parse into words.  Thus, one cannot babble Loglan, because even when run together, the language is still parsable.

== Lojban ==

The constructed language '''Lojban''' (SAMPA &amp;#0091;'loZban]) was created by the Logical Language Group in 1987 based on the earlier Loglan, with the intent to make the language more complete, usable, and freely available.  The language itself shares many of the features and goals of Loglan; in particular:

* The grammar is based on predicate logic, and is capable of expressing complex logical constructs precisely.
* It has no irregularities or ambiguities in spelling or grammar, so it can be easily parsed by computer.
* Lojban is designed to be as culturally neutral as possible.
* It is, nonetheless, simple to learn and use compared to many natural languages.

While the initial goal of the Loglan project was to investigate the Sapir-Whorf hypothesis, the active Lojban community has additional goals for the language, including:

* General research into linguistics.
* Research in artificial intelligence and machine understanding.
* Improved human-computer communication, storage ontologies, and computer translation of natural language text.
* Use of language as an educational tool.
* Personal creativity.

=== Lojban Grammar ===

Lojban has three parts of speech: one, called ''brivla'', for both common noun(s) and verb(s); one, called ''cmene'', for proper nouns; and another, called ''cmavo'', for structural particles: articles, numerals, tense indicators and other such modifiers. The ''cmavo'' are further subdivided into ''selma'o'', which are closer to the notion of parts of speech (e.g., UI includes interjections and discursives). There are no adjectives or adverbs in the sense that Indo-European languages have them. The articles inflect to indicate individual, mass, set, or typical element. ''Brivla'' do not inflect for tense, person, or number; tense is indicated by separate ''cmavo'', but grammatical number is absent.

As befits a logical language, there is a large assortment of conjunctions. Logical conjunctions take different forms depending on whether they connect ''sumti'' (the equivalent of noun phrases), ''selbri'' (phrases that can serve as verbs; all ''brivla'' are ''selbri''), parts of a ''tanru'' (a construct whose closest English equivalent is a string of nouns), or clauses in a sentence.

The typology is Subject Verb Object, with Subject Object Verb also common. Word formation is polysynthetic; many ''brivla'' (all of which, except for a handful of borrowings such as ''alga'', have at least five letters) have one to three three-letter forms called ''rafsi'' which are used in making longer words.  For example, ''gasnu'' means &quot;to make something happen&quot;; its ''rafsi'' form of ''-gau'' regularly forms compounds meaning &quot;to cause...x&quot;, in which the agent is in the subject place of the new predicate.

Lojban has a positional case system, though this can be overridden by marking predicate arguments with explicit modal particles. For instance, ''bramau'' means &quot;is bigger than&quot;; the bigger thing is in first position, and the smaller is second, and the measured property in the third.  So ''mi bramau do le ka clani'' means &quot;I am bigger than you in the property of height&quot; or &quot;I am taller than you&quot;; but this could also be expressed as something like ''fi le ka clani fe do fa mi bramau'', &quot;In height, you are exceeded by me&quot;.

* ''le cinfo cu bramau le mlatu'' -- &quot;The lion is bigger than the cat&quot;
* ''mi bramaugau le cinfo le mlatu'' -- &quot;I make the lion bigger than the cat&quot;

What a particular place means depends entirely on the ''brivla''. For animals and plants the second place is the species, variety, breed, or other taxon; for verbs of measurement it is the numerical measurement, and a further place is the standard; for ''klama'' (&quot;go&quot; / &quot;come&quot;) it is the destination.

Something of the flavor of Lojban (and Loglan) can be imparted by this lightbulb joke:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Q: How many Lojbanists does it take to change a broken light bulb?&lt;br&gt;
A: Two: one to decide what to change it into, and one to figure out what kind of bulb emits broken light.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
This makes use of two features of the language; first, the language attempts to eliminate polysemy, that is, having a word with more than one meaning.  So while the English word &quot;change&quot; can mean &quot;to transform into a different state&quot;, or &quot;to replace&quot;, or even &quot;small-denomination currency&quot;, Lojban has different words for each.  In particular, the use of a ''brivla'' such as the word for &quot;change&quot; (&quot;binxo&quot;) implies that all of its predicate places exist, so there must
be something for it to change into.  Another feature of the language is that it has no grammatical ambiguities such as appear in English phrases like &quot;big dog catcher&quot;, which can mean either a big person who catches dogs or a person who catches big dogs.  In Lojban, unless you clearly specify otherwise with ''cmavo'', such modifiers always group left-to-right, so &quot;big dog catcher&quot; is a catcher of big dogs, and a &quot;broken light bulb&quot; is a bulb that emits broken light (you can also avoid the ambiguity by creating a new word, so &quot;broken lightbulb&quot; has the intended meaning).

==External links==
*[[w:Loglan|Wikipedia: Loglan]]
*[[w:Lojban|Wikipedia: Lojban]]

[[Category:Lojban]]</text>
      <sha1>roqtt89ko6ei3jcwcxpjvn3poz37wk0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Lojban/Other resources</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>429</id>
    <revision>
      <id>733416</id>
      <parentid>518443</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-01-27T07:56:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Az1568</username>
        <id>37227</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Cleaning el links</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">*[[w:Lojban|Wikipedia: Lojban]]
*[http://www.loglan.org/ Official Loglan Homepage]
*[http://www.lojban.org/jbovlaste/ Online Lojban Dictionary]
*[http://lojban.org/publications/cll.html Printed copy of &lt;u&gt;The Complete Lojban Language&lt;/u&gt;] by John Woldemar Cowan ISBN 0-9660283-0-9
*[http://www.lojban.org/tiki/ Lojban Wiki]
*[http://ptolemy.tlg.uci.edu/~opoudjis/lojbanbrochure/lessons/book1.html Lojban for Beginners Lessons]
*[http://www.lojban.org/jboski/index.php lojbo skicu] (jbofi'e) - Automatic Lojban parser and glosser
*[http://www.thestonecutters.net/xod/lojban/gismu-thesaurus.html Gismu Thesaurus]

[[Category:Lojban]]</text>
      <sha1>ed1p8dttagqq9z1nt9f64a7cghdn4dc</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Lojban/Attitudinals</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>430</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2389138</id>
      <parentid>2359546</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-08-10T03:38:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Acdibble</username>
        <id>654676</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Complex propositional emotions: */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Attitudinals are markers of attitude or [[Lojban/Emotions|emotion]], modifying the word (brivla, cmavo, cmene, sumti, or tanru) directly before it. For example, the simple &lt;&lt; ''mlatu'' &gt;&gt; for &quot;cat&quot; can become &lt;&lt; ''mlatu .ui'' &gt;&gt; for &quot;cat (happiness!/:D)&quot;. At the beginning of a sentence (after the place of .i) they modify the entire sentence (bridi), and after the attitudinal beginning bracket &lt;&lt; ''fu'e'' &gt;&gt; continues the emotion for all the statement until the closing bracket &lt;&lt; ''fu'o'' &gt;&gt;.

Attitudinals can also effect [[Lojban/Vocatives|vocatives]] the same way a change in vocal tone can greatly effect a simple &quot;hello&quot; - for example, &lt;&lt; ''coi .ui'' &gt;&gt; means not a simple &quot;Hello.&quot;, but a &quot;Hello! :D&quot;. Combined with the attitudinal question-maker ''pei'', you can easily create more complex &lt;&lt; ''coi .uipei'' &gt;&gt; may be thought of as &quot;Hello - are you glad to see me?&quot;, while &lt;&lt; ''co'o .uipei'' &gt;&gt; may be viewed as &quot;Good-bye - are you happy that we part?&quot;.

Beyond mere emotion, they can mark prepositional ideas such as desire (&quot;I want this to happen&quot;), obligation (&quot;This needs to happen&quot;), and many other complex functions we take for granted - for example, &lt;&lt; ''mi citka'' &gt;&gt; means &quot;I eat&quot;, while &lt;&lt; ''.au mi citka'' &gt;&gt; means &quot;I want to eat&quot;, and &lt;&lt; ''.e'e mi citka'' &gt;&gt; means &quot;I am able to eat&quot;.

==Emotional modifiers:== 
{|class=wikitable
!Modifier
!Modification
|-
|cai
|very strong
|-
|sai
|strong
|-
|(nothing)
|felt
|-
|ru'e
|weak
|-
|cu'i
|not felt
|-
|nairu'e
|weak negative
|-
|nai
|negative felt
|-
|naisai
|strong negative
|-
|naicai
|very strong negative
|}

==Attitudinal indicators and suffixes with examples of modifier use:==
===Attitudinals===
====Simple propositional emotions:====
{|class=wikitable
!Attitudinal !! attitude !! -cu'i !! -nai
|-
|.a'a || attentive || inattentive || avoiding
|-
|.a'e || alertness ||  || exhaustion
|-
|.ai || intent || indecision || refusal
|-
|.a'i || effort || lack of effort || repose
|-
|.a'o || hope ||  || despair
|-
|.au || desire || indifference || reluctance
|-
|.a'u || interest || no interest || repulsion
|}

====Complex propositional emotions:====
{|class=wikitable
!Attitudinal !! attitude !! -cu'i !! -nai
|-
|.e'a || permission ||  || prohibition
|-
|.e'e || competence ||  || incompetence
|-
|.ei || obligation ||  || freedom
|-
|.e'i || constraint || independence || resistance to constraint
|-
|.e'o || request ||  || negative request
|-
|.e'u || suggestion || no suggestion || warning
|-
|.ia || belief || skepticism || disbelief
|-
|.i'a || acceptance ||  || blame
|-
|.ie || agreement || neutrality || disagreement
|-
|.i'e || approval || non-approval || disapproval
|}

====Miscellaneous pure emotions:====
{|class=wikitable
!Attitudinal
!(nothing)
!-cu'i
!-nai
|-
|.ii
|fear
|nervousness
|security
|-
|.i'i
|togetherness
|
|privacy
|-
|.io
|respect
|lack of respect
|disrespect
|-
|.i'o
|appreciation
|lack of appreciation
|envy
|-
|.iu
|love
|lack of love
|hatred/fear
|-
|.i'u
|familiarity
|
|mystery
|}

====Complex pure emotions:====
{|class=wikitable
!Attitudinal
!(nothing)
!-cu'i
!-nai
|-
|.o'a
|pride
|modesty
|shame
|-
|.o'e
|closeness
|detachment
|distance
|-
|.oi
|complaint/pain
|no complaints
|pleasure
|-
|.o'i
|caution
|boldness
|rashness
|-
|.o'o
|patience
|mere tolerance
|anger
|-
|.o'u
|relaxation
|composure
|stress
|}

====Simple pure emotions:====
{|class=wikitable
!Attitudinal
!(nothing)
!-cu'i
!-nai
|-
|.ua
|discovery
|
|confusion
|-
|.u'a
|gain
|
|loss
|-
|.ue
|surprise
|no surprise
|expectation
|-
|.u'e
|wonder
|
|commonplace
|-
|.ui
|happiness
|
|unhappiness
|-
|.u'i
|amusement
|
|weariness
|-
|.uo
|completion
|
|incompleteness
|-
|.u'o
|courage
|timidity
|cowardice
|-
|.uu
|pity
|
|cruelty
|-
|.u'u
|repentance
|lack of regret
|innocence
|}

===Emotional categories:===
{|class=wikitable
!Category
!(nothing)
!-cu'i
!-nai
|-
|ro'a
|social
|asocial
|antisocial
|-
|ro'e
|mental
|absentminded
|mindless
|-
|ro'i
|emotional
|emotionless
|denying emotion
|-
|ro'o
|physical
|intangible
|denying physical
|-
|ro'u
|sexual
|asexual
|sexual abstinence
|-
|re'e
|spiritual
|secular
|sacrilegious
|}

===Attitudinal modifiers:===
{|class=wikitable
!Modifier
!(nothing)
!-cu'i
!-nai
![gismu]
|-
|ga'i
|hauteur/rank
|equal rank
|meekness/lack of rank
|[galtu]
|-
|le'o
|aggressive
|passive
|defensive
|
|-
|vu'e
|virtue [zabna]
|
|sin [mabla]
|[vrude]
|-
|se'i
|self-orientation
|
|other-orientation
|[sevzi]
|-
|ri'e
|release
|restraint
|control
|[zifre]
|-
|fu'i
|easily/with help
|without help
|with difficulty/opposition
|[frili]
|-
|be'u
|lack/need
|presence/satisfaction
|satiation
|
|-
|se'a
|self-sufficiency
|
|dependency
|[sevzi]
|}

===Special:===
{|class=wikitable
!cmavo
!(nothing)
!-cu'i
!-nai
|-
|pei
|attitude question
|
|
|-
|dai
|empathy
|
|
|-
|bu'o
|start emotion
|continue emotion
|end emotion
|}

===Evidentials:===
{|class=wikitable
!Evidential
!(nothing)
!-cu'i
!-nai
![gismu]
|-
|ja'o
|I conclude
|
|
|[jalge]
|-
|ca'e
|I define
|
|
|
|-
|ba'a
|I expect / I anticipate
|I experience
|I remember
|[balvi]
|-
|su'a
|I generalize
|
|I particularize
|[sucta]
|-
|ti'e
|I hear (hearsay) - not necessarily literally &quot;hear&quot;
|
|
|[tirna]
|-
|ka'u
|I know by cultural means
|
|
|[kulnu]
|-
|se'o
|I know by internal experience
|
|
|[senva]
|-
|za'a
|I observe
|
|
|[zgana]
|-
|pe'i
|I opine / It is my opinion that...
|
|
|[pensi]
|-
|ru'a
|I postulate / I presume
|
|
|[sruma]
|-
|ju'a
|I state (elliptical discursive)
|
|
|[jufra]
|}

===Consecutive discourse:===
{|class=wikitable
!cmavo
!(nothing)
![gismu]
|-
|ku'i
|however/but/in contrast
|[karbi]
|-
|ji'a
|additionally
|[jmina]
|-
|si'a
|similarly
|[simsa]
|-
|mi'u
|ditto
|[mintu]
|-
|po'o
|the only relevant case
|
|}

===Commentary on words:===
{|class=wikitable
!cmavo
!(nothing)
!-nai
![gismu]
|-
|va'i
|in other words
|in the same words
|[valsi]
|-
|ta'u
|expanding a tanru
|making a tanru
|[tanru]
|}

===Commentary on discourse:===
{|class=wikitable
!cmavo
!(nothing)
!-cu'i
!-nai
![gismu]
|-
|li'a
|clearly/obviously
|
|obscurely
|[klina]
|-
|ba'u
|exaggeration
|accuracy
|understatement
|[banli]
|-
|zo'o
|humorously
|dully
|seriously
|
|-
|sa'e
|precisely speaking
|
|loosely speaking
|[satci]
|-
|to'u
|in brief
|
|in detail
|[tordu]
|-
|do'a
|generously
|
|parsimoniously
|[dunda]
|-
|sa'u
|simply
|
|elaborating
|[sampu]
|-
|pa'e
|justice
|
|prejudice
|[pajni]
|-
|je'u
|truly/It is true that,...
|
|falsely
|[jetnu]
|}

===Knowledge:===
{|class=wikitable
!cmavo
!(nothing)
!-cu'i
!-nai
![gismu]
|-
|ju'o
|certainly
|uncertain
|certainly not
|[djuno]
|-
|la'a
|probably
|
|improbably
|[lakne]
|}

===Discourse management:===
{|class=wikitable
!cmavo
!(nothing)
!-cu'i
!-nai
![gismu]
|-
|ta'o
|by the way
|(sometimes: speaking of which,...)
|returning to point
|[tanjo]
|-
|ra'u
|chiefly
|equally
|incidentally
|[ralju]
|-
|mu'a
|for example
|omitting ex.
|end examples
|[mupli]
|-
|zu'u
|on the one hand
|
|on the other hand
|
|-
|ke'u
|repeating
|
|continuing
|[krefu]
|-
|da'i
|supposing
|
|in fact
|
|}

===Miscellaneous indicators:===
{|class=wikitable
!Attitudinal
!(nothing)
!-nai
|-
|ki'a
|metalinguistic confusion
|
|-
|na'i
|metalinguistic negator
|
|-
|jo'a
|metalinguistic affirmer
|
|-
|li'o
|omitted text (quoted material)
|
|-
|sa'a
|material inserted by editor/narrator
|
|-
|xu
|true-false question
|
|-
|pau
|question premarker
|rhetorical question
|-
|pe'a
|figurative language
|literal language
|-
|bi'u
|new information
|old information
|-
|ge'e
|non-specific indicator
|}

See also: [[Emotions (Lojban)|Emotions]]

==External links==
*[http://ptolemy.tlg.uci.edu/~opoudjis/lojbanbrochure/lessons/less1attitude.html Lojban for Beginners Chapter 1 Section 6: Lojban with attitude!]
*[http://ptolemy.tlg.uci.edu/~opoudjis/lojbanbrochure/lessons/less13.html#less13attit Lojban for Beginners Chapter 13 Section 1: Lojban with lots more attitude]
*[http://ptolemy.tlg.uci.edu/~opoudjis/lojbanbrochure/lessons/less13attmine.html Lojban for Beginners Chapter 13 Section 2: My attitudinals! All mine! (And you?)]
*[http://lojban.org/publications/reference_grammar/chapter13.html Lojban Reference Grammar Chapter 13: Oooh! Arrgh! Ugh! Yecch! Attitudinal and Emotional Indicators]
*[http://community.livejournal.com/cniglic the Cniglic Livejournal page]

[[Category:Lojban]]</text>
      <sha1>fgq30fm1f8dntdiygljx34ku0sxo1xa</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Lojban/Vocatives</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>431</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2515261</id>
      <parentid>2408766</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-04-22T15:55:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2.97.39.143</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve"> {| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! jbovla !! English !! -cu'i !! -nai !! brivla
|-
| coi || greeting ||  ||  || 
|-
| do'u || (terminates vocative) ||  ||  || 
|-
| doi || (vocative director) ||  ||  || 
|-
| co'o || parting ||  ||  || 
|-
| ju'i || attention ||  ||  || jundi 
|-
| nu'e || promise ||  ||  || nupre
|-
| ta'a || interruption ||  ||  || tavla
|-
| pe'u || request ||  ||  || cpedu
|-
| ki'e || appreciation/gratitude ||  ||  || ckire
|-
| fi'i || welcome ||  ||  ||  friti
|-
| be'e || request to send ||  ||  || benji 
|-
| re'i || ready to recieve ||  ||  || bredi
|-
| mu'o || completed message ||  ||  || mulno
|-
| je'e || confirm success ||  ||  || jimpe
|-
| vi'o || will comply ||  ||  || 
|-
| ke'o || please repeat ||  ||  || krefu
|-
| fe'o || end communication ||  ||  || fanmo 
|-
| mi'e || self-identification ||  ||  || mi 
|-
| y || pause ||  ||  || 
|}


Since {ki'e} means approximately &quot;Thank you,&quot; it might seem appropriate to respond by saying {fi'i}, seemingly corresponding to the English &quot;You're welcome.&quot;  However, {fi'i} means &quot;welcome&quot; in the sense of an invitation/acceptance only. In order to respond, {je'e} should be used.

{coi co'o} means &quot;Greetings in passing.&quot; English speakers generally just say &quot;Hi.&quot;

==Exercises==
In Exercises 1-7, give the most suitable Lojban word(s) to say in each situation.

01. The beginning of a conversation.&lt;br&gt;
02. Begging.&lt;br&gt;
03. During an oath.&lt;br&gt;
04. Inviting a guest into your house.&lt;br&gt;
05. Getting a group of people to listen to your announcement.&lt;br&gt;
06. You desire the floor while someone else has it.&lt;br&gt;
07. Leaving a party.

In Exercises  8-43, give the closest Lojban translation of the English sentences.

08. Attention!&lt;br&gt;
09. Listen to me, Victoria.&lt;br&gt;
10. I swear, Benjamin.&lt;br&gt;
11. I don't understand, Christian.&lt;br&gt;
12. I am Pete.&lt;br&gt;
13. Goodbye, Jonathan.&lt;br&gt;
14. Roger, Logan.&lt;br&gt;
15. Wilco.&lt;br&gt;
16. Hello, Rodrigo.&lt;br&gt;
17. Hi, Bertand.&lt;br&gt;
18. Wait! We're not done discussing this!&lt;br&gt;
19. Hark!&lt;br&gt;
20. Agreed.&lt;br&gt;
21. Can I say something, Jose?&lt;br&gt;
22. Just a minute, Jennifer.&lt;br&gt;
23. I'm not done talking, Morgan.&lt;br&gt;
24. Please, Sydney.&lt;br&gt;
25. Over and out.&lt;br&gt;
26. I appreciate that, Chloe.&lt;br&gt;
27. Make yourself at home, Rachel.&lt;br&gt;
28. May I speak, Jasmine?&lt;br&gt;
29. Sorry for interrupting, Sophia, but...&lt;br&gt;
30. I promise, Megan.&lt;br&gt;
31. Thanks, Samuel.&lt;br&gt;
32. Hold on, Nathan.&lt;br&gt;
33. What did you say, Natalie?&lt;br&gt;
34. I interrupt.&lt;br&gt;
35. Greetings, Justin.&lt;br&gt;
36. Uh-huh.&lt;br&gt;
37. Thank you, Dylan.&lt;br&gt;
38. At your service, Austin.&lt;br&gt;
39. I'm listening, Kevin.&lt;br&gt;
40. I understand, Julia.&lt;br&gt;
41. &quot;Houston, we have a problem.&quot;&lt;br&gt;
42. Hello! Susan has just left Harold.&lt;br&gt;
43. Hello, Susan! Harold has just left.

==Answers to exercises==
01. coi&lt;br&gt;
02. pe'u&lt;br&gt;
03. nu'e&lt;br&gt;
04. fi'i&lt;br&gt;
05. ju'i&lt;br&gt;
06. ta'a&lt;br&gt;
07. co'o

----

08. ju'i&lt;br&gt;
09. ju'i. vektarias.&lt;br&gt;
10. nu'e. bendjamen.&lt;br&gt;
11. je'enai. krestien.&lt;br&gt;
12. mi'e. pit.&lt;br&gt;
13. co'o. janaten.&lt;br&gt;
14. je'e. logen.&lt;br&gt;
15. vi'o&lt;br&gt;
16. coi. radrigos.&lt;br&gt;
17. coi. bertrend.&lt;br&gt;
18. fe'onai&lt;br&gt;
19. ju'i&lt;br&gt;
20. vi'o&lt;br&gt;
21. be'e. xozeis.&lt;br&gt;
22. re'inai. djenefer.&lt;br&gt;
23. mu'onai. morgen.&lt;br&gt;
24. pe'u. sednis.&lt;br&gt;
25. fe'o&lt;br&gt;
26. ki'e. clos.&lt;br&gt;
27. fi'i. reitcel.&lt;br&gt;
28. be'e. djezmen.&lt;br&gt;
29. ta'a. sofias.&lt;br&gt;
30. nu'e. meigen.&lt;br&gt;
31. ki'e. semiul.&lt;br&gt;
32. re'inai. neitan.&lt;br&gt;
33. ke'o. netalis.&lt;br&gt;
34. ta'a&lt;br&gt;
35. coi. jesten.&lt;br&gt;
36. je'e&lt;br&gt;
37. ki'e. delen.&lt;br&gt;
38. fi'i. .asten.&lt;br&gt;
39. re'i. keven.&lt;br&gt;
40. je'e. djulias.&lt;br&gt;
41. doi xustyn. mi'a se nabmi&lt;br&gt;
42. coi do'u la suzyn. la xeirold. puzi cliva&lt;br&gt;
43. coi la suzyn. la xeirold. puzi cliva

==External links==
* [http://lojban.org/publications/reference_grammar/chapter13.html Lojban reference Grammar Chapter 13: Oooh! Arrgh! Ugh! Yecch! Attitudinal and Emotional Indicators] - Despite the title, also discusses vocatives.
* [http://ptolemy.tlg.uci.edu/~opoudjis/lojbanbrochure/lessons/less12voc.html Lojban for Beginners Chapter 12 Lesson 3: Vocatives]

[[Category:Lojban]]</text>
      <sha1>m2w4yxct339oxi3yjdt9a2s4h77ym3e</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Wintermute</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>436</id>
    <revision>
      <id>482822</id>
      <parentid>457581</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-06-10T17:44:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Think Fast</username>
        <id>10874</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>change ser and estar solutions link</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">My log:
--------
[[User:Wintermute|Wintermute]] 22:14 4 Aug 2003 (UTC)

I have created this user.
-------
[[User:Wintermute|Wintermute]] 22:14 4 Aug 2003 (UTC)

Examples and little corrections in [[Spanish]].
-------
[[User:Wintermute|Wintermute]] 18:23 6 Aug 2003 (UTC)

Vocabulary and navigation bartools in [[Spanish]].

-----
[[User:Wintermute|Wintermute]] 13:04, 11 Aug 2003 (UTC)

Vocabulary in [[Spanish]].


-----
[[User:Wintermute|Wintermute]] 13:03, 12 Aug 2003 (UTC)


Vocabulary and little corrections in [[Spanish]].
----
[[User:Wintermute|Wintermute]] 19:09, 12 Aug 2003 (UTC)

A page for my drafts.
A few of grammar drafts for [[Spanish]].
------------------

A few execises for the [[Spanish]] lesson 1.

[[User:Wintermute|Wintermute]] 17:56, 27 Aug 2003 (UTC)
--------

I have created:
[[Spanish/Exercises/Verbs_ser_And_estar_-_Solutions]]

[[User:Wintermute|Wintermute]] 21:00, 11 Sep 2003 (UTC)


-----------------
------------------------------------------------------------------------

-----

[[User:Wintermute/drafts|Wintermute_drafts]]</text>
      <sha1>pycs5bo28bnc5gayxrbv330b5e1yhg3</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Discrete Mathematics/Set theory</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>438</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2713566</id>
      <parentid>2691335</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-14T14:59:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>39.58.78.206</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Real numbers */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{wikipedia|set theory}}

Set Theory starts very simply: it examines whether an object ''belongs'', or does ''not belong'', to a ''set'' of objects which has been described in some non-ambiguous way.  From this simple beginning, an increasingly complex (and useful!) series of ideas can be developed, which lead to notations and techniques with many varied applications.

==Definition of a Set==
The definition of a set sounds very vague at first.  A '''''set''''' can be defined as a collection of '''''things''''' that are brought together because they obey a certain '''''rule'''''.

These 'things' may be anything you like: numbers, people, shapes, cities, bits of text ..., literally anything.

The key fact about the 'rule' they all obey is that it must be ''well-defined''.  In other words, it enables us to say for sure whether or not a given 'thing' belongs to the collection.  If the 'things' we're talking about are English words, for example, a well-defined rule might be:

::'... has 5 or more letters'

A rule which is not well-defined (and therefore couldn't be used to define a set) might be:

::'... is hard to spell'

===Elements===
A 'thing' that belongs to a given set is called an '''''element''''' of that set.  For example:
::Henry VIII is an element of the set of Kings of England.

== Notation ==
'''Curly brackets''' &lt;math&gt;\{ \dots \}&lt;/math&gt; are used to stand for the phrase 'the set of ...'.  These braces can be used in various ways. For example:
*: We may ''list'' the elements of a set:
*:: &lt;math&gt;\{ -3, -2, -1, 0, 1, 2, 3 \}&lt;/math&gt;

*: We may ''describe'' the elements of a set:
*:: &lt;math&gt;\{ \text{ integers between } -3 \text{ and  } 3 \text{ inclusive} \}&lt;/math&gt;

*: We may use an ''identifier'' (the letter &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt; for example) to represent a ''typical element'', a &lt;math&gt;|&lt;/math&gt; symbol to stand for the phrase 'such that', and then the rule or rules that the identifier must obey:
*:: &lt;math&gt;\{x | x \text{ is an integer and } |x| &lt; 4 \}&lt;/math&gt;
*: or
*:: &lt;math&gt;\{x | x \in \mathbb{Z}, |x| &lt; 4 \}&lt;/math&gt;

The last way of writing a set - called ''set comprehension'' notation - can be generalized as:
: &lt;math&gt;{x | P(x)}&lt;/math&gt;, where &lt;math&gt;P(x)&lt;/math&gt; is a statement (technically a ''propositional function'') about &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt; and the set is the collection of all elements &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt; for which &lt;math&gt;P&lt;/math&gt; is true.


The symbol &lt;math&gt;\in&lt;/math&gt; is used as follows:
*: &lt;math&gt;\in&lt;/math&gt; means 'is an element of ...'.  For example: &lt;math&gt;\text{dog } \in \{ \text{quadrupeds}\}&lt;/math&gt;
*: &lt;math&gt;\notin&lt;/math&gt; means 'is not an element of ...'. For example: &lt;math&gt;\text{Washington DC} \notin \{\text{European capital cities}\}&lt;/math&gt;

A set can be ''finite'': &lt;math&gt;\{\text{British citizens}\}&lt;/math&gt;

... or ''infinite'': &lt;math&gt;\{7, 14, 21, 28, 35, \dots \}&lt;/math&gt;

(Note the use of the ''ellipsis'' &lt;math&gt;\dots&lt;/math&gt; to indicate that the sequence of numbers continues indefinitely.)


Sets will usually be denoted using ''upper case'' letters: &lt;math&gt;A&lt;/math&gt;, &lt;math&gt;B&lt;/math&gt;, ...

Elements will usually be denoted using ''lower case'' letters: &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt;, &lt;math&gt;y&lt;/math&gt;, ...

== Set Operations ==

===Universal Set===
The set of all the 'things' currently under discussion is called the '''''universal set''''' (or sometimes, simply the '''''universe''''').  It is denoted by '''U'''.

The universal set doesn’t contain everything in the whole universe.  On the contrary, it restricts us to just those things that are relevant at a particular time.  For example, if in a given situation we’re talking about numeric values – quantities, sizes, times, weights, or whatever – the universal set will be a suitable set of numbers (see below).  In another context, the universal set may be {alphabetic characters} or {all living people}, etc.

===Empty set===
The set containing no elements at all is called the '''''null set''''', or '''''empty set'''''.  It is denoted by a pair of empty braces: &lt;math&gt;\{ \}&lt;/math&gt; or by the symbol &lt;math&gt;\varnothing&lt;/math&gt;.

It may seem odd to define a set that contains no elements.  Bear in mind, however, that one may be looking for solutions to a problem where it isn't clear at the outset whether or not such solutions even exist.  If it turns out that there isn't a solution, then the set of solutions is empty.

For example:

*: If &lt;math&gt;U = \{\text{words in the English language}\}&lt;/math&gt; then &lt;math&gt;\{\text{words with more than 50 letters}\} = \varnothing&lt;/math&gt;.
*: If &lt;math&gt;U = \{\text{whole numbers}\}&lt;/math&gt; then &lt;math&gt;\{x | x^2 = 10\} = \varnothing&lt;/math&gt;.

====Operations on the empty set====
Operations performed on the empty set (as a set of things to be operated upon) can also be confusing. (Such operations are nullary operations.) For example, the sum of the elements of the empty set is zero, but the product of the elements of the empty set is one (see empty product). This may seem odd, since there are no elements of the empty set, so how could it matter whether they are added or multiplied (since “they” do not exist)? Ultimately, the results of these operations say more about the operation in question than about the empty set. For instance, notice that zero is the identity element for addition, and one is the identity element for multiplication.

===Some special sets of numbers===
Several sets are used so often, they are given special symbols.

====The natural numbers====
The 'counting' numbers (or whole numbers) starting at 1, are called the '''''natural numbers'''''.  This set is sometimes denoted by '''N'''.  So '''N''' = {1, 2, 3, ...}

Note that, when we write this set by hand, we can't write in '''bold''' type so we write an N in blackboard bold font: &lt;math&gt;\mathbb{N}&lt;/math&gt;

====Integers====
''All'' whole numbers, positive, negative and zero form the set of '''''integers'''''.  It is sometimes denoted by '''Z'''.  So '''Z''' = {..., -3, -2, -1, 0, 1, 2, 3, ...}

In blackboard bold, it looks like this: &lt;math&gt;\mathbb{Z}&lt;/math&gt;

====Real numbers====
If we expand the set of integers to include all decimal numbers, we form the set of '''''real numbers'''''.  The set of reals is sometimes denoted by '''R'''.

A real number may have a ''finite'' number of digits after the decimal point (e.g. 3.625), or an ''infinite'' number of decimal digits.  In the case of an infinite number of digits, these digits may:

*: recur; e.g. 8.127127127

*: ... or they may not recur; e.g. 3.141592653...

In blackboard bold: &lt;math&gt;\mathbb{R}&lt;/math&gt;

====Rational numbers====
Those real numbers whose decimal digits are finite in number, or which recur, are called '''''rational numbers'''''.  The set of rationals is sometimes denoted by the letter '''Q'''.

A rational number can always be written as exact fraction ''p''/''q''; where ''p'' and ''q'' are integers.  If ''q'' equals 1, the fraction is just the integer ''p''.  Note that ''q'' may NOT equal zero as the value is then undefined.
*: For example: 0.5, -17, 2/17, 82.01, 3.282828... are all rational numbers.

In blackboard bold: &lt;math&gt;\mathbb{Q}&lt;/math&gt;
 set theory
union-
{a,b,c}^{a,f,g,}
={a,b,c,f,g,}

====Irrational numbers====
If a number ''can't'' be represented exactly by a fraction ''p''/''q'', it is said to be '''''irrational'''''.
*: Examples include: &amp;radic;2, &amp;radic;3, &amp;pi;.

== Set Theory Exercise 1 ==
Click the link for [[Discrete_Mathematics/Set_theory/Exercises#Set_Theory_Exercise_1|Set Theory Excercise 1]]

== Relationships between Sets ==
We’ll now look at various ways in which sets may be related to one another.

=== Equality ===
Two sets ''A'' and ''B'' are said to be '''''equal''''' if and only if they have exactly the same elements.  In this case, we simply write:

: ''A'' = ''B''


Note two further facts about equal sets:

*: The ''order'' in which elements are listed does not matter.

*: If an element is listed ''more than once'', any repeat occurrences are ignored.


So, for example, the following sets are all equal:
: {1, 2, 3} = {3, 2, 1} = {1, 1, 2, 3, 2, 2}

(You may wonder why one would ever come to write a set like {1, 1, 2, 3, 2, 2}.  You may recall that when we defined the ''[[#Null set (empty set)|empty set]]'' we noted that there may be no solutions to a particular problem - hence the need for an empty set.  Well, here we may be trying several different approaches to solving a problem, some of which in fact lead us to the same solution.  When we come to consider the ''distinct'' solutions, however, any such repetitions would be ignored.)

=== Subsets ===
If all the elements of a set ''A'' are also elements of a set ''B'', then we say that ''A'' is a '''''subset''''' of ''B'', and we write:

: ''A'' &amp;sube; ''B''

For example:

In the examples below:

*: If ''T'' = {2, 4, 6, 8, 10} and ''E'' = {even integers}, then ''T'' &amp;sube; ''E''

*: If ''A'' = {alphanumeric characters} and ''P'' = {printable characters}, then ''A'' &amp;sube; ''P''

*: If ''Q'' = {quadrilaterals} and ''F'' = {plane figures bounded by four straight lines}, then ''Q'' &amp;sube; ''F''


Notice that ''A'' &amp;sube; ''B'' does not imply that ''B'' must necessarily contain extra elements that are not in ''A''; the two sets could be equal – as indeed ''Q'' and ''F'' are above.  However, if, in addition, ''B'' does contain at least one element that isn’t in ''A'', then we say that ''A'' is a '''''proper subset''''' of ''B''.  In such a case we would write:

: ''A'' &amp;sub; ''B''

In the examples above:

: ''E'' contains ... -4, -2, 0, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 14, ... , so ''T'' &amp;sub; ''E''

: ''P'' contains $, ;, &amp;, ..., so ''A'' &amp;sub; ''P''

But ''Q'' and ''F'' are just different ways of saying the same thing, so ''Q'' = ''F''

The use of &amp;sub; and &amp;sube; is clearly analogous to the use of &lt; and ≤ when comparing two numbers.

Notice also that ''every'' set is a subset of the ''universal set'', and the ''empty set'' is a subset of ''every'' set.

(You might be curious about this last statement: how can the empty set be a subset of ''anything'', when it doesn’t contain any elements?  The point here is that for every set ''A'', the empty set '''doesn’t''' contain any elements that '''aren't''' in ''A''.  So &lt;big&gt;&amp;oslash;&lt;/big&gt; &amp;sube; ''A'' for all sets ''A''.)

Finally, note that if ''A'' &amp;sube; ''B'' and ''B'' &amp;sube; ''A'' then ''A'' and ''B'' must contain exactly the same elements, and are therefore equal.  In other words:

*: If ''A'' &amp;sube; ''B'' and ''B'' &amp;sube; ''A'' then ''A'' = ''B''

=== Disjoint ===
Two sets are said to be '''''disjoint''''' if they have no elements in common.  For example:

*: If ''A'' = {even numbers} and ''B'' = {1, 3, 5, 11, 19}, then ''A'' and ''B'' are disjoint sets

== Venn Diagrams ==
A ''Venn diagram'' can be a useful way of illustrating relationships between sets.

In a Venn diagram:

*: The ''universal set'' is represented by a ''rectangle''.  Points inside the rectangle represent elements that are in the universal set; points outside represent things not in the universal set.  You can think of this rectangle, then, as a 'fence' keeping unwanted things out - and concentrating our attention on the things we're talking about.

*: Other sets are represented by ''loops'', usually oval or circular in shape, drawn inside the rectangle.  Again, points inside a given loop represent elements in the set it represents; points outside represent things ''not'' in the set.
[[Image:VennSubset02.jpg|right|thumb|350px|''Venn diagrams: Fig. 2'']]
[[Image:VennDisjoint.jpg|left|thumb|350px|''Venn diagrams: Fig. 1'']]


On the left, the sets ''A'' and ''B'' are [[#Disjoint|disjoint]], because the loops don't overlap.

On the right ''A'' is a [[#Subsets|subset]] of ''B'', because the loop representing set ''A'' is entirely enclosed by loop ''B''.
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot;&gt;

=== Venn diagrams: Worked Examples ===
[[Image:VennTwoSetsGeneralCase.jpg|right|thumb|350px|''Venn diagrams: Fig. 3'']]
''Example 1''


''Fig. 3'' represents a Venn diagram showing two sets ''A'' and ''B'', in the general case where nothing is known about any relationships between the sets.

Note that the rectangle representing the universal set is divided into four regions, labelled ''i'', ''ii'', ''iii'' and ''iv''.

What can be said about the sets ''A'' and ''B'' if it turns out that:

: (a) region ''ii'' is empty?

: (b) region ''iii'' is empty?
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot;&gt;

(a) If region ''ii'' is empty, then ''A'' contains no elements that are not in ''B''.  So ''A'' is a subset of ''B'', and the diagram should be re-drawn like ''Fig 2'' above.


(b) If region ''iii'' is empty, then ''A'' and ''B'' have no elements in common and are therefore disjoint.  The diagram should then be re-drawn like ''Fig 1'' above.

''Example 2''

: (a) Draw a Venn diagram to represent three sets ''A'', ''B'' and ''C'', in the general case where nothing is known about possible relationships between the sets.

: (b) Into how many regions is the rectangle representing '''U''' divided now? 	

: (c) Discuss the relationships between the sets ''A'', ''B'' and ''C'', when various combinations of these regions are empty.

[[Image:VennThreeSetsGeneralCase.jpg|right|thumb|350px|''Venn diagrams: Fig. 4'']]


(a) The diagram in ''Fig. 4'' shows the general case of three sets where nothing is known about any possible relationships between them.

(b) The rectangle representing '''U''' is now divided into 8 regions, indicated by the Roman numerals ''i'' to ''viii''.

(c) Various combinations of empty regions are possible. In each case, the Venn diagram can be re-drawn so that empty regions are no longer included.  For example:
*: If region ''ii'' is empty, the loop representing ''A'' should be made smaller, and moved inside ''B'' and ''C'' to eliminate region ''ii''.

*: If regions ''ii'', ''iii'' and ''iv'' are empty, make ''A'' and ''B'' smaller, and move them so that they are both inside ''C'' (thus eliminating all three of these regions), but do so in such a way that they still overlap each other (thus retaining region ''vi'').

*: If regions ''iii'' and ''vi'' are empty, 'pull apart' loops ''A'' and ''B'' to eliminate these regions, but keep each loop overlapping loop ''C''.

*: ...and so on.  Drawing Venn diagrams for each of the above examples is left as an exercise for the reader.


{{clear}}
''Example 3''

The following sets are defined:

: '''U''' = {1, 2, 3, …, 10}
: ''A'' = {2, 3, 7, 8, 9}
: ''B'' = {2, 8}
: ''C'' = {4, 6, 7, 10}

Using the two-stage technique described below, draw a Venn diagram to represent these sets, marking all the elements in the appropriate regions. 

The technique is as follows:

*: Draw a 'general' 3-set Venn diagram, like the one in ''Example 2''.

*: Go through the elements of the universal set one at a time, once only, entering each one into the appropriate region of the diagram.

*: Re-draw the diagram, if necessary, moving loops inside one another or apart to eliminate any empty regions.

'''Don't''' begin by entering the elements of set ''A'', then set ''B'', then ''C'' – you'll risk missing elements out or including them twice!


''Solution''

After drawing the three empty loops in a diagram looking like ''Fig. 4'' (but without the Roman numerals!), go through each of the ten elements in '''U''' - the numbers 1 to 10 - asking each one three questions; like this:

[[Image:VennThreeSetsAllocatingElements01.jpg|right|thumb|350px|''Venn diagrams: Fig. 5'']]

First element: 1
: Are you in ''A''? No
: Are you in ''B''? No
: Are you in ''C''? No

A 'no' to all three questions means that the number 1 is outside all three loops.  So write it in the appropriate region (region number ''i'' in ''Fig. 4'').

Second element: 2
: Are you in ''A''? Yes
: Are you in ''B''? Yes
: Are you in ''C''? No

Yes, yes, no: so the number 2 is inside ''A'' and ''B'' but outside ''C''.  Goes in region ''iii'' then.

...and so on, with elements 3 to 10.

The resulting diagram looks like ''Fig. 5''.
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot;&gt;

[[Image:VennThreeSetsAllocatingElements02.jpg|right|thumb|350px|''Venn diagrams: Fig. 6'']]


The final stage is to examine the diagram for empty regions - in this case the regions we called ''iv'', ''vi'' and ''vii'' in ''Fig. 4'' - and then re-draw the diagram to eliminate these regions. When we've done so, we shall clearly see the relationships between the three sets.

So we need to:
*: pull ''B'' and ''C'' apart, since they don't have any elements in common.

*: push ''B'' inside ''A'' since it doesn't have any elements outside ''A''.


The finished result is shown in ''Fig. 6''.
{{clear}}

=== The regions in a Venn Diagram and Truth Tables ===
Perhaps you've realized that adding an additional set to a Venn diagram ''doubles'' the number of regions into which the rectangle representing the universal set is divided.  This gives us a very simple pattern, as follows:

*: With one set loop, there will be just two regions: the inside of the loop and its outside.

*: With two set loops, there'll be four regions.

*: With three loops, there'll be eight regions.

*: ...and so on.

It's not hard to see why this should be so.  Each new loop we add to the diagram divides each existing region into two, thus doubling the number of regions altogether.

{| border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; cellpadding=&quot;5&quot; align=&quot;right&quot;
! In ''A''?
! In ''B''?
! In ''C''?
|- 
| Y 
| Y
| Y
|- 
| Y
| Y
| N
|- 
| Y
| N
| Y
|- 
| Y
| N
| N
|- 
| N
| Y
| Y
|- 
| N
| Y
| N
|- 
| N
| N
| Y
|- 
| N
| N
| N
|}

But there's another way of looking at this, and it's this.  In the solution to ''Example 3'' above, we asked three questions of each element: ''Are you in A? Are you in B?'' and ''Are you in C?''  Now there are obviously two possible answers to each of these questions: ''yes'' and ''no''. When we ''combine'' the answers to three questions like this, one after the other, there are then 2&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; = 8 possible sets of answers altogether. Each of these eight possible combinations of answers corresponds to a different region on the Venn diagram.

The complete set of answers resembles very closely a ''Truth Table'' - an important concept in [[Discrete_mathematics/Logic#Truth_Tables|''Logic'']], which deals with statements which may be ''true'' or ''false''. The table on the right shows the eight possible combinations of answers for 3 sets ''A'', ''B'' and ''C''.

You'll find it helpful to study the patterns of Y's and N's in each column.

*: As you read down column ''C'', the letter changes on every row: Y, N, Y, N, Y, N, Y, N

*: Reading down column ''B'', the letters change on every other row: Y, Y, N, N, Y, Y, N, N

*: Reading down column ''A'', the letters change every four rows: Y, Y, Y, Y, N, N, N, N
{{clear}}

== Set Theory Exercise 2 ==
Click link for [[/Exercises#Set Theory Exercise 2|Set Theory Exercise 2]].

== Operations on Sets ==
Just as we can combine two numbers to form a third number, with operations like 'add', 'subtract', 'multiply' and 'divide', so we can combine two sets to form a third set in various ways.  We'll begin by looking again at the Venn diagram which shows two sets ''A'' and ''B'' in a general position, where we don't have any information about how they may be related.


[[Image:VennTwoSetsGeneralCase.jpg|left|thumb|350px|''Venn diagrams: Fig. 7'']]


{| border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; cellpadding=&quot;5&quot; align=&quot;right&quot;
! In ''A''?
! In ''B''?
! Region
|- 
| Y 
| Y
| ''iii''
|- 
| Y
| N
| ''ii''
|- 
| N
| Y
| ''iv''
|- 
| N
| N
| ''i''
|}

&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot;&gt;

The first two columns in the table on the right show the four sets of possible answers to the questions ''Are you in A?'' and ''Are you in B?'' for two sets ''A'' and ''B''; the Roman numerals in the third column show the corresponding region in the Venn diagram in ''Fig. 7''.

=== Intersection ===
Region ''iii'', where the two loops overlap (the region corresponding to 'Y' followed by 'Y'), is called the ''intersection'' of the sets ''A'' and ''B''. It is denoted by ''A'' &amp;cap; ''B''.  So we can define intersection as follows:

*: The '''''intersection''''' of two sets ''A'' and ''B'', written ''A'' &amp;cap; ''B'', is the set of elements that are in ''A'' '''and''' in ''B''.

(Note that in [[Discrete_mathematics/Logic#Compound_Propositions|symbolic logic]], a similar symbol, &lt;math&gt;\scriptstyle \wedge&lt;/math&gt;, is used to connect two logical propositions with the '''AND''' operator.)

For example, if ''A'' = {1, 2, 3, 4} and ''B'' = {2, 4, 6, 8}, then ''A'' &amp;cap; ''B'' = {2, 4}.

We can say, then, that we have combined two sets to form a third set using the ''operation of intersection''.

=== Union ===
In a similar way we can define the ''union'' of two sets as follows:
*: The '''''union''''' of two sets ''A'' and ''B'', written ''A'' &amp;cup; ''B'', is the set of elements that are in ''A'' '''or''' in ''B'' (or both).

The union, then, is represented by regions ''ii'', ''iii'' and ''iv'' in ''Fig. 7''.

(Again, in logic a similar symbol, &lt;math&gt;\scriptstyle \vee&lt;/math&gt;, is used to connect two propositions with the '''OR''' operator.)

*: So, for example,  {1, 2, 3, 4} &amp;cup; {2, 4, 6, 8} = {1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8}.

You'll see, then, that in order to get into the intersection, an element must answer 'Yes' to ''both'' questions, whereas to get into the union, ''either'' answer may be 'Yes'. 

The &amp;cup; symbol looks like the first letter of 'Union' and like a cup that will hold a lot of items.  The &amp;cap; symbol looks like a spilled cup that won't hold a lot of items, or possibly the letter 'n', for i'n'tersection.  Take care not to confuse the two.

=== Difference ===
*: The '''''difference''''' of two sets ''A'' and ''B'' (also known as the '''''set-theoretic difference''''' of ''A'' and ''B'', or the '''''relative complement''''' of ''B'' in ''A'') is the set of elements that are '''in''' ''A'' '''but not in''' ''B''.

This is written ''A'' - ''B'', or sometimes ''A \ ''B''.

The elements in the difference, then, are the ones that answer 'Yes' to the first question ''Are you in A?'', but 'No' to the second ''Are you in B?''. This combination of answers is on row 2 of the above table, and corresponds to region ''ii'' in ''Fig.7''.

*: For example, if ''A'' = {1, 2, 3, 4} and ''B'' = {2, 4, 6, 8}, then ''A'' - ''B'' = {1, 3}.

=== Complement ===
So far, we have considered operations in which ''two'' sets combine to form a third: ''binary'' operations.  Now we look at a ''unary'' operation - one that involves just ''one'' set.

*: The set of elements that are '''not''' in a set ''A'' is called the '''''complement''''' of ''A''.  It is written ''A''&amp;prime; (or sometimes ''A''&lt;sup&gt;C&lt;/sup&gt;, or &lt;sup&gt;&lt;math&gt;\scriptstyle \bar{A}&lt;/math&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;).
Clearly, this is the set of elements that answer 'No' to the question ''Are you in A?''.

*: For example, if '''U''' = '''N''' and ''A'' = {odd numbers}, then ''A''&amp;prime; = {even numbers}.

Notice the spelling of the word ''complement'': its literal meaning is 'a complementary item or items'; in other words, 'that which completes'. So if we already have the elements of ''A'', the complement of ''A'' is the set that ''completes'' the universal set.

=== Summary ===
{| border=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; cellpadding=&quot;5&quot; align=&quot;left&quot;
| [[Image:VennIntersection.jpg|centre|thumb|350px|'''Intersection''': things that are in ''A'' '''and''' in ''B'']]
| [[Image:VennUnion.jpg|centre|thumb|350px|'''Union''': things that are in ''A'' '''or''' in ''B'' (or both)]]
|-
| [[Image:VennDifference.jpg|centre|thumb|350px|'''Difference''': things that are in ''A'' '''and not''' in ''B'']]
| [[Image:VennSymmetricDifference.jpg|centre|thumb|350px|'''Symmetric Difference''': things that are in ''A'' '''or''' in ''B'' '''but not''' both]]
|-
|[[Image:VennComplement.jpg|center|thumb|350px|'''Complement''': things that are '''not''' in ''A'']]
|}
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot;&gt;

=== Cardinality ===
Finally, in this section on ''Set Operations'' we look at an operation on a set that yields not another set, but an integer.

*: The '''''cardinality''''' of a finite set ''A'', written | ''A'' | (sometimes #(''A'') or ''n''(''A'')), is the number of (distinct) elements in ''A''.  So, for example:
*: If ''A'' = {lower case letters of the alphabet}, | ''A'' | = 26.

=== Generalized set operations ===
If we want to denote the intersection or union of ''n'' sets, ''A''&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;, ''A''&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, ..., ''A''&lt;sub&gt;''n''&lt;/sub&gt; (where we may not know the value of ''n'') then the following ''generalized set notation'' may be useful:

: ''A''&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;cap; ''A''&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;cap; ... &amp;cap; ''A''&lt;sub&gt;''n''&lt;/sub&gt; = &lt;math&gt;\scriptstyle \bigcap_{i=1}^{n}&lt;/math&gt; ''A''&lt;sub&gt;''i''&lt;/sub&gt;

: ''A''&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;cup; ''A''&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;cup; ... &amp;cup; ''A''&lt;sub&gt;''n''&lt;/sub&gt; = &lt;math&gt;\scriptstyle \bigcup_{i=1}^{n}&lt;/math&gt; ''A''&lt;sub&gt;''i''&lt;/sub&gt;

In the symbol &lt;math&gt;\scriptstyle \bigcap_{i=1}^{n}&lt;/math&gt; ''A''&lt;sub&gt;''i''&lt;/sub&gt;, then, ''i'' is a variable that takes values from 1 to ''n'', to indicate the repeated intersection of all the sets ''A''&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; to ''A''&lt;sub&gt;''n''&lt;/sub&gt;.

== Set Theory Exercise 3 ==
Click link for [[/Exercises#Set Theory Exercise 3|Set Theory Exercise 3]]

== Set Theory Page 2 ==
Set Theory continues on [[../Set_theory/Page_2|Page 2]].

----

Previous topic: [[../Introduction/]] | Contents:[[Discrete Mathematics]] | Next topic: [[../Functions and relations/]]

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>4mk3bfnj5nlcgy42xtnzyxk6n7myn3p</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Calculus</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>439</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2599219</id>
      <parentid>2527633</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-01-08T18:04:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Melikamp</username>
        <id>11845</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Exercises */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{talk header}}
{{todolink|Calculus|todo-list of Calculus}}

== gfdl vector calculus book ==

You know about this?  http://mecmath.net  It looks in terms of licensing like it can be incorporated into the wikibook, and maybe the author would like to participate. &lt;small&gt;—The preceding unsigned comment was added by [[User:207.241.238.217|207.241.238.217]] ([[User talk:207.241.238.217|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/207.241.238.217|contribs]]) 04:46, 2 July 2008  (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned2 --&gt;

== Current Contributors ==
Hello, I'm fairly new to Wikibooks but interested in helping on this chapter. Would anyone be willing to give me an overview of the goals and organization, as well as where the most help is needed

Hearing no objections, I'm planning on doing some reorganization of the Integration Techniques modules. I would love to get some input from the community, let me know. [[User:W3asal|W3asal]] ([[User talk:W3asal|talk]]) 05:32, 20 September 2008 (UTC)

: If anyone else is currently working on this book, let me know. I'm planning on doing major rewrites of several sections (starting in the Applications of Integration), and I'd love to coordinate with others. Leave me a message below or on my talk page. Thanks, [[User:W3asal|W3asal]] ([[User talk:W3asal|talk]]) 01:27, 28 January 2009 (UTC)

== Style for theorems. ==

Is there a standard style for stating theorems in this book? &lt;small&gt;—The preceding unsigned comment was added by [[User:199.170.84.172|199.170.84.172]] ([[User talk:199.170.84.172|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/199.170.84.172|contribs]]) 09:39, 7 October 2008  (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned2 --&gt;
: This book seems to lack a contributor's guide or local manual of style. --[[User:Swift|Swift]] ([[User talk:Swift|talk]]) 06:36, 13 February 2009 (UTC)
:I've created {{tlx|Calculus/Def}} for this sort of thing.
:The old [[Calculus/Outline]] resembled a contributor's guide, so I've expanded it at [[Calculus/Contributing]]. --[[User:Mrwojo|Mrwojo]] ([[User talk:Mrwojo|talk]]) 16:28, 8 September 2009 (UTC)

== Merge with Solving Integrals by Trigonometric substitution ==

I would agree with this merger. Unless there are objections, I will be happy to start this process. --[[User:Shiftout|Shiftout]] ([[User talk:Shiftout|talk]]) 23:11, 29 October 2008 (UTC)

: The merger sounds like a good idea to me.[[User:Thenub314|Thenub314]] ([[User talk:Thenub314|talk]]) 19:13, 20 January 2009 (UTC)

: I've moved the merge notice to the appropriate sub-page. Go ahead and be bold. --[[User:Swift|Swift]] ([[User talk:Swift|talk]]) 06:12, 13 February 2009 (UTC)

== Expanded TOC ==

I've just expanded the TOC on the main page. While the collapsed version may be more contributor friendly, those who are new to calculus and unfamiliar with the book structure benefit from a more detailed view. To further help them catch their bearings (and pretty this up a bit) I've added some relevant images to the first few sections. --[[User:Swift|Swift]] ([[User talk:Swift|talk]]) 06:11, 13 February 2009 (UTC)


== Inclusion of more examples and intent of book ==

Is there a policy on the number of examples/worked problems within the text?  I think more examples would be of great value.  Secondly, I'm curious as to the intent of the book.  Certainly, someone looking for a survey of calc text would not be served well by this book but the content they want/need is within.  Any suggested reading ideas? [[User:Tiled|Tiled]] ([[User talk:Tiled|talk]]) 17:47, 17 November 2009 (UTC)

:I think lots of examples is a good thing.  However, the exercises have solutions so it's not that important.  I mean, you should have enough examples to show how to do the standard calculations/problems.  Beyond that, people can just look at solutions to exercises if they need more help.  So, an extra example won't hurt anything either probably, but once there are a good amount of examples, you could just add to exercises maybe.  This is just what seems good to me at the time but I'm not saying it is definitely the best way.

:I'm not sure what your second question is supposed to mean.  This is just a calculus book like any other calculus text, at least that's what I assume.  What do you mean someone looking for a survey of calc text would not be served well by this?  If you just want a survey of calculus, skip some sections.  All the basics are here, as well as nonbasics.  Of course, the book could use a lot of work but it's certainly got a lot of good stuff in it already.  [[User:NumberTheorist|NumberTheorist]] ([[User talk:NumberTheorist|talk]]) 20:42, 17 February 2010 (UTC)

== Exercises ==

The exercises in this book need lots of work.  I will work on them a little but they could use a lot of work.  For example, problem 8 in Differentiation is currently to find the derivative of &lt;math&gt;x^3 * 2 \sqrt{y}&lt;/math&gt; and the solution is given as &lt;math&gt;\frac{x^3}{\sqrt{y}} + 6\sqrt{y} x^2&lt;/math&gt;.  Hopefully if you're helping on this book, you understand that this makes no sense, sort of a hybrid of a derivative with respect to x in some parts and with y in other parts.  And, the exercises have all sorts of formats.  This looks bad.  Also, some come in the middle of the section and some come in their own section at the end.  This is actually fine if we want to do it that way but it's probably best to just put them all at the end in one section (or to have all exercises pertaining to a certain section at the end of that section).  Any way, point is all aspects of exercises need work and I will do only a little work so need lots of help. [[User:NumberTheorist|NumberTheorist]] ([[User talk:NumberTheorist|talk]]) 02:39, 18 February 2010 (UTC)

:Okay, for starters, what are opinions on where exercises should go?  My vote is they should be at the end of each section because there are too many topics per chapter to have them all there.  For example, currently we have a chapter Differentiation with sections
:Differentiation - An introduction
:More differentiation rules - More rules for differentiation
:Higher Order derivatives - An introduction to second power derivatives
:Implicit Differentiation
:Exercises
:My thought is we do away with the section Exercises altogether and we put exercises at the end of each of the 4 other sections.  This is how your typical calculus book does thing.  [[User:NumberTheorist|NumberTheorist]] ([[User talk:NumberTheorist|talk]]) 02:46, 18 February 2010 (UTC)

:: I suggest that each module end on an exercise section with problems that specifically practice the concepts just covered. We could also collect the exercises into a special set of modules, but little is gained and it would make keeping the content up to date harder. --[[User:Swift|Swift]] ([[User talk:Swift|talk]]) 10:10, 18 February 2010 (UTC)

:::Hmm, well, I don't know the terminology here :)  What's a module?  If you look above, you'll see my terminology.  Differentiation is a chapter and then there are 5 sections under it, Differentiation through Exercises.  I am saying, and perhaps you are too, that exercises should go at the end of each section.  This is what basically any calculus book, and almost any math textbook, would do.  It would be way too confusing to cover all of differentiation and then go to the exercises.  You need to cover a little bit and then have focused exercises on those concepts.  Then, cover a bit more and do some exercises, and on and on.  All of the Differentiation chapter covers a ton of material, equal to at least 9 sections in the calculus book I am teaching from right now.  [[User:NumberTheorist|NumberTheorist]] ([[User talk:NumberTheorist|talk]]) 16:00, 18 February 2010 (UTC)
::::Also, I realized that most calc books have a section at the end of each chapter with additional exercises, so it's not wrong to put them at the end of a chapter but there need to be exercises at the end of each section, if you ask me. [[User:NumberTheorist|NumberTheorist]] ([[User talk:NumberTheorist|talk]]) 16:02, 18 February 2010 (UTC)
:::::And, sorry, but I looked up what a module is and it seems that we agree if I understand it correctly. [[User:NumberTheorist|NumberTheorist]] ([[User talk:NumberTheorist|talk]]) 16:15, 18 February 2010 (UTC)

:::::: Yes, we seem to see this the same way. --[[User:Swift|Swift]] ([[User talk:Swift|talk]]) 22:47, 18 February 2010 (UTC)

=== question-answer template ===

I am assuming that the question-answer template is OK for all exercises? I love it. I will be sandboxing some multivariate exercises, and will try to include them here in the next few weeks.

=== Multivariable Calc Exercises ===

I dumped a bunch of multivar calc exercises in the corresponding sub-section (it used to be empty). Some of them in the beginning may be more properly located in single-var calc, and the reason they are there is because I used them as a part of review in a multivar calc course. Of course, now we can move them, as long as they work with the text already written. Another area where more work is almost certainly needed is the consistency of the notation: I didn't look very carefully, so some of the notation I used (which is the same as that used by Stewart and Sullivan, and is pretty standard) may be in conflict with the text already written. I believe, though, that many exercises may be used as they are. [[User:Melikamp|Melikamp]] ([[User talk:Melikamp|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Melikamp|contribs]]) 18:04, 8 January 2014 (UTC)

== A few questions, how should this book be organized ==

1. Should we introduce some sort of numbering system, such as Precalculus is labeled Chapter 1 and Limits is Chapter 2 (some books might make Precalculus Chapter 0 and Limits Chapter 1)?  And, then below that, sections being labeled.  And, how should this be done?  Should it be Chapter 1, then Section 1, or we could do an outline form, I and then 1 and then a and so forth?  Or other?

: I'm against the idea of numbering systems. They serve little purpose and make restructuring content a pain. --[[User:Swift|Swift]] ([[User talk:Swift|talk]]) 23:11, 18 February 2010 (UTC)

2. Does it make sense to put solutions to all exercises?  If so, where should these go?  Should there be a link to the solutions?  Should we just Hide the solutions so you click on &quot;Show&quot; and they pop up?

: I think solutions to all examples are a good idea. Something along the lines of {{tlx|DropBox}} might be useful. --[[User:Swift|Swift]] ([[User talk:Swift|talk]]) 23:11, 18 February 2010 (UTC)

3. What is the standard format for an exercise?  I see some putting the \, in to make the math bigger and then I see some without it.  And, if you have a question, such as &quot;What is the area of blah blah blah &lt;math&gt;f(x) = 6x&lt;/math&gt;?&quot;, what do you do with that if your general rule is to make all the math type bigger?

That's a good start I guess. [[User:NumberTheorist|NumberTheorist]] ([[User talk:NumberTheorist|talk]]) 16:30, 18 February 2010 (UTC)

: There doesn't seem to be a standard format. Just be bold. The format can always be changed later. --[[User:Swift|Swift]] ([[User talk:Swift|talk]]) 23:11, 18 February 2010 (UTC)

== [[Calculus/More Differentiation Rules]] ==

Without going into extreme detail, this section has the amount of material in about 5-8 sections in your normal calculus book (I've looked through 2 different ones and I think it's 5 sections for one and 7 or 8 for the other).  So, it seems to me this section should be split up some.  It could be done in many ways probably.  Any thoughts? [[User:NumberTheorist|NumberTheorist]] ([[User talk:NumberTheorist|talk]]) 16:51, 18 February 2010 (UTC)

: I think this content would best be split in four along the level-two headings: One for the chain rule, another for the product (and quotient) rule, a third for implicit differentiation and a fourth for derivatives of common functions. --[[User:Swift|Swift]] ([[User talk:Swift|talk]]) 23:19, 18 February 2010 (UTC)

::Hmm, I was thinking more like separate pages (or modules might be the right word).  The reason I thought that was because of exercises.  Right now, it seems like too much material to go through before having exercises.  If it were split at least in 2 or 3 or 4 modules (for example, your suggestion), then there would be less material before the exercises show up and it seems like this would be easier to learn from.  What do you think? [[User:NumberTheorist|NumberTheorist]] ([[User talk:NumberTheorist|talk]]) 23:49, 18 February 2010 (UTC)

::: Yes, that was what I was talking about: To split the content (up into separate modules/pages). --[[User:Swift|Swift]] ([[User talk:Swift|talk]]) 00:51, 20 February 2010 (UTC)

::::Alright, hehe, I guess I need to get down this new vocab.  I think your four headings are good but with the added point that product and quotient rule should come first.  I noticed that in the discussion on some page, maybe this one, it was already mentioned by one person and agreed by another that those are easier and should come first.  They came first in the 2 calc books I looked at. [[User:NumberTheorist|NumberTheorist]] ([[User talk:NumberTheorist|talk]]) 03:01, 20 February 2010 (UTC)

:::::Upon looking at it again, I have a couple thoughts.  First off Implicit Differentiation is already a section so the implicit differentiation part of this section should just be merged with the implicit differentiation one that is already there.  Beyond that, it might be nice to do the derivatives of trig functions before the chain rule, as you only need the quotient rule to do them, so that you can have a little more variety than just a polynomial to a power.  And, technically you use implicit differentiation to prove the derivative of logs and also of inverse trig functions.  So, I propose we put inverse trig functions in the implicit differentiation section and then after that put exponential and logarithm functions as another section.  I will create these sections right now. [[User:NumberTheorist|NumberTheorist]] ([[User talk:NumberTheorist|talk]]) 03:14, 20 February 2010 (UTC)

::::::I put in the top nav bars for each of the new pages and labeled them to not included &quot;More Differentiation Rules&quot;.  As far as that section, I moved all the exercises to the Exercises section temporarily.  I did notice all the new sections are showing up under Subject:Calculus but maybe they will go away now that I deleted BookCat from each one.  I don't know what causes that.  [[User:NumberTheorist|NumberTheorist]] ([[User talk:NumberTheorist|talk]]) 22:34, 20 February 2010 (UTC)

== Reorganization of Structure ==

Contents page is too long.  I propose we stick to just major sections on the contents page, and their subsections.  Links to subsections introduce the subsection and show the contents of its pages.  Links to major sections show table of contents for the whole section.  I believe this was what was originally planned (from the contribution page) but seems to have been drifted away from. [[User:Italienmoose|Italienmoose]] ([[User talk:Italienmoose|talk]]) 19:31, 5 June 2010 (UTC)

:Dude, I'm in totally agreement with you on the length.  Personally, I don't think that this wikibook should be one giant treatise, like the popular Stewart Calculus book.  That book is over 1,100 pages.  That's too long, too much content.  It takes about three semesters to go through the whole thing.  That's the real reason why this contents page is too long.  If this book, with its current ambitions, was seen to total fruition, it would be ''way'' long.  If anyone ever wanted to make a physical version of it, you could use it for [[w:crushing|crushing]].  Anybody else think it would be smart to split this book up? [[User:Tiled|Tiled]] ([[User talk:Tiled|talk]]) 22:20, 26 August 2010 (UTC)

::Uhh, it covers the material that would be 3 semesters at most colleges.  And, most colleges would use 1 textbook for such a course.  I own 3 different calculus books (one begin Stewart's) and teach from another and they're all essentially the same, as far as the main topics covered goes.  I say it's smart to leave this wiki book as is.  Perhaps you could do, as most textbooks do, and make several editions of the book.  There could be a single variable version, a multivariable version, an early transcendentals version, whatever.  But, this one book should stay together as it is a standard list of topics for one textbook.  I will admit it may have a few sections here and there that wouldn't be in a standard calculus book but that's the beauty of an online book.  We don't have to exclude topics to save money in printing. [[User:NumberTheorist|NumberTheorist]] ([[User talk:NumberTheorist|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/NumberTheorist|contribs]]) 19:20, 26 April 2011 (UTC)


== GFDL ==

This book (at least in the printable version) ends with a copy of the GFDL. I think it should be removed since now wikibooks is under CC-BY-SA. Can I do it, or am I wrong? [[User:Fale|Fale]] ([[User talk:Fale|talk]]) 16:45, 9 June 2010 (UTC)
: I don't have a problem with it.  The whole point of moving to CC-BY-SA was to avoid having to include the full text of the GFDL with every instance of the content. &amp;ndash;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Adrignola|Adrignola]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Adrignola|talk]]&amp;nbsp;[[Special:Contributions/Adrignola|contribs]]&lt;/sup&gt; 16:58, 9 June 2010 (UTC)

:Go ahead and remove it, this was indeed one of the benefits of relicensing. [[User:Thenub314|Thenub314]] ([[User talk:Thenub314|talk]]) 17:40, 9 June 2010 (UTC)

== the title of the &quot;Infinite Limits&quot; section  ==

The section titled &quot;Infinite Limits&quot; should be titled &quot;Limits at Infinity&quot;. The definition is for &quot;limits at infinity&quot; and we talk about limits at infinity for rational functions. The discussion is almost exclusive about finite limits at infinity.  Only the last example is an infinite limit. [[User:Chrislmorin|Chrislmorin]] ([[User talk:Chrislmorin|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Chrislmorin|contribs]]) 16:20, 27 January 2013 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>7ie16fcr1tmjq3jpyrn7l69vlntynla</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>