<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>United States Government/General Provisions</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1294</id>
    <revision>
      <id>541632</id>
      <parentid>259433</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-07-30T17:29:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{USConstitionAndGovtTOC}}
----

==Introduction==

The Constitution provides for many things other than the Union and member state government operation.

==Supreme Law==

The Constitution calls itself, the United States laws, and treaties, the Supreme Law of the land. No state law may conflict with the Supreme Law. If they do, the conflicting parts are ruled void.

Also, the Constitution is itself superior to federal laws and treaties. If either of these, or any Executive order made by the President, or a state law, or other regulation similar to law, conflicts with the constitution, the Courts may declare it unconstitutional, and the law or regulation becomes void. Note that this is not explicitly provided for by the Constitution. Chief Justice John Marshall originally used '''judicial review'''- the power to declare laws unconstitutional- in the early 1800's when he decided the case ''Marbury v. Madison''.

==Oaths==

The Union and member state officers take an oath to support and defend the Constitution. Only the Union President's oath is explicitly spelled out- the form of the other oaths is left to the appropriate government. The Constitution, while mentioning oaths, specifically prohibits the United States or a member state from requiring a religious oath or observance of a certain religion in order to qualify for any office.

==Amendment==

The Constitution is not an unchangeable document. Changes to it are known as '''amendments'''. By tradition, an amendment does not strike out words and insert others. In order to leave the original Constitution whole, Amendments are added as separate Articles at the end of the Constitution. 

There are two ways in which an amendment can be proposed, and two ways in which it can be '''ratified''', or approved. First, the Amendment can be proposed by Congress. For this to occur, two-thirds of the House of Representatives and two-thirds of the Senate must vote for the Amendment. Second, an Amendment can be proposed by a Constitutional Convention. If two-thirds of the member states make an application to Congress, Congress must call this Convention, which then proposes Amendments. However, a Constitutional Convention has never been called. 

Regardless of the way in which the Amendment is proposed, it must be ratified by three-fourths of the member states. The first manner in which ratification by a member state may occur is through the legislature. Secondly, a state convention can be called to ratify an amendment. The second method has only been used once. Note that each member state cannot decide which method it wishes to use. Whoever proposed the Amendment- the Congress or a Union Convention- will decide if legislatures or state conventions will ratify. 

There have been twenty-seven Constitutional Amendments to date. The first ten guarantee certain already existing rights to the people and member states- they are therefore known as the Bill of Rights.
----
{{USConstitionAndGovtTOC}}

[[Category:United States Government]]</text>
      <sha1>q4l37nxozkc6ehtauh3v4h9hcm0vs3e</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>United States Government/The Bill of Rights</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1295</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2532640</id>
      <parentid>2532639</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-06-03T20:39:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>98.243.119.251</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* First Amendment */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{USConstitionAndGovtTOC}}
----

==First Amendment==


&quot;Congress shall make no law respecting an establishment of religion, or prohibiting the free exercise thereof; or abridging the freedom of speech, or of the press; or the right of the people peaceably to assemble, and to petition the government for a redress of grievances.&quot;

The First Amendment is the best-known amendment to most Americans. It provides, firstly, that &quot;Congress shall make no law respecting an establishment of religion, or prohibiting the free exercise thereof.&quot; Basically, this means that Congress cannot make one religion official, or require people to worship in a certain way. The courts have interpreted the clause to mean that, in addition to Congress, the executive and judicial branch, as well as the states, cannot prohibit free exercise of religion. Thomas Jefferson referred to these prohibitions as &quot;separation of church and state&quot;.

The First also allows free speech to people. This has been interpreted to mean free action, as well. However, as one Supreme Court Justice put it, &quot;My right to swing my arm stops at another man's chin.&quot; One cannot use free speech rights to violate the rights of other people. 

Also, the First guarantees people the right to assemble peacefully, and to petition the government.Also keep your hands to yourself

==Second Amendment==

&quot;A well regulated militia, being necessary to the security of a free state, the right of the people to keep and bear arms, shall not be infringed.&quot;

The Second Amendment, subject to much controversy, forbids the outlawing of firearms and militias.

==Third Amendment==

&quot;No soldier shall, in time of peace be quartered in any house, without the consent of the owner, nor in time of war, but in a manner to be prescribed by law.&quot;


Soldiers, according to the Third, may not during peacetime be '''quartered''' or housed in a residence without the consent of the owner. Furthermore, even in wartime, a law is required to force people to quarter soldiers.

The Supreme Court and others have also attributed a right to personal privacy within this amendment this is true

==Fourth Amendment==
The fourth amendment of the United States Constitution reads as follows: 
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The right of the people to be secure in their persons, houses, papers, and effects, against unreasonable searches and seizures, shall not be violated, and no Warrants shall issue, but upon probable cause, supported by Oath or affirmation, and particularly describing the place to be searched, and the persons or things to be seized.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The fourth amendment can be broken into two distinct parts. The first part provides protection against unreasonable searches and seizures, although unreasonable has been defined in a myraid of different ways.  However, the framers did not qualify how a violation of this amendment was to be punished.  Case law has afforded the exclusionary rule to ensure that evidence improperly collected is excluded from trial. (See ''Wolf v. Colorado'', ''Mapp v. Ohio'', and ''United States v. Leon'' for more information on the progression of the exclusionary rule.) This gives law enforcement officers the incentive to respect the amendment.

The second part of the amendment provides for the proper issue of warrants.  However, it is important to note that it does not require that warrants be obtained prior to a search or seizure, only that searches and seizures are reasonable.  When warrants are issued, their must be probable cause. Probable cause is tested using the &quot;totality of circumstances&quot; test as defined in ''Illinois v. Gates''. (See ''Spinelli v. United States'' and ''Illinois v. Gates'' for the progression on probable cause tests. Also see ''Maryland v. Garison'' and ''Richards v. Wisconsin'' for more on search warrants.)  

'''Interesting Search and Seizure Cases'''
*http://www.wdnweb.com/2011/02/17/city-beefs-up-code/
*''Katz v. United States'': use of electronic eavesdropping by law enforcement
*''California v. Greenwood'': examination of curbside garbage
*''Florida v. Riley'': use of aerial surveillance by law enforcement
*''United States v. Karo'': use of electronic tracking by law enforcement
*''Kyllo v. United States'': use of thermal imaging by law enforcement

==Fifth Amendment==


&quot;No person shall be held to answer for a capital, or otherwise infamous crime, unless on a presentment or indictment of a grand jury, except in cases arising in the land or naval forces, or in the militia, when in actual service in time of war or public danger; nor shall any person be subject for the same offense to be twice put in jeopardy of life or limb; nor shall be compelled in any criminal case to be a witness against himself, nor be deprived of life, liberty, or property, without due process of law; nor shall private property be taken for public use, without just compensation.&quot;


While the Fourth protects one against the police, the Fifth guarantees one's rights relating to actual charges of criminal activity. Firstly, the Fifth requires that a Grand Jury (a special body of lay-people) indict, or accuse, a person of a serious crime before he or she may be tried for it. The sole exception relates to the military, where Grand Juries are not used.

2:  the Amendment prohibits &quot;double jeopardy.&quot; Once a person has been tried and acquitted (found not guilty), the prosecutor cannot retry him, even if new evidence is discovered. However, the prohibition against double jeopardy does not extend to mistrials. If a jury cannot reach a verdict and the judge declares a mistrial, then the case may be retried.

3:   the Amendment provides that one cannot be compelled to testify against oneself. A person may &quot;take the Fifth&quot; to avoid incriminating him or herself. However, the government may grant immunity, or formal protection from prosecution, to a person. Then, the person cannot be punished for what crimes he might have committed, and can be forced to give evidence.

4:  the Fifth requires due process to be used. While due process is not defined in the Constitution, one may conclude that it involves fair trials with impartial juries and judges. 

5:  the Fifth prohibits government from taking away a person's property unless it provides fair compensation.

==Sixth Amendment==

In all criminal prosecutions, the accused shall enjoy the right to a speedy and public trial, by an impartial jury of the State and district wherein the crime shall have been committed, which district shall have been previously ascertained by law, and to be informed of the nature and cause of the accusation; to be confronted with the witnesses against him; to have compulsory process for obtaining witnesses in his favor, and to have the Assistance of Counsel for his defence.

==Seventh Amendment==

&quot;In suits at common law, where the value in controversy shall exceed twenty dollars, the right of trial by jury shall be preserved, and no fact tried by a jury, shall be otherwise reexamined in any court of the United States, than according to the rules of the common law.

Trial by jury in common law cases

==Eighth Amendment==

&quot;Excessive bail shall not be required, nor excessive fines imposed, nor cruel and unusual punishments inflicted.&quot;

bail, cruel, and unusual punishment

==Ninth Amendment==

The enumeration in the Constitution, of certain rights, shall not be construed to deny or disparage others retained by the people.

Rights retained by the people

==Tenth Amendment==

&quot;The powers not delegated to the United States by the Constitution, nor prohibited by it to the states, are reserved to the states respectively, or to the people.

The Tenth Amendment prevents the Union government from regulating a matter it is not constitutionally entitled to regulate. The Union government, therefore, cannot infringe upon a state's reserved powers.

==Conclusion==

[[Category:United States Government]]</text>
      <sha1>cw7sksb6tfzit554s9ntl0pp1qbb2o4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>United States Government/The Constitution and Amendments</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1296</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2489200</id>
      <parentid>2028525</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-02-18T13:02:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>189.133.22.21</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Amendment I */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{USConstitionAndGovtTOC}}
----

==The Preamble==

We the People of the United States, in Order to form a more perfect Union,
establish Justice, insure domestic Tranquility, provide for the common
defence, promote the general Welfare, and secure the Blessings of Liberty to
ourselves and our Posterity, do ordain and establish this Constitution for the
United States of America.

==Article I==

===Section 1===
All legislative Powers herein granted shall be vested in a Congress of the
United States, which shall consist of a Senate and House of Representatives.

===Section 2===
The House of Representatives shall be composed of Members chosen every second
Year by the People of the several States, and the Electors in each State shall
have the Qualifications requisite for Electors of the most numerous Branch of
the State Legislature.

No Person shall be a Representative who shall not have attained to the Age of
twenty five Years, and been seven Years a Citizen of the United States, and who
shall not, when elected, be an Inhabitant of that State in which he shall be
chosen.

&lt;b&gt;Representatives and direct Taxes shall be apportioned among the several States
which may be included within this Union, according to their respective Numbers,
which shall be determined by adding to the whole Number of free Persons,
including those bound to Service for a Term of Years, and excluding Indians not
taxed, three fifths of all other Persons.&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;[Superseded by Amendment XIV, section 2]&lt;/i&gt;

The actual Enumeration shall be made within three Years after the first Meeting
of the Congress of the United States, and within every subsequent Term of ten
Years, in such Manner as they shall by Law direct. The Number of
Representatives shall not exceed one for every thirty Thousand, but each State
shall have at Least one Representative; and until such enumeration shall be
made, the State of New Hampshire shall be entitled to chuse three,
Massachusetts eight, Rhode Island and Providence Plantations one, Connecticut
five, New York six, New Jersey four, Pennsylvania eight, Delaware one, Maryland
six, Virginia ten, North Carolina five, South Carolina five and Georgia three.

When vacancies happen in the Representation from any State, the Executive
Authority thereof shall issue Writs of Election to fill such Vacancies.

The House of Representatives shall chuse their Speaker and other Officers; and
shall have the sole Power of Impeachment.

===Section 3===
The Senate of the United States shall be composed of two Senators from each
State, &lt;b&gt;chosen by the Legislature thereof,&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;[Superseded by Amendment XVII, section 1]&lt;/i&gt; for six Years; and each Senator shall
have one Vote.

Immediately after they shall be assembled in Consequence of the first Election,
they shall be divided as equally as may be into three Classes. The Seats of the
Senators of the first Class shall be vacated at the Expiration of the second
Year, of the second Class at the Expiration of the fourth Year, and of the
third Class at the Expiration of the sixth Year, so that one third may be
chosen every second Year; &lt;b&gt;and if Vacancies happen by Resignation, or otherwise,
during the Recess of the Legislature of any State, the Executive thereof may
make temporary Appointments until the next Meeting of the Legislature, which
shall then fill such Vacancies.&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;[Superseded by Amendment XVII, section 2]&lt;/i&gt;

No person shall be a Senator who shall not have attained to the Age of thirty
Years, and been nine Years a Citizen of the United States, and who shall not,
when elected, be an Inhabitant of that State for which he shall be chosen.

The Vice President of the United States shall be President of the Senate, but
shall have no Vote, unless they be equally divided.

The Senate shall choose their other Officers, and also a President pro tempore,
in the absence of the Vice President, or when he shall exercise the Office of
President of the United States.

The Senate shall have the sole Power to try all Impeachments. When sitting for
that Purpose, they shall be on Oath or Affirmation. When the President of the
United States is tried, the Chief Justice shall preside: And no Person shall be
convicted without the Concurrence of two thirds of the Members present.

Judgment in Cases of Impeachment shall not extend further than to removal from
Office, and disqualification to hold and enjoy any Office of honor, Trust or
Profit under the United States: but the Party convicted shall nevertheless be
liable and subject to Indictment, Trial, Judgment and Punishment, according to
Law.

===Section 4===
The Times, Places and Manner of holding Elections for Senators and
Representatives, shall be prescribed in each State by the Legislature thereof;
but the Congress may at any time by Law make or alter such Regulations, except
as to the Place of Chusing Senators.

The Congress shall assemble at least once in every Year, and such Meeting shall
be on &lt;b&gt;the first Monday in December,&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;[Superseded by Amendment XX, section 2]&lt;/i&gt; unless they shall by Law appoint a
different Day.

===Section 5===
Each House shall be the Judge of the Elections, Returns and Qualifications of
its own Members, and a Majority of each shall constitute a Quorum to do
Business; but a smaller number may adjourn from day to day, and may be
authorized to compel the Attendance of absent Members, in such Manner, and
under such Penalties as each House may provide.

Each House may determine the Rules of its Proceedings, punish its Members for
disorderly Behavior, and, with the Concurrence of two-thirds, expel a Member.

Each House shall keep a Journal of its Proceedings, and from time to time
publish the same, excepting such Parts as may in their Judgment require
Secrecy; and the Yeas and Nays of the Members of either House on any question
shall, at the Desire of one fifth of those Present, be entered on the Journal.

Neither House, during the Session of Congress, shall, without the Consent of
the other, adjourn for more than three days, nor to any other Place than that
in which the two Houses shall be sitting.

===Section 6===
&lt;b&gt;The Senators and Representatives shall receive a Compensation for their
Services, to be ascertained by Law, and paid out of the Treasury of the United
States.&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;[Modified by Amendment XXVII]&lt;/i&gt; They shall in all Cases, except Treason, Felony and Breach of the
Peace, be privileged from Arrest during their Attendance at the Session of
their respective Houses, and in going to and returning from the same; and for
any Speech or Debate in either House, they shall not be questioned in any other
Place.

No Senator or Representative shall, during the Time for which he was elected,
be appointed to any civil Office under the Authority of the United States which
shall have been created, or the Emoluments whereof shall have been increased
during such time; and no Person holding any Office under the United States,
shall be a Member of either House during his Continuance in Office.

===Section 7===
All bills for raising Revenue shall originate in the House of Representatives;
but the Senate may propose or concur with Amendments as on other Bills.

Every Bill which shall have passed the House of Representatives and the Senate,
shall, before it become a Law, be presented to the President of the United
States; If he approve he shall sign it, but if not he shall return it, with his
Objections to that House in which it shall have originated, who shall enter the
Objections at large on their Journal, and proceed to reconsider it. If after
such Reconsideration two thirds of that House shall agree to pass the Bill, it
shall be sent, together with the Objections, to the other House, by which it
shall likewise be reconsidered, and if approved by two thirds of that House, it
shall become a Law. But in all such Cases the Votes of both Houses shall be
determined by Yeas and Nays, and the Names of the Persons voting for and
against the Bill shall be entered on the Journal of each House respectively. If
any Bill shall not be returned by the President within ten Days (Sundays
excepted) after it shall have been presented to him, the Same shall be a Law,
in like Manner as if he had signed it, unless the Congress by their Adjournment
prevent its Return, in which Case it shall not be a Law.

Every Order, Resolution, or Vote to which the Concurrence of the Senate and
House of Representatives may be necessary (except on a question of Adjournment)
shall be presented to the President of the United States; and before the Same
shall take Effect, shall be approved by him, or being disapproved by him, shall
be repassed by two thirds of the Senate and House of Representatives, according
to the Rules and Limitations prescribed in the Case of a Bill.

===Section 8===
The Congress shall have Power To lay and collect Taxes, Duties, Imposts and
Excises, to pay the Debts and provide for the common Defense and general
Welfare of the United States; but all Duties, Imposts and Excises shall be
uniform throughout the United States;

To borrow money on the credit of the United States;

To regulate Commerce with foreign Nations, and among the several States, and
with the Indian Tribes;

To establish an uniform Rule of Naturalization, and uniform Laws on the subject
of Bankruptcies throughout the United States;

To coin Money, regulate the Value thereof, and of foreign Coin, and fix the
Standard of Weights and Measures;

To provide for the Punishment of counterfeiting the Securities and current Coin
of the United States;

To establish Post Offices and Post Roads;

To promote the Progress of Science and useful Arts, by securing for limited
Times to Authors and Inventors the exclusive Right to their respective Writings
and Discoveries;

To constitute Tribunals inferior to the supreme Court;

To define and punish Piracies and Felonies committed on the high Seas, and
Offenses against the Law of Nations;

To declare War, grant Letters of Marque and Reprisal, and make Rules concerning
Captures on Land and Water;

To raise and support Armies, but no Appropriation of Money to that Use shall be
for a longer Term than two Years;

To provide and maintain a Navy;

To make Rules for the Government and Regulation of the land and naval Forces;

To provide for calling forth the Militia to execute the Laws of the Union,
suppress Insurrections and repel Invasions;

To provide for organizing, arming, and disciplining the Militia, and for
governing such Part of them as may be employed in the Service of the United
States, reserving to the States respectively, the Appointment of the Officers,
and the Authority of training the Militia according to the discipline
prescribed by Congress;

To exercise exclusive Legislation in all Cases whatsoever, over such District
(not exceeding ten Miles square) as may, by Cession of particular States, and
the acceptance of Congress, become the Seat of the Government of the United
States, and to exercise like Authority over all Places purchased by the Consent
of the Legislature of the State in which the Same shall be, for the Erection of
Forts, Magazines, Arsenals, dock-Yards, and other needful Buildings; And

To make all Laws which shall be necessary and proper for carrying into
Execution the foregoing Powers, and all other Powers vested by this
Constitution in the Government of the United States, or in any Department or
Officer thereof.

===Section 9===
The Migration or Importation of such Persons as any of the States now existing
shall think proper to admit, shall not be prohibited by the Congress prior to
the Year one thousand eight hundred and eight, but a tax or duty may be imposed
on such Importation, not exceeding ten dollars for each Person.

The privilege of the Writ of Habeas Corpus shall not be suspended, unless when
in Cases of Rebellion or Invasion the public Safety may require it.

No Bill of Attainder or ex post facto Law shall be passed.

&lt;b&gt;No capitation, or other direct, Tax shall be laid, unless in Proportion to the
Census or Enumeration herein before directed to be taken.&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;[Modified by Amendment XVI]&lt;/i&gt;

No Tax or Duty shall be laid on Articles exported from any State.

No Preference shall be given by any Regulation of Commerce or Revenue to the
Ports of one State over those of another: nor shall Vessels bound to, or from,
one State, be obliged to enter, clear, or pay Duties in another.

No Money shall be drawn from the Treasury, but in Consequence of Appropriations
made by Law; and a regular Statement and Account of the Receipts and
Expenditures of all public Money shall be published from time to time.

No Title of Nobility shall be granted by the United States: And no Person
holding any Office of Profit or Trust under them, shall, without the Consent of
the Congress, accept of any present, Emolument, Office, or Title, of any kind
whatever, from any King, Prince or foreign State.

===Section 10===
No State shall enter into any Treaty, Alliance, or Confederation; grant Letters
of Marque and Reprisal; coin Money; emit Bills of Credit; make any Thing but
gold and silver Coin a Tender in Payment of Debts; pass any Bill of Attainder,
ex post facto Law, or Law impairing the Obligation of Contracts, or grant any
Title of Nobility.

No State shall, without the Consent of the Congress, lay any Imposts or Duties
on Imports or Exports, except what may be absolutely necessary for executing
it's inspection Laws: and the net Produce of all Duties and Imposts, laid by
any State on Imports or Exports, shall be for the Use of the Treasury of the
United States; and all such Laws shall be subject to the Revision and Controul
of the Congress.

No State shall, without the Consent of Congress, lay any duty of Tonnage, keep
Troops, or Ships of War in time of Peace, enter into any Agreement or Compact
with another State, or with a foreign Power, or engage in War, unless actually
invaded, or in such imminent Danger as will not admit of delay.

==Article II==

===Section 1===
The executive Power shall be vested in a President of the United States of
America. He shall hold his Office during the Term of four Years, and, together
with the Vice-President chosen for the same Term, be elected, as follows:

Each State shall appoint, in such Manner as the Legislature thereof may direct,
a Number of Electors, equal to the whole Number of Senators and Representatives
to which the State may be entitled in the Congress: but no Senator or
Representative, or Person holding an Office of Trust or Profit under the United
States, shall be appointed an Elector.

The Electors shall meet in their respective States, and vote by Ballot for two
persons, of whom one at least shall not lie an Inhabitant of the same State
with themselves. And they shall make a List of all the Persons voted for, and
of the Number of Votes for each; which List they shall sign and certify, and
transmit sealed to the Seat of the Government of the United States, directed to
the President of the Senate. The President of the Senate shall, in the Presence
of the Senate and House of Representatives, open all the Certificates, and the
Votes shall then be counted. The Person having the greatest Number of Votes
shall be the President, if such Number be a Majority of the whole Number of
Electors appointed; and if there be more than one who have such Majority, and
have an equal Number of Votes, then the House of Representatives shall
immediately chuse by Ballot one of them for President; and if no Person have a
Majority, then from the five highest on the List the said House shall in like
Manner chuse the President. But in chusing the President, the Votes shall be
taken by States, the Representation from each State having one Vote; a quorum
for this Purpose shall consist of a Member or Members from two-thirds of the
States, and a Majority of all the States shall be necessary to a Choice. In
every Case, after the Choice of the President, the Person having the greatest
Number of Votes of the Electors shall be the Vice President. But if there
should remain two or more who have equal Votes, the Senate shall chuse from
them by Ballot the Vice-President.

The Congress may determine the Time of chusing the Electors, and the Day on
which they shall give their Votes; which Day shall be the same throughout the
United States.

No person except a natural born Citizen, or a Citizen of the United States, at
the time of the Adoption of this Constitution, shall be eligible to the Office
of President; neither shall any Person be eligible to that Office who shall not
have attained to the Age of thirty-five Years, and been fourteen Years a
Resident within the United States.

In Case of the Removal of the President from Office, or of his Death,
Resignation, or Inability to discharge the Powers and Duties of the said
Office, the same shall devolve on the Vice President, and the Congress may by
Law provide for the Case of Removal, Death, Resignation or Inability, both of
the President and Vice President, declaring what Officer shall then act as
President, and such Officer shall act accordingly, until the Disability be
removed, or a President shall be elected.

The President shall, at stated Times, receive for his Services, a Compensation,
which shall neither be increased nor diminished during the Period for which he
shall have been elected, and he shall not receive within that Period any other
Emolument from the United States, or any of them.

Before he enter on the Execution of his Office, he shall take the following
Oath or Affirmation:

&quot;I do solemnly swear (or affirm) that I will faithfully execute the Office of
President of the United States, and will to the best of my Ability, preserve,
protect and defend the Constitution of the United States.&quot;

===Section 2===
The President shall be Commander in Chief of the Army and Navy of the United
States, and of the Militia of the several States, when called into the actual
Service of the United States; he may require the Opinion, in writing, of the
principal Officer in each of the executive Departments, upon any subject
relating to the Duties of their respective Offices, and he shall have Power to
Grant Reprieves and Pardons for Offenses against the United States, except in
Cases of Impeachment.

He shall have Power, by and with the Advice and Consent of the Senate, to make
Treaties, provided two thirds of the Senators present concur; and he shall
nominate, and by and with the Advice and Consent of the Senate, shall appoint
Ambassadors, other public Ministers and Consuls, Judges of the supreme Court,
and all other Officers of the United States, whose Appointments are not herein
otherwise provided for, and which shall be established by Law: but the Congress
may by Law vest the Appointment of such inferior Officers, as they think
proper, in the President alone, in the Courts of Law, or in the Heads of
Departments.

The President shall have Power to fill up all Vacancies that may happen during
the Recess of the Senate, by granting Commissions which shall expire at the End
of their next Session.

===Section 3===
He shall from time to time give to the Congress Information of the State of the
Union, and recommend to their Consideration such Measures as he shall judge
necessary and expedient; he may, on extraordinary Occasions, convene both
Houses, or either of them, and in Case of Disagreement between them, with
Respect to the Time of Adjournment, he may adjourn them to such Time as he
shall think proper; he shall receive Ambassadors and other public Ministers; he
shall take Care that the Laws be faithfully executed, and shall Commission all
the Officers of the United States.

===Section 4===
The President, Vice President and all civil Officers of the United States,
shall be removed from Office on Impeachment for, and Conviction of, Treason,
Bribery, or other high Crimes and Misdemeanors.

==Article III==

===Section 1===
The judicial Power of the United States, shall be vested in one supreme Court,
and in such inferior Courts as the Congress may from time to time ordain and
establish. The Judges, both of the supreme and inferior Courts, shall hold
their Offices during good Behavior, and shall, at stated Times, receive for
their Services a Compensation which shall not be diminished during their
Continuance in Office.

===Section 2===
The judicial Power shall extend to all Cases, in Law and Equity, arising under
this Constitution, the Laws of the United States, and Treaties made, or which
shall be made, under their Authority; to all Cases affecting Ambassadors, other
public Ministers and Consuls; to all Cases of admiralty and maritime
Jurisdiction; to Controversies to which the United States shall be a Party; to
Controversies between two or more States; between a State and Citizens of
another State; between Citizens of different States; between Citizens of the
same State claiming Lands under Grants of different States, and between a
State, or the Citizens thereof, and foreign States, Citizens or Subjects.

In all Cases affecting Ambassadors, other public Ministers and Consuls, and
those in which a State shall be Party, the supreme Court shall have original
Jurisdiction. In all the other Cases before mentioned, the supreme Court shall
have appellate Jurisdiction, both as to Law and Fact, with such Exceptions, and
under such Regulations as the Congress shall make.

The Trial of all Crimes, except in Cases of Impeachment, shall be by Jury; and
such Trial shall be held in the State where the said Crimes shall have been
committed; but when not committed within any State, the Trial shall be at such
Place or Places as the Congress may by Law have directed.

===Section 3===
Treason against the United States, shall consist only in levying War against
them, or in adhering to their Enemies, giving them Aid and Comfort. No Person
shall be convicted of Treason unless on the Testimony of two Witnesses to the
same overt Act, or on Confession in open Court.

The Congress shall have power to declare the Punishment of Treason, but no
Attainder of Treason shall work Corruption of Blood, or Forfeiture except
during the Life of the Person attainted.

==Article IV==

===Section 1===
Full Faith and Credit shall be given in each State to the public Acts, Records,
and judicial Proceedings of every other State. And the Congress may by general
Laws prescribe the Manner in which such Acts, Records and Proceedings shall be
proved, and the Effect thereof.

===Section 2===
The Citizens of each State shall be entitled to all Privileges and Immunities
of Citizens in the several States.

A Person charged in any State with Treason, Felony, or other Crime, who shall
flee from Justice, and be found in another State, shall on demand of the
executive Authority of the State from which he fled, be delivered up, to be
removed to the State having Jurisdiction of the Crime.

No Person held to Service or Labour in one State, under the Laws thereof,
escaping into another, shall, in Consequence of any Law or Regulation therein,
be discharged from such Service or Labour, But shall be delivered up on Claim
of the Party to whom such Service or Labour may be due.

===Section 3===
New States may be admitted by the Congress into this Union; but no new States
shall be formed or erected within the Jurisdiction of any other State; nor any
State be formed by the Junction of two or more States, or parts of States,
without the Consent of the Legislatures of the States concerned as well as of
the Congress.

The Congress shall have Power to dispose of and make all needful Rules and
Regulations respecting the Territory or other Property belonging to the United
States; and nothing in this Constitution shall be so construed as to Prejudice
any Claims of the United States, or of any particular State.

===Section 4===
The United States shall guarantee to every State in this Union a Republican
Form of Government, and shall protect each of them against Invasion; and on
Application of the Legislature, or of the Executive (when the Legislature
cannot be convened) against domestic Violence.

==Article V==

The Congress, whenever two thirds of both Houses shall deem it necessary, shall
propose Amendments to this Constitution, or, on the Application of the
Legislatures of two thirds of the several States, shall call a Convention for
proposing Amendments, which, in either Case, shall be valid to all Intents and
Purposes, as part of this Constitution, when ratified by the Legislatures of
three fourths of the several States, or by Conventions in three fourths
thereof, as the one or the other Mode of Ratification may be proposed by the
Congress; Provided that no Amendment which may be made prior to the Year One
thousand eight hundred and eight shall in any Manner affect the first and
fourth Clauses in the Ninth Section of the first Article; and that no State,
without its Consent, shall be deprived of its equal Suffrage in the Senate.

==Article VI==

All Debts contracted and Engagements entered into, before the Adoption of this
Constitution, shall be as valid against the United States under this
Constitution, as under the Confederation.

This Constitution, and the Laws of the United States which shall be made in
Pursuance thereof; and all Treaties made, or which shall be made, under the
Authority of the United States, shall be the supreme Law of the Land; and the
Judges in every State shall be bound thereby, any Thing in the Constitution or
Laws of any State to the Contrary notwithstanding.

The Senators and Representatives before mentioned, and the Members of the
several State Legislatures, and all executive and judicial Officers, both of
the United States and of the several States, shall be bound by Oath or
Affirmation, to support this Constitution; but no religious Test shall ever be
required as a Qualification to any Office or public Trust under the United
States.

==Article VII==

The Ratification of the Conventions of nine States, shall be sufficient for the
Establishment of this Constitution between the States so ratifying the Same.

Done in Convention by the Unanimous Consent of the States present the
Seventeenth Day of September in the Year of our Lord one thousand seven hundred
and Eighty seven and of the Independence of the United States of America the
Twelfth. In Witness whereof We have hereunto subscribed our Names.

[Signatures Omitted]

==Amendment I==
Congress shall make no law respecting an establishment of religion, or
prohibiting the free exercise thereof; or abridging the freedom of speech, or of the press; or the right of the People peaceably to assemble, and to petition
the Government for a redress of grievances.

''Ratified December 15, 1791''

==Amendment II==
A well regulated Militia, being necessary to the security of a free State, the
right of the people to keep and bear Arms, shall not be infringed. 

''Ratified December 15, 1791''

==Amendment III==
No Soldier shall, in time of peace be quartered in any house, without the
consent of the Owner, nor in time of war, but in a manner to be prescribed by
law. 

''Ratified December 15, 1791''

==Amendment IV==
The right of the people to be secure in their persons, houses, papers, and
effects, against unreasonable searches and seizures, shall not be violated, and
no Warrants shall issue, but upon probable cause, supported by Oath or
affirmation, and particularly describing the place to be searched, and the
persons or things to be seized. 

''Ratified December 15, 1791''

==Amendment V==
No person shall be held to answer for a capital, or otherwise infamous crime,
unless on a presentment or indictment of a Grand Jury, except in cases arising
in the land or naval forces, or in the Militia, when in actual service in time
of War or public danger; nor shall any person be subject for the same offense
to be twice put in jeopardy of life or limb; nor shall be compelled in any
criminal case to be a witness against himself, nor be deprived of life,
liberty, or property, without due process of law; nor shall private property be
taken for public use, without just compensation. 

''Ratified December 15, 1791''

==Amendment VI==
In all criminal prosecutions, the accused shall enjoy the right to a speedy and
public trial, by an impartial jury of the State and district wherein the crime
shall have been committed, which district shall have been previously
ascertained by law, and to be informed of the nature and cause of the
accusation; to be confronted with the witnesses against him; to have compulsory
process for obtaining witnesses in his favor, and to have the Assistance of
Counsel for his defence. 

''Ratified December 15, 1791''

==Amendment VII==
In Suits at common law, where the value in controversy shall exceed twenty
dollars, the right of trial by jury shall be preserved, and no fact tried by a
jury, shall be otherwise re-examined in any Court of the United States, than
according to the rules of the common law. 

''Ratified December 15, 1791''

==Amendment VIII==
Excessive bail shall not be required, nor excessive fines imposed, nor cruel
and unusual punishments inflicted. 

''Ratified December 15, 1791''

==Amendment IX==
The enumeration in the Constitution, of certain rights, shall not be construed
to deny or disparage others retained by the people. 

''Ratified December 15, 1791''

==Amendment X==
The powers not delegated to the United States by the Constitution, nor
prohibited by it to the States, are reserved to the States respectively, or to
the people. 

''Ratified December 15, 1791''

==Amendment XI==
The Judicial power of the United States shall not be construed to extend to any
suit in law or equity, commenced or prosecuted against one of the United States
by Citizens of another State, or by Citizens or Subjects of any Foreign State. 

''Ratified February 7, 1795''

==Amendment XII==
The Electors shall meet in their respective states, and vote by ballot for
President and Vice-President, one of whom, at least, shall not be an inhabitant
of the same state with themselves; they shall name in their ballots the person
voted for as President, and in distinct ballots the person voted for as
Vice-President, and they shall make distinct lists of all persons voted for as
President, and of all persons voted for as Vice-President and of the number of
votes for each, which lists they shall sign and certify, and transmit sealed to
the seat of the government of the United States, directed to the President of
the Senate;

The President of the Senate shall, in the presence of the Senate and House of
Representatives, open all the certificates and the votes shall then be counted;

The person having the greatest Number of votes for President, shall be the
President, if such number be a majority of the whole number of Electors
appointed; and if no person have such majority, then from the persons having
the highest numbers not exceeding three on the list of those voted for as
President, the House of Representatives shall choose immediately, by ballot,
the President. But in choosing the President, the votes shall be taken by
states, the representation from each state having one vote; a quorum for this
purpose shall consist of a member or members from two-thirds of the states, and
a majority of all the states shall be necessary to a choice. And if the House
of Representatives shall not choose a President whenever the right of choice
shall devolve upon them, before the fourth day of March next following, then
the Vice-President shall act as President, as in the case of the death or other
constitutional disability of the President.

The person having the greatest number of votes as Vice-President, shall be the
Vice-President, if such number be a majority of the whole number of Electors
appointed, and if no person have a majority, then from the two highest numbers
on the list, the Senate shall choose the Vice-President; a quorum for the
purpose shall consist of two-thirds of the whole number of Senators, and a
majority of the whole number shall be necessary to a choice. But no person
constitutionally ineligible to the office of President shall be eligible to
that of Vice-President of the United States. 

''Ratified June 15, 1804''

==Amendment XIII==

===Section 1===
Neither slavery nor involuntary servitude, except as a punishment for crime
whereof the party shall have been duly convicted, shall exist within the United
States &amp; all of its territories, or any place subject to their jurisdiction.

===Section 2===
Congress shall have power to enforce this article by appropriate
legislation. 

''Ratified December 6, 1865''

==Amendment XIV==

===Section 1===
All persons born or naturalized in the United States, and subject to the
jurisdiction thereof, are citizens of the United States and of the State
wherein they reside. No State shall make or enforce any law which shall abridge
the privileges or immunities of citizens of the United States; nor shall any
State deprive any person of life, liberty, or property, without due process of
law; nor deny to any person within its jurisdiction the equal protection of the
laws.

===Section 2===
Representatives shall be apportioned among the several States according to
their respective numbers, counting the whole number of persons in each State,
excluding Indians not taxed. But when the right to vote at any election for the
choice of electors for President and Vice-President of the United States,
Representatives in Congress, the Executive and Judicial officers of a State, or
the members of the Legislature thereof, is denied to any of the male
inhabitants of such State, being twenty-one years of age, and citizens of the
United States, or in any way abridged, except for participation in rebellion,
or other crime, the basis of representation therein shall be reduced in the
proportion which the number of such male citizens shall bear to the whole
number of male citizens twenty-one years of age in such State.

===Section 3===
No person shall be a Senator or Representative in Congress, or elector of
President and Vice-President, or hold any office, civil or military, under the
United States, or under any State, who, having previously taken an oath, as a
member of Congress, or as an officer of the United States, or as a member of
any State legislature, or as an executive or judicial officer of any State, to
support the Constitution of the United States, shall have engaged in
insurrection or rebellion against the same, or given aid or comfort to the
enemies thereof. But Congress may by a vote of two-thirds of each House, remove
such disability.

===Section 4===
The validity of the public debt of the United States, authorized by law,
including debts incurred for payment of pensions and bounties for services in
suppressing insurrection or rebellion, shall not be questioned. But neither the
United States nor any State shall assume or pay any debt or obligation incurred
in aid of insurrection or rebellion against the United States, or any claim for
the loss or emancipation of any slave; but all such debts, obligations and
claims shall be held illegal and void.

===Section 5===
The Congress shall have power to enforce, by appropriate legislation, the
provisions of this article. 

''Ratified July 9, 1868''

==Amendment XV==

===Section 1===
The right of citizens of the United States to vote shall not be denied or
abridged by the United States or by any State on account of race, color, or
previous condition of servitude.

===Section 2===
The Congress shall have power to enforce this article by appropriate
legislation. 

''Ratified February 3, 1870''

==Amendment XVI==
The Congress shall have power to lay and collect taxes on incomes, from
whatever source derived, without apportionment among the several States, and
without regard to any census or enumeration.

''Ratified February 3, 1913''

==Amendment XVII==
The Senate of the United States shall be composed of two Senators from each
State, elected by the people thereof, for six years; and each Senator shall
have one vote. The electors in each State shall have the qualifications
requisite for electors of the most numerous branch of the State legislatures.

When vacancies happen in the representation of any State in the Senate, the
executive authority of such State shall issue writs of election to fill such
vacancies: Provided, That the legislature of any State may empower the
executive thereof to make temporary appointments until the people fill the
vacancies by election as the legislature may direct.

This amendment shall not be so construed as to affect the election or term of
any Senator chosen before it becomes valid as part of the Constitution. 

''Ratified April 8, 1913''

==Amendment XVIII==

===Section 1===
After one year from the ratification of this article the manufacture, sale,
or transportation of intoxicating liquors within, the importation thereof into,
or the exportation thereof from the United States and all territory subject to
the jurisdiction thereof for beverage purposes is hereby prohibited.

===Section 2===
The Congress and the several States shall have concurrent power to enforce
this article by appropriate legislation.

===Section 3===
This article shall be inoperative unless it shall have been ratified as an
amendment to the Constitution by the legislatures of the several States, as
provided in the Constitution, within seven years from the date of the
submission hereof to the States by the Congress.

''Ratified January 16, 1919.  Repealed by Amendment XXI December 5, 1933''

==Amendment XIX==
The right of citizens of the United States to vote shall not be denied or
abridged by the United States or by any State on account of sex.

Congress shall have power to enforce this article by appropriate legislation.

''Ratified August 18, 1920''

==Amendment XX==

===Section 1===
The terms of the President and Vice President shall end at noon on the 20th
day of January, and the terms of Senators and Representatives at noon on the 3d
day of January, of the years in which such terms would have ended if this
article had not been ratified; and the terms of their successors shall then
begin.

===Section 2===
The Congress shall assemble at least once in every year, and such meeting
shall begin at noon on the 3rd day of January, unless they shall by law appoint
a different day.

===Section 3===
If, at the time fixed for the beginning of the term of the President, the
President elect shall have died, the Vice President elect shall become
President. If a President shall not have been chosen before the time fixed for
the beginning of his term, or if the President elect shall have failed to
qualify, then the Vice President elect shall act as President until a President
shall have qualified; and the Congress may by law provide for the case wherein
neither a President elect nor a Vice President elect shall have qualified,
declaring who shall then act as President, or the manner in which one who is to
act shall be selected, and such person shall act accordingly until a President
or Vice President shall have qualified.

===Section 4===
The Congress may by law provide for the case of the death of any of the
persons from whom the House of Representatives may choose a President whenever
the right of choice shall have devolved upon them, and for the case of the
death of any of the persons from whom the Senate may choose a Vice President
whenever the right of choice shall have devolved upon them.

===Section 5===
Sections 1 and 2 shall take effect on the 15th day of October following the
ratification of this article.

===Section 6===
This article shall be inoperative unless it shall have been ratified as an
amendment to the Constitution by the legislatures of three-fourths of the
several States within seven years from the date of its submission.

''Ratified January 23, 1933''

==Amendment XXI==

===Section 1===
The eighteenth article of amendment to the Constitution of the United States
is hereby repealed.

===Section 2===
The transportation or importation into any State, Territory, or possession
of the United States for delivery or use therein of intoxicating liquors, in
violation of the laws thereof, is hereby prohibited.

===Section 3===
The article shall be inoperative unless it shall have been ratified as an
amendment to the Constitution by conventions in the several States, as provided
in the Constitution, within seven years from the date of the submission hereof
to the States by the Congress.

''Ratified December 5, 1933''

==Amendment XXII==

===Section 1===
No person shall be elected to the office of the President more than twice,
and no person who has held the office of President, or acted as President, for
more than two years of a term to which some other person was elected President
shall be elected to the office of the President more than once. But this
Article shall not apply to any person holding the office of President, when this Article was proposed by the Congress, and shall not prevent any person who may be holding the office of President, or acting as President, during the term within which this Article becomes operative from holding the office of
President or acting as President during the remainder of such term.

===Section 2===
This article shall be inoperative unless it shall have been ratified as an
amendment to the Constitution by the legislatures of three-fourths of the
several States within seven years from the date of its submission to the States
by the Congress.

''Ratified February 27, 1951''

==Amendment XXIII==

===Section 1===
The District constituting the seat of Government of the United States shall
appoint in such manner as the Congress may direct: A number of electors of
President and Vice President equal to the whole number of Senators and
Representatives in Congress to which the District would be entitled if it were
a State, but in no event more than the least populous State; they shall be in
addition to those appointed by the States, but they shall be considered, for
the purposes of the election of President and Vice President, to be electors
appointed by a State; and they shall meet in the District and perform such
duties as provided by the twelfth article of amendment.

===Section 2===
The Congress shall have power to enforce this article by appropriate
legislation.

''Ratified March 29, 1961''

==Amendment XXIV==

===Section 1===
The right of citizens of the United States to vote in any primary or other
election for President or Vice President, for electors for President or
Vice President, or for Senator or Representative in Congress, shall not be
denied or abridged by the United States or any State by reason of failure to
pay any poll tax or other tax.

===Section 2===
The Congress shall have power to enforce this article by appropriate
legislation.

''Ratified January 23, 1964''

==Amendment XXV==

===Section 1===
In case of the removal of the President from office or of his death or
resignation, the Vice President shall become President.

===Section 2===
Whenever there is a vacancy in the office of the Vice President, the
President shall nominate a Vice President who shall take office upon
confirmation by a majority vote of both Houses of Congress.

===Section 3===
Whenever the President transmits to the President pro tempore of the Senate
and the Speaker of the House of Representatives his written declaration that he
is unable to discharge the powers and duties of his office, and until he
transmits to them a written declaration to the contrary, such powers and duties
shall be discharged by the Vice President as Acting President.

===Section 4===
Whenever the Vice President and a majority of either the principal officers
of the executive departments or of such other body as Congress may by law
provide, transmit to the President pro tempore of the Senate and the Speaker of
the House of Representatives their written declaration that the President is
unable to discharge the powers and duties of his office, the Vice President
shall immediately assume the powers and duties of the office as Acting
President.

Thereafter, when the President transmits to the President pro tempore of the
Senate and the Speaker of the House of Representatives his written declaration
that no inability exists, he shall resume the powers and duties of his office
unless the Vice President and a majority of either the principal officers of
the executive department or of such other body as Congress may by law provide,
transmit within four days to the President pro tempore of the Senate and the
Speaker of the House of Representatives their written declaration that the
President is unable to discharge the powers and duties of his office. Thereupon
Congress shall decide the issue, assembling within forty eight hours for that
purpose if not in session. If the Congress, within twenty one days after
receipt of the latter written declaration, or, if Congress is not in session,
within twenty one days after Congress is required to assemble, determines by
two thirds vote of both Houses that the President is unable to discharge the
powers and duties of his office, the Vice President shall continue to discharge
the same as Acting President; otherwise, the President shall resume the powers
and duties of his office.

''Ratified February 10, 1967''

==Amendment XXVI==

===Section 1===
The right of citizens of the United States, who are eighteen years of age or
older, to vote shall not be denied or abridged by the United States or by any
State on account of age.

===Section 2===
The Congress shall have power to enforce this article by appropriate
legislation.

''Ratified July 1, 1971''

==Amendment XXVII==
No law, varying the compensation for the services of the Senators and
Representatives, shall take effect, until an election of Representatives shall
have intervened.

''Ratified May 7, 1992''

----
{{USConstitionAndGovtTOC}}

[[Category:United States Government]]</text>
      <sha1>dqfzem6ozi5haiz541ct5h250deijg5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>United States Government/The Declaration of Independence</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1297</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1050303</id>
      <parentid>1050301</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-12-10T01:43:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mike.lifeguard</username>
        <id>55262</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edit of [[Special:Contributions/76.103.88.161|76.103.88.161]], changed back to last version by Az1568</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{USConstitionAndGovtTOC}}
----
In Congress, July 4, 1776

The unanimous Declaration of the thirteen united States of America

When in the Course of human events, it becomes necessary for one people to dissolve the political bands which have connected them with another, and to assume among the powers of the earth, the separate and equal station to which the Laws of Nature and of Nature's God entitle them, a decent respect to the opinions of mankind requires that they should declare the causes which impel them to the separation.

We hold these truths to be self-evident, that all men are created equal, that they are endowed by their Creator with certain unalienable Rights, that among these are Life, Liberty and the pursuit of Happiness. That to secure these rights, Governments are instituted among Men, deriving their just Powers from the consent of the governed, -- That whenever any Form of Government becomes destructive of these ends, it is the Right of the People to alter or to abolish it, and to institute new Government, laying its foundation on such principles and organizing its powers in such form, as to them shall seem most likely to effect their Safety and Happiness. Prudence, indeed, will dictate that Governments long established should not be changed for light and transient causes; and accordingly all experience hath shewn, that mankind are more disposed to suffer, while evils are sufferable, than to right themselves by abolishing the forms to which they are accustomed. But when a long train of abuses and usurpations, pursuing invariably the same Object evinces a design to reduce them under absolute Despotism, it is their right, it is their duty, to throw off such Government, and to provide new guards for their future security -- Such has been the patient sufferance of these Colonies; and such is now the necessity which constrains them to alter their former Systems of Government. -- The history of the present King of Great Britain is a history of repeated injuries and usurpations, all having in direct object the establishment of an absolute Tyranny over these States. To prove this, let facts be submitted to a candid world.

He has refused his Assent to Laws, the most wholesome and necessary for the public good.

He has forbidden his Governors to pass Laws of immediate and pressing importance, unless suspended in their operation till his Assent should be obtained; and when so suspended, he has utterly neglected to attend to them.

He has refused to pass other Laws for the accommodation of large districts of people, unless those people would relinquish the right of Representation in the Legislature, a right inestimable to them and formidable to tyrants only.

He has called together legislative bodies at places unusual, uncomfortable, and distant from the depository of their Public Records, for the sole purpose of fatiguing them into compliance with his measures.

He has dissolved Representative Houses repeatedly, for opposing with manly firmness his invasions on the rights of the people.

He has refused for a long time, after such dissolutions, to cause others to be elected; whereby the Legislative Powers, incapable of Annihilation, have returned to the People at large for their exercise; the State remaining in the mean time exposed to all the dangers of invasion from without, and convulsions within.

He has endeavoured to prevent the population of these States; for that purpose obstructing the Laws for Naturalization of Foreigners; refusing to pass others to encourage their migrations hither, and raising the conditions of new Appropriations of Lands.

He has obstructed the Administration of Justice, by refusing his Assent to Laws for establishing Judiciary Powers.

He has made Judges dependent on his Will alone, for the tenure of their offices, and the amount and payment of their salaries.

He has erected a multitude of New Offices, and sent hither swarms of Officers to harrass our People, and eat out their substance.

He has kept among us, in times of peace, Standing Armies without the Consent of our legislatures.

He has affected to render the Military independent of and superior to the Civil Power.

He has combined with others to subject us to a jurisdiction foreign to our constitution, and unacknowledged by our laws; giving his Assent to their Acts of pretended Legislation:

For Quartering large bodies of armed troops among us:

For protecting them, by a mock Trial, from Punishment for any Murders which they should commit on the Inhabitants of these States:

For cutting off our Trade with all parts of the world:

For imposing Taxes on us without our Consent:

For depriving us in many cases, of the benefits of Trial by Jury:

For transporting us beyond seas to be tried for pretended offences:

For abolishing the free system of English Laws in a neighbouring Province, establishing therein an Arbitrary government, and enlarging its Boundaries so as to render it at once an example and fit instrument for introducing the same absolute rule into these Colonies:

For taking away our Charters, abolishing our most valuable Laws, and altering fundamentally the forms of our Governments:

For suspending our own Legislature, and declaring themselves invested with power to legislate for us in all cases whatsoever.

He has abdicated Government here, by declaring us out of his Protection and waging War against us.

He has plundered our seas, ravaged our Coasts, burnt our towns, and destroyed the lives of our people.

He is at this time transporting large Armies of foreign Mercenaries to compleat the works of death, desolation and tyranny, already begun with circumstances of Cruelty and perfidy scarcely paralleled in the most barbarous ages, and totally unworthy the Head of a civilized nation.

He has constrained our fellow Citizens taken Captive on the high Seas to bear Arms against their Country, to become the executioners of their friends and Brethren, or to fall themselves by their Hands.

He has excited domestic insurrections amongst us, and has endeavoured to bring on the inhabitants of our frontiers, the merciless Indian Savages, whose known rule of warfare, is an undistinguished destruction of all ages, sexes and conditions.

In every stage of these Oppressions we have Petitioned for Redress in the most humble terms: Our repeated Petitions have been answered only by repeated injury. A Prince, whose character is thus marked by every act which may define a Tyrant, is unfit to be the ruler of a free people.

Nor have we been wanting in attention to our British brethren. We have warned them from time to time of attempts by their legislature to extend an unwarrantable jurisdiction over us. We have reminded them of the circumstances of our emigration and settlement here. We have appealed to their native justice and magnanimity, and we have conjured them by the ties of our common kindred to disavow these usurpations, which, would inevitably interrupt our connections and correspondence. They too have been deaf to the voice of justice and of consanguinity. We must, therefore, acquiesce in the necessity, which denounces our Separation, and hold them, as we hold the rest of mankind, Enemies in War, in Peace Friends.

We, therefore, the Representatives of the united States of America, in General Congress, Assembled, appealing to the Supreme Judge of the world for the rectitude of our intentions, do, in the Name, and by Authority of the good People of these Colonies, solemnly publish and declare, That these United Colonies are, and of Right ought to be Free and Independent States; that they are absolved from all Allegiance to the British Crown, and that all political connection between them and the State of Great Britain, is and ought to be totally dissolved; and that as Free and Independent States, they have full Power to levy War, conclude Peace, contract Alliances, establish Commerce, and to do all other Acts and Things which Independent States may of right do.

And for the support of this Declaration, with a firm reliance on the protection of Divine Providence, we mutually pledge to each other our Lives, our Fortunes and our sacred Honor.

[Signatures Omitted]
----
{{USConstitionAndGovtTOC}}

[[Category:United States Government]]</text>
      <sha1>pvezi44tsyq4vx8apcpuhwjjies9kks</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>United States Government/The Articles of Confederation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1298</id>
    <revision>
      <id>541638</id>
      <parentid>393104</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-07-30T17:31:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{USConstitionAndGovtTOC}}
----

==Preamble==

To all to whom these Presents shall come, we the undersigned Delegates of the States affixed to our Names send greeting.

Articles of Confederation and perpetual Union between the States of New Hampshire, Massachusetts bay, Rhode Island and Providence Plantations, Connecticut, New York, New Jersey, Pennsylvania, Delaware, Maryland, Virginia, North Carolina, South Carolina and Georgia.

==Article I==

The Stile of this Confederacy shall be &quot;The United States of America.&quot;

~~Article II~~

Each state retains its sovereignty, freedom, and independence, and every power, jurisdiction, and right, which is not by this Confederation expressly delegated to the United States, in Congress assembled.

~~Article III~~

The said States hereby severally enter into a firm league of friendship with each other, for their common defense, the security of their liberties, and their mutual and general welfare, binding themselves to assist each other, against all force offered to, or attacks made upon them, or any of them, on account of religion, sovereignty, trade, or any other pretense whatever.

==Article IV==

The better to secure and perpetuate mutual friendship and intercourse among the people of the different States in this Union, the free inhabitants of each of these States, paupers, vagabonds, and fugitives from justice excepted, shall be entitled to all privileges and immunities of free citizens in the several States; and the people of each State shall free ingress and regress to and from any other State, and shall enjoy therein all the privileges of trade and commerce, subject to the same duties, impositions, and restrictions as the inhabitants thereof respectively, provided that such restrictions shall not extend so far as to prevent the removal of property imported into any State, to any other State, of which the owner is an inhabitant; provided also that no imposition, duties or restriction shall be laid by any State, on the property of the United States, or either of them.

If any person guilty of, or charged with, treason, felony, or other high misdemeanor in any State, shall flee from justice, and be found in any of the United States, he shall, upon demand of the Governor or executive power of the State from which he fled, be delivered up and removed to the State having jurisdiction of his offense.

Full faith and credit shall be given in each of these States to the records, acts, and judicial proceedings of the courts and magistrates of every other State.

==Article V==

For the most convenient management of the general interests of the United States, delegates shall be annually appointed in such manner as the legislatures of each State shall direct, to meet in Congress on the first Monday in November, in every year, with a power reserved to each State to recall its delegates, or any of them, at any time within the year, and to send others in their stead for the remainder of the year.

No State shall be represented in Congress by less than two, nor more than seven members; and no person shall be capable of being a delegate for more than three years in any term of six years; nor shall any person, being a delegate, be capable of holding any office under the United States, for which he, or another for his benefit, receives any salary, fees or emolument of any kind.

Each State shall maintain its own delegates in a meeting of the States, and while they act as members of the committee of the States.

In determining questions in the United States in Congress assembled, each State shall have one vote.

Freedom of speech and debate in Congress shall not be impeached or questioned in any court or place out of Congress, and the members of Congress shall be protected in their persons from arrests or imprisonments, during the time of their going to and from, and attendance on Congress, except for treason, felony, or breach of the peace.

==Article VI==

No State, without the consent of the United States in Congress assembled, shall send any embassy to, or receive any embassy from, or enter into any conference, agreement, alliance or treaty with any King, Prince or State; nor shall any person holding any office of profit or trust under the United States, or any of them, accept any present, emolument, office or title of any kind whatever from any King, Prince or foreign State; nor shall the United States in Congress assembled, or any of them, grant any title of nobility.

No two or more States shall enter into any treaty, confederation or alliance whatever between them, without the consent of the United States in Congress assembled, specifying accurately the purposes for which the same is to be entered into, and how long it shall continue.

No State shall lay any imposts or duties, which may interfere with any stipulations in treaties, entered into by the United States in Congress assembled, with any King, Prince or State, in pursuance of any treaties already proposed by Congress, to the courts of France and Spain.

No vessel of war shall be kept up in time of peace by any State, except such number only, as shall be deemed necessary by the United States in Congress assembled, for the defense of such State, or its trade; nor shall any body of forces be kept up by any State in time of peace, except such number only, as in the judgement of the United States in Congress assembled, shall be deemed requisite to garrison the forts necessary for the defense of such State; but every State shall always keep up a well-regulated and disciplined militia, sufficiently armed and accoutered, and shall provide and constantly have ready for use, in public stores, a due number of filed pieces and tents, and a proper quantity of arms, ammunition and camp equipage.

No State shall engage in any war without the consent of the United States in Congress assembled, unless such State be actually invaded by enemies, or shall have received certain advice of a resolution being formed by some nation of Indians to invade such State, and the danger is so imminent as not to admit of a delay till the United States in Congress assembled can be consulted; nor shall any State grant commissions to any ships or vessels of war, nor letters of marque or reprisal, except it be after a declaration of war by the United States in Congress assembled, and then only against the Kingdom or State and the subjects thereof, against which war has been so declared, and under such regulations as shall be established by the United States in Congress assembled, unless such State be infested by pirates, in which case vessels of war may be fitted out for that occasion, and kept so long as the danger shall continue, or until the United States in Congress assembled shall determine otherwise.

==Article VII==

When land forces are raised by any State for the common defense, all officers of or under the rank of colonel, shall be appointed by the legislature of each State respectively, by whom such forces shall be raised, or in such manner as such State shall direct, and all vacancies shall be filled up by the State which first made the appointment.

==Article VIII==

All charges of war, and all other expenses that shall be incurred for the common defense or general welfare, and allowed by the United States in Congress assembled, shall be defrayed out of a common treasury, which shall be supplied by the several States in proportion to the value of all land within each State, granted or surveyed for any person, as such land and the buildings and improvements thereon shall be estimated according to such mode as the United States in Congress assembled, shall from time to time direct and appoint.

The taxes for paying that proportion shall be laid and levied by the authority and direction of the legislatures of the several States within the time agreed upon by the United States in Congress assembled.

==Article IX==

The United States in Congress assembled, shall have the sole and exclusive right and power of determining on peace and war, except in the cases mentioned in the sixth article -- of sending and receiving ambassadors -- entering into treaties and alliances, provided that no treaty of commerce shall be made whereby the legislative power of the respective States shall be restrained from imposing such imposts and duties on foreigners, as their own people are subjected to, or from prohibiting the exportation or importation of any species of goods or commodities whatsoever -- of establishing rules for deciding in all cases, what captures on land or water shall be legal, and in what manner prizes taken by land or naval forces in the service of the United States shall be divided or appropriated -- of granting letters of marque and reprisal in times of peace -- appointing courts for the trial of piracies and felonies committed on the high seas and establishing courts for receiving and determining finally appeals in all cases of captures, provided that no member of Congress shall be appointed a judge of any of the said courts.

The United States in Congress assembled shall also be the last resort on appeal in all disputes and differences now subsisting or that hereafter may arise between two or more States concerning boundary, jurisdiction or any other causes whatever; which authority shall always be exercised in the manner following. Whenever the legislative or executive authority or lawful agent of any State in controversy with another shall present a petition to Congress stating the matter in question and praying for a hearing, notice thereof shall be given by order of Congress to the legislative or executive authority of the other State in controversy, and a day assigned for the appearance of the parties by their lawful agents, who shall then be directed to appoint by joint consent, commissioners or judges to constitute a court for hearing and determining the matter in question: but if they cannot agree, Congress shall name three persons out of each of the United States, and from the list of such persons each party shall alternately strike out one, the petitioners beginning, until the number shall be reduced to thirteen; and from that number not less than seven, nor more than nine names as Congress shall direct, shall in the presence of Congress be drawn out by lot, and the persons whose names shall be so drawn or any five of them, shall be commissioners or judges, to hear and finally determine the controversy, so always as a major part of the judges who shall hear the cause shall agree in the determination: and if either party shall neglect to attend at the day appointed, without showing reasons, which Congress shall judge sufficient, or being present shall refuse to strike, the Congress shall proceed to nominate three persons out of each State, and the secretary of Congress shall strike in behalf of such party absent or refusing; and the judgement and sentence of the court to be appointed, in the manner before prescribed, shall be final and conclusive; and if any of the parties shall refuse to submit to the authority of such court, or to appear or defend their claim or cause, the court shall nevertheless proceed to pronounce sentence, or judgement, which shall in like manner be final and decisive, the judgement or sentence and other proceedings being in either case transmitted to Congress, and lodged among the acts of Congress for the security of the parties concerned: provided that every commissioner, before he sits in judgement, shall take an oath to be administered by one of the judges of the supreme or superior court of the State, where the cause shall be tried, 'well and truly to hear and determine the matter in question, according to the best of his judgement, without favor, affection or hope of reward': provided also, that no State shall be deprived of territory for the benefit of the United States.

All controversies concerning the private right of soil claimed under different grants of two or more States, whose jurisdictions as they may respect such lands, and the States which passed such grants are adjusted, the said grants or either of them being at the same time claimed to have originated antecedent to such settlement of jurisdiction, shall on the petition of either party to the Congress of the United States, be finally determined as near as may be in the same manner as is before prescribed for deciding disputes respecting territorial jurisdiction between different States.

The United States in Congress assembled shall also have the sole and exclusive right and power of regulating the alloy and value of coin struck by their own authority, or by that of the respective States -- fixing the standards of weights and measures throughout the United States -- regulating the trade and managing all affairs with the Indians, not members of any of the States, provided that the legislative right of any State within its own limits be not infringed or violated -- establishing or regulating post offices from one State to another, throughout all the United States, and exacting such postage on the papers passing through the same as may be requisite to defray the expenses of the said office -- appointing all officers of the land forces, in the service of the United States, excepting regimental officers -- appointing all the officers of the naval forces, and commissioning all officers whatever in the service of the United States -- making rules for the government and regulation of the said land and naval forces, and directing their operations.

The United States in Congress assembled shall have authority to appoint a committee, to sit in the recess of Congress, to be denominated 'A Committee of the States', and to consist of one delegate from each State; and to appoint such other committees and civil officers as may be necessary for managing the general affairs of the United States under their direction -- to appoint one of their members to preside, provided that no person be allowed to serve in the office of president more than one year in any term of three years; to ascertain the necessary sums of money to be raised for the service of the United States, and to appropriate and apply the same for defraying the public expenses -- to borrow money, or emit bills on the credit of the United States, transmitting every half-year to the respective States an account of the sums of money so borrowed or emitted -- to build and equip a navy -- to agree upon the number of land forces, and to make requisitions from each State for its quota, in proportion to the number of white inhabitants in such State; which requisition shall be binding, and thereupon the legislature of each State shall appoint the regimental officers, raise the men and cloath, arm and equip them in a solid- like manner, at the expense of the United States; and the officers and men so cloathed, armed and equipped shall march to the place appointed, and within the time agreed on by the United States in Congress assembled. But if the United States in Congress assembled shall, on consideration of circumstances judge proper that any State should not raise men, or should raise a smaller number of men than the quota thereof, such extra number shall be raised, officered, cloathed, armed and equipped in the same manner as the quota of each State, unless the legislature of such State shall judge that such extra number cannot be safely spread out in the same, in which case they shall raise, officer, cloath, arm and equip as many of such extra number as they judge can be safely spared. And the officers and men so cloathed, armed, and equipped, shall march to the place appointed, and within the time agreed on by the United States in Congress assembled.

The United States in Congress assembled shall never engage in a war, nor grant letters of marque or reprisal in time of peace, nor enter into any treaties or alliances, nor coin money, nor regulate the value thereof, nor ascertain the sums and expenses necessary for the defense and welfare of the United States, or any of them, nor emit bills, nor borrow money on the credit of the United States, nor appropriate money, nor agree upon the number of vessels of war, to be built or purchased, or the number of land or sea forces to be raised, nor appoint a commander in chief of the army or navy, unless nine States assent to the same: nor shall a question on any other point, except for adjourning from day to day be determined, unless by the votes of the majority of the United States in Congress assembled.

The Congress of the United States shall have power to adjourn to any time within the year, and to any place within the United States, so that no period of adjournment be for a longer duration than the space of six months, and shall publish the journal of their proceedings monthly, except such parts thereof relating to treaties, alliances or military operations, as in their judgement require secrecy; and the yeas and nays of the delegates of each State on any question shall be entered on the journal, when it is desired by any delegates of a State, or any of them, at his or their request shall be furnished with a transcript of the said journal, except such parts as are above excepted, to lay before the legislatures of the several States.

==Article X==

The Committee of the States, or any nine of them, shall be authorized to execute, in the recess of Congress, such of the powers of Congress as the United States in Congress assembled, by the consent of the nine States, shall from time to time think expedient to vest them with; provided that no power be delegated to the said Committee, for the exercise of which, by the Articles of Confederation, the voice of nine States in the Congress of the United States assembled be requisite.

==Article XI==

Canada acceding to this confederation, and adjoining in the measures of the United States, shall be admitted into, and entitled to all the advantages of this Union; but no other colony shall be admitted into the same, unless such admission be agreed to by nine States.

==Article XII== 

All bills of credit emitted, monies borrowed, and debts contracted by, or under the authority of Congress, before the assembling of the United States, in pursuance of the present confederation, shall be deemed and considered as a charge against the United States, for payment and satisfaction whereof the said United States, and the public faith are hereby solemnly pledged.

==Article XIII==

Every State shall abide by the determination of the United States in Congress assembled, on all questions which by this confederation are submitted to them. And the Articles of this Confederation shall be inviolably observed by every State, and the Union shall be perpetual; nor shall any alteration at any time hereafter be made in any of them; unless such alteration be agreed to in a Congress of the United States, and be afterwards confirmed by the legislatures of every State.

==Conclusion==

And Whereas it hath pleased the Great Governor of the World to incline the hearts of the legislatures we respectively represent in Congress, to approve of, and to authorize us to ratify the said Articles of Confederation and perpetual Union. Know Ye that we the undersigned delegates, by virtue of the power and authority to us given for that purpose, do by these presents, in the name and in behalf of our respective constituents, fully and entirely ratify and confirm each and every of the said Articles of Confederation and perpetual Union, and all and singular the matters and things therein contained: And we do further solemnly plight and engage the faith of our respective constituents, that they shall abide by the determinations of the United States in Congress assembled, on all questions, which by the said Confederation are submitted to them. And that the Articles thereof shall be inviolably observed by the States we respectively represent, and that the Union shall be perpetual.

[Signatures Omitted]

----
{{USConstitionAndGovtTOC}}

[[Category:United States Government]]</text>
      <sha1>tvo3tv5hof6dk7r558jymkxgfw1118q</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>United States Government/The Later Amendments</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1299</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2618149</id>
      <parentid>2618145</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-03-18T13:43:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jianhui67</username>
        <id>1013809</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/168.184.14.11|168.184.14.11]] ([[User talk:168.184.14.11|talk]]) to last version by Savh</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{USConstitionAndGovtTOC}}
----

==Introduction==

Since the Bill of Rights, there have been seventeen Amendments to the Constitution.

==Eleventh Amendment==

When the Supreme Court decided ''Chisolm v. Georgia'', it frustrated the state of Georgia, which felt that the federal courts had no business meddling by ruling on a suit against a state. Other states, fearing similar actions against them, pushed for the Eleventh Amendment, which prohibited lawsuits against a state in Federal court unless the state concerned grants its consent.

==Twelfth Amendment==

The Twelfth Amendment fine-tuned the process for electing the President. [[United States Government/The Executive Branch#Elections|(See Part III, Chapter 2 for details.)]]

==Thirteenth Amendment==

The Thirteenth Amendment abolished slavery and involuntary servitude in the United States and all areas under its jurisdiction. The courts have ruled that involuntary servitude does not include duly convicted persons working on prison gangs.

==Fourteenth Amendment==

Amended in 1868, the [[w:Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]] served to extend much of the Bill of Rights to the states by requiring that &quot;No State shall make or enforce any law which shall abridge the privileges or immunities of citizens of the United States.&quot; It was essentially a reaffirmation that all citizens are considered equal regardless of race, which  Southern states had been subverting through &quot;Black Codes&quot;. A code might prevent voters from being able to cast a ballot unless they could read and write, which on the surface might sound reasonable. This was instead a way of keeping former slaves away from the polls because many were then illiterate. White illiteracy was assumed to be nonexistent, with those having difficulty being &quot;helped&quot;. 

Secondly, the Amendment provided that a state must follow the same due process requirements as the federal government.

Thirdly, the states were required to provide equal protection to all of its citizens- this clause intended to prevent discrimination against African-Americans, though it failed miserably in that regard.

Fourthly, it removed the original Constitutional requirement that &quot;other persons&quot; (slaves) count as three-fifths of a person when determining the official state population.

Fifthly, it required that a state's representation in Congress would be reduced if that state prohibited males over twenty-one from voting for a reason other than commission of a crime.

Sixthly, the Amendment prohibited any person who participates in a rebellion such as the Civil War from serving in government unless the Congress formally agrees, by a two-thirds vote in each house, to exempt the person from this requirement.

Seventhly, the Fourteenth required that any debts incurred by the Union (the North) during the Civil War were to be paid, but any debts incurred by a State of the Confederacy would be void. Furthermore, it provided that a former owner of slaves could not sue the government for the loss of his slaves.

==Fifteenth Amendment==
The Fifteenth Amendment took another barrier away from minorities right to vote by barring the creation of laws that barred someone from voting based on their color, race, or having been former slaves.

==Sixteenth Amendment==

The Sixteenth Amendment made Income Taxes constitutional. It was passed to resolve disputes regarding the matter. At one time, the Supreme Court ruled that the Tax was constitutional, while ruling at another time that it was not. All doubts were removed by the Sixteenth.

==Seventeenth Amendment==

The Seventeenth provided that the people of a state, and not the legislature, would be the electors of Senators. However, it retained the power of legislatures to temporarily fill vacancies until an election can be held.

==Eighteenth Amendment==

The Eighteenth Amendment created Prohibition, banning intoxicating liquors in the United States. It allowed both the federal and the state governments to concurrently legislate on the matter.

==Nineteenth Amendment==

The Nineteenth granted women the right to vote on an equal basis with men.

==Twentieth Amendment==

The Twentieth Amendment was known as the &quot;lame duck&quot; amendment.  According to the original constitution and the twelfth amendment, a newly elected president did not take office until March 4.  In the early days of the Republic, elections were held on different days in different jurisdictions, and travel and communication were slow.  By the 1930s, however, the election was uniformly held in early November, and the winner of a presidential election was usually apparent by the next morning.  This meant that a newly elected president had to wait four months take take office, leavin the outgoing president a &quot;lame duck.&quot;

This amendment moved up the date for a new president to take office from March 4 to January 20.  The first day for the newly elected Congress was moved up to January 3, allowing Congress time to select the president or vice president should the need arise.  The amendment also required that Congress meet each year on January 3, unless a different day was chosen.

The amendment also provided for several remote circumstances involving deaths or resignations of presidents-elect and vice presidents-elect, as well presidential and vice presidential candidates.

==Twenty-First Amendment==

The Twenty-First is the only Amendment that repeals, or cancels, a previous Amendment. The Twenty-First repealed the Eighteenth Amendment and ended Prohibition.

==Twenty-Second Amendment==

George Washington set a standard for all future Presidents when he declined to seek a third term. This standard was either voluntarily followed by the President, or enforced by the voters, in every case until Franklin Roosevelt, who was elected four times. In order to restore Washington's tradition, the Amendment limited all future Presidents to a maximum of two terms.

==Twenty-Third Amendment==

The Twenty-third Amendment gave citizens of the District of Columbia the right to vote in Presidential election.

==Twenty-Fourth Amendment==

The Twenty-fourth prohibited the denial of a vote based on failure to pay a tax such as the poll tax. Southern states had used the poll tax to deny poor African-Americans the right to vote.

==Twenty-Fifth Amendment==

The Twenty-fifth provided special provisions for an emergency such as a disabled but still living President. The Amendment allowed the Vice President and a majority of the Cabinet to formally declare the President unable to carry out his duties. If this was the case, then the Vice President would become Acting President until the President declared himself fit to continue. If the Vice President still felt that the President was not capable of continuing, then he and the Cabinet could again declare the President's disability. If this was the case, then Congress had to assemble to decide the matter. The President would continue unless the Congress, by a vote of two-thirds of each house, agreed with the Vice President and Cabinet.

==Twenty-Sixth Amendment==

The Twenty-sixth provided that all persons eighteen years or older could not be denied the right to vote due to age. 

==Twenty-Seventh Amendment==

The Twenty-seventh Amendment was originally proposed by Congress in 1789 at the same time as the Bill of Rights. However, it was not ratified by legislatures of the required three-fourths of the states until 1992. It provides that Congressional salary changes cannot take effect until an election (of Representatives) occurs.
----
{{USConstitionAndGovtTOC}}

[[Category:United States Government]]</text>
      <sha1>43p6xi4xwye265h5m3idd6dksedzpxw</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>United States Government/The Legislative Branch</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1300</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2615647</id>
      <parentid>2615592</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-03-10T20:50:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Xania</username>
        <id>40302</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rejected the last text change (by [[Special:Contributions/164.58.172.158|164.58.172.158]]) and restored revision 2603808 by 206.15.228.208</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{USConstitionAndGovtTOC}}
----

==Congress==
As has been stated earlier, Congress includes two distinct houses- the Senate and the House. The House represents the people of the States based upon the population of each, while the Senate allows two Senators to each state regardless of population.

==The Legislative==

The Congress is the Legislative Branch. Its main function is to make laws. It also oversees the execution of these laws, and checks various executive and judicial powers.

The Congress is ''bicameral''- it is composed of two houses. One house is the House of Representatives, the other is the Senate. 

The House of Representatives, or House for short, is currently composed of four hundred and thirty-five members. Each of the fifty states is allocated one or more representatives based on its population as calculated by the decennial (once in ten years) census. Each state is guaranteed at least one representative. A state that is allocated more than one representative divides itself, as state procedures dictate, into a number of districts equal to the number of representatives to which it is entitled. The people of each district vote to elect one representative to Congress (States that have only one representative allocated choose ''at-large'' representatives- the state votes as one entire district). The District of Columbia and a number of U.S. territories have been permitted to elect delegates to the House. These delegates may participate in debates, and sit and vote in committee, but are not allowed to vote in the full House. Every House member faces re-election in an even-numbered year and is elected to a two-year term. The House is presided over by a Speaker, who is directly elected by the members of the House.

The Senate is the upper house of the United States' legislative branch, possessing only one hundred members to the house's four hundred thirty-five. Each state chooses two senators, regardless of that state's population. The Constitution originally dictated that a state's senators were to be chosen by the state's legislature; after the Seventeenth Amendment was ratified in 1913, senators were elected directly by the state's population. In contrast to the House's two-year terms, Senators are elected to a six-year stint in office. In addition, only one-third of the Senate stands for election during an even year. These differences between the two houses were deliberately put into place by the Founding Fathers; the Senate was intended to be a more stable, austere body, whereas the House would be more responsive to the people's will.

The Vice-President is President of the Senate, but he/she only votes if there is a tie. The Senate also chooses a President Pro Tempore to preside in the Vice-President's absence (though, in practice, most of the time, senators from the majority take turns presiding for short periods).

The Senate and the House are both required to approve legislation before it becomes a law. The two houses are equal in legislative power, but revenue bills (bills relating to taxation) may only originate in the House. However, as with any other bill, the Senate's approval is still required, and the Senate may amend such bills.

The Senate holds additional powers relating to treaties and the appointments of executive and judicial officials. This power is known as &quot;advice and consent.&quot; The Senate's advice and consent is required for the President to appoint judges and many executive officers, and also to ratify treaties. To grant advice and consent on treaties, two-thirds of the Senators must concur (agree).

While most votes require a simple majority to pass, it sometimes takes three-fifths of senators to bring a bill to a vote. This is because Senate rules hold that a bill cannot be voted on as long as it is being debated--and there is no limit on how long a senator may debate a bill. Senators sometimes use this rule to filibuster a bill--that is, continue debating a bill endlessly so that it cannot be voted on.  The only way to end a filibuster is for three-fifths of all Senators to vote for a cloture resolution, which ends all debate and brings the bill up for voting. Use of the filibuster tends to be controversial. Whichever party is in the majority tends to call its use &quot;obstructionism,&quot; while the other side sees it as an important check on the majority. 

The House has the sole power to impeach federal executive and judicial officers. According to the Constitution, officers may be impeached for &quot;treason, bribery, or other high crimes and misdemeanors. The Senate has the sole power to try all such impeachments, a two-thirds vote being required for conviction. The Constitution requires that any individual convicted by the Senate to be removed from office. The Senate also has the power to bar that individual from further federal office. The Senate may not impose any further punishment, although the parties are still subject to trial in the courts. As the Vice-President (being next-in-line to the Presidency) would have an obvious conflict of interest in presiding at a trial of the President, in such cases, the Chief Justice presides. Interestingly, no similar provision prevents the Vice-President from presiding at his or her own trial.

==House of Representatives==

Every ten years, the United States conducts a Census to determine the population of each state. Then, each state is apportioned, or allocated, a number of seats based on its Census population, with the more populous states receiving more seats than the less populous ones. Currently, one seat equals roughly 600,000 constituents. However, no matter how low a state's population is, it is always entitled to at least one seat.

The state then conducts a process known as redistricting. In this process, the state divides itself into a number of districts of equal population; each district may then elect one representative. Of course, in states entitled to only one representative, the entire state is one district and redistricting does not occur. (See [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gerrymander gerrymandering])

In addition to representatives for the states, five American territories- the District of Columbia, Puerto Rico, Guam, the US Virgin Islands, and American Samoa- each choose non-voting members. Puerto Rico chooses a &quot;Resident Commissioner&quot; for a four-year term, while the others choose &quot;Delegates&quot; for two-year terms.

Representatives hold office for two-year terms. The election for Representatives is held on the Tuesday immediately after the first Monday in November of every even numbered year. A Representative actually takes office on January 3rd after the election.

No person may be a Representative unless he qualifies under the Constitution as follows. The requirements are: at least twenty-five years of age, inhabitance in the state of election, and citizenship of the United States for at least seven years.

Though no specific number of Representatives is set by the Constitution, the law of the United States sets the number of Representatives at 435.

The House of Representatives elects a Speaker who is presides over the House.&lt;ref&gt;U.S. Constitution Article I, Section 2&lt;/ref&gt; The Speaker is traditionally the leader of the majority party of the House.&lt;ref&gt;Sinclair, B. (1995). ''Legislators, leaders, and lawmaking the U.S. House of Representatives in the postreform era.'' Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press. p. 67&lt;/ref&gt; The Speaker of the House does have a significant role outside of the Congress in that she or he is  third in line to the Presidency.&lt;ref&gt; Presidential Succession Act(3 U.S.C.  19) and Section 4 of Twentieth Amendment to the United States Constitution&lt;/ref&gt;

Because of its size, the House relies heavily upon fixed rules and strict timetables for debate.  When bills are debated on the floor of the House, each party's leader is allocated a fixed amount of time to present their argument for or against the bill, and they can appropriate this time to members of their party as they see fit.  During House debates, it is common for representatives to &quot;yield their time&quot; to one another.  Times for debate and other procedures are set by the House Rules Committee, which is generally considered to be one of the most powerful committees in Congress.

==Senate==

Each state is entitled to two senators regardless of population. Originally, the state legislatures chose the senators. However, the people of the states choose their own senators at present.

Senators hold office for six-year terms. Elections are held every two years, at the same time as the election for Representatives. The Senators are classified into three separate classes. At each election, the Senate seats of one particular class are up for election. 

Constitutional requirements for Senators are slightly more strict than those for Representatives. The qualifications are: at least thirty years of age, inhabitance in the state of election, and citizenship of the United States for at least nine years. 

The Vice President of the United States presides over the Senate and holds the title of President of the Senate. His power is considerably lesser than that of the Speaker of the House. He also does not have a vote in the Senate, unless the Senate is tied. As the Vice President normally does not attend unless there is a likelihood of a tie vote, the Senate chooses one of its members to be President of the Senate ''pro tempore'', or temporarily. The President pro tem, as he is often called, is normally the most senior Senator of the majority party. Just as in the house, the President or President pro tem does not preside during most meetings; this task is often given to new Senators so that they may learn the procedures of the body. This is not as easily possible in the House because of the much greater authority of whoever presides over the Representatives.

In comparison to the House, the Senate has relatively few procedural rules, and no fixed schedules for debate.  It is possible for a Senator to continue speaking for hours on end to delay unwanted legislation: this tactic is called a &quot;filibuster.&quot;  Any individual Senator is also allowed, by Senate rules, to stop the introduction of a bill with a motion from the floor, although this is almost never done in practice.

==Party leaders, committees, and caucuses==

Both major political parties (the Republican Party and the Democratic Party) have designated floor leaders in both houses of Congress.  The floor leader for the majority party is called the House (or Senate) Majority Leader, while the floor leader for the minority party is called the House (or Senate) Minority Leader.  The second-in-command of each party's delegation is called the Whip, as their job is to &quot;whip&quot; other members of the party into action on various legislative measures.

Each party's leadership is responsible for allocating its members to committees.  There are a number of &quot;standing committees&quot; in each house, dedicated to various government functions such as the armed forces, education, and transportation.  At any time, there are also several &quot;select committees&quot; that are set up for more timely problems such as government reforms.  Occasionally, both houses of Congress will establish a &quot;joint committee&quot; to deal with certain issues.

There are also many less formal associations in Congress, known as &quot;caucuses,&quot; which are formed by members interested in various issues, such as relations with specific countries, ethnic issues, and industrial sectors.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

----

[[Category:United States Government]]</text>
      <sha1>ocx0zwlfab422ectnmhnbh2cvxbefgt</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>United States Government/The Executive Branch</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1302</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2609884</id>
      <parentid>2609879</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-02-17T17:35:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rejected the last text change (by [[Special:Contributions/67.175.238.157|67.175.238.157]]) and restored revision 2176364 by Kzokum</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{USConstitionAndGovtTOC}}
----

The Executive Branch, which executes and enforces the laws, is headed by the President and the Vice President. In addition, it includes the executive departments, which deal with general topics, and the heads of departments, who are known as Secretaries (Attorney-General in the Department of Justice). Each Department, in turn, is divided into a number of bodies, which are known as agencies, services, commissions, councils, bureaus, authorities, offices, administrations, and boards.

==The President==

The President is the highest elected official in the United States.

===Functions===

The Constitution grants the President a numbers of powers, including:

*''' to implement laws passed by Congress.
*'''Representing the United States''' in foreign affairs. The President has the power to enter treaties and executive agreements with foreign countries. Treaties must be approved by the Senate, but supersede any existing federal law, whereas executive agreements do not supersede existing law.
*'''Command of the armed forces'''.
*'''Veto power''' over bills passed by both houses of Congress. Congress can only override a presidential veto by a 2/3 vote.
*'''Nominating''' Supreme Court justices, executive officials, ambassadors and other public officers. By default, the Senate must grant its advice and consent before the nominee takes office.
minor officials to be appointed by the President only, or by the head of a department, by passing a law to that effect.
*'''Removing''' high-level executive officers at any time and for any reason. The President's power to remove lower-level executive officials may be limited by Congress, however.
*'''Pardoning''' any person who has been convicted of a crime, except impeachment and civil contempt.

===Succession===

If the President vacates office for any reason whatsoever, the Vice President becomes President. After the Vice President, the line of succession is as follows:
* Speaker of the House of Representatives
* President pro tempore of the Senate
* Secretary of State
* Secretary of the Treasury
* Secretary of Defense
* Attorney General (Department of Justice)
* Secretary of the Interior
* Secretary of Agriculture
* Secretary of Commerce
* Secretary of Labor
* Secretary of Health and Human Services
* Secretary of Housing and Urban Development
* Secretary of Transportation
* Secretary of Energy
* Secretary of Education
* Secretary of Veterans Affairs
* Secretary of Homeland Security 

The Secretaries are included in the order of the creation of their respective departments. The Secretary of Homeland Security was promoted from last to eight in the Line of Succession. 

Representative Christopher Cox (R-CA), Chairman of the House Policy Committee and Chairman of the Homeland Security Committee, along with Rep. Martin Frost (D-TX), Rep. Brian Baird (D-WA), Rep. Sheila Jackson-Lee (D-TX), Rep. David Vitter (R-LA), Rep. John Shadegg (R-AZ), Rep. Steve Chabot (R-OH), and Rep. Dave Camp (R-MI), introduced H.R. 2319, a bill to amend the Presidential Succession Act of 1947. 

Since the constitution only allows native born Americans to serve as President, any Secretaries who are naturalized citizens would be skipped in the succession.

==The Vice President==

The Vice President's only executive function in the Constitution is to become President in the event that the President dies or is incapacitated. The 25th Amendment provides that this may occur when:

#&quot;the President transmits to the President pro tempore of the Senate and the Speaker of the House of Representatives his written declaration that he is unable to discharge the powers and duties of his office, and until he transmits to them a written declaration to the contrary;&quot; or

#&quot;the Vice President and a majority of either the principal officers of the executive departments or of such other body as Congress may by law provide, transmit to the President pro tempore of the Senate and the Speaker of the House of Representatives their written declaration that the President is unable to discharge the powers and duties of his office.&quot;

Additionally, &quot;whenever there is a vacancy in the office of the Vice President, the President shall nominate a Vice President who shall take office upon confirmation by a majority vote of both Houses of Congress.&quot;

In practice, the Vice President often takes an active role in policy making.

The Vice President also serves as president of the Senate, but cannot vote except to break a tie.

==Elections==

Each state is entitled to choose a number of Electors equal to the number of Representatives and Senators it elects to Congress. Thus, a state will choose no less than three electors- two for the Senators, and one for the minimum of one Representative.

The state may choose its Electors in any way it pleases. However, all the states allow the people to choose all Electors. Forty-eight states use the following system: each candidate nominates a panel of electors. When a voter votes for a candidate, he or she actually votes for the nominated panel. Then, the candidate who wins more votes than any other candidate has his nominated panel appointed. Thus, a candidate who does not necessarily win all the votes will receive all of the state's electors. The exceptions to this system are Maine and Nebraska. These states allow a candidate to nominate one state panel of two electors, plus one elector for each district. Then, the candidate who wins the state has his two-member state panel appointed as electors, while the candidate who wins an individual district has his or her nominee for that district appointed. In all cases, the election for the Electors is held on the same day as Congressional elections.

Regardless of how they are chosen, the Electors all assemble in their own states in December. The manner of the voting by Electors has changed. Firstly, the following is the original system:
* Each Elector casts two votes for President. One of those votes must be for a person not an inhabitant of the same state as the Elector. Then, if a candidate receives the votes of a majority of Electors becomes President, while the runner-up becomes Vice President. If one compares the Presidency to a gold medal, then one may say that the Vice Presidency was like a silver medal.
If, however, no candidate received a majority, then the House of Representatives would choose one of the top five candidates as President. In voting for President, each state casts one block vote. In any case, whichever other candidate holds the greatest number of votes other than the candidate elected President becomes Vice President. In case of a tie for second-place, the Senate elects the Vice President.
* The above system seems to allow for all contingencies, but it did not allow for the development of political parties. Prior to the election of 1800, parties did not nominate candidates. However, in 1800, the Democratic-Republican Party nominated Thomas Jefferson for President and Aaron Burr for Vice President. The pair won a clear majority of the votes. However, both had an equal number of Electoral votes. Though the original intention was clearly for Jefferson to become President and Burr to become Vice President, the House still had to vote to choose one or the other as President. The House votes tied thirty-five times until Jefferson was finally elected President.
* In order to prevent a recurrence, the Twelfth Amendment was passed. Under the Amendment, the electors would vote separately for President and Vice President. In each case, a majority was required for someone to be elected. If no majority was apparent for President, then the House would choose among the top three candidates, again voting by states. Similarly, the Senate would vote between the top two candidates for Vice President.

The District of Columbia chooses Electors like the other states, but the District can in no event choose more Electors than any other state.

==Executive departments==

At present, there are fifteen executive departments. They are the departments of:

*Department of Agriculture (USDA)
*Department of Commerce (DOC)
*Department of Defense (DOD)
*Department of Education (ED)
*Department of Energy (DOE)
*Department of Health and Human Services (HHS)
*Department of Homeland Security (DHS)
*Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD)
*Department of Justice (DOJ)
*Department of Labor (DOL)
*Department of State (DOS)
*Department of the Interior (DOI)
*Department of the Treasury
*Department of Transportation (DOT)
*Department of Veterans Affairs (VA)

Each department is subdivided into a number of agencies, bureaus and other divisions.

==Executive agencies==

In addition to the Cabinet departments, there are certain independent bodies which are not part of any department, but report directly to the Executive Office of the President. These include:

* Environmental Protection Agency (EPA)
* National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA)
* Office of Management and Budget (OMB)
* Office of National Drug Control Policy (ONDCP)
* Office of the United States Trade Representative (USTR)

==The Cabinet==
The Cabinet currently consists of the Vice President, the White House Chief of Staff, the heads of each executive department, and the heads of the EPA, OMB, ONDCP and USTR.


----
{{USConstitionAndGovtTOC}}</text>
      <sha1>cnijday4p8ds7dz414isf0a9uzt5rqk</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>United States Government/The Judicial Branch</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1303</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2582785</id>
      <parentid>2580868</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-11-18T22:47:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Recent Runes</username>
        <id>66908</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/66.210.101.126|66.210.101.126]] ([[User talk:66.210.101.126|talk]]) to last version by Jomegat</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{USConstitionAndGovtTOC}}
----

==The Courts==

The United States judicial system includes the Supreme Court of the United States and the inferior federal courts. The President nominates an individual to serve as a judge, after which the Senate must grant its advice and consent before the President can formally appoint the judge. A judge holds office during &quot;good behavior&quot;, which is usually interpreted as meaning a life term.

==The Supreme Court==

The Constitution creates the Supreme Court, but permits Congress to set the number of Justices. Currently, the Supreme Court includes the Chief Justice of the United States and eight Associate Justices. The Supreme Court has original jurisdiction over limited categories of cases, such as cases between two or more states.  It hears most of its cases through its appellate jurisdiction, in which it hears appeals from lower federal and state courts. It exercises its appellate jurisdiction selectively; four of the nine Justices must grant a ''writ of certiorari'' before a case can be heard.

==The Court of Appeals==

The United States is divided into twelve regional ''circuits'', each of which has a Court of Appeal. Additionally, there is a Federal Circuit which hears appeals from certain special tribunals and courts. The regional circuits (which are officially known by a number only, except for the DC circuit) are as follows:
* District of Columbia
* First Circuit- Northern New England (Maine, New Hampshire, Massachusetts, and Rhode Island plus the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico)
* Second Circuit- Southern New England (Vermont, New York, and Connecticut)
* Third Circuit- Middle Atlantic (Pennsylvania, Delaware, and New Jersey plus US Territory Virgin Islands)
* Fourth Circuit- Upper Southeast (Maryland, Virginia, West Virginia, North Carolina, and South Carolina)
* Fifth Circuit- Deep South (Texas, Louisiana, and Mississippi)
* Sixth Circuit- Eastern Great Lakes (Michigan, Ohio, Kentucky, and Tennessee)
* Seventh Circuit- Western Great Lakes (Wisconsin, Illinois, and Indiana)
* Eighth Circuit- Midwest (Minnesota, Iowa, Missouri, Arkansas, North Dakota, South Dakota, and Nebraska)
* Ninth Circuit- West (Alaska, Hawaii, Washington, Oregon, California, Montana, Idaho, Nevada, and Arizona plus US Territories Guam and the Northern Mariana Islands)
* Tenth Circuit- Southwest (Wyoming, Utah, Colorado, Kansas, Oklahoma, and New Mexico)
* Eleventh Circuit- Lower Southeast (Alabama, Georgia, and Florida)

Each Court of Appeal includes a different number of members. The First Circuit has the fewest with six members, while the Ninth Circuit has the most with twenty-eight.

==District Court==

Every state is divided into one or more Court Districts (which are distinct from Congressional districts). The total number of districts is ninety-four. 

Each district court includes a different number of members. The Eastern and Western District of Kentucky, the Eastern District of Oklahoma, and the Northern, Eastern, and Western District of Oklahoma, each have the fewest number of judges with one, while the Central District of California has the most with twenty-seven.

==Other Courts==

The Congress has established special bankruptcy courts and other courts to rule on specific matters.

----
{{USConstitionAndGovtTOC}}

[[Category:United States Government]]</text>
      <sha1>cmnnjk8kowl47phuja0loc6sphpoflq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Flockmeal</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>1304</id>
    <revision>
      <id>153425</id>
      <parentid>3572</parentid>
      <timestamp>2003-09-28T00:47:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Flockmeal</username>
        <id>133</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Leave a message notice</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[http://textbook.wikipedia.org/w/wiki.phtml?title=User_talk:Flockmeal&amp;action=edit&amp;section=new Leave a message]

My Wikipedia [http://www.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Flockmeal User page].</text>
      <sha1>jpqsy3v280adzxq8y9i9lyf1mm3tao4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Japanese/Grammar/Basic Particles</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1305</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2575204</id>
      <parentid>2519666</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-10-28T16:55:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>50.102.115.123</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Fixed 'can not' to 'cannot'.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Japanese related|resources|
* [http://tisc.isc.u-toyama.ac.jp/self/quiz_particles.html Particles quiz] at the Toyama International Student Center Self Japanese Learning Support Site.
* [[w:Japanese particles]]}}
{{Japanese related|content|
* [[../Sentence ending particles/]]}}
The Japanese language uses post-position particles (; ) to denote the direction of an action and who is performing the action.  They consistently come after the word that they modify.

There are three particles used very frequently in the language: ,  and . This module covers these along with a few other common ones but an exhaustive list would run very long.

== The topic and subject markers  and  ==

The particle &quot;&quot; (pronounced as &quot;&quot; when used as a particle) is the ''topic marker'' denoting topic of discussion, while &quot;&quot; is the ''subject marker'' and marks a noun that performs an action. The difference between the two tends to cause confusion among beginners but their usage can be summed up as matter of focus.

The topic particle &quot;&quot; is used when introducing a topic and gives focus to the ''action'' of the sentence (i.e., the verb or the adjective). The subject marker &quot;&quot; is used when emphasising the subject giving  focus to the ''subject'' of the action.

One can also think of it as replacing &quot;~&quot; with the phrase &quot;as for ~&quot;, &quot;on the topic of ~&quot; or &quot;regarding ~&quot; to distinguish it from &quot;&quot;. While these phrases aren't common in English we can use these expressions here to better show the main difference between &quot;&quot; and &quot;&quot;. 
{| {{Japanese example}}
| style=&quot;width:20em&quot; | ''''''   || The cat is eating (or: Regarding the cat, it is eating.)
|-
| ''''''   || The ''cat'' is eating (as opposed to someone else).
|-
|  ''''''  || You are strong.
|-
|  ''''''  || ''You'' are strong (only you and not anyone else)
|-
|  ''''''   || That's the telephone.
|-
|  ''''''   || ''That's'' the telephone (and not anything else)
|}

The difference can also be displayed by using both subject and topic markers in one sentence: 
{| {{Japanese example}}
| style=&quot;width:20em&quot; | '''''' ''''''   || I like you. (Or literally: as for me, like you.)
|-
| '''''' ''''''   || I dislike/hate wasabi. (Or: As for me, hate wasabi.)
|-
| '''''' ''''''   || Your English is good! (Or: As for you, English good!)
|}
One has to be careful using both &quot;&quot; and &quot;&quot; in one sentence. If a verb is actually acting on the (direct) subject, usually a different particle (like ) has to be used.

&quot;&quot; is generally more flexible, because the &quot;it&quot; can be assumed, and is therefore recommended to novices who have not grasped the difference between the two.

&quot;&quot; also has the specialized function of being used for comparisons as well. 
{| {{Japanese example}}
| style=&quot;width:20em&quot; | ''''''  || There is a cat.
|-
| ''''''  || There is a dog.
|-
| ''''''   , ''''''   || The cat is eating, but the dog is not.
|}

Often the grammatical subject may also be the topic. In this case, &quot;&quot; normally replaces &quot;&quot;. However, if the subject is never known, you cannot use &quot;&quot; and must use &quot;&quot;. This is similar to using pronouns: You can't state, &quot;It is over there&quot;, without first stating what &quot;it&quot; may be.

== The direct object marker  ==

The particle &quot;&quot; (pronounced &quot;&quot;) is the ''direct object marker'' and marks the recipient of an action.
{| {{Japanese example}}
| style=&quot;width:20em&quot; |  ''''''  || To drink sake.
|-
|  ''''''  || To read a magazine.
|-
|    ''''''   || The cat is drinking water.
|}

It also indicates the place through which the action occurs:
{| {{Japanese example}}
| style=&quot;width:20em&quot; |  ''''''  || To fly through the sky
|-
|  ''''''  || To walk down the street
|}

As with much of the language, parts of a sentence that can be assumed from context are often omitted and the direct object particle is commonly dropped in conversational (colloquial) Japanese.

== The indirect object marker  ==

&quot;&quot; marks the verb's ''indirect object'' (i.e. the destination of a targeted verb action) translating as &quot;to&quot;, &quot;in&quot;, &quot;at&quot; or &quot;by&quot;. It also indicates the location touched or affected by an event or action:
{| {{Japanese example}}
| style=&quot;width:20em&quot; | '''''' || Fly '''to''' the stars.
|-
| ''''''   || Give a present '''to''' a friend.
|-
|  ''''''  || To tell (something) to the teacher.
|-
| ''''''  || To be '''in''' school.
|-
|  ''''''  || To be '''at''' home.
|-
|  ''''''  || To meet '''on''' Saturday
|}

The particle &quot;&quot; described below is used exclusively for marking the destination.

== The destination marker  ==
 (pronounced &quot;&quot; when used as a particle) indicates the direction of an action, roughly the equivalent of &quot;to&quot; or &quot;toward&quot; in English.
{| {{Japanese example}}
| style=&quot;width:20em&quot; | ''''''  || Mother is going to the store.
|-
| ''''''  || To go to Tokyo.
|}

== The question marker  ==

Placing  at the end of a sentence changes a statement into a question. Use it at the end of a verb to make it a question, or at the end of an interrogative [[../Pro-forms|pro-form]] to make it into a demonstrative pronoun.

{| {{Japanese example}}
| style=&quot;width:20em&quot; | '''''' || Am I a man?
|-
|    '''''' || How do you describe this?
|-
|   '''''' || Is there a cat?
|-
|  ''''''  ''''''|| Did you go somewhere?
|}

For more on the question marker, see: [[../Sentence ending particles/]].

== The possessive marker  ==

&quot;&quot;, is most commonly used as a ''possessive marker'' (similar to the English &quot;'s&quot;).
{| {{Japanese example}}
| style=&quot;width:20em&quot; | '''''' || The teacher''''s''' apple
|-
|  ''''''  || '''My''' bag.
|-
|  ''''''  || '''His''' watch.
|}
The particle can also function as a noun link, indicating that the preceding noun (or [[Japanese/Lessons/Na-adjectives|adjectival noun]]) modifies the following noun.
{| {{Japanese example}}
| style=&quot;width:20em&quot; | ''''''  || Buildings '''in/of''' Tokyo.
|-
|  ''''''  || A green book.
|}
It can also be used for ''nominalisation'', converting verbs and [[Japanese/Lessons/I-adjectives|(proper) adjectives]] into nouns.
{| {{Japanese example}}
| style=&quot;width:20em&quot; |  ''''''   || Read'''ing''' is good.
|}
Note that in this last example two particles are used together:  and : the first makes the action a noun, and the second tells that this action is what the sentence is all about.

== The exhaustive list conjunction  ==

This particle acts as a conjunction on the words it separates. Unlike conjunctions of more than two words in English, where only the last two are separated with an &quot;and&quot; and the rest with commas, the Japanese conjunction separates each word and commas are not used.
{| {{Japanese example}}
| style=&quot;width:20em&quot; |  ''''''     || This '''and''' that are green.
|-
|  ''''''  || A book '''and''' a magazine.
|-
|   ''''''  ''''''  ''''''  || There is a pen''',''' a pencil''',''' an eraser '''and''' a ruler in the bag.
|}

This applies to exhaustive lists, i.e. when all objects are explicitly mentioned.

The particle is used to indicate parallelism with the subject, often meaning &quot;with&quot;:
{| {{Japanese example}}
| style=&quot;width:20em&quot; |  ''''''  || I spoke '''with''' him.
|-
|  ''''''  || {I/He/She/They} went '''with''' her.
|-
|  ''''''    || (I) played tennis with Smith&quot;
|-
|    ''''''   || I will marry you. (I will get married '''with''' you)
|}

== The incomplete list marker  ==

This particle is used to connect various words implying that the listing is not exhaustive. The particle &quot;&quot; may be added after the list to emphasise that the list is incomplete.
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
| Noun || Particle || Noun || ...
| style=&quot;color:gray&quot; | 
|}
{| {{Japanese example}}
| style=&quot;width:20em&quot; |  ''''''   || There are books '''and''' pens (among other things).
|-
|  ''''''  || A book '''and''' a magazine (among other things).
|-
|  ''''''  ''''''  ''''''  || (I) need eggs''',''' salad''',''' chicken '''and such'''.
|}

== The &quot;also&quot; marker  ==

 is quite simply a marker that says &quot;also&quot;. It replaces the particles ,  and  but can also follow other particles. This can also be used to form a large list of words all acting as though one of the basic particles (, , or ) were affecting the whole list.  
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
| Subject || Particle || Verb
|}
{| {{Japanese example}}
| style=&quot;width:20em&quot; |  ''''''  || The cat also drinks.
|-
|  ''''''  || I'm going too.
|-
|  ''''''  ''''''  ''''''  ''''''   || Boys, girls, women and men are human.
|}

{{Japanese related|content|
* [[../Pro-forms/]]}}
Worth noting is that used with an interrogative pro-form (e.g. who, where, how) the  particle negates the pro-form:
{| {{Japanese example}}
| style=&quot;width:20em&quot; |  || anybody
|-
| e.g.  || General knowledge.
|-
|  || nobody
|-
| e.g.  || Nobody's here.
|}

== The means particle  ==

The particle  can be used in several situations indicating means. These can be for example an instrument, a location or a language.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
| Means || Particle || Verb
|}
{| {{Japanese example}}
| style=&quot;width:20em&quot; |  ''''''  || '''By''' what means do you go to University?
|-
| ''''''  || I go '''by''' bicycle.
|-
| ''''''  || I go '''by''' car.
|-
|   ''''''  || I eat '''at''' a restaurant.
|-
|   ''''''   || I played tennis with Smith '''at''' the park.&quot;
|-
|  ''''''  || To learn '''at''' school.
|}

As a note of interest, the  from the copula  is also actually an instrumental-maker.  marks the whole previous expression instrumental to the verb . However, this is the classical meaning of the copula and rarely ''explicitly'' treated this way in modern Japanese.

== Origin and limit  and  ==

These particles indicate the starting point or border of an action. This may be a location as well as a time and corresponds roughly with &quot;from&quot; and &quot;until&quot;.
{| {{Japanese example}}
| style=&quot;width:20em&quot; |  ''''''  || Come '''from''' Tokyo.
|-
|  ''''''  || To go '''to''' the mountains.
|-
| {{furi||}}{{furi|9|}}'''''' {{furi|5|}}'''''' 
| The hours are '''from''' 9 '''to''' 5.
|}

{{BookCat|filing=deep}}</text>
      <sha1>m6akz358kwa9jv0wjxtqxh0m87sxaot</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>The Once and Future King</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1306</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2684533</id>
      <parentid>1961028</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-07-25T01:36:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Koavf</username>
        <id>16549</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">''The Once and Future King''  is a novel by [[w:T. H. White|T. H. White]] about the legend of King Arthur. It is often assigned reading in English literature classes and is composed of five books:

#[[/The Sword in the Stone/]]
#[[The Queen of Air and Darkness]]
#[[/The Ill-Made Knight/]]
#[[/The Candle in the Wind/]]
#[[/The Book of Merlyn/]]

While the first four were originally published separately, and reworked for inclusion in ''The Once and Future King'', the last was to be published in the greater work for the first time. This was vetoed by White's publisher, supposedly due to wartime paper restrictions.  It wasn't until after White's death that The Book of Merlyn joined the other four.

==Characters==
*[[/Arthur/]]
*[[/Merlyn/]]
*[[/Kay/]]
*[[/Lancelot/]]
* [[/Templates/]]
*[[/Gawaine/]]
*[[/Gaheris/]]
*[[/Gareth/]]
*[[/Uther Pendragon/]]

{{Alphabetical|O}}
{{Subjects|Fantasy literature|Novels}}
{{status|0%}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Once And Future King}}</text>
      <sha1>71nam8p0mihh6gof3hvfnkj9yt7okvx</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>The Once and Future King/The Sword in the Stone</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1307</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1439110</id>
      <parentid>866662</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-03-09T19:09:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>75.89.46.171</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">''[[The Once and Future King]]'' - '''''The Sword in the Stone'''''

Book I covers [[../Major Characters#Arthur|the Wart]]'s (Arthur's) childhood education by [[../Major Characters#Merlyn|Merlyn]], including his adventures into [[../Minor Characters#Morgan|Morgan le Fay]]'s castle with [[../Minor Characters#Robin Wood|Robin Wood]], and his transformations into many different animals. It ends with the Wart removing the sword from the stone after [[../Minor Characters#Uther|King Uther]]'s death, and his subsequent [[w:Coronation|coronation]]

*[[/Chapter 1/]]
*[[/Chapter 2/]]
*[[/Chapter 3/]]
*[[/Chapter 4/]]
*[[/Chapter 5/]]
*[[/Chapter 6/]]
*[[/Chapter 7/]]
*[[/Chapter 8/]]
*[[/Chapter 9/]]
*[[/Chapter 10/]]
*[[/Chapter 11/]]
*[[/Chapter 12/]]
*[[/Chapter 13/]]
*[[/Chapter 14/]]
*[[/Chapter 15/]]
*[[/Chapter 16/]]
*[[/Chapter 17/]]
*[[/Chapter 18/]]
*[[/Chapter 19/]]
*[[/Chapter 20/]]
*[[/Chapter 21/]]
*[[/Chapter 22/]]
*[[/Chapter 23/]]
*[[/Chapter 24/]]
*[[/Chapter 25/]] 

[[Category:The Once and Future King]]</text>
      <sha1>fozcui21wu51tjw6pfoe25zgpe6hepo</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>The Once and Future King/The Sword in the Stone/Chapter 17</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1308</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1972396</id>
      <parentid>1972377</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-11-16T02:10:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/76.113.8.193|76.113.8.193]] ([[User talk:76.113.8.193|talk]]) to last revision by [[User:75.89.46.171|75.89.46.171]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[The Once and Future King]] - Book I: [[The Sword in the Stone]] - '''Chapter 17'''

==Plot summary==
The chapter begins a few months after the boar-hunt. [[The Once and Future King/King Pellinore|King Pellinore]] gives the [[The Once and Future King/Questing Beast|Questing Beast]], now healthy, a two-hour headstart in the chase. [[Merlyn (OaFK)|Merlyn]], [[The Once and Future King/Archimedes|Archimedes]], and the [[Arthur (OaFK)|Wart]] discuss the birds, a subject that has arisen due to spring's arrival. The Wart asks to become a bird again, because the last time he didn't get a chance to fly; Archimedes plans to go with him at night. The Wart then mentions his favorite bird is the rook, because rooks fly just for pleasure, not necessarily with a purpose. Archimedes mentions rooks are one of few birds with a legal and social system, and in response to Merlyn says his favorite are pigeons. Then Merlyn says he prefers the chaffinch, and continues that bird calls arise out of imitation of their prey or their environment. Finally [[The Once and Future King/Kay|Kay]] enters, ironically saying that he was shooting birds.

==Analysis==
'''Anachronisms''' - Merlyn mentions both [[en:Gilbert White|Gilbert White]] and [[en:Carolus Linnaeus|Carolus Linnaeus]], and Archimedes compares pigeons to [[en:Quakers|Quakers]]. All came much later.
'''Animals as forms of government''' - Archimedes mentions that the rooks have &quot;parliaments...and a social system;&quot; (a play upon the [[en:Collective noun|collective noun]] for rooks being a &quot;parliament&quot;) they make &quot;laws about the defense of the rookery, and marriage, and so forth&quot;
[[Category:The Once and Future King]]</text>
      <sha1>orx74jkbtxqvnuxrbjv5fdbe9pbzfwq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>United States Government/Colonial Government in America</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1311</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2624180</id>
      <parentid>2624179</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-04-01T17:56:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Aldnonymous</username>
        <id>414537</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/169.244.80.102|169.244.80.102]] ([[User talk:169.244.80.102|talk]]) to last version by Stryn</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{USConstitionAndGovtTOC}}
----
Under the Kingdom of Great Britain, the American colonies experienced five situations which would guide them in creating a constitution. The British Parliament believed that it had the right to impose taxes on the colonists; it had ''virtual'' representation over the entire empire, while the colonists believed Parliament had no such right, as they had no ''direct'' representation in Parliament. By the 1720s all but two of the colonies had a locally elected legislature and a British appointed governor. Often, these two branches of government would clash, with the legislatures imposing their &quot;power of the purse&quot; to control the British governor. Thus, Americans viewed their legislative branch as a guardian of their liberty, while the executive branches was deemed tyrannical.

There were several examples of royal actions that upset the Americans. For example, taxes on the importation of lead, paint, tea, paper, spirits, rum, wine, molasses, sugar, and other products were imposed at various times. Also, the Parliament provided for a duty to be paid on court documents, certificates, licenses, deeds, other legal documents, playing cards, pamphlets, books, calendars, newspapers, and other papers, as well as dice. The variety of taxes imposed, as well as other causes, led to the Americans' disdain for the British system of government.

After the Boston Tea Party, the Parliament of Great Britain and the King passed Acts that outlawed the Massachusetts legislature. The Parliament also provided for special courts in which British judges, rather than American juries, would try colonists. The Quartering Act and the Intolerable Acts required Americans to provide room and board for British soldiers. Americans especially feared British actions in Canada, where civil law was once suspended in favor of British military rule. 

American distaste for the system of British government would lead to revolution.  Americans had formed their own local institutions which were not British at all, but American.  The political ideas of the Americans actually had their root in the British radicals of the early 18th century.  England had passed beyond those ideas by 1776 and the resulting conflict resulted in the first American attempts at a national government.
----
{{USConstitionAndGovtTOC}}

[[Category:United States Government]]</text>
      <sha1>lf2odd86pfrxhnlbstgs0sxgzyvtupn</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>United States Government/The U.S. under the Articles of Confederation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1312</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2711422</id>
      <parentid>2711416</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-08T16:29:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Glaisher</username>
        <id>963423</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/205.222.248.120|205.222.248.120]] ([[User talk:205.222.248.120|talk]]) to last version by Ixfd64</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{USConstitionAndGovtTOC}}
----

==The Articles of Confederation==
The Articles of Confederation accomplished certain things, but without a strict leader, they were bad. First, they expressly provided that the states were sovereign. (A ''sovereign state'' is a state that is both self-governing and independent.) The United States as a Confederation was much like the present-day European Union. Each member was able to make its own laws; the entire Union was merely for the purposes of common defense.

The reason for the independence of the colonies is clear- the colonies were afraid of the power of a central government such as the one in the State of Great Britain. 

The Articles provided that a Congress, consisting of two to seven members per state, would hold legislative power. The states, regardless of the number of Congress members representing them, each have one total vote. 

The Congress was empowered to settle boundary and other disputes between states. It could also establish courts with jurisdiction over the seas. Also, it could tax the states, even though it did not possess the power to require the collection these taxes by law.

==Faults of the Articles==

The Congress, overall, was absolutely ineffectual. The Congress had to rely on the states for its funding. Since it could not forcibly collect taxes, the states could grant or withhold money and force Congress to accept their demands. 

Because it could not collect taxes, Congress printed paper dollars. This policy, however, absolutely wrecked the economy because of an overabundance of paper dollars, which had lost almost all value. 

The several states also printed their own currency. This led to much confusion relating to exchange rates and trade; some states accepted the currency of others, while other states refused to honor bills issued by their counterparts.

Furthermore, the Articles included certain fallacies. For instance, it suggested that the approval of &quot;nine states&quot; was required to make certain laws. However, it made no provision for additional states. Thus, it would appear that the number nine would be in effect even if that number would actually be a minority of states. 

Also, the Articles required the approval of all states for certain important decisions such as making Amendments. As the number of 'States&quot; would grow, securing this approval would become more and more difficult.

==The Conference at Annapolis==

At Annapolis, Maryland, the delegates of the thirteen states were supposed to meet to discuss various changes to the Articles to grant more authority to Congress. However, eight of the states failed to send representatives. Thus, the Conference did not even occur. However, another Conference was called for 1787. This Conference at Philadelphia is what we now know to be the Constitutional Convention.
----
{{USConstitionAndGovtTOC}}

[[Category:United States Government]]</text>
      <sha1>qs7doob9sepkn47ekzb6lrh3k1yq7pc</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>United States Government/The Constitutional Convention</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1313</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2434486</id>
      <parentid>2434473</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-05T19:28:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jomegat</username>
        <id>12605</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rejected the last 18 text changes (by [[Special:Contributions/50.200.15.222|50.200.15.222]]) and restored revision 2408620 by QuiteUnusual</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{USConstitionAndGovtTOC}}
----

==Philadelphia==

After the Annapolis Conference, the Congress called a more important conference at Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. States, except for Rhode Island, appointed delegates. Some delegates did not attend due to the perceived inconvenience. Others stayed home because they held important political offices in their state. Furthermore, some refused to attend because they disagreed with the very concept of a more powerful central and less powerful state governments.

==The Legislature==

The United States were basically divided into two classes- the large (more populous) states and the small (less populous) states. The large states included Pennsylvania, Virginia, and Massachusetts. The small states included New Jersey, Delaware, Connecticut, New Hampshire, Maryland, and even New York. Also, one may consider Georgia and the two Carolinas as small states, but these states hoped to increase their population and become large by importing slaves and attracting &quot;immigrants&quot; from other states.

The large states wanted to have '''proportional representation''' in Congress. They wished that the more populous states have more representatives than the less populous states. However, fearing that they would be overwhelmed by large numbers of representatives from other states, the small state delegates suggested that all states receive '''equal representation''' like under the Articles.

James Madison of Virginia proposed a plan, which was presented by Edmund Randolph, supported by the large states, the Virginia Plan. It entailed:
* A very powerful Congress of two houses based on proportional representation
* One house elected by the people, and the second house elected by the first one
* An executive chosen by Congress
* Congressional power to cancel any state law
* Based on population


Meanwhile, New Jersey politician William Paterson proposed a plan on behalf of the small states. It involved:
* A Congress equivalent in structure to the Articles Congress
* A Congress more powerful than the Articles Congress, but not as powerful as the Virginia Plan Congress
* An executive chosen by Congress
* Congressional law being supreme over state law

Thirdly, Alexander Hamilton of New York proposed a plan extremely similar to the British government. The British plan included:
* A legislature of two houses
* One house chosen by the people for limited terms
* Another house chosen by a special body for life terms
* An executive chosen by a special body for a life term
* Congressional power to cancel any state law.
* Based on population
Hamilton's plan was rejected very quickly- it reminded the delegates too much of the tyranny and unhappiness under the King of the State of Great Britain.

Connecticut Delegate Roger Sherman suggested that the small and large states compromise. He felt that the large states would never accept equal representation, while the small ones would never accept just proportional representation. His compromise, known as the Great Compromise, suggested the following:
* A Congress with two houses
* One house based on proportional representation
* Another house based on equal representation

Though Sherman's compromise was initially rejected, the delegates were forced to accept it eventually. Otherwise, the Convention would have clearly broken down on the issue of representation.

==The Executive==

Once the issue of representation was resolved, other issues seemed relatively easy to negotiate. The delegates continued to compromise on several issues, including the executive.

Firstly, the delegates were concerned about a single individual as executive. The King, they said, was an individual with too much power. However, the argument failed when some pointed out that every single state in the union had one Chief Executive called a President or a Governor, rather than a Council of Presidents or Governors, and none of the states suffered from that Governor's tyranny. Similarly, the executive was granted substantial but not absolute power, after the example of the individual states. 

(Pennsylvania at one time in its history had a council of three Presidents.)

The manner of choosing the executive was the only one of concern. The following were proposed as electors for the President:
* The People
* The state Legislatures
* The state Governors
* The Congress

The Framers rejected the idea of election by the People because they felt that, it would be impractical in the days of difficult communication, and inappropriate because the people would &quot;naturally&quot; vote for local candidates without any regard for those from other states. Also, they rejected the state or Congressional choice because they assumed that the President would feel indebted to and controlled by the states or the Congress. Such a problem would be present with any permanent body. Thus, they established a temporary body whose sole purpose was to elect the President- the Electoral College. (See Part III, Chapter 2.)

==Slavery==

The problem of slavery, after the issue of representation, was probably the most dangerous one for the Convention to tackle. If the Convention adopted a plan that upset one region, then the states of that region might have withdrawn from the Convention, breaking up the meeting. 

Related to the issue of representation was the counting of slaves to decide the population of a state for the purpose of proportional representation in Congress. The South wanted slaves to count, but the North feared that the South could increase its power in Congress by importing more slaves. The Three-Fifths Compromise suggested the same standard as the Article of Confederation-&quot;other persons,&quot; or slaves would be counted as three-fifths of persons. The three-fifths rule would be applied for deciding proportions in Congress '''and''' amounts of direct tax due from each state.

Another compromise relating to slavery involved the importation of slaves. The Constitutional Convention compromised by allowing the slave trade to continue until 1808, when the Congress could lawfully ban it.

==Conclusion==

The tired delegates were faced with a problem - that of a Bill of Rights. The delegates, however, refused to take the risk of breaking up the Convention and wasting hard work by debating specific rights. Thus, they assumed that a newly assembled Congress would add these Amendments, or they felt that the present Constitutional protections were sufficient. 

In order for the Constitution to gain effect, the Convention required that nine states approve it. In addition, the states not ratifying, or approving, the Constitution would not be subject to it.


----
{{USConstitionAndGovtTOC}}

[[Category:United States Government]]</text>
      <sha1>et2ie08138ouak776erb4evy7oulik4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>United States Government/Ratification</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1314</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1390272</id>
      <parentid>1390244</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-01-27T21:26:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jomegat</username>
        <id>12605</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/99.190.9.4|99.190.9.4]] ([[User talk:99.190.9.4|Talk]]) to last version by [[User:65.220.79.5|65.220.79.5]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{USConstitionAndGovtTOC}}
----
==Introduction==

The Constitution required ratification by nine states in order to come into effect. The fight for ratification was long and difficult.  An important factor in ratifying the constitution was the fact the delegates to the Constitutional Convention required that ratification be done by special ratifying conventions, not by state legislature.  Being interested in retaining state powers, the states would understandably have been resistant to ratifying a new, stronger central government.

==Federalists versus Anti- Federalists==

Those who favored ratification were known as '''Federalists''',while those who opposed it were considered '''Anti- Federalists'''. 

The Federalists attacked the weaknesses of the Articles of Confederation. They acknowledged that the Constitution was not perfect, but they said that it was much better than any other proposal then made.

Three Federalists- Alexander Hamilton, James Madison, and John Jay- wrote a series of essays called ''The Federalist Papers''. The essays explained the constitution and defended its provisions. The documents were intended for the state of New York, though people from across the country read them.

The Federalists defended the weakest point of the Constitution- a lack of a Bill of Rights- by suggesting that current protections were sufficient and that the Congress could always propose Amendments.

Anti- Federalists such as Patrick Henry attacked the Constitution, suggesting that it would lead to a dangerously powerful national government. The Anti- Federalist arguments relating to the Bill of Rights were especially powerful. However, many were convinced by the assurances provided by the Federalists.

==State Conventions==

Each state was to hold a convention to debate the Constitution and ratify or reject it. The Constitution was proposed in September, 1787. By the end of the year, some states that were in favor of the document ratified. Delaware's convention approved it by a vote of 30- 0; Pennsylvania's by a vote of 46- 23; New Jersey's by a vote of 38- 0. The next year, Georgia ratified by a vote of 26- 0 and Connecticut followed with a vote of 128- 40.

The Federalists were already more than halfway to the nine-state margin. However, the states that did not ratify the Constitution in that year included the extremely important states of Massachusetts, New York, and Virginia. Massachusetts ratified the document by a close margin (187- 168) in February, 1788. Maryland followed with a 63- 11 vote, and South Carolina did the same with a 149- 73 vote. Then, New Hampshire provided the all-important ninth ratification by a 57- 47 vote.

The United States was established under the new Constitution, but the important commercial state of New York and the populous state of Virginia, among others, still did not ratify. After tough battles, these states also ratified, Virginia by a 89- 79 margin and New York with 30- 27.

The Bill of Rights was then created under the new Constitution, leading to North Carolina's ratification by a vote of 194- 77. Seeing itself alone, Rhode Island finally agreed to ratify with a 34- 32 vote.

All thirteen colonies had ratified the Constitution by May, 1790.
----
{{USConstitionAndGovtTOC}}

[[Category:United States Government]]</text>
      <sha1>gx0wgc252wsytq484acl5fhhrpw8o15</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Wackybrit</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>1316</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1690246</id>
      <parentid>1690242</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-01-02T00:37:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undo revision 1690242 by [[Special:Contributions/81.86.235.109|81.86.235.109]] ([[User talk:81.86.235.109|Talk]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[en:User:Wackybrit]] is Peter Cooper from the United Kingdom. I contribute at the main Wikipedia also.

I plan to help out with the French textbook, as well as textbooks on technical issues. I would also like to start a textbook focused towards marketing, offline and/or online, or perhaps one on finance, as these are my 'specialist subjects.'</text>
      <sha1>kugalcr1lep4m069ym452zupxt9acwx</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>High School Mathematics Extensions</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1317</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2311298</id>
      <parentid>2311294</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-04-23T12:42:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pi zero</username>
        <id>75960</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/204.39.64.2|204.39.64.2]] ([[User talk:204.39.64.2|talk]]) to last version by Addihockey10</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{featured book|print=Print Version|PDF=High School Mathematics Extensions}}

==Topics==
{{RenderPNG}}
{| class=wikitable cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
 ! colspan=&quot;6&quot; | Table of Contents
 |-
 ! # || Chapter || Status || Pages || Difficulty || Solutions
 |-
 | 1
 |style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|[[/Primes|Primes AND Modular Arithmetic]]
 |{{decistage|10}}|| 24 || [[File:100%.svg]][[File:100%.svg]][[File:100%.svg]]
 | [[/Primes/Solutions|ES]] - [[/Primes/Problem Set/Solutions|PS]]
 |-
 | 2
 |style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|[[/Logic/]]
 |{{decistage|7}}|| 18
 | [[File:100%.svg]][[File:100%.svg]]
 | [[/Logic/Solutions|ES]] - [[/Logic/Problem Set/Solutions|PS]]
 |-
 | 3
 |style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|[[/Mathematical Proofs/]] 
 |{{decistage|8}}|| 11
 | [[File:100%.svg]][[File:100%.svg]]
 | [[/Mathematical Proofs/Solutions|ES]] - [[/Mathematical Proofs/Problem Set/Solutions|PS]]
 |-
 | 4
 |style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|[[/Set Theory and Infinite Processes/]]
 |{{decistage|5}}|| 10
 | [[File:100%.svg]][[File:100%.svg]][[File:100%.svg]]
 | [[/Set Theory and Infinite Processes/Solutions|ES]] - [[/Set Theory and Infinite Processes/Problem Set/Solutions|PS]]
 |-
 | 5
 |style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|[[/Counting and Generating Functions/]]
 |{{decistage|7}}|| 14
 | [[File:100%.svg]][[File:100%.svg]][[File:100%.svg]][[File:100%.svg]]
 | [[/Counting and Generating Functions/Solutions|ES]] - [[/Counting and Generating Functions/Problem Set/Solutions|PS]]
 |-
 | 6
 |style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|[[/Discrete Probability/]]
 |{{decistage|3}}|| 12
 | [[File:100%.svg]][[File:100%.svg]][[File:100%.svg]]
 | [[/Discrete Probability/Solutions|ES]] - [[/Discrete Probability/Problem Set/Solutions|PS]]
 |-
 | 7
 |style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|[[/Matrices/]]
 |{{decistage|9}}|| 31
 | [[File:100%.svg]][[File:100%.svg]][[File:100%.svg]][[File:100%.svg]]
 | [[/Matrices/Solutions|ES]] - [[/Matrices/Problem Set/Solutions|PS]]
 |-
 | 8
 |style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|[[/Further Modular Arithmetic/]] 
 |{{decistage|6}}|| 14
 | [[File:100%.svg]][[File:100%.svg]][[File:100%.svg]][[File:100%.svg]][[File:100%.svg]]
 | [[/Further Modular Arithmetic/Solutions|ES]] - [[/Further Modular Arithmetic/Problem Set/Solutions|PS]]
 |-
 | 9
 |style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|[[/Mathematical Programming/]] 
 |{{decistage|1}}|| 4 || unrated
 | [[/Mathematical Programming/Solutions|ES]] - [[/Mathematical Programming/Problem Set/Solutions|PS]] 
 |-
 |
 ||  || || 143 ||
 |}

''' Supplementary '''
# [[/Supplementary/Basic Counting|Basic Counting]] - [[/Supplementary/Basic Counting/Solutions|ES]]
# [[/Supplementary/Partial Fractions|Partial Fractions]] - [[/Supplementary/Partial Fractions/Solutions|ES]]
# [[/Supplementary/Summation Sign|Summation Sign]] - [[/Supplementary/Summation Sign/Solutions|ES]] 
# [[/Supplementary/Complex Numbers|Complex Numbers]] - [[/Supplementary/Complex Numbers/Solutions|ES]] 
# [[/Supplementary/Differentiation|Differentiation]] - [[/Supplementary/Differentiation/Solutions|ES]]


&lt;small&gt;'' '''Note:''' '' * Means that the chapter is currently under active development by the author.&lt;/small&gt;

== Introduction ==

This online textbook is aimed at, but not limited to, 14 to 18 year olds who are interested in mathematics in general. Several interesting topics not covered in the standard high school curriculum of most countries are introduced in this text.

The materials presented here can be challenging.  But at the same time we strive to make this book accessible to all with 910 years of formal education.  We sincerely hope to interest, stimulate and challenge you with this book.

''' From the authors '''

It is our firm belief that math textbooks shouldn't just be a collection of mathematical facts carefully laid out, so the student can open it and cram in whatever formula they have to remember for tomorrow's exam.  A math textbook, especially for the youthful, should be full of questions, not just exercises.  Questions that require some thought to answer.  After all, &quot;it's the questions that keep the students interested, not the answers.&quot;
*Also (as it seems fitting):  Facts alone are as alike to math as bricks are to a house.  However, when math is explained, toughed and thought about, shown in context, etc. &amp;mdash; it resembles a house.

==Authors &amp; Contributors==
A number of persons not listed below have also made important contributions to this book.

{| width=&quot;100%&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;5&quot; cellpadding=&quot;5&quot;
 !Name
 !Role
 !Affiliation
 !Quote
 |-
 |[[User:Xiaodai|Zhuo Jia Dai]] 
 |Author
 |Former Honours Student of University of Sydney
 |Welcomes any criticism or praise. 
 |-
 |[[User:R3m0t|R3m0t]]
 |Corrections
 |Student of JFS Secondary school
 |&quot;To iterate is human; to recurse, divine.&quot;
 |-
 |[[User:Mmartin|Martin Warmer]]
 |Corrections&amp;solutions
 |Student of HBL high school
 |Welcomes all corrections and other help
 |-
 |[[User:Lemontea|Tom Lam]]
 |Supplementaries&amp;solutions
 |Student of Sha Tin Methodist College
 |&quot;Answer is merely the fuel for more questions.&quot;
 |}

{{subjects|K-12 mathematics}}
{{alphabetical|H}}
{{Status|50%}}

[[ja:]]</text>
      <sha1>gauz11t6n5spzsxq0bbhmkto5u6bhjd</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>