<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>File:FlowerLab1.jpg</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1821</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1604002</id>
      <parentid>1370845</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-08-09T10:46:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Retropunk</username>
        <id>34934</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Licensing */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Photograph for Botany Lab Excercise taken by Eric Guinther at Na Pohaku o Hauwahine, O'ahu, Hawai'i (October 2003) and released here under the GNU Free Documentation License.

==Licensing==
{{Information
|Description=Photograph for Botany Lab Excercise
|Source=
|Date=October 2003
|Author=Eric Guinther at Na Pohaku o Hauwahine, O'ahu, Hawai'i 
|Permission={{GFDL}}
}}

[[Category:Botany]]</text>
      <sha1>tbtsd31yqo39zjxkvorogklw3q3odsj</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:FlowerLab3.jpg</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1825</id>
    <revision>
      <id>730059</id>
      <parentid>153911</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-01-23T04:34:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Iamunknown</username>
        <id>3310</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>tag with {{GFDL}} (it was stated explicitly in the existing image description)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Photograph of ''Bidens torta'' taken at Kolekole Pass on O'ahu, Hawai'i by Eric Guinther and released under the GNU Free Documentation License. Also used at '''Wikipedia'''.

== Licensing ==

{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>rcsci14s1gybcu26p822wipdo9jtu1d</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:FlowerLab3 reduced.jpg</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1826</id>
    <revision>
      <id>730060</id>
      <parentid>153912</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-01-23T04:35:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Iamunknown</username>
        <id>3310</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>tag as {{GFDL}} (it was explicitly released in the image description, but not machine-readable tagged)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Photograph of ''Bidens torta'' taken at Kolekole Pass on O'ahu, Hawai'i by Eric Guinther and released under the GNU Free Documentation License. Also used at '''Wikipedia'''.  Larger version at [[media:FlowerLab3.jpg]].

== Licensing ==

{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>h56uvhub091g87a1y469jxzxko2ncyn</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Latin/Lesson 1-Nominative</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1829</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2120992</id>
      <parentid>2120989</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-06-14T19:58:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Robert.Baruch</username>
        <id>344325</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Furthur Examples */ There is -&gt; it is</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{WikiProject Languages}} 




== Declension? ==

Like the editor of &quot;Pronunciation?&quot;, I'm attempting to learn Latin via this book, however, on the vocabulary lists māter, triclīnium, and templum don't match any of the nominative endings that we're given in the previous table. I'm assuming they're third declension, but clarification would be nice.


The last word in the first homework sentence should perhaps be 'malus', not 'magnus'. Would it be a good idea to give the English of these sentences in Lesson 4?

== Pronunciation? ==

I haven't read the book, and don't speak latin, but I'm hoping to and this might be a good section to add proper pronunciation of words.

I've improved upon the pronunciation section in the last page so that it's more than just a link.

== Example ==

I'm attempting to learn Latin from this book and seem to have spotted something inconsistent on this page. With the fourth example given in the
&quot;Examples&quot; section, &quot;poēta est bonus&quot; the declensions are different in gender. If this is an exception to the rule that all adjectives must have
the same gender, case and number as the noun it is describing, I think this should be explicitly stated, otherwise this could be confusing. - [[User:Nibjib|Nibjib]] ([[User talk:Nibjib|talk]]) 20:19, 1 June 2008 (UTC)


-Poeta is actually a masculine word, owing to the fact that it describes a traditionally masculine profession. There are a variety of words in the first declension that operate in this way, including nauta, poeta, and agricola. Furthermore, there are some words in the second declension, mainly trees, that are feminine. However, the most obvious example of cross gender words in unusual declensions is &quot;manus&quot; of the 4th, which is feminine, and not masculine as is the case with most of the declension.

-Asv


== Furthur Examples ==

Why are these different from the examples preceding it? The &quot;Furthur Examples&quot; say &quot;Triclinium magnum est&quot; is wrong, and &quot;Tricilinium est magnum&quot; is correct. Yet in the &quot;Examples&quot;, all the Latin sentences are constructed in this manner, i.e. &quot;Puellae bonae sunt&quot;, and not &quot;Puellae sunt bonae&quot;.

Which is correct? -Anam



Actually, in this case, and most cases, it does not matter because you can tell what it means either way. However, it is much more common to use subject-adjective-verb format, so one would normally use &quot;Triclinium magnum est&quot;. There is not a &quot;wrong&quot; sentence structure in Latin, although with longer sentences it may often be confusing, so it is usually better to use the common nom-adj-vb format.

-Froggyfred

...Except in the case of ''est'', where the neutral sentence is ''X est Y''. Moving ''est'' to the end gives you emphasis. Verbs that normally come in the middle of two nominatives are called copulative verbs (because they equate, or link, or ''copulate'', one thing to another). Some others are: apparēre, vidēri, manēre. Consider:

* Est puella. There is a girl.
* Puella est. It is ''a girl'' (as opposed to a boy).
* Puella est bona. The girl is good.
* Est puella bona. There is a good girl.
* Puella bona est. The girl is ''good'' (as opposed to bad).
* Bona est puella. ''Good'' is what the girl is (as opposed to bad).
* Bona puella est. What is good is ''the girl'' (as opposed to the boy).


* Puer videtur fessus. The boy seems tired.
* Puer fessus videtur. The boy seems ''tired'' (as opposed to energetic).
* Fessus videtur puer. ''Tired'' is what the boy seems (as opposed to energetic).
* Videtur puer fessus. He seems (to be) a tired boy.

Note that the translations are colloquial, not literal, because a literal translation would not convey the nuances of the word order.

See, for example, D'Ooge ¶28. --[[User:Robert.Baruch|Robert.Baruch]] ([[User talk:Robert.Baruch|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Robert.Baruch|contribs]]) 19:34, 14 June 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>rku29cnyi220v89khm4rkskn7gscdqx</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Latin/Lesson 3-Present Verbs</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1833</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2554400</id>
      <parentid>2489513</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-09-05T16:08:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>216.8.136.34</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Excercises */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Latin}}

= Grammatical Introduction to Verbs =

This introductory section may be a bit overwhelming, but is an overall look at verbs. The majority of this section will be covered in later chapters. Nevertheless, looking over this chapter may help you to familiarize yourself with verbs. 

Verbs are parts of speech which denote action. There are two main forms of verbs in Latin:

• Principal Verbs (the main verb which is found in every sentence. e.g.,: vir &lt;B&gt;ambulat&lt;B&gt; = the man &lt;B&gt;is walking&lt;B&gt;)

• Adjectival Verbs (also known as participles, gerunds and gerundives which describe the state of the described noun. e.g.,: vir &lt;B&gt;ambulans&lt;B&gt; = the &lt;B&gt;walking&lt;B&gt; man. The verb behaves as an adjective)

Every sentence &lt;B&gt;must&lt;/B&gt; have a verb. In a sense, the principal verb is the sentence and all the nouns, adverbs and participles are only describing the scenario of the verb. Thus in Latin this constitutes a sentence:

 &lt;I&gt;est.&lt;/I&gt;

If you want to explain 'who' is or exists, you add a nominative substantive:

 &lt;I&gt;Cornēlia est.&lt;/I&gt;

We now know Cornelia 'is'. But what is she? So we add an adjective.

 &lt;I&gt;Cornēlia est bona.&lt;/I&gt;

Now we can see that Cornelia is good, but to elaborate further we can add an adverb:

 &lt;I&gt;Cornēlia vix est bona.&lt;/I&gt;

Now we know that Cornelia is 'hardly' (''[[wiktionary:vix#Latin|vix]]'': hardly, scarcely, barely) good.

Thus, in English, the shortest Latin sentence is:

You are.

in Latin:

 &lt;I&gt;es&lt;/I&gt;

==Examples==

These two examples will demonstrate the difference between an adjectival verb and a principal verb.

{| border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | The '''resurrected''' Jesus '''appeared''' to his disciples.
|-
| 'resurrected' is a ''perfect participle'' (Adjectival) describing Jesus, while 'appeared' is the ''principal verb'' in the sentence.
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;#CCFFFF&quot; | The '''shocked''' disciples '''see''' Jesus.
|-
| 'shocked' is a ''perfect participle'' (Adjectival) describing the disciples, while 'see' is the ''principal verb'' in the sentence.
|}

===Exercises===
{{Latin/Exercise|Answer|
#What is the difference between a principal and adjectival verb?
#What constitutes a sentence?
#Write a sentence in English, and Latin.
#Conjugate the verb 'to be' in the present tense in English and Latin (I am, You are, He is etc.)
|
#Principal verbs are main verb which is found in every sentence.   Adjectival Verbs are participles, gerunds and gerundives which describe the state of the described noun.
#a verb
#Egō Sum, I am
#Sum, es, est, sumus, estis, sunt
  
}}

==Personal Endings==

Verbs in Latin are inflected to reflect the person who performs the action. English does the same to some extent in the verb to be:


{| border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
| Latin || English
|-
| sum || I am
|-
| es || You are
|-
| est || (He/she/it) is
|-
| sumus || We are
|-
| estis || You (all) are
|-
| sunt || They are
|}

Latin, however, inflects all verbs, and is much more extensive than English, allowing writers and speakers of Latin to often drop the personal pronoun (as mentioned last lesson), as the performer of the action is understood by the formation of the verb. The Personal pronoun is only usually added for emphasis. In a way, the ending on Latin verbs are a type of pronoun.

===Exercises===

{{Latin/Exercise|Answer|
# What do the personal pronouns indicate?
|
# Personal pronouns (ego, tu, nos, vos, etc.) add emphasis. They are usually omitted (left out) because they are understood.
#: Example: ''[Ego] amō [[wikt:pater#Latin|patrem]] meum et [[wikt:mater#Latin|matrem]] meam.'' 
#: I love my mother and my father. (you don't have to write ''ego'', it is understood)
}}

== Moods ==

There are several moods. Each has its own uses to convey certain ideas.  The most commons moods are:

• Indicative
• Subjunctive or Conjunctive
• Imperative

The two moods we will first learn are the &lt;B&gt;imperative&lt;/B&gt; (commands and orders) and the &lt;B&gt;indicative&lt;/B&gt; (declarative statements and factual questions).

=== Exercises ===

{{Latin/Exercise|Answer|
# List the most common moods.
# What two moods are we going to learn about in this lesson, and what do they let us construct?
|
# Indicative, subjunctive (or conjunctive) and imperative.
# The moods we are going to learn about first are:
#: '''Imperative''': Which we use when we make orders.
#:: ''Go'' away. ''Fetch'' me the keys. ''Do'' not order me around!
#: '''Indicative''': Statements which are declarative, and questions concerning facts.
#:: John ''plays'' football.
}}

== Voice ==

There are two constructions verbs can have regarding voice.

Verbs can have either an active or passive voice.

E.g.  'I smash the car.' 'smash' is an active verb construct.

The passive is used when the nominative is affected by the verb. 

E.g. 'The car is smashed by me.' 'is smashed' is a passive construct.

=== Exercises ===

{{Latin/Exercise|Translate|
# What is 'voice'?
# What is active voice?
# What is passive voice?
# Construct a sentence in English using each of these voices.
|
# Voice is how a verb is constructed.
# When the subject affects the verb
# When the nominative is affected by the verb
#Ex.- I carried, I am being carried.
}}

== Tense ==

Tense in Latin comprises two parts: TIME and ASPECT.  Time reflects when the action is occurring or did occur: past, present, or future.  Aspect refers to the nature of the action: simple, completed, or repeated.  The &quot;completed&quot; aspect is generally termed &quot;perfective&quot; and repeated aspect &quot;imperfective.&quot;  

Theoretically, a verb could have nine tenses (combinations of time and aspect).  However, Latin only has six, since some possible combinations are expressed by the same verb forms.  Latin tenses do not correspond exactly to English ones.

Below is a rough guide to tense in Latin.


{| border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
|
| colspan=&quot;5&quot; | &lt;CENTER&gt;&lt;B&gt;Time&lt;/B&gt;&lt;/CENTER&gt;
|-
| rowspan=&quot;4&quot; | &lt;CENTER&gt;&lt;B&gt;A&lt;BR&gt;S&lt;BR&gt;P&lt;BR&gt;E&lt;BR&gt;C&lt;BR&gt;T&lt;/B&gt;&lt;/CENTER&gt;
|
 || Present || Future || Past
|-
| Simple
&lt;TD&gt;&lt;i&gt;Present Tense&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&quot;I walk&quot;
| &lt;i&gt;Future Tense&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&quot;I will walk&quot;
| &lt;i&gt;Perfect Tense&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&quot;I walked&quot;
|-
| Imperfective
| &lt;i&gt;Present Tense&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&quot;I am walking&quot;
| &lt;i&gt;Future Tense&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&quot;I will be walking&quot;
| &lt;i&gt;Imperfect Tense&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&quot;I was walking&quot;
|-
| Perfective
| &lt;i&gt;Perfect Tense&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&quot;I have walked&quot;
| &lt;i&gt;Future Perfect Tense&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&quot;I will have walked&quot;
| &lt;i&gt;Pluperfect Tense&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&quot;I had walked&quot;
|}

As is evident, some Latin tenses do &quot;double duty.&quot;  The Latin Present and Future Tenses can either express simple or progressive aspect.  Particularly difficult to grasp is the Latin Perfect tense, which can either express an action completed from the point of view of the present (&quot;I have just now finished walking&quot;), or a simple action in past time (its &quot;aorist&quot; sense, from the old Indo European aorist tense, which Latin lost but is still present in Greek).

=== Exercises ===
{{Latin/Exercise|Translate|
#Copy out the above table.
#Study the table.
|
Vide (see) the table above.
}}

== Infinitive ==

The infinitive (impersonal) is the form of the verb which simply means 'to (verb)' e.g. 'to do', or 'to be', or 'to love', or 'to hate' etc. All forms which are not in the infinitive are in the finite (personalised) form.

The infinitive has a -re at the end of the stem of the verb. The infinitive of 'to be' is an exception and is 'esse'.

Dēbeō curre&lt;B&gt;re&lt;/B&gt; nunc = I ought to run now.

Esse, aut nōn esse = To be, or not to be?

===Exercises===

Answer these two question about the '''infinitive''' and '''finite'''.

{{Latin/Exercise|Answer|
# What is the '''infinitive'''? Give an example.
# What is the '''finite'''? Give an example.
|
# The '''infinitive''' is the verb-form that simply mean &quot;to (verb)&quot;.
#: To ''sing'', to ''dance'', to ''drink'', to ''love''.
# Every verb which is not in the infinitive, is in the '''finite'''.
#: He ''smells'', we ''plot'', she had ''drunk'', he ''pours''.
}}

== Irregularities ==

Verbs which use the passive formation in an active sense are known as deponent. Verbs which don't have a form for every tense and mood are known as defective. You will meet a few words like this soon.

===Exercises===
{{Latin/Exercise|Answer|
#What is a deponent verb?
#What is an irregular verb?
#What is a defective verb?
|
#A verb which uses the passive voice in an active sense.
#A verb that does not follow the normal rules of conjugation.
#A verb missing forms for some tenses or moods.
}}

== Personal Pronouns ==

In case you do ever use a personal pronoun to emphasise the SUBJECT of the verb, you must remember that the personal pronoun must be in the nominative case and the number and person of the verb must match that of the subject. (Review Lesson 7 if unfamiliar with the terms person and subject).

=== Exercises ===
{{Latin/Exercise|Translate|
#What case should the subject (performer) of the verb be in?
#What number should the principal verb be?
#What person and number is 'ego'?
#What person and number is 'I'?
#What person and number is 'we'?
#What person and number is 'thou'?
#What person and number is 'ye'?
#What person and number is 'vōs'?
#What person and number is 'nōs'?
#What person and number is 'tū'?
#What person and number is 'boy'?
|
# Nominative case
# First person, singular.
# First person, singular.
# First person, singular.
# First person, plural.
# Second person, singular.
# Second person, plural.
# Second person, plural.
# First person, plural.
# Second person, singular.
# Third person, singular.
}}

== Principal Parts ==

When one looks up a verb in the dictionary, the principal parts are given. From these principal parts you can find the correct form of the verb for every circumstance.


{| border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
| Present Indicative Active 1st Person || Present Infinitive
| Perfect Indicative Active 1st Person || Supine
|-
| amō || amāre || amāvi || amātum
|-
| Determines whether the vowel is dropped in the 1st person singular present.
| Gives the imperfect stem and infinitive
| Gives the perfect stem
| Allows you to form adjectival forms of the verb (Participles)
|}

=== Exercises ===
Answer this question about '''principal parts'''.

{{Latin/Exercise|Answer|
# What do the '''principal parts''' allow you to do?
|
# The principal parts are the verb-forms you find when you look in the dictionary. E.g. if you look for the verb ''amō'' (love) in a dictionary you would find:
#: amō • amāre • amāvi • amātum 
:: These four forms will help you form every Latin verb you want.
}}

== Using the Dictionary ==

All nouns are given in the nominative, as well as the declension and gender of the noun. Verbs are alphabetized using the 1st person singular  (the first principal part) and the infinitive is given.  Supplementary principal parts are given if the various other principal parts do not follow the standard pattern of formation from the infinitive and 1st person singular.

=Verbs: Conjugation in the Present Imperfect =
 
The present imperfect is the simplest tense. To form the present imperfect all that is required is to place the personal endings at the end of the verb stem.
 
Thus, if you have the stem 'ama' (love), to make it 'I love' you place an ō at the end.

 I love  =  amō (amaō*)
 we love =  amāmus

* Latin drops the 'a' in amaō forming amō.

Latin '''could''' add personal pronouns, however only for added emphasis and in conjunction with the corresponding person ending on the verb. Otherwise the sentence will not make sense. For example:
 
ego amō = I (not you) love

nōs amāmus = We (not you) love
 
but that would be for special emphasis: It's '''I''', not you, who love.

Here are the forms of the verb 'porta', carry, in the present imperfect tense:

 portō     I carry                     first person singular
 portās    thou carriest, you carry    second person singular
 portat    he, she, it carries         third person singular 
 portāmus  we carry                    first person plural
 portātis  you (all) carry             second person plural
 portant   they carry                  third person plural

'porto' can also be translated 'I am carrying' (present imperfect), 'I do carry' (present emphatic).  'I carry' is known as the 'present simple' tense in English.. Again the 'a' gets dropped when the 'ō' is placed on porta. Porta, and ama are known as 1st conjugation verbs; in other words, verbs which have a stem ending in 'a'.

There are three other conjugations, and below are some examples of verbs from each of the four conjugations (present imperfect tense):

 
{| border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
| porta, carry (1st. Conj) || mone, warn (2nd Conj)
| rege, rule (3rd Conj.) || audī, hear (4th Conj)
|-
| portō, I carry || moneō, I warn || regō, I rule
| audiō, I hear
|-
| portās, thou carriest || monēs, thou warnest
| regis, thou rulest || audis, thou hearest
|-
| portat, he/she/it carries || monet, he/she/it warns
| regit, he/she/it rules || audit, he/she/it hears
|-
| portāmus, we carry || monēmus, we warn
| regimus, we rule || audimus, we hear
|-
| portātis, ye carry || monētis, ye warn
| regitis, ye rule || auditis, ye hear
|-
| portant, they carry || monent, they warn
| regunt, they rule || audiunt, they hear
|}

Each verb uses the same final letter or letters to indicate the 'subject' - I, thou, he/she/it, we, you, they.

Before these final letters, the first conjugation has an 'a' (although when an 'o' is placed, the 'a' is often dropped), the second an 'e', and the third and fourth usually an 'i'. The third person plural forms in the third and fourth conjugations have a 'u'. These verb forms really should be learned by heart.

The most common verb of all is irregular (see next lesson). Here is a table of the verb 'to be' in Latin, English, and four Romantic languages (French, Spanish, Italian and Portuguese)

{| border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
| colspan=&quot;6&quot; | esto: be
|-
| &lt;B&gt;Latin&lt;/B&gt; || &lt;B&gt;English&lt;/B&gt; || &lt;B&gt;French&lt;/B&gt;
| &lt;B&gt;Spanish&lt;/B&gt;|| &lt;B&gt;Italian&lt;/B&gt; || &lt;B&gt;Portuguese&lt;/B&gt;
|-
| sum || I am || je suis || yo soy || sono || eu sou
|-
| es || thou art || tu es || tú eres || sei || tu és
|-
| est || he/she/it is || il/elle est || él/ella es || è || ele/ela é
|-
| sumus || we are || nous sommes || nosotros/-as somos || siamo || nós somos
|-
| estis || ye are || vous &amp;ecirc;tes || vosotros/-as sois || siete  || vós sois
|-
| sunt || they are || ils/elles sont || ellos/-as son || sono  || eles/elas são
|}

The personal endings are the same as in the four regular conjugations.

=== Exercises ===
:''Conjugate (find how a verb is in different forms) the verb 'amõ'.''

{{Latin/Exercise|Translate|What form of the verb 'amõ' (hint: amõ is conjugated like portõ in the table above) would the following words use to become the suffix:
#ego (I)
#tū (thou)
#puer (the boy)
#nōs (we)
#vōs (ye)
#puellae (the girls)
|
#[ego] amõ (I love)
#[tu] amās (thou lovest ''pl.'', you love ''pl.'')
#puer amat (the boy loves)
#[nos] amāmus (we love)
#[vos] amātis (ye love ''pl.'', you love ''pl.'')
#puellae amant (the girls love)
}}

&lt;br&gt;

== Imperative Mood ==

The imperative mood conveys an order (e.g. Go!, Run!, Away Now!). The imperative mood is formed by simply using the stem of the verb. If the order is to a large group of people, or you are trying to show respect, you must use the -te suffix.

amō eum = I love him.

amā eum = Love him!.

amāte eum = Love (respectful, or plural) him!


currō casam = I run home.

curre casam = Run home!

currite casam = Run (respectful, or plural) home!


Regō prudente = I rule wisely.

Rege prudente = Rule wisely!

Regite prudente = Rule (respectful order) wisely!

=== Exercises ===

* ''Translate Latin verbs:''

{{Latin/Exercise|Translate|Translate the following verbs:
# portāmus • regunt • monēs • estis • audītis • monent • regō • portās • sunt
|
# we carry • they rule • thou warnest • ye are •ye hear • they warn • I rule • you carry • they are
}}

* ''Translate sentences into Latin:''

{{Latin/Exercise|Translate|Translate Into Latin:
# I carry my book.
# Thou kill not.
# They hear music.
|
# Meum lībrum portō.
# Interficis nōn.
# Mūsicam audiunt.
}}</text>
      <sha1>1n1w6og4v42nc53mf2b26e0jvyzp6nh</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Latin/Appendix H</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1834</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1182069</id>
      <parentid>518202</parentid>
      <timestamp>2008-05-10T17:08:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>86.145.156.94</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Adversus eos qui ecclesia relicta ad circenses ludos et ad theatra transfigerunt
A complete textbook for spoken Classical Latin, G.J. Adler's &quot;A Practical Grammar of the Latin Language for Speaking and Writing Latin&quot; can be found on Google Books: 
http://www.google.co.uk/books?id=GJgAAAAAYAAJ
This textbook can be heard read out aloud here:
http://latinum.mypodcast.com

[[Category:Latin]]</text>
      <sha1>80qnjf6p7n4g6v0csnee7gxqb3k6f26</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Noldoaran</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>1835</id>
    <revision>
      <id>433665</id>
      <parentid>433660</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-04-20T01:49:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Noldoaran</username>
        <id>214</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">My other user pages: [[m:User:Noldoaran|MetaWiki]] | '''[[Wikipedia:en:User:Noldoaran|Wikipedia]]''' | Wikibooks | [[Wiktionary:User:Noldoaran|Wiktionary]] | [[Commons:User:Noldoaran|Commons]]</text>
      <sha1>md67g9h73ak09v4ibr3e8nb0sl3k3sw</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:US History/Civil War</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1837</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2677157</id>
      <parentid>2359465</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-06-28T19:47:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pittsburgh Poet</username>
        <id>1449338</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Technical firsts in the Amercan Civil War */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Your section on McClellan is so filled with errors and mis-representations as to be laughable.  That being the case, I did not bother to read the rest of your piece.  Suggest you do a bit more homework in future.
--

Would the user making the above statement like References? Perhaps if he or she would point out the specific &quot;errors and mis-representations,&quot; one may attempt to amend them in to provide greater accuracy. [[User:Lord Emsworth|Lord Emsworth]]

I changed the name of John (born Johan) Ericsson to the (dare I say) correct spelling (was Ericcson), but missed the summary box. The main wikipedia entry supports this spelling. It is also the spelling on his mausoleum in Filipstad, Sweden. Also his brother Nils, changed the spelling to 'Ericson' when he was knighted, something that John reportedly never forgave him for. In that light I find it unlikely that he would have let himself to be known under the name of 'Ericcson'. I do however find numerous sources on the web that lists his name with the odd spelling, so there might be a controversy regarding that on the other side of the atlantic? (Or is it just an early error that has been propagated?) I have several links to back this up, but as they are in Swedish it's perhaps not very useful to include them here. (I also went to the Nils Ericson high school, but that's another story).

----
I've been adding a few things to this section starting under 'Shiloh'. Let me know if this is all right, but I'm assuming so. There is a good article on the battle in Wikipedia (and probably on others) so what I have tried to do is a brief expansion of the section to set up the situation and then encourage use of the link. [[User:Erraunt|erraunt]] 16:27, 4 October 2005 (UTC)

Ran into the kilobyte limit when trying to edit this section. Are there any plans to create subsections? Any reasons not to before I start making more involved changes? Personally, if it is desireable to grow and develop this book, I believe it will be necessary to break this &quot;chapter&quot; on the Civil War out into multiple subsections to provide the space necessary for the topics. [[User:Erraunt|erraunt]] 19:56, 4 October 2005 (UTC)

I changed some misspellings on this page and corrected one error. Ben Butler, the Beast of New Orleans, was from Massachusetts, not New Jersey.

== Technical firsts in the Amercan Civil War ==

According to the article the American Civil War was the first to see the use of flamethrowers, organised medical and nursing units and ambulance corps and the introduction of the income tax. This is incorrect, as the Chinese invented the flamethrower in the 10th Century (the following article has a picture of a 12th Century version: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Chinese_Flamethrower.JPG) and is attributed to have been first used in World War 1 elsewhere in Wikipedia (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flamethrower). 

Furthermore income tax is reckoned to have been introduced by the Chinese (again) in the year 10 and used by the UK in the 12th Century, to fund wars against Saladin, and at the end of the 18th Century, to fund wars against Napoleon.  Speaking of Napoleon, he introduced organised medical units and ambulances into his armies (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dominique_Jean_Larrey).   Lastly nursing, specifically military nursing, was what Florence Nightgale (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Florence_Nightingale) became famous for in the Crimean War in the 1850s, so cannot hae been introduced during the American Civil War. 

Due to these factual errors, the article stands somewhat degraded and should be edited following further research. [[Special:Contributions/81.159.107.166|81.159.107.166]] ([[User talk:81.159.107.166|discuss]]) 19:41, 4 June 2012 (UTC)

I'm going to try to amend it to *the 1st American use* of these things. Thank you. [[User:Pittsburgh Poet|Pittsburgh Poet]] ([[User talk:Pittsburgh Poet|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Pittsburgh Poet|contribs]]) 19:47, 28 June 2014 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>rdpdvwkx5ag7ruiftne3f42lcka453t</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Linear Algebra/Eigenvalues and eigenvectors</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1838</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2544192</id>
      <parentid>1841348</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-07-19T03:07:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>78.160.123.71</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Finding eigenvalues and eigenvectors */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Eigenvalues and eigenvectors''' are related to fundamental properties of matrices.

:The word ''eigenvalue'' comes from the German ''Eigenwert'' which means &quot;proper or characteristic value.&quot;

== Motivations ==
Large matrices can be costly, in terms of computational time, to use, and may have to be iterated hundreds or thousands of times for a calculation.  Additionally, the behavior of matrices would be hard to explore without important mathematical tools.  One mathematical tool, which has applications not only for Linear Algebra but for differential equations, calculus, and many other areas, is the concept of ''eigenvalues'' and ''eigenvectors''.  Eigenvalues and eigenvectors are based upon a common behavior in linear systems.  Let's look at an example.

Let
: &lt;math&gt;A=\begin{pmatrix} 
1 &amp; 2  \\
0 &amp; -2 \\
\end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;
and
: &lt;math&gt;\mathbf{x}=\begin{pmatrix} -2 \\ 3 \\ \end{pmatrix},\quad \mathbf{y}=\begin{pmatrix} 1 \\ 0 \\ \end{pmatrix}.&lt;/math&gt;

What happens with '''x''' and '''y''' if they are transformed by ''A''? Well,
: &lt;math&gt;A\mathbf{x}=\begin{pmatrix} 4 \\ -6 \\ \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;
: &lt;math&gt;A\mathbf{y}=\begin{pmatrix} 1 \\ 0 \\ \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;

But what is remarkable is that 
: &lt;math&gt;A\mathbf{x}=(-2)\begin{pmatrix} -2 \\ 3 \\ \end{pmatrix}=-2\mathbf{x}&lt;/math&gt;
: &lt;math&gt;A\mathbf{y}=(1)\begin{pmatrix} 1 \\ 0 \\ \end{pmatrix}=\mathbf{y}=(1)\mathbf{y}&lt;/math&gt;

So when we operate on the vector '''x''' with the matrix ''A'', instead of getting a different vector (as we would normally do),  we get the ''same'' vector '''x''' multiplied by some constant. And the same goes for vector '''y'''.

We call the values 1 and -2 the ''eigenvalues'' of the matrix ''A'', and the vectors '''x''' and '''y'''  are called ''eigenvectors'' for the matrix ''A''.

== Definitions ==
We now generalize this concept of when a matrix/vector product is the same as a product by a scalar as above: essentially if we have a ''n''&amp;times;''n'' matrix A, we seek solutions in '''v''' to find the eigenvectors, and solutions in &amp;lambda; to find the eigenvalues for the equation
: A'''v'''=&amp;lambda;'''v'''

How are we to do this? Let us rearrange the equation
: A'''v'''-&amp;lambda;'''v'''='''0'''
: (A-&amp;lambda;I)'''v'''='''0''' (''note we must multiply the scalar by the identity matrix otherwise A-&amp;lambda; makes no sense'')

But (A-&amp;lambda;I) is a matrix, so we are trying to solve B'''v'''='''0''' where B=(A-&amp;lambda;I), and this solution is merely the kernel of B, ker B. So the eigenvectors are in ker (A-&amp;lambda;I), where &amp;lambda; is an eigenvalue. But how do we find the eigenvalues?

B'''v'''='''0''' has nonzero solution if |B| = det(B) is zero. So to find the eigenvalues, we let |A-&amp;lambda;I|=0 and then solve for &amp;lambda;. We will thus obtain a polynomial equation over the complex numbers (eigenvalues can be complex), known as the ''characteristic equation''. The roots of the characteristic equation are the eigenvalues.

Note that we exclude '''0''' as an eigenvector, because it is trivially a solution to A'''v'''=&amp;lambda;'''v''' and is not really interesting to consider.  Additionally, if the zero vector were to be included, it would allow for an infinite number of eigenvalues, since any value of &amp;lambda; satisfies A'''0'''=&amp;lambda;'''0'''.

If we have an eigenvalue &amp;lambda; of a matrix A, together with a corresponding eigenvector, '''x''', then any multiple of '''x''' is also an eigenvector for the same eigenvalue. To see that k'''x''' is also an eigenvector, follow this argument:
If A'''x'''=&amp;lambda;'''x''', then A(k'''x''')=kA'''x'''=k&amp;lambda;'''x'''=&amp;lambda;(k'''x'''). (Here k may be any scalar.) Thus, every multiple of an eigenvector is also an eigenvector. 

Note the asymmetry here: eigenvalues are unique, while an eigenvalue has many eigenvectors.

=== Finding eigenvalues and eigenvectors ===
Here are some examples of finding eigenvalues and eigenvectors using our definitions.

Let 
: &lt;math&gt;A = \begin{pmatrix} 3 &amp; 0 \\
                           -1 &amp; 2 \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;

Firstly, we expand |A-&amp;lambda;I|=0 to find the eigenvalues: 
:  &lt;math&gt;\left| \begin{pmatrix} 3 &amp; 0 \\  
                                                -1 &amp; 2 \end{pmatrix}-
                \begin{pmatrix} \lambda &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; \lambda\end{pmatrix}
               \right|=0&lt;/math&gt;


: &lt;math&gt;\begin{vmatrix} 3 - \lambda &amp; 0 \\
                                 -1 &amp; 2 - \lambda \end{vmatrix}=0&lt;/math&gt;
:&lt;math&gt; (3-\lambda)(2-\lambda)-(0)(-1)=0&lt;/math&gt;
:&lt;math&gt; (3-\lambda)(2-\lambda)=0&lt;/math&gt;

Now, elementary algebra tells us the roots of this equation are 3 and 2, and thus these are our eigenvalues. 

(''Exercise: prove that in a 2&amp;times;2 triangular matrix the eigenvalues are on the principal diagonal. Harder: generalize this result'')

Now we can find our eigenvectors. Consider the first eigenvalue &amp;lambda;=3. To find our first eigenvector
: &lt;math&gt; \mbox{ker} (A-3I) =  \mbox{ker} 
            \begin{pmatrix} 3-3 &amp; 0 \\
                           -1 &amp; 2-3 \end{pmatrix}
                            =  \mbox{ker} 
            \begin{pmatrix} 0 &amp; 0 \\
                           -1 &amp; -1 \end{pmatrix} &lt;/math&gt;
At this point we can row-reduce and back-substitute, '''but usually it suffices to''' guess the kernel since our matrix is small and we have linearly dependent columns. Now, observe:
: &lt;math&gt; \begin{pmatrix}
                            0 &amp; 0 \\
                           -1 &amp; -1 \end{pmatrix} 
\begin{pmatrix} a \\ -a \end{pmatrix}=\mathbf{0}&lt;/math&gt;
So, for any scalar a, the vector
:&lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} a \\ -a \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt; is an eigenvector. Stated another way, the set of all eigenvectors of the matrix ''A'' includes the set &lt;math&gt;\mbox{span} \{\begin{pmatrix} 1 \\ -1 \end{pmatrix}\}&lt;/math&gt;. In the plane, this represents a line of slope -1 through the origin.

As noted above the eigenvalues of a matrix are uniquely determined, but for each eigenvalue there are many eigenvectors. We usually choose an eigenvector for some convenience such as &quot;most whole number entries&quot;, &quot;first entry is 1&quot;, or &quot;length of the eigenvector is 1&quot;.  
Most Computer Algebra Systems choose unit vectors for eigenvectors.

So here we may take &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} 1 \\ -1 \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt; to be the eigenvector, for example. 

Similarly for our second eigenvalue &amp;lambda;=2, to find our second eigenvector:
: &lt;math&gt; \mbox{ker} (A-2I) =  \mbox{ker} 
            \begin{pmatrix}1 &amp; 0 \\
                           -1 &amp; 0 \end{pmatrix}=
\mbox{span} \{\begin{pmatrix} 0 \\ 1 \end{pmatrix}\}=\mathbf{0}&lt;/math&gt;
And so, our second eigenvector is chosen as
:&lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} 0 \\ 1 \end{pmatrix}.&lt;/math&gt;

Our eigenvalues then are &amp;lambda;=2,3, with eigenvectors &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} 1 \\ -1 \end{pmatrix}, \begin{pmatrix} 0 \\ 1 \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;, as may be checked by multiplying each by the given matrix.

(We also could choose &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} 1/\sqrt(2) \\-1/\sqrt(2)  \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt; as an eigenvector for the eigenvalue &amp;lambda;=3 . Check this.)

=== Problem set ===
Given the above, find the eigenvalues and eigenvectors of the following matrices (Answers follow to even-numbered questions):
# &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} 3 &amp; 0 \\ -4 &amp; 5 \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;
# &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} 1 &amp; 1 \\ 3 &amp; -1 \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;
# &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} -2 &amp; 0 &amp; 3 \\ 2 &amp; 4 &amp; 0 \\ 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt; 
:(Harder. Hint: one eigenvalue is 4.)

==== Answers ====
# eigenvalues: 3, 5; eigenvectors: &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} 1 \\ 2 \end{pmatrix}, \begin{pmatrix}  0\\1  \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;
# eigenvalues: -2, 2; eigenvectors: &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} -1 \\ 3 \end{pmatrix}, \begin{pmatrix}  1\\1  \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;
# eigenvalues: -3, 1, 4; eigenvectors: &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix}21\\-6\\-7\end{pmatrix},\begin{pmatrix}3\\-2\\3\end{pmatrix},\begin{pmatrix}0\\1\\0\end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;

== Applications ==
Eigenvalues and eigenvectors are not mere pretty facts about these vectors; they have relevant and important applications.

=== Matrix powers ===
Let us first examine a certain class of matrices known as ''diagonal'' matrices: these are matrices in the form
:&lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} 
a_0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; \ldots &amp; 0 \\
0 &amp; a_1 &amp; 0 &amp; \ldots &amp; 0 \\
0 &amp; 0 &amp; a_2 &amp; \ldots &amp; 0 \\
0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; \ldots &amp; a_k \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;

Now, observe that 
:&lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} 
a_0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; \ldots &amp; 0 \\
0 &amp; a_1 &amp; 0 &amp; \ldots &amp; 0 \\
0 &amp; 0 &amp; a_2 &amp; \ldots &amp; 0 \\
0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; \ldots &amp; a_k \end{pmatrix}^k=
\begin{pmatrix} 
a_0^k &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; \ldots &amp; 0 \\
0 &amp; a_1^k &amp; 0 &amp; \ldots &amp; 0 \\
0 &amp; 0 &amp; a_2^k &amp; \ldots &amp; 0 \\
0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; \ldots &amp; a_k^k \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;

This is a very useful property! However, the number of matrices to which we can apply this fact is clearly limited, so we ask ourselves whether we can transform a given matrix into a diagonal matrix. 

The answer to this question is &quot;sometimes&quot;, but for the moment, we will only look at matrices for which this answer is &quot;yes&quot;. 

What we seek is a matrix P such that
:PAP&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;=D
where D is diagonal.

If such a matrix P exists, we say that A is ''diagonalizable''. (Note that ''xyx''&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; is often called a ''similarity transformation'').

Then
: PAP&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;=D
: AP&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;=P&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;D
by multiplying throughout forward by P&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, then
: A=P&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;DP
by multiplying backward by P.

Now, we have
: A&lt;sup&gt;k&lt;/sup&gt;=(P&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;DP)&lt;sup&gt;k&lt;/sup&gt;
::=(P&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;DP)(P&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;DP)(P&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;DP)... (''k'' times)
::=P&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;D(PP&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;)D(PP&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;)DP... (''k'' times)
The PP&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; terms cancel to give
::=P&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;DDD...P (''k'' times)
::=P&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;D&lt;sup&gt;k&lt;/sup&gt;P

We can calculate D&lt;sup&gt;k&lt;/sup&gt; easily, so we need to find P.

It turns out (the entire proof is quite difficult) that we simply create a matrix from concatenating the linearly independent eigenvectors to create P.

D, then, is the diagonal matrix containing the eigenvalues on the main diagonal corresponding to the associated eigenvectors (the eigenvalue in the first place corresponds to the eigenvector it is created from, in the first column).

==== Example ====
Let's work through an example to show these ideas.
: &lt;math&gt;A=\begin{pmatrix} 
3 &amp; 1 \\
4 &amp; 0 \\
\end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;

So what do we do if we want to find A&lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;? Let's use the method we've just described.

Find the eigenvalues: 
: |A-&amp;lambda;I|=0
: (3-&amp;lambda;)(-&amp;lambda;)-4=0
: &amp;lambda;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;-3&amp;lambda;-4=0
: &amp;lambda;=-1, 4

Find the eigenvectors:
: for &amp;lambda;=-1 &lt;math&gt;
\mbox{ker}\begin{pmatrix} 
4 &amp; 1 \\
4 &amp; 1 \\
\end{pmatrix}=\mbox{span}\{\begin{pmatrix}-1 \\ 4\end{pmatrix}\}&lt;/math&gt;
: for &amp;lambda;=4 &lt;math&gt;
\mbox{ker}\begin{pmatrix} 
-1 &amp; 1 \\
4 &amp; -4 \\
\end{pmatrix}=\mbox{span}\{\begin{pmatrix}1 \\ 1\end{pmatrix}\}&lt;/math&gt;

The eigenvectors are then 
: &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix}-1 \\ 4\end{pmatrix}, \begin{pmatrix}1 \\ 1\end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;
so put the eigenvectors together to form the matrix P
: &lt;math&gt;P=\begin{pmatrix}-1 &amp; 1 \\ 4 &amp; 1\end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;

Now -1 generated the eigenvector in the ''first'' column, and 4 generated the eigenvector in the ''second'' column, so form D in this way:
: &lt;math&gt;D=\begin{pmatrix} 
-1 &amp; 0 \\
0 &amp; 4 \\
\end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;

We can easily calculate (-1)&lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;=1, so we get
: &lt;math&gt;D^{14}=\begin{pmatrix} 
1 &amp; 0 \\
0 &amp; 4^{14} \\
\end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;

and we have the fast method for creating inverses of 2&amp;times;2 matrices:
: &lt;math&gt;P^{-1} = -\frac{1}{5}\begin{pmatrix}1 &amp; -1 \\
                             -4 &amp;-1 \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;

So now we can now directly multiply out
: &lt;math&gt;-\frac{1}{5}
\begin{pmatrix}
1 &amp; -1 \\ 
-4 &amp; -1\end{pmatrix}
\begin{pmatrix} 
1 &amp; 0 \\
0 &amp; 4^{14} \end{pmatrix}
\begin{pmatrix}
-1 &amp; 1 \\ 
4 &amp; 1\end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;
Simplifying we get
:&lt;math&gt;
\begin{pmatrix}
 214748365 &amp; 53687091 \\
 214748364 &amp; 53687092 \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;

==== Problem set ====
Given the above, find the following matrix powers (Answers follow to even-numbered questions):
# &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} 1 &amp; 0 \\ -2 &amp; 5 \end{pmatrix}^6&lt;/math&gt;
# &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} 1 &amp; 3 \\ 3 &amp; -7 \end{pmatrix}^5&lt;/math&gt;
# &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} -1 &amp; 9 \\ -10 &amp; 16 \end{pmatrix}^4&lt;/math&gt; 
# &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} -2 &amp; 0 &amp; 3 \\ 0 &amp; 4 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 2 \end{pmatrix}^3&lt;/math&gt; 
:(More tedious: only slightly easier because this matrix is in row echelon form)

=====Answers=====
:2.&lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} -3248 &amp; 9840 \\ 9840 &amp; -29488\end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;
:4.&lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix}1/4\end{pmatrix}*\begin{pmatrix} -32 &amp; 0 &amp; 48\\  0 &amp; 256 &amp; 0\\ 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 32\end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;

===Coupled ordinary differential equations ===
We can use the method of diagonalisation to solve coupled ordinary differential equations . For example, let x(t) and y(t) be differentiable functions and x' and y' their derivatives. The differential equations are relatively difficult to solve:
:x' = 4x - y
:y' = 2x + y
but
:u' = ku for a constant k is easy to solve
it has solution
:u = Ae&lt;sup&gt;kx&lt;/sup&gt; where A is a constant
remembering this fact, we translate the ODEs into matrix form
:&lt;math&gt;
\begin{pmatrix}
x'\\
y'
\end{pmatrix}
=
\begin{pmatrix}
4&amp;-1\\
2&amp;1
\end{pmatrix}
\begin{pmatrix}
x\\
y
\end{pmatrix}
&lt;/math&gt;
Diagonalise the square matrix, we get:
:&lt;math&gt;
\begin{pmatrix}
x'\\
y'
\end{pmatrix}
=
\begin{pmatrix}
1&amp;1\\
1&amp;2
\end{pmatrix}
\begin{pmatrix}
3&amp;0\\
0&amp;2
\end{pmatrix}
\begin{pmatrix}
1&amp;1\\
1&amp;2
\end{pmatrix}^{-1}
\begin{pmatrix}
x\\
y
\end{pmatrix}
&lt;/math&gt;

we put
:&lt;math&gt;
\begin{pmatrix}
u\\
v
\end{pmatrix}
=
\begin{pmatrix}
1&amp;1\\
1&amp;2
\end{pmatrix}^{-1}
\begin{pmatrix}
x\\
y
\end{pmatrix}
&lt;/math&gt;
then it follows that 
:&lt;math&gt;
\begin{pmatrix}
u'\\
v'
\end{pmatrix}
=
\begin{pmatrix}
1&amp;1\\
1&amp;2
\end{pmatrix}^{-1}
\begin{pmatrix}
x'\\
y'
\end{pmatrix}
&lt;/math&gt;
thus
:&lt;math&gt;
\begin{pmatrix}
u'\\
v'
\end{pmatrix}
=
\begin{pmatrix}
3&amp;0\\
0&amp;2
\end{pmatrix}
\begin{pmatrix}
u\\
v
\end{pmatrix}
&lt;/math&gt;
as discussed above the solutions are easy. We have
:&lt;math&gt;u = Ce^{3t}&lt;/math&gt;
:&lt;math&gt;v = De^{2t}&lt;/math&gt;
for some constants C and D. Now that
:&lt;math&gt;
\begin{pmatrix}
u\\
v
\end{pmatrix}
=
\begin{pmatrix}
1&amp;1\\
1&amp;2
\end{pmatrix}^{-1}
\begin{pmatrix}
x\\
y
\end{pmatrix}
&lt;/math&gt;
we get
:&lt;math&gt;

\begin{pmatrix}
1&amp;1\\
1&amp;2
\end{pmatrix}
\begin{pmatrix}
u\\
v
\end{pmatrix}
=
\begin{pmatrix}
x\\
y
\end{pmatrix}
&lt;/math&gt;
and so
:&lt;math&gt;x = Ce^{3t} + De^{2t}&lt;/math&gt;
:&lt;math&gt;y = Ce^{3t} + 2De^{2t}&lt;/math&gt;
This method generalises well into higher dimensions.

=== Coupled differential equations ===
Matrices, strangely enough, have a great use in relation to ''calculus'' in the calculation of solutions to coupled differential equations, where one differential equation has some  function that depends on another differential equation. For example:
: D ''y'' = 3''y'' + ''x''
: D ''x'' = ''y'' + 3''x''

Without going any further, the solution to these differential equations looks very difficult! However if we formulate this in terms of matrices, it becomes a little bit easier to analyze.

==== Example ====
Let's take the above example, so
: D ''y''(''t'') = 3''y'' + ''x''
: D ''x''(''t'') = ''y'' + 3''x''

Now form a vector:
: &lt;math&gt; \mathbf{v}(t) = \begin{pmatrix} y \\ x \end{pmatrix} &lt;/math&gt;
Then
: &lt;math&gt; D \mathbf{v}(t) = \begin{pmatrix} D y \\ D x \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;

Now the problem becomes
: &lt;math&gt; D(\mathbf{v}) = \begin{pmatrix} 3 &amp; 1 \\ 1 &amp; 3 \end{pmatrix}\mathbf{v}&lt;/math&gt;

This is reminiscent of the differential equation we have already encountered in calculus, that of
: D ''y'' = ''ky''
in which the solution is y = ''c''e&lt;sup&gt;kt&lt;/sup&gt;.
We can make a wild guess then the solution to the above matrix equation will have a solution in a similar form.

So let's try a solution '''v''' = '''w'''e&lt;sup&gt;&amp;lambda;t&lt;/sup&gt;. Then D '''v''' = &amp;lambda;'''w'''e&lt;sup&gt;&amp;lambda;t&lt;/sup&gt;.

Let us then try and substitute this guess solution into our equation:
: &lt;math&gt;\lambda\mathbf{w}e^{\lambda t} = \begin{pmatrix} 3 &amp; 1 \\ 1 &amp; 3 \end{pmatrix}\mathbf{w}e^{\lambda t}&lt;/math&gt;
If we let 
: &lt;math&gt; A = \begin{pmatrix} 3 &amp; 1 \\ 1 &amp; 3 \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;
we see that the equation above becomes, on dividing through by &lt;math&gt;e^{\lambda t}&lt;/math&gt; (since it is never zero)
: &lt;math&gt; A\mathbf{w} = \lambda\mathbf{w}&lt;/math&gt;
But wait - this is the equation before to find the eigenvalues - and we have that the solution '''v''' = '''w'''e&lt;sup&gt;&amp;lambda;t&lt;/sup&gt; is a solution if and only if &amp;lambda; is an eigenvalue of A and '''w''' is its corresponding eigenvector.

The eigenvalues are 4, 2, with eigenvectors
:&lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} 1 \\ 1 \end{pmatrix}, \begin{pmatrix} -1 \\ 1 \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;
respectively. 

So we have two solutions 
: &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} 1 \\ 1 \end{pmatrix}e^{4 t}&lt;/math&gt;
and 
: &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} -1 \\ 1 \end{pmatrix}e^{2 t}&lt;/math&gt;

Note that if we have two solutions to the differential equation D '''v''' = A'''v''', linear combinations of the two solutions will give the same solution. So then we have then the general solution:
: &lt;math&gt;\mathbf{v}=j\begin{pmatrix} 1 \\ 1 \end{pmatrix}e^{4 t}+k\begin{pmatrix} -1 \\ 1 \end{pmatrix}e^{2 t}=&lt;/math&gt;
: &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} y(t) \\ x(t) \end{pmatrix}=j\begin{pmatrix} 1 \\ 1 \end{pmatrix}e^{4 t}+k\begin{pmatrix} -1 \\ 1 \end{pmatrix}e^{2 t}=&lt;/math&gt;

Seperating into the first and second components we get our two solutions
: &lt;math&gt; y(t) = je^{4 t}-ke^{2 t}, x(t) = je^{4 t}+ k e^{2 t}&lt;/math&gt;.

==== Problem set ====
Given the above solve the following problems (Answers follow to even-numbered questions)
# Find y(''t'') and x(''t'') where D y(''t'')=3x(''t'')+6y(''t'') and D x(''t'')=x(''t'')+4y(''t'')
# Find y(''t'') and x(''t'') where D y(''t'')=2x(''t'')+2y(''t'') and D x(''t'')=x(''t'')-2y(''t'')

=====Answers=====
Form the matrix 
: &lt;math&gt;A=\begin{pmatrix} 2 &amp; 2 \\ 1 &amp; -2 \end{pmatrix}.&lt;/math&gt; 
The eigenvalues of this matrix are
: &lt;math&gt;\pm\sqrt{6}&lt;/math&gt;
and the eigenvectors are
: &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} 2-\sqrt{6} \\ 1 \end{pmatrix}, \begin{pmatrix} 2+\sqrt{6} \\ 1 \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;
So now
: &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} y(t) \\ x(t) \end{pmatrix}=\alpha\begin{pmatrix} 2-\sqrt{6} \\ 1 \end{pmatrix}e^{-\sqrt{6}t}+\beta\begin{pmatrix} 2+\sqrt{6} \\ 1 \end{pmatrix}e^{\sqrt{6}t}&lt;/math&gt;
and y(''t'') and x(''t'') can be read off by inspection.

==External links==
*[http://www.bluebit.gr/matrix-calculator/ Online Matrix Calculator] Calculates eigenvalues, eigenvectors and other decompositions of matrices online.

[[Category:Linear Algebra|{{SUBPAGENAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>rxks8fwehek10qw964g0qqmj3jau1ao</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Linear Algebra/OLD/Vector Spaces</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1839</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1852555</id>
      <parentid>1528504</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-06-23T12:02:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Thenub314</username>
        <id>38087</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>correct link</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">A '''vector space''' is a way of generalizing the concept of a set of [[Linear Algebra/Vectors|vectors]]. For example, the complex number 2+3i can be considered a vector, since in some way it is the vector &lt;math&gt;\begin{bmatrix} 2 \\ 3\end{bmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;.

The vector space is a &quot;space&quot; of such abstract objects, which we term &quot;vectors&quot;.

== Some familiar friends ==
Currently in our study of vectors we have looked at vectors with real entries: 
&lt;math&gt;\mathbb{R}^2, \mathbb{R}^3, ..., \mathbb{R}^n&lt;/math&gt;, and so on. These are all vector spaces. The advantage we gain in abstracting to vector spaces is a way of talking about a space without any particular choice of objects (which define our vectors), operations (which act on our vectors), or coordinates (which identify our vectors in the space). Further results may be applied to more general spaces which may have infinite dimension, such as in Functional Analysis.

== Notations and concepts==
We write a vector, like we have before, bold, but you should write these on paper underlined or with an arrow on top. So we write &lt;math&gt;\mathbf{v}=\begin{pmatrix} 2 \\ 3\end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt; for that vector.

When we multiply a vector by a scalar number, we usually ascribe it a Greek letter, writing &amp;lambda;'''v''' for the multiplication of '''v''' by a scalar &amp;lambda;. We write addition and subtraction of vectors as we have been doing before, '''x'''+'''y''' for the sum of vectors '''x''' and '''y'''.

With scalar multiplication and adding vectors, we can move to our definition of a vector space.

When we refer to an operation being 'closed' in a definition, we are saying that the result of the operation does not violate our definition.  For example, if we are looking at the set of all integers, we can say that it is closed under addition, because adding any integers results in something inside the set of integers.  However the set of integers is not closed under division, because dividing 3 by 2 (for example) doesn't result in a member of the set of integers.

== Definition==
A ''vector space'' is a nonempty set V of objects, called ''vectors'', on which are defined two operations, called ''vector addition'' and ''scalar multiplication'', respectively, such that, for &lt;math&gt;x,y\in V&lt;/math&gt; and &amp;alpha;&lt;math&gt; \in F&lt;/math&gt;, where F is a field '''x'''+'''y''' and &amp;alpha;'''x''' are well-defined elements of V with the following properties: 
#''commutativity of addition'': '''x'''+'''y'''='''y'''+'''x'''
# ''associativity of addition'': '''x'''+('''y'''+'''z''')=('''x'''+'''y''')+'''z'''
# ''additive identity'': there is a vector '''0''' such that '''0'''+'''x'''='''x''' for all '''x'''
# ''additive inverse'': for each vector '''x''', there exists another vector '''y''' such that '''x'''+'''y''' ='''0'''

# ''scalar associativity'': &amp;alpha;(&amp;beta;'''x''') = (&amp;alpha;&amp;beta;)'''x'''
# ''scalar distributivity'': (&amp;alpha; + &amp;beta;)'''x'''=&amp;alpha;'''x'''+&amp;beta;'''x'''
# ''vector distributivity'': &amp;alpha;('''x'''+'''y''')=&amp;alpha;'''x'''+&amp;alpha;'''y'''
# ''scalar identity'': 1'''x'''='''x'''

=== Alternative Definition ===
People who are familiar with [[w:group theory|group theory]] and [[w:field theory (mathematics) |field theory]] may find the following alternative definition more compact:

* &lt;math&gt;(V, +)&lt;/math&gt; is an [[w:Abelian group|Abelian group]].
* &lt;math&gt;\forall \alpha \in F, (\forall x, y \in V), \alpha (x+y) = \alpha x + \alpha y&lt;/math&gt;
* &lt;math&gt;\forall \alpha, \beta \in F, \forall x\in V, (\alpha + \beta)x = \alpha x + \beta x&lt;/math&gt;
* &lt;math&gt;\forall \alpha, \beta \in F, \forall x\in V, (\alpha \beta)x = \alpha (\beta x)&lt;/math&gt;
* &lt;math&gt;\forall x\in V, 1x = x&lt;/math&gt;

=== Some Basic Theorems===
#The 0 vector is unique. &lt;br&gt; Proof: Let 0&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; and 0&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; both be 0 vectors. Then 0&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;=0&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;+0&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;=0&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;.
#The additive inverse is unique. &lt;br&gt; Proof: Suppose there is a x and y&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; and a y&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. are inverses of x Then y&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;=y&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;+(x+y&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;)=(y&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;+x)+y&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;=y&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;.
#0x=0. &lt;br&gt; Proof: Let y be the additive inverse of x. Then 0x= 0x + x + y = (0+1)x + y = x+y=0.
#(-1)x is the inverse of x. &lt;br&gt; Proof: x+(-1)x=x(1-1)=x0=0.

== Linear Spaces ==
The linear space is a very important vector space. Let n&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;, n&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, n&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;, ..., n&lt;sub&gt;k&lt;/sub&gt; be k elements of a field F. Then the ordered k-tuples (n&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;, n&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, n&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;, ..., n&lt;sub&gt;k&lt;/sub&gt;) form a vector space with addition being the sum of the corresponding numbers, and scalar multiplication by an element of F being the result of multiplying each one in the k-tuple. This would then be the k dimensional linear space.

== Subspaces ==
A ''subspace'' is a vector space inside a vector space. When we look at various vector spaces, it is often useful to examine their subspaces. 

The subspace S of a vector space V means that S is a sub''set'' of V and that it has the following key characteristics
* S is closed under scalar multiplication: if &amp;lambda;&amp;isin;'''R''', '''v'''&amp;isin;S, &amp;lambda;'''v'''&amp;isin;S
* S is closed under addition: if '''u''', '''v''' &amp;isin; S,  '''u'''+'''v'''&amp;isin;S.

Any subset with these characteristics is a vector space. 

==== The trivial subspace ====
The singleton set with the zero vector ({'''0'''}) is a subspace of every vector space. 

'''Scalar multiplication closure''': ''a'' '''0'''='''0''' for all ''a'' in '''R'''

'''Addition closure''': '''0'''+'''0'''='''0'''.  Since '''0''' is the only member of the set we need to check only '''0'''

'''Zero vector''': '''0''' is the only member of the set and it is the zero vector.

=== Examples ===
Let us examine some subspaces of some familiar vector spaces, and see how we can prove that a certain subset of a vector space is in fact a subspace.

==== A slightly less trivial subspace ====
In '''R'''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, the set '''V''' of all vectors from '''R'''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; of the form (0,&amp;alpha;) where &amp;alpha; is in '''R''' is a subspace

'''Scalar multiplication closure''': ''a'' (0,&amp;alpha;) = (0,a &amp;alpha;) and a &amp;alpha; is in '''R'''

'''Addition closure''': (0,&amp;alpha;) +(0,&amp;beta;) =(0, &amp;alpha; + &amp;beta;) and &amp;alpha; + &amp;beta; is in '''R'''

'''Zero vector''': taking &amp;alpha; to be zero in our definition of (0, &amp;alpha;) in '''V''' we get the zero vector (0,0)

==== A whole family of subspaces ====
Pick any number from '''R''', say &amp;rho;.  Then the set '''V''' of all vectors of the form (&amp;alpha;, &amp;rho;&amp;alpha;) is a subspace of  '''R'''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;

'''Scalar multiplication closure''': ''a'' (&amp;alpha;, &amp;rho;&amp;alpha;) = (a&amp;alpha;, &amp;rho;a&amp;alpha;) which is in '''V'''.

'''Addition closure''': (&amp;alpha;, &amp;rho;&amp;alpha;) +(&amp;beta;, &amp;rho;&amp;beta;) =(&amp;alpha; + &amp;beta;, &amp;rho;&amp;alpha; + &amp;rho;&amp;beta;) = (&amp;alpha;+&amp;beta;, &amp;rho;(&amp;alpha;+&amp;beta;)) which  is in '''V'''

'''Zero vector''': taking &amp;alpha; to be zero in our definition we get (0, &amp;rho;0) = (0,0) in '''V'''.

That means '''V'''&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; = the set of all vectors of the form (&amp;alpha;,2&amp;alpha;) is a subspace of '''R'''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;

and '''V'''&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; = the set of all vectors of the form (&amp;alpha;,3&amp;alpha;) is a subspace of '''R'''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;

and '''V'''&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; = the set of all vectors of the form (&amp;alpha;,4&amp;alpha;) is a subspace of '''R'''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;

and '''V'''&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt; = the set of all vectors of the form (&amp;alpha;,5&amp;alpha;) is a subspace of '''R'''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;

and '''V'''&lt;sub&gt;&amp;pi;&lt;/sub&gt; = the set of all vectors of the form (&amp;alpha;,&amp;pi;&amp;alpha;) is a subspace of '''R'''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;

and '''V'''&lt;sub&gt;&amp;radic;2&lt;/sub&gt; = the set of all vectors of the form 
&lt;math&gt;(\alpha,\sqrt{2}\alpha)&lt;/math&gt; is a subspace of '''R'''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;

As you can see, even a simple vector space like '''R'''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; can have many different subspaces.

== Linear Combinations, Spans and Spanning Sets, Linear Dependence, and Linear Independence ==

=== Linear Combinations ===

Definition: Assume &lt;math&gt;V&lt;/math&gt; is a ''vector space'' over a field &lt;math&gt;(F, +, \cdot)&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;S&lt;/math&gt; is a nonempty subset of &lt;math&gt;V&lt;/math&gt;. Then a vector &lt;math&gt;x\in V&lt;/math&gt; is said to be a '''linear combination''' of elements of &lt;math&gt;S&lt;/math&gt; if there exists a finite number of elements &lt;math&gt;y_1, y_2, ..., y_n\in S&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;a_1, a_2, ..., a_n\in F&lt;/math&gt; such that &lt;math&gt; x = a_1y_1 + a_2y_2 + ... a_ny_n&lt;/math&gt;.

=== Spans ===

Definition: Assume &lt;math&gt;V&lt;/math&gt; is a ''vector space'' over a field &lt;math&gt;(F, +, \cdot)&lt;/math&gt;. The set of all linear combinations of &lt;math&gt;y_1, y_2, ..., y_n\in V&lt;/math&gt; is called the '''span''' of &lt;math&gt;y_1, y_2, ..., y_n&lt;/math&gt;. This is sometimes denoted by &lt;math&gt;Span(y_1, y_2, ..., y_n)&lt;/math&gt;. 


Note that &lt;math&gt;Span(y_1, y_2, ..., y_n\in V)&lt;/math&gt; is a subspace of &lt;math&gt;V&lt;/math&gt;.  

Proof: Consider closure under addition and scalar multiplication for two vectors, x and y, in the span of the vectors &lt;math&gt;{v_1, v_2, ..., v_n}.&lt;/math&gt;

&lt;math&gt;x = a_1v_1 + a_2v_2 + ... + a_nv_n&lt;/math&gt;

&lt;math&gt;y = b_1v_1 + b_2v_2 + ... + b_nv_n&lt;/math&gt;

&lt;math&gt;x+y = (a_1+b_1)*v_1 + (a_2+b_2)*v_2 + ... + (a_n+b_n)*v_n&lt;/math&gt;, which is also contained in the set.

&lt;math&gt;k*x = (k*a_1)v_1 + (k*a_2)v_2 + ... + (k*a_n)v_n&lt;/math&gt;, which is also contained in the set.


==== Spanning Sets ====

Definition: Assume &lt;math&gt;V&lt;/math&gt; is a ''vector space'' over a field &lt;math&gt;(F, +, \cdot)&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;y_1, y_2, ..., y_n&lt;/math&gt; are vectors in such a vector space. The set &lt;math&gt;{y_1, y_2, ..., y_n}&lt;/math&gt; is a '''spanning set''' for the vector space &lt;math&gt;V&lt;/math&gt; if and only if every vector in &lt;math&gt;V&lt;/math&gt; is a linear combination of &lt;math&gt;y_1, y_2, ..., y_n&lt;/math&gt;. Alternately, &lt;math&gt;\forall x\in V, (\exists a_1, a_2, ..., a_n\in F), x = a_1y_1 + a_2y_2 + ... +a_ny_n&lt;/math&gt;

=== Linear Independence ===

Definition:  Assume &lt;math&gt;V&lt;/math&gt; is a ''vector space'' over a field &lt;math&gt;(F, +, \cdot)&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;S = \{x_1, x_2, ..., x_n\}&lt;/math&gt; is a finite subset of &lt;math&gt;V&lt;/math&gt;.  Then we say &lt;math&gt;S&lt;/math&gt; is linearly independent if &lt;math&gt;a_1x_1+a_2x_2+...a_nx_n = 0&lt;/math&gt; implies &lt;math&gt;a_1 = a_2 = ... = a_n = 0&lt;/math&gt;.

Linear independence is a very important topic in Linear Algebra. The definition implies that linearly dependent vectors may form the nulvector as a non-trivial combination, from which we may conclude that one of the vectors can be expressed as a linear combination of the others. 

If we have a vector space V spanned by 3 vectors &lt;math&gt;{v_1, v_2, v_3}&lt;/math&gt; we say that v&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;, v&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, and v&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; are linearly dependent if there is a combination of one or two of them that can produce a third. For instance, if one of the following equations:

:&lt;math&gt;a_1v_1 + a_2v_2 = v_3&lt;/math&gt;
:&lt;math&gt;a_2v_2 + a_3v_3 = v_1&lt;/math&gt;
:&lt;math&gt;a_1v_1 + a_3v_3 = v_2&lt;/math&gt;

can be satisfied, then the vectors in V are said to be '''linearly dependant'''. 

How can we test for linear independence? The definition sets it out to us: If V is a vector space spanned by 3 vectors of length N:

:&lt;math&gt;\tilde{V} = [v_1, v_2, v_3]&lt;/math&gt;

and we try to test whether these 3 vectors are linearly independent, we form the equations:

:&lt;math&gt;a_1v_1+a_2v_2+a_3v_3=0\,&lt;/math&gt;

and solve them. If the only solution is 

:&lt;math&gt;a_1=a_2=a_3=0,\,&lt;/math&gt;

then the 3 vectors are linearly independent. If there is another solution they are linearly dependent.


??????
We can say that for V to be linearly independent it must satisfy this condition:

:&lt;math&gt;\tilde{V}\bar{a} = 0&lt;/math&gt;

Where we are using 0 to denote the null vector in V.  If &lt;math&gt;\tilde{V}&lt;/math&gt; is square and invertable, we can solve this equation directly:

:&lt;math&gt;\tilde{V}^{-1}\tilde{V}\bar{a} = \bar{a} = \tilde{V}^{-1} \cdot 0&lt;/math&gt;
:&lt;math&gt;\bar{a} = 0&lt;/math&gt;

And if we know that &lt;math&gt;\bar{a}&lt;/math&gt; is zero, then we know that the system is linearly independent. If, however, &lt;math&gt;\tilde{V}&lt;/math&gt; is not square, or if it is not invertable, we can try the following technique:

Multiply through by the transpose matrix:
:&lt;math&gt;\tilde{V}^T\tilde{V}\bar{a} = 0&lt;/math&gt;

Find the inverse of &lt;math&gt;[\tilde{V}^T\tilde{V}&lt;/math&gt;, and multiply through by the inverse:
:&lt;math&gt;[\tilde{V}^T\tilde{V}]^{-1}\tilde{V}^T\tilde{V}\bar{a} = [\tilde{V}^T\tilde{V}]^{-1} \cdot 0&lt;/math&gt;

Cancel the terms:
:&lt;math&gt;\bar{a} = \tilde{V}^T\tilde{V} \cdot 0&lt;/math&gt;

And our conclusion:
:&lt;math&gt;\bar{a} = 0&lt;/math&gt;

This again means that V is linearly independent.

=== Span ===

A '''span''' is the set of all possible vectors that are in a given vector space. 

===Basis===

A '''basis''' for a vector space is the least amount of linearly independent vectors that can be used to describe the vector space completely. The most common basis vectors are the '''kronecker vectors''', also called '''canonical basis''':

:&lt;math&gt;i = \begin{bmatrix}1 \\ 0 \\ 0\end{bmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;&lt;math&gt;j = \begin{bmatrix}0 \\ 1 \\ 0\end{bmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;&lt;math&gt;k = \begin{bmatrix}0 \\ 0 \\ 1\end{bmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;

In the cartesian graphing space, we say an ordered triple of coordinates is defined as:

:&lt;math&gt;v = \begin{bmatrix}x \\ y \\ z\end{bmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;

And we can make any point (x, y, z) by combining the kronecker basis vectors:

:&lt;math&gt;\begin{bmatrix}x \\ y \\ z\end{bmatrix} = xi + yj + zk&lt;/math&gt;

'''Some theorems''':
*A basis &lt;math&gt;\mathcal{B}(v_1, \ldots, v_n)&lt;/math&gt; of a vector space V has the maximal number of linearly independet vectors.
*(Converse) A maximal number of linearly independent vectors in a vector space is a basis.

== Bases and Dimension ==

If a vector space &lt;b&gt;V&lt;/b&gt; is such that:&lt;br&gt;
it contains a linearly independent set &lt;i&gt;B&lt;/i&gt; of N vectors,and&lt;/br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;i&gt;any&lt;/i&gt; set of N + 1 or more vectors in &lt;b&gt;V&lt;/b&gt; is linearly dependent,&lt;/br&gt;

then &lt;b&gt;V&lt;/b&gt; is said to have &lt;b&gt;dimension&lt;/b&gt; N, and &lt;i&gt;B&lt;/i&gt; is said to be a   &lt;b&gt;basis&lt;/b&gt; of &lt;b&gt;V&lt;/b&gt;.



== External links ==

*[http://wims.unice.fr/wims/wims.cgi?module=home&amp;search_category=X&amp;search_keywords=vector+space Online interactive exercises] on vector spaces.

== TODO ==

Tell about what is a ''basis'' in a vector space and about coordinate transformations. ([http://www.mathematics21.org/formulas-theory.html this article] contains an abstract definition of a ''basis'' which is a generalization of a basis in vector space and can be used as the foundation to explain about bases and coordinate transformations.)


Discuss the geometry of subspaces (points, lines, planes, hypersurfaces) and connect them to the geometry of solutions of linear systems.  Connect the algebra of subspaces and linear combinations of vectors to the algebra of linear systems.

[[Category:Linear Algebra|{{SUBPAGENAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>1whhsafee43chnrcn7ms74kn87bzssm</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Vulture</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>1840</id>
    <revision>
      <id>153925</id>
      <timestamp>2003-10-30T14:16:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Vulture</username>
        <id>217</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">See [[de:Benutzer:Vulture]]

There's not much though ...</text>
      <sha1>drk64klzjkl1oxspp490ntk87kk4wox</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Japanese/Introduction</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1846</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1926484</id>
      <parentid>1208514</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-09-02T17:42:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Adding {{WikiProject Languages}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{WikiProject Languages}} 

== A question about contributing ==

Hi,

I have been talking with other Japan-related bloggers about how we can work together to improve the Japan-related content available online and this wikibooks project came up as one of the things that would be great to contribute to. 

I was wondering how we could best get involved and also if anyone who has worked on the project would like to comment on it and I will post the comments on my blog dailyj.net

Please let me know. Thanks ([[User:Toritaiyo|Toritaiyo]] 17:33, 29 November 2007 (UTC))

: Find a page you're interested in contributing to, [[WB:BOLD|be bold]] and have fun. Contact others on talk pages relevant to the page in question &amp;mdash; [[Talk:Japanese]] for the whole book. --[[User:Swift|Swift]] ([[User talk:Swift|talk]]) 07:58, 12 June 2008 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>r4r3q11b70k02jvon3ibjvc02cadsdp</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>PHP Programming</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1847</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2714491</id>
      <parentid>2714416</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-17T08:47:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rejected the last 4 text changes (by [[Special:Contributions/95.91.247.131|95.91.247.131]]) and restored revision 2696646 by 14.139.227.2</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Image:PHPWikibookCover.png|right]]
'''PHP''' is a [[w:Scripting programming language|scripting]] language designed to fill the gap between [[w:Server Side Includes|SSI]] (Server Side Includes) and [[Perl]], intended for the web environment. Its principal application is the implementation of web pages having dynamic content. PHP has gained quite a following in recent times, and it is one of the frontrunners in the Open Source software movement. Its popularity derives from its C-like syntax, and its simplicity. The newest version of PHP is 5.5 and it is heavily recommended to always use the newest version for better security, performance and of course features.

If you've ever been to a website that prompts you to login, you've probably encountered a server-side scripting language. Due to its market saturation, this means you've probably come across PHP. [[Wikipedia:PHP|PHP]] was designed by [[Wikipedia:Rasmus Lerdorf|Rasmus Lerdorf]] to display his resume online and to collect data from his visitors.

Basically, PHP allows a static webpage to become dynamic. &quot;PHP&quot; is an acronym that stands for &quot;'''P'''HP: '''H'''ypertext '''P'''reprocessor&quot;. The word &quot;Preprocessor&quot; means that PHP makes changes before the HTML page is created. This enables developers to create powerful applications which can publish a blog, remotely control hardware, or run a powerful website such as Wikipedia or Wikibooks. Of course, to accomplish something such as this, you need a database application such as MySQL.

Before you embark on the wonderful journey of Server Side Processing, it is recommended that you have a basic understanding of the [[HTML|HyperText Markup Language (HTML)]]. But [[Wikipedia:PHP|PHP]] can also be used to build [[Wikipedia:GUI|GUI]]-driven applications for example by using [[w:PHP-GTK|PHP-GTK]].

== Setup and Installation ==

* [[{{BOOKNAME}}/Setup_and_Installation#Windows|Installation on Windows]]
** '''[[{{BOOKNAME}}/Setup_and_Installation#Easy_Windows_Setup_Instructions|Easy Windows Setup Instructions]]'''
* [[{{BOOKNAME}}/Setup_and_Installation#Linux|Installation on Linux]]
* [[{{BOOKNAME}}/Setup_and_Installation#Mac_OS_X|Installation on Mac OS X]]
* [[{{BOOKNAME}}/Uses|Uses of PHP]]

Note: Before contributing, check out the [[{{TALKPAGENAME}}|discussion]] page. [[{{TALKPAGENAME}}#The_newline_.22operator.22|How to write your examples]].

== Learning the Language ==
=== The Basics ===
:This section is about things that are important for any type of PHP development. Useful for a PHP programmer of any level.

#[http://www.afterhoursprogramming.com/tutorial/PHP/Overview/ Start a PHP Beginner Tutorial]
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/hello world|Beginning with &quot;Hello World!&quot;]] {{stage|100%|10 Feb 2006}}
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/basics|Nuts and Bolts]] {{stage|75%|14 Jan 2006}}
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/comments|Commenting and Style]] {{stage|100%|14 Jan 2006}}
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/arrays|Arrays]] {{stage|75%|10 Feb 2006}}
#Control structures
##[[{{BOOKNAME}}/if structure|The if Structure]] {{stage|75%|19 Mar 2009}}
##[[{{BOOKNAME}}/switch structure|The switch Structure]] {{stage|75%|14 Jan 2006}}
##[[{{BOOKNAME}}/while loop|The while Loop]] {{stage|75%|14 Jan 2006}}
##[[{{BOOKNAME}}/do while loop|The do while Loop]] {{stage|50%|14 Jan 2006}}
##[[{{BOOKNAME}}/for loop|The for Loop]] {{stage|50%|14 Jan 2006}}
##[[{{BOOKNAME}}/foreach loop|The foreach Loop]] {{stage|75%|14 Jan 2006}}
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/functions|Functions]] {{stage|75%|10 Feb 2006}}
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/Files|Files]] {{stage|100%|12 Feb 2008}}
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/mail|Mailing]] {{stage|50%|14 Jan 2006}}
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/cookies|Cookies]] {{stage|75%|14 Jan 2006}}
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/sessions|Sessions]] {{stage|75%|2008-05-07}}
#Databases
##[[{{BOOKNAME}}/mysql|MySQL]] {{stage|75%|14 Jan 2006}}
##[[{{BOOKNAME}}/PostgreSQL|PostgreSQL]] {{stage|25%|18 Apr 2009}}
##[[{{BOOKNAME}}/pdo|PHP Data Objects]] {{stage|00%|18 Dec 2006}}
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/integration_methods|Integration Methods (HTML Forms, etc.)]] {{stage|75%|14 Jan 2006}}

=== Advanced PHP ===
: Advanced PHP includes high level programming and PHP techniques designed to make PHP even more useful and powerful.

====Data Structures====
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/Data_Structures|Data Structures]]

====Object Oriented Programming (OOP)====
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/Classes|Classes]]
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/Special_Methods|Special Methods]]
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/Overriding_Overloading|Over riding and Over loading]]
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/Inheritance|Class Extensions (Inheritance)]]
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/SSH Class| The SSH Class]]

==== Templating ====
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/whytemplating| Why Templating]]
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/template| Templates]]
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/caching| Caching]]
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/smarty| SMARTY templating system]]
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/prado| PRADO Component Framework]]
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/Flat Frog| Flat Frog templating system]] {{stage|25%|23 march 2006}}
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/XSL| XSL]]

==== Libraries ====
[[{{BOOKNAME}}/PEAR|PHP PEAR]]

==== Frameworks ====
*[http://www.cakephp.org/ CakePHP]
*[http://codeigniter.com/ CodeIgniter]
*[http://kohanaframework.org/ Kohana]
*[http://nette.org/ Nette]
*[http://www.qcodo.com/ Qcodo]
*[http://www.solarphp.com/ Solar]
*[http://www.symfony-project.org/ Symfony]
*[http://framework.zend.com/ Zend Framework]
*[http://www.yiiframework.com/ Yii]
*[http://www.drupal.org/ Drupal]
*[http://www.silverstripe.com/ Silverstripe]
*[http://www.laravel.com/ Laravel]

==== Security ====
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/Register Globals| Configuration: Register Globals]]
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/SQL Injection| SQL Injection Attacks]]
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/Cross Site Scripting| Cross Site Scripting Attacks]]
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/User login systems|Building a secure user login system]]

''See also the [[{{BOOKNAME}}/sessions#Avoiding Session Fixation|section on avoiding session fixation]] in the [[{{BOOKNAME}}/sessions|Sessions chapter]].''

==== Command-Line Interface (CLI) ====
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/CLI| PHP CLI]]
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/CLI/PHP-GTK| PHP-GTK]]
#[[{{BOOKNAME}}/CLI/Daemonization| Daemonization]]

==Appendices==
*[[/Code Snippets/]]
*[[/Coding Standards/]]
*[[/Alternative Hungarian Notation/]]
*[[/Editors/]]
*[[/Resources/]]
*[[/Contributors/]]

{{Subjects|PHP scripting language}}
{{alphabetical|P}}
{{status|75%}}
__NOTOC__ __NOEDITSECTION__

[[ar:لغات البرمجة/بي اش بي]]
[[ca:PHP]]
[[de:Websiteentwicklung: PHP]]
[[et:PHP]]
[[es:Programación en PHP]]
[[eu:PHP]]
[[fr:Programmation PHP]]
[[id:Pemrograman PHP]]
[[it:PHP]]
[[he:PHP]]
[[nl:Programmeren in PHP]]
[[ja:PHP]]
[[pl:PHP]]
[[pt:Curso de PHP]]
[[ro:PHP]]
[[ru:PHP]]
[[fi:PHP]]
[[th:ภาษาพีเอชพี]]
[[vi:PHP]]</text>
      <sha1>tkczbxzwlylgl0v7vyfxorsd5123ano</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Physics Study Guide</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1848</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2516212</id>
      <parentid>2157852</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-04-25T12:38:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cdh1001</username>
        <id>951062</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Added intro section--~~~~</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{featured book|print=Print version}}

&lt;small&gt;&lt;[[Physics Study Guide/Cover|Cover and interwiki]]&lt;/small&gt;
==Introduction==
#[[/Purpose/]] 
#[[/Laws/]] 
#[[/Scientific Method/]] 

==Section One==
#[[/Basic Units|Units]] S.I. units
#[[/Linear Motion|Kinematics]] Displacement, velocity, acceleration
#[[/Force/]] Newton's 3 Laws of Motion
#[[/Momentum/]] Elastic and inelastic collisions
#[[/Normal Force and Friction|Friction and the Normal Force]]
#[[/Work/]] Force times distance
#[[/Energy/]] The potential to do Work

==Section Two==
#[[/Gravity/]] A universal force of attraction
#[[/Circular Motion/]]
#[[/Torque/]] 
#[[/Periodic Motion/]]
#[[/Waves/]]
#[[/Wave overtones/]] 
#[[/Standing waves/]] 
#[[/Sound/]]

==Section Three==
#[[/Fluids/]] 
#[[/Fields/]]
#[[/Thermodynamics/]]
#[[/Electricity/]] Charge, current, electric fields
#[[/Magnetism/]] Magnetic dipoles, magnetic fields
#[[/Electronics/]] Resistance, voltage, capacitance, inductance (incomplete)
#[[/Optics/]] Light, lasers etc
#[[/Theories of Electricity/]] Theories behind Electricity

==Appendices==
{{print version}}
#[[/Physics constants|Commonly Used Physical Constants]]
#[[/Frictional_Coefficients|Approximate Coefficients of Friction]]
#[[/Greek alphabet/]]
#[[/Logs/]]
#[[/Vectors and scalars/]]
#[[/Symbols|Symbols Used in This Book]]
#[[Physics Exercises|Exercises]]
#[[/Topics|More topics]]
#[[/Style Guide/]]
__NOTOC__ __NOEDITSECTION__
{{alphabetical|P}}
{{Subjects|Physics}}
{{status|100%}}</text>
      <sha1>l3luq0f3b5lppiik2pymdugmi3h0jk1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Physics Study Guide/Authors</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1849</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2427953</id>
      <parentid>1571863</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-26T19:54:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Msmithma</username>
        <id>37282</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{|cellpadding=&quot;10&quot;
|[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
|[[User:Flonejek|Adon Metcalfe]]
|Brendan Abbott
|Tristan Sabel
|Fromund Hock
|[[User:msmithma|Martin Hoecker-Martinez]]
|}

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>rsf82o9n4zu3l64l4wwgmmjca2b4lnd</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Physics Study Guide/Linear motion</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1850</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2624386</id>
      <parentid>2623832</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-04-01T22:58:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Xania</username>
        <id>40302</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rejected the last text change (by [[Special:Contributions/123.231.126.163|123.231.126.163]]) and restored revision 2615210 by Fishpi</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{PSG}}

= Kinematics =
Kinematics is the description of motion.  The motion of a point particle is fully described using three terms - position, velocity, and acceleration.&lt;!-- Not fully: the acceleration may change, and its change, in turn, etc. --&gt;  For real objects (which are not mathematical points), translational kinematics describes the motion of an object's center of mass through space, while angular kinematics describes how an object rotates about its centre of mass.  In this section, we focus only on translational kinematics.

Position, displacement, velocity, and acceleration are defined as follows.

== Position ==
A vector is a quantity that has both magnitude and direction, typically written as a column of scalars. That is, a number that has a direction assigned to it. 

In physics, a vector often describes the motion of an object. For example, Warty the Woodchuck goes 10 meters towards a hole in the ground. 

We can divide vectors into parts called &quot;components&quot;, of which the vector is a sum.&lt;!-- A link to &quot;Geometry&quot; (sum of vectors) needed. --&gt; For example, a two-dimensional vector is divided into '''x''' and '''y''' components.

{|
|[[Image:Real Number Line.svg|thumb|One dimensional coordinate system]]
|[[Image:2D Cartesian Coordinates.svg|thumb|Two dimensional coordinate system]]
|[[Image:Cartesian_coordinates_3D.svg|thumb|Three dimensional coordinate system]]
|}

== Displacement ==
{{PSG/eq|&lt;math&gt;\Delta \vec{x}\equiv\vec x_f- \vec x_i\,&lt;/math&gt;}}

Displacement answers the question, &quot;Has the object moved?&quot;

Note the &lt;math&gt;\equiv&lt;/math&gt; symbol.  This symbol is a sort of &quot;super equals&quot; symbol, indicating that not only does &lt;math&gt;\vec x_f- \vec x_i&lt;/math&gt; EQUAL the displacement &lt;math&gt;\Delta\vec{x}&lt;/math&gt;, but more importantly displacement is OPERATIONALLY DEFINED by &lt;math&gt;\vec x_f- \vec x_i&lt;/math&gt;.

We say that &lt;math&gt;\vec x_f- \vec x_i&lt;/math&gt; operationally defines displacement, because &lt;math&gt;\vec x_f- \vec x_i&lt;/math&gt; gives a step by step procedure for determining displacement.  Namely ...

# Measure where the object is initially.
# Measure where the object is at some later time.
# Determine the difference between these two position values.

Be sure to note that DISPLACEMENT is NOT the same as DISTANCE travelled.

For example, imagine travelling one time along the circumference of a circle.  If you end where you started, your displacement is zero, even though you have clearly travelled some distance.  In fact, displacement is an average distance travelled.  On your trip along the circle, your north and south motion averaged out, as did your east and west motion.

Clearly we are losing some important information.  The key to regaining this information is to use smaller displacement intervals.  For example, instead of calculating your displacement for your trip along the circle in one large step, consider dividing the circle into 16 equal segments.  Calculate the distance you travelled along each of these segments, and then add all your results together.  Now your total travelled distance is not zero, but something approximating the circumference of the circle.  Is your approximation good enough?  Ultimately, that depends on the level of accuracy you need in a particular application, but luckily you can always use finer resolution.  For example, we could break your trip into 32 equal segments for a better approximation.

Returning to your trip around the circle, you know the true distance is simply the circumference of the circle.  The problem is that we often face a practical limitation for determining the true distance travelled.  (The travelled path may have too many twists and turns, for example.)  Luckily, we can always determine displacement, and by carefully choosing small enough displacement steps, we can use displacement to obtain a pretty good approximation for the true distance travelled.  (The mathematics of calculus provides a formal methodology for estimating a &quot;true value&quot; through the use of successively better approximations.)  In the rest of this discussion, I will replace &lt;math&gt;\Delta&lt;/math&gt; with &lt;math&gt;\delta&lt;/math&gt; to indicate that small enough displacement steps have been used to provide a good enough approximation for the true distance travelled.

== Velocity ==
{{PSG/eq|&lt;math&gt;\vec v_{av}\equiv \frac{\vec{x_f}-\vec{x_i}}{t_f-t_i}\equiv \frac{\Delta\vec{x}}{\Delta t}&lt;/math&gt;}}

[Δ, ''delta'', upper-case Greek D, is a ''prefix'' conventionally used to denote a ''difference''.] Velocity answers the question &quot;Is the object moving now, and if so - how quickly?&quot;

Once again we have an ''operational'' definition: we are told what steps to follow to calculate velocity.

Note that this is a definition for '''average''' velocity.  The displacement Δ''x'' is the '''vector''' sum of the smaller displacements which it contains, and some of these may subtract out. By contrast, the distance travelled is the '''scalar''' sum of the smaller distances, all of which are non-negative (they are the ''magnitudes'' of the displacements). Thus the distance travelled can be larger than the magnitude of the displacement, as in the example of travel on a circle, above. Consequently, the average velocity may be small (or zero, or negative) while the speed is positive.

If we are careful to use very small displacement steps, so that they come pretty close to approximating the true distance travelled, then we can write the definition for INSTANTANEOUS velocity as 
{{PSG/eq|&lt;math&gt;\vec v_{inst}\equiv \frac{\vec{\delta x}}{\delta t}&lt;/math&gt;}}

[δ is the lower-case ''delta''.] Or with the idea of limits from [[calculus]], we have ...

{{PSG/eq|&lt;math&gt;\vec v_{inst}\equiv \frac{d \vec x}{dt}&lt;/math&gt;}}

[d, like Δ and δ, is merely a ''prefix''; however, its use definitely specifies that this is a sufficiently small difference so that the error--due to stepping (instead of smoothly changing) the quantity--becomes negligible.]

== Acceleration ==
{{PSG/eq|&lt;math&gt;\vec a_{av}\equiv \frac{\vec{v_f}-\vec{v_i}}{t_f-t_i}\equiv \frac{\Delta\vec{v}}{\Delta t}&lt;/math&gt;}}
Acceleration answers the question &quot;Is the object's velocity changing, and if so - how quickly?&quot;

Once again we have an operational definition.  We are told what steps to follow to calculate acceleration.

Again, also note that technically we have a definition for AVERAGE acceleration.  As for displacement, if we are careful to use a series of small velocity changes, then we can write the definition for INSTANTANEOUS acceleration as 
{{PSG/eq|&lt;math&gt;\vec a_{inst}\equiv \frac{\delta\vec{v}}{\delta t}&lt;/math&gt;}}

Or with the help of [[calculus]], we have ...

{{PSG/eq|&lt;math&gt;\vec a_{inst}\equiv \frac{d \vec v}{dt} = \frac{d^2\vec x}{dt^2}&lt;/math&gt;}}

== Vectors ==
Notice that the definitions given above for displacement, velocity, and acceleration included little arrows over many of the terms.  The little arrow reminds us that direction is an important part of displacement, velocity, and acceleration.&lt;!-- &quot;the change in velocity&quot; is the acceleration — an extra passage. (the next editor should rub this out) --&gt;  These quantities are VECTORS.  By convention, the little arrow always points right when placed over a letter.  So for example, &lt;math&gt;\vec v&lt;/math&gt; just reminds us that velocity is a vector, and does NOT imply that this particular velocity is rightward.  Why do we need vectors? As a simple example, consider velocity.  It is not enough to know how fast one is moving.  We also need to know which direction we are moving.  Less trivially, consider how many different ways an object could be experiencing an acceleration (a change in its velocity).  Ultimately there are three distinct ways an object could accelerate.  

#The object could be speeding up.
#The object could be slowing down.
#The object could be traveling at constant speed, while changing its direction of motion.
(More general accelerations are simply combinations of 1 and 3 or 2 and 3).

Importantly, a change in the direction of motion is just as much an acceleration as is speeding up or slowing down.  In classical mechanics, no direction is associated with time (you cannot point to next Tuesday).  So the definition of &lt;math&gt;\vec a_{av}&lt;/math&gt; tells us that acceleration will point wherever the CHANGE in velocity &lt;math&gt;\Delta\vec{v}&lt;/math&gt; points.  Understanding that the direction of &lt;math&gt;\Delta \vec{v}&lt;/math&gt; determines the direction of &lt;math&gt;\vec a&lt;/math&gt; leads to three non-mathematical but very powerful rules of thumb.
#If the velocity and acceleration of an object point in the same direction, the object's speed is increasing.
#If the velocity and acceleration of an object point in opposite directions, the object's speed is decreasing.
#If the velocity and acceleration of an object are perpendicular to each other, the object's initial speed stays constant (in that initial direction), while the speed of the object in the direction of the acceleration increases--think of a bullet fired horizontally in a vertical gravitational field.  Since velocity in the one direction remains constant, and the velocity in the other direction increases, the overall velocity (absolute velocity) also increases.

(Again, more general motion is simply a combination of 1 and 3 or 2 and 3.)

Using these three simple rules will dramatically help your intuition of what is happening in a particular problem.  In fact, much of the first semester of college physics is simply the application of these three rules in different formats.

= Equations of motion : Constant acceleration =
A particle is said to move with constant acceleration if its velocity changes by equal amounts in equal intervals of time, no matter how small the intervals may be.

{{PSG/eq|&lt;math&gt; \frac{d \vec v}{dt} = 0\ \mathrm{m\ s^{-2}}&lt;/math&gt;}}

Since acceleration is a vector, constant acceleration means that '''both''' direction and magnitude of this vector don't change during the motion.  This means that average and instantaneous acceleration are equal.  We can use that to derive an equation for velocity as a function of time by integrating the constant acceleration.

{{PSG/eq|&lt;math&gt; \boldsymbol{v}(t)=\boldsymbol{v}(0)+\int\limits_{0}^{t}\boldsymbol{a}\ dt&lt;/math&gt;}}

Giving the following equation for velocity as a function of time.

{{PSG/eq|&lt;math&gt; \boldsymbol{v}(t)=\boldsymbol{v}_0+\boldsymbol{a}t&lt;/math&gt;}}

To derive the equation for position we simply integrate the equation for velocity.

{{PSG/eq|&lt;math&gt;\boldsymbol{x}(t)=\boldsymbol{x}(0)+\int\limits_{0}^{t}\boldsymbol{v}(t)\ dt&lt;/math&gt;}}

Integrating again gives the equation for position.

{{PSG/eq|&lt;math&gt;\boldsymbol{x}(t)=\boldsymbol{x}_0+\boldsymbol{v}_0t+\frac{1}{2}\boldsymbol{a}t^2&lt;/math&gt;}}

The following are the 'Equations of Motion'. They are simple and obvious equations if you think over them for a while.

{|
|+Equations of Motion
!Equation||Description
|-
|&lt;math&gt; \vec{x}=\vec{x}_0 + \vec{v}_0 t+\frac{\vec{a}t^2}{2} \ &lt;/math&gt;||Position as a function of time
|-
|&lt;math&gt; \vec v = \vec v_0 + \vec a t  \ &lt;/math&gt;||Velocity as a function of time
|-
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; |The following equations can be derived from the two equations above by combining them and eliminating variables.
|-
|&lt;math&gt; v^2 = v_0^2 + 2\vec{a}\cdot(\vec{x}-\vec{x}_0) \ &lt;/math&gt;||Eliminating time (''Very useful, see the section on'' [[Physics Study Guide/Energy|Energy]])
|-
|&lt;math&gt;\vec{x}=\vec{x}_0+\frac{\vec{v}_0t+\vec{v}t}{2}&lt;/math&gt;||Eliminating acceleration
|}

{|
|+Key to Symbols
!Symbol||Description
|-
|&lt;math&gt;\vec{v}&lt;/math&gt;||velocity at time t
|-
|&lt;math&gt;\vec{v_0}&lt;/math&gt;||initial velocity
|-
|&lt;math&gt;\vec{a}&lt;/math&gt;||acceleration (constant)
|-
|&lt;math&gt;t\ &lt;/math&gt;||time taken during the motion
|-
|&lt;math&gt;\vec{x}&lt;/math&gt;||position at time t
|-
|&lt;math&gt;\vec{x_0}&lt;/math&gt;||initial position
|}


== Acceleration in One Dimension ==

[[File:Example 1D Kinematics constant acceleration.ogv|thumbtime=0:05|middle|400px|Example of 1D Kinematics with constant acceleration'']]

[[File:Example vertical projectile motion.ogv|thumbtime=10:01|middle|400px|Example of 1D Kinematics: Vertical projectile motion with constant acceleration (g)'']]

== Acceleration in Two Dimensions ==
(Needs content)

== Acceleration in Three Dimensions ==
(Needs content)







{{mergeto|Physics Study Guide|This is because the module itself describes a small chapter already made in another module.}}

'''Force''' in motion


We need force in our life and motion too because there are things which needs to have force while it is moving, and if there is no force and there is motion in an object, then the object won't move. If it was the opposite the result will be the same.

== What does force in motion mean? ==
 
Force means strength and power.
Motion means movement.
That’s why we need forces and motions in our life.
We need calculation when we want to know how fast things go, travel and other things which have force and motion.
...

== How do we calculate? ==

If you want to calculate the average speed, distance travelled or time taken you need to use this formula and remember it:       
 &lt;math&gt; {speed} = \frac{distance}{time\ taken} &lt;/math&gt;
This is an easy formula to use, you can find the distance travelled, time taken or average speed, you need at least 2 values to find the whole answer.

== What is velocity? ==

It is not just the speed which is important when you go on a journey. The direction matters as well, then when you want to talk about direction as well as a speed we use the word velocity. This equation for the velocity is using the distance travelled, average speed and time taken. So it will be the same.

Those two racers are in a high speed while racing each other, they are stable in their direction, because they are in high speed and if the direction went out of control slightly and they are in high speed, then maybe the cyclist will get injured. 

== Acceleration ==

When a car is speeding up we say that it is accelerating, when it slows down we say it is decelerating.

== How do we calculate it? ==

When we want to calculate it, the method goes like that: A lorry driver brakes hard, and slows from 25 m/s to 5 m/s in 5 seconds. What was the vehicle's acceleration? 
 &lt;math&gt; {acceleration} = \frac{change\ in\ velocity}{time\ taken} = \frac{5 - 25}{5} = \frac{-20}{5} = -4\ ms^{-2} &lt;/math&gt;
'''''What is initial velocity and final velocity?'''''
Initial velocity is the beginning before motion starts or in the middle of the motion, final velocity is when the motion stops.

There is another way to calculate it and it is like that  
This equations which are written is the primary ones, which means that when you don’t have lets say final velocity, how will you calculate the equation?
 
This is the way you are going to calculate.

== Observing motion ==

When you want to know how fast an athletic person is running, what you need is a stopwatch in your hand, then when the person starts to run, you start the stopwatch and when the person who is sprinting stops at the end point, you stop the watch and see how fast he ran, and if you want to see if the athlete is wasting his energy, while he is running look at his movement, and you will know by that if he is wasting his energy or not.

This athletic person is running, and while he is running the scientist could know if he was wasting his energy if they want by the stop watch and looking at his momentum.

== Measuring acceleration ==

Take a slope, a trolley, some tapes and a stop watch, then put the tapes on the slope and take the trolley on the slope, and the stopwatch in your hand, as soon as you release the trolley, start timing the trolley at how fast it will move, when the trolley stops at the end then stop the timing.
After wards, after seeing the timing , record it, then you let the slope a little bit high, and you will see, how little by little it will decelerate.

== Who is Newton, and what did he observe? ==

He was an English physicist, mathematician, astronomer, alchemist, and natural philosopher, he has three laws for physics, and they are:
# Newton's First Law (also known as the Law of Inertia) states that an object at rest tends to stay at rest and that an object in uniform motion tends to stay in uniform motion unless acted upon by a net external force. 
# Newton's Second Law states that an applied force, F, on an object equals the time rate of change of its momentum, p. the acceleration of an object is directly proportional to the magnitude of the net force acting on the object and inversely proportional to its mass. In the MKS system of measurement, mass is given in kilograms, acceleration in metres per second squared, and force in newtons (named in his honour). 
# Newton's Third Law states that for every action there is an equal and opposite reaction.

'''Symbols'''

Distance travelled=D

Force= F

Initial velocity=U

Final velocity=V

Velocity=V

Acceleration=A

Change in velocity=∆V

Mass=M

Newton=N

Gravity= G

Weight=W

== Force ==

Now here we are going to learn how to calculate the force, mass and acceleration. When we want to calculate the force, and we have the mass and acceleration, how are we going to calculate it?
force=mass multiply acceleration
This is considered in the second law of Newton.
What is mass?
Sometimes it is defined as the amount of matter in a body. But in Newton’s second law is defined as a numerical measure of inertia.
What is inertia?
The tendency of a body to maintain is state of rest or uniform motion unless acted upon by an external force.

Who is Hooke, and what is his law?
(July 18, 1635 – March 3, 1703.)He was an English polymath who played an important role in the scientific revolution, through both experimental and theoretical work. His law was about the spring limit, if you have stretched the spring beyond its limit, it will then change permanently, and will not return to its original place.
The rubber band doesn’t obey Hooke’s law.
This spring is not beyond its limit, so when you remove the weight, then it will automatically return to its place.

{{Alphabetical|F}}
{{Subjects|Physics}}
{{status|25%}}






{{BookCat}}

[[ar:دليل دراسة الفيزياء/الحركة]]</text>
      <sha1>kytjb9r7pyqmf6voovk4iugadvumoe5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>German/Lesson 4</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1851</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2653646</id>
      <parentid>1709647</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-05-11T18:00:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Harrybrowne1986</username>
        <id>430968</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>m</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;small&gt;&lt;&lt; [[German/Lesson_3|Lesson 3]] |&lt;/small&gt; '''Lektion 4''' &lt;small&gt;| [[German/Lesson 5|Lektion 5]] &gt;&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
----
[[image:Zurich.jpeg|thumb|543px|Zürich: am Ausfluss des Zürichsees]]

== Lesestück 4-1 ~ Eine Geschichte über Zürich ==
:&lt;big&gt;Zürich ist die größte Stadt der Schweiz. Sie liegt am Ausfluss des Zürichsees und ist die Hauptstadt des gleichnamigen Kantons, des Kantons Zürich. Zürich ist ausgesprochen schön gelegen, am nördlichen Ende des Zürichsees&amp;mdash;bei klarem Wetter hat man eine gute Sicht auf die Glarner Alpen.&lt;/big&gt;

:&lt;big&gt;Zürich ist das Zentrum der schweizer Bankenwirtschaft. Neben den beiden Grossbanken ('Credit Suisse' und 'UBS') haben auch etliche kleinere Bankinstitute ihren Sitz in der Stadt.&lt;/big&gt;

Although this short story contains quite a number of impressive German nouns and adjectives, with the aid of ''Vokabeln 4-1'' following you should have no trouble reading and understanding it. The passage makes considerable use of the German genitive case (English possessive case), which you have not yet learned. However, a clue applicable here: translate ''des'' as &quot;of the&quot; or &quot;of&quot; and note there are other ''der''-words that also mean &quot;of the&quot;.

== Vokabeln 4-1 ==

  &lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;die Alpen&lt;/font&gt;               Alps 
  &lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;der Ausfluss&lt;/font&gt;            outlet, effluence           (of a lake)
  &lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;die Bankinstitute&lt;/font&gt;       banking institutes 
  &lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;die Bankenwirtschaft&lt;/font&gt;    banking business
  &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;das Ende&lt;/font&gt;                end
  &lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;die Grossbanken&lt;/font&gt;         major banks
  &lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;die Hauptstadt&lt;/font&gt;          capital city
  &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;das Haus&lt;/font&gt;                house
  &lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;der Kanton&lt;/font&gt;              canton                      (Swiss state)
  &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;das Lesestück&lt;/font&gt;           reading passage
  &lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;die Schweiz&lt;/font&gt;             Switzerland
  &lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;die Sicht&lt;/font&gt;               view
  &lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;der Sitz&lt;/font&gt;                office
  &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;das Wetter&lt;/font&gt;              weather
  &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;das Zentrum&lt;/font&gt;             center (centre)
  &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;das Zürich&lt;/font&gt;              Zurich                      (city and canton in Switzerland)
  &lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;der Zürichsee&lt;/font&gt;           Lake Zurich

  d.h. (das heißt)        i.e. (&quot;that is&quot; in Latin)
  Glarner Alpen           Glarner Alps
  man hat...              one has... 
  nach Hause              (toward) home               (compare: ''zu Hause'' = &quot;at home&quot;)

  anrufen                 call, telephone
  geben  (gab, gegeben)   give
  kommen (kam, gekommen)  come
  liegen (lag, gelegen)   lie (lay, lain)

  am (an dem)             at the
  ausgesprochen           markedly
  bei                     in
  beiden                  two
  etliche                 a number of, quite a few, several
  gleichnamig             same named
  größte                  largest
  klar                    clear
  klein                   small
  neben                   besides
  nördlich                northern
  schweizer               of or pertaining to Swiss
  
&lt;small&gt;[[German/Appendices/Alphabet|Pronunciation Guide]] &gt;&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
----

== Grammatik 4-1 ~ Introduction to adjectives ==
An '''[[Wikipedia:en:Adjective|adjective]]''' is a part of speech which can be thought of as a &quot;describing word&quot;&amp;mdash;typically, an adjective modifies a noun. In both English and German, adjectives come before the noun they describe or modify. In many other languages (such as French) they usually come after the noun. Here are some examples of &lt;u&gt;adjectives&lt;/u&gt; (underlined) you have already encountered:
{|
|''Ich habe &lt;u&gt;viel&lt;/u&gt; Arbeit.''
|I have &lt;u&gt;much&lt;/u&gt; work.
|-
|''Wir haben &lt;u&gt;keinen&lt;/u&gt; Käse.''
|We have &lt;u&gt;no&lt;/u&gt; cheese.
|-
|''Bei &lt;u&gt;klarem&lt;/u&gt; Wetter hat man eine &lt;u&gt;gute&lt;/u&gt; Sicht.''&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
|In &lt;u&gt;clear&lt;/u&gt; weather, one has a &lt;u&gt;good&lt;/u&gt; view
|-
|Zürich ist die &lt;u&gt;größte&lt;/u&gt; Stadt.''
|Zurich is the largest city. 
|}
Because nouns are capitalized in German, it is fairly obvious in these sentences where the adjectives occur: just before the nouns they modify. Note how the endings on German adjectives can change, depending upon the noun (''kein'''en''' Käse''; ''klar'''em''' Wetter''; ''gut'''e''' Sicht'')&amp;mdash;specifically, the '''gender''' and '''case''' of the noun they are modifying.  Before explaining the basic rules governing adjective endings, you need to have a better understanding of person, gender, and case in German nouns&amp;mdash;concepts that will be explored in the next few lessons.

Finally, realize that the '''ordinal numbers''' you learned in [[German/Lesson_3|Lektion 3]] are, in fact, adjectives&amp;mdash;subject to the same rules governing word endings for adjectives.
{|
|''Wer ist das &lt;u&gt;dritte&lt;/u&gt; Mädchen?''
|Who is the &lt;u&gt;third&lt;/u&gt; girl?
|-
|''Wir verstehen nur die &lt;u&gt;erste&lt;/u&gt; Lektion.''
|We understand only the &lt;i&gt;first&lt;/i&gt; lesson.         
|}
----
== Gespräch 4-1 ~ Das neue Mädchen ==
:&lt;big&gt;Markus und Helena sind Freunde.&lt;/big&gt;
:* ''Markus'': &lt;Big&gt;Lena, wer ist das neue Mädchen? Die Brünette dort drüben. 
:* ''Helena'': &lt;big&gt;Ich glaube, sie heißt 'Karoline'. 
:* ''Markus'': &lt;big&gt;Sie ist sehr schön.
:* ''Helena'': &lt;big&gt;Sie ist hübsch, wenn man kleine Mädchen mit langen dunklen Haaren mag.
:* ''Markus'': &lt;big&gt;Ja. Ihre Haare gefallen mir sehr.''
:* ''Helena'': &lt;big&gt;Markus, du bist ein Ferkel!
This short conversational passage contains more examples of adjectives.

== Vokabeln 4-2 ==

 &lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;die Brünette&lt;/font&gt;             brunette
 &lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;die Haare&lt;/font&gt;                hair(s)
 &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;das Mädchen&lt;/font&gt;              girl
 &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;das Ferkel&lt;/font&gt;               piglet 

 ge'''fall'''en                appeal to
 glauben                  believe
 heißen                   name, call
 mag                      like, desire, wish

 dort                     there
 (dort) drüben            over there
 dunkel                   dark
 ihr                      her
 hübsch                   cute
 klein                    short
 lang                     long
 neue                     new
 wenn                     if
 wer?                     who?

&lt;small&gt;[[German/Appendices/Alphabet|Pronunciation Guide]] &gt;&gt; &lt;/small&gt;
----

== Grammatik 4-2 ~ Nouns and pronouns in the accusative and dative ==

As was noted previously when the concept of '''case''' was introduced for pronouns ([[German/Lesson_2#Grammatik 2-2 ~ Pronouns in the Nominative Case|Grammatik 2-2]]), there are four cases used in German. Recall that the '''nominative''' case in German corresponds to the ''subjective case'' in English and applies to nouns and pronouns used in a sentence as the subject of a verb. Nouns (and pronouns) that are used as objects of transitive (action) verbs are in the English objective case.  If these are '''direct objects''' (recipients of the action of a verb), then these nouns are in the '''accusative case''' in German.  If '''indirect objects''', then these nouns are in the '''dative case''' in German.  Essentially, the English ''objective case'' is divided, in German, into an &lt;u&gt;accusative case used for direct objects&lt;/u&gt; and a &lt;u&gt;dative case used for indirect objects&lt;/u&gt;.

===Pronouns===
For comparison with English, recall that the singular personal pronouns (''nominative case'') are &quot;I&quot;, &quot;you&quot;, and &quot;he/she/it&quot; (1st, 2nd, and 3rd persons). The ''objective case'', personal pronouns in English are &quot;me&quot;, &quot;you&quot;, and &quot;him/her/it&quot;&amp;mdash;and are used for both direct and indirect objects of verbs. For example:

:He gives &lt;big&gt;&lt;u&gt;it&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/big&gt; &lt;small&gt;[the Direct Object]&lt;/small&gt; to &lt;big&gt;&lt;u&gt;me&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/big&gt; &lt;small&gt;[the Indirect Object]&lt;/small&gt;.

The German '''accusative case''', personal pronouns (singular) are: ''mich, dich, ihn/sie/es''. The German '''dative case''', personal pronouns (singular) are: ''mir'', ''dir'', ''ihm/ihr/ihm''. Thus, the above English example sentence becomes, in German:

:''Er gibt &lt;u&gt;es&lt;/u&gt;'' &lt;small&gt;[the Direct Object]&lt;/small&gt; ''&lt;u&gt;mir&lt;/u&gt;'' &lt;small&gt;[the Indirect Object]&lt;/small&gt;.

Because ''mir'' is a dative pronoun, there is no need in German to use a modifier as in English, where &quot;to&quot; is used as a signal of an indirect object.  The following table summarizes the German pronouns in three cases for both singular and plural number:


{| border=&quot;1&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#FFFFCC&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot;
|-
|
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; | Singular || || colspan=&quot;3&quot; | Plural
|-
|
 || NOM. || ACC. || DAT. || || NOM. || ACC. || DAT.
|-
| 1st person || '''ich''' || '''mich'''
| '''mir''' || || '''wir''' || '''uns''' || '''uns'''
|-
| 2nd person || '''du''' ('''Sie'''*) || '''dich''' ('''Sie'''*)
| '''dir''' ('''Ihnen'''*) || || '''ihr''' ('''Sie'''*)
| '''euch''' ('''Sie'''*) || '''euch''' ('''Ihnen'''*)
|-
| 3rd person || '''er''', '''sie''', '''es'''
| '''ihn''', '''sie''', '''es''' || '''ihm''', '''ihr''', '''ihm''' ||
| '''sie''' || '''sie''' || '''ihnen'''
|}
:&lt;nowiki&gt;*&lt;/nowiki&gt; Polite form

Recall from [[German/Lesson_2#Gespräch 2-1 ~ Die Geschäftsleute|Gespräch 2-1]] the &quot;incomplete&quot; sentence ''Und Ihnen?'' ('And you?'). Note that the pronoun agrees in case (here, dative) with the implied sentence &amp;mdash; ''Und wie geht es Ihnen?'' The same rule is evident in [[German/Lesson 1#Gespräch 1-1 ~ Die Freunde|Gespräch 1-1]] (''Und dir?''). Such agreement is important to convey the correct meaning. Tables giving the German personal pronouns in all cases can be found in an appendix:  [[German/Appendix_3|Pronoun Tables]].

=== Nouns ===
Nouns do not change their form (spelling) relative to case in German; instead, a preceding article indicates case. You have learned the nominative case definite and indefinite articles ([[German/Lesson 3#Grammatik 3-3 ~ Gender of Nouns|Grammatik 3-3]]: ''der'', ''die'', ''das'' and ''ein'', ''eine''. ''ein'') for each of the three noun  genders. Now we will learn the ''accusative'' (used to signal a direct object) and ''dative'' (used to signal an indirect object) articles. First, the definite articles:


{| border=&quot;1&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#FFFFCC&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot;
|-
|
|colspan=&quot;3&quot;  | Singular || || colspan=&quot;3&quot; | Plural  
|-
|
 || NOM. || ACC. || DAT. || || NOM. || ACC. || DAT.
|-
| Masculine || '''der''' || '''den''' || '''dem''' ||
| '''die''' || '''die''' || '''den'''
|-
| Feminine || '''die''' || '''die''' || '''der''' ||
| '''die''' || '''die''' || '''den'''
|-
| Neuter || '''das''' || '''das''' || '''dem'''
|
 || '''die''' || '''die''' || '''den'''
|}

This table might seem a bit overwhelming (and there is yet one more case in German: the genitive!), but some points to note can make memorizing much easier.  First, as you can see from the table, ''gender'' does not really exist for plural nouns.  No matter what the noun gender in its singular number, its plural always has the same set of definite articles: ''die'', ''die'', ''den'' for nominative, accusative, and dative cases. The plural ''der''-words are similar to the  feminine singular ''der''-words, differing only in the dative case. Another point: the dative for both masculine and neuter nouns is the same: ''dem''. Finally, for feminine, neuter, and plural nouns, there is no change between nominative and accusative cases. Thus, only for masculine nouns is there a definite article change in the accusative compared with the nominative.   

The following examples demonstrate the use of the definite article in various parts of speech:
{|
|''Du hast &lt;u&gt;die&lt;/u&gt; Wurst und &lt;u&gt;den&lt;/u&gt; Käse.''
|You have &lt;u&gt;the&lt;/u&gt; sausage and &lt;u&gt;the&lt;/u&gt; cheese.
|(accusative case)
|-
|''&lt;u&gt;Die&lt;/u&gt; Geschäftsleute verstehen &lt;u&gt;die&lt;/u&gt; Arbeit''
|The business associates understand the work.
|(nominative and accusative cases)
|-
|''Zürich ist &lt;u&gt;die&lt;/u&gt; größte Stadt.''
|Zurich is &lt;u&gt;the&lt;/u&gt; largest city.
|(nominative case)
|}

In the last example, you need to know that in both English and German, the noun (or pronoun) that follows the verb 'to be' is a '''predicate noun''', for which the correct case is the '''nominative'''. That is why, in English, 'It is I' is grammatically correct and 'It is me' is simply incorrect. 

The indefinite articles are as follows:


{| border=&quot;1&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#FFFFCC&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot;
|-
|
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; | Singular
|-
|
 || NOM. || ACC. || DAT.
|-
| Masculine || '''ein''' || '''einen'''
| '''einem'''
|-
| Feminine || '''eine''' || '''eine'''
| '''einer''' 
|-
| Neuter
| '''ein''' || '''ein''' || '''einem'''
|}

Of course, there are no plural indefinite articles in German or English (''ein'' means &quot;a&quot;. &quot;an&quot;, or &quot;one&quot;).  It is important to see that there is a pattern in the case endings added to ''ein'' related to the ''der''-words in the definite articles table above.  For example, the dative definite article for masculine nouns is ''dem''&amp;mdash;the indefinite article is formed by adding ''-em'' onto ''ein'' to get ''einem''.  The dative definite article for feminine nouns is ''der''&amp;mdash;the indefinite is ''ein'' plus ''-er'' or ''einer''.  These ending changes will be covered in greater detail in a future lesson.  You will see that there are a number of words (adjectives, for example) whose form relative changes by addition of these endings to signal the case of the noun they modify. Finally, we can see a pattern relationship between these &quot;endings&quot; and the 3rd person pronouns as well: 

{| border=&quot;1&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#FFFFCC&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot;
|-
|
 ||  || NOM. || ACC. || DAT.
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Masculine || indef. article
| '''ein''' || '''einen''' || '''einem'''
|-
| 3rd pers. pronoun || '''er''' || '''ihn'''
| '''ihm'''
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Feminine || indef. article
| '''eine''' || '''eine''' || '''einer'''
|-
| 3rd pers. pronoun || '''sie''' || '''sie'''
| '''ihr''' 
|-
|rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Neuter
| indef. article || '''ein''' || '''ein'''
| '''einem'''
|-
| 3rd pers. pronoun || '''es''' || '''es'''
| '''ihm'''
|}
We could construct a similar table to compare the definite articles to the 3rd person pronouns.  And in that case, we would also see how the plural definite articles (''die'', ''die'', ''den'') compare with the third person plural pronouns (''sie'', ''sie'', ''ihnen'').  
----

== Grammatik 4-3 ~ Interrogatives ==
You have encountered nearly all of the '''interrogatives''' commonly used in German (review [[German/Lesson_1#Grammatik_1-2 ~ Word Order in Questions|Grammatik 1-2]]):
  ''wann''                  when
  ''war&lt;b&gt;um&lt;/b&gt;''                 why            ''&lt;u&gt;Warum&lt;/u&gt; sind Sie müde?''
  ''was''                   what           ''&lt;u&gt;Was&lt;/u&gt; ist das?''
  ''wer''                   who            ''&lt;u&gt;Wer&lt;/u&gt; ist das Mädchen?''
  ''wie''                   how            ''&lt;u&gt;Wie&lt;/u&gt; geht es dir?''
  ''wieviel''               how much       ''&lt;u&gt;Wieviel&lt;/u&gt; Uhr ist es?''
  ''wo''                    where          ''&lt;u&gt;Wo&lt;/u&gt; ist das Buch?''
  ''wohin''                 where (to)     ''&lt;u&gt;Wohin&lt;/u&gt; gehst du?'' 
In a question, interrogatives replace the unknown object and establish the class of answer expected.
{|
|''&lt;u&gt;Was&lt;/u&gt; haben Sie?''
|What do you have?
|(Expected is a 'thing')
|-
|''&lt;u&gt;Wieviel&lt;/u&gt; Arbeit ist zu viel?''
|How much work is too much?
|(Expected is a 'quantity')
|-
|''&lt;u&gt;Wann&lt;/u&gt; gehst du nach Hause?''
|When do you go home?
|(Expected is a sense of 'time')
|-
|''&lt;u&gt;Wo&lt;/u&gt; ist der Zürichsee?''
|Where is Lake Zurich?
|(Expected is a 'place')
|}
Note that the English construction for some of the questions differs from the German in that the former uses the progressive form of &quot;do&quot;. 
----

== &lt;font color=&quot;#009900&quot;&gt;Übersetzung 4-1&lt;/font&gt; ==
Translate the following sentences into German:
&lt;big&gt;
#They have a good view of the Alps.
#Lake Zurich is very beautiful.
:* [[German/Answers_1#Lektion_4 Antworten|Antworten]] &gt;

{{BookCat}}
&lt;noinclude&gt;{{German/Level II/Footer}}&lt;/noinclude&gt;</text>
      <sha1>n8em8q1vmvlvp9obphfmnvscaleubl5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Esperanto/Introducing yourself</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1853</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1866487</id>
      <parentid>1717857</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-06-28T22:36:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Adding {{WikiProject Languages}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{WikiProject Languages}} 

== Comments ==

:So far, I like it.  One suggestion: you instroduce the concept of direct and indirect objects, and you give a rule for forming direct object, but you do not yet give a rule for forming indirect objects.  Those of us who have studied languages before are at the edges of our seats with anticipation...

Has anyone any comments on this lesson? Especially those with no knowledge of Esperanto, is this first lesson clear enough to follow (especially the grammar)? --[[User:Gabriel Beecham|Gabriel Beecham]] 12:31, 31 Oct 2003 (UTC)

:Looks like you are structuring things along the lines I have been using for [[German]], and I started out there by copying the [[Spanish]] language textbook well set up by Thomas. So I would say &quot;good start&quot;! What to actually present in each lesson is a difficult decision, and my feeling is, you may shift things around as you progress.  I do believe you should start simple, but make lots of ties (as you are doing) to English grammar as an English speaker can relate to these connections and some learners (like myself) need to see rules to understand why things are said as they are in the foreign language. I'd say you have a good handle on these concepts. - [[User:Marshman|Marsh]] 20:36, 13 Nov 2003 (UTC)


--:Interesting, indeed fairly facsinating, and good choices of words introductory words (Or perhaps it's just that I like reading and cities).  Fairly useful, for a very basic introduction, but as an English speaker learning Spanish and hoping to learn Esparanto, I've found that I've had to go to several other sites to find much what I'm looking for.  It might be helpful if you gave certain common or useful words such as &quot;no&quot; &quot;on&quot; &quot;in&quot; &quot;as&quot; (or all ases) &quot;yes&quot; &quot;who&quot; &quot;what&quot; &quot;when&quot; &quot;why&quot; &quot;how&quot; and &quot;how many/much&quot;, perhaps as your next lesson.  Thanks though, nice introduction, and useful lesson. 6:24, 9 December 2004 (EST)

Does anyone have ideas for the review section? -[[User:Travisg|travisg]] 23:42, 27 Sep 2004 (UTC)

== Errors ==

I'm new to Esperanto, and I am finding this book fascinating!  Keep it up.  When you say &quot;Please note that not all adverbs use this rule, but the overwhelming majority of them do.&quot; do you mean that not all adverbs end -e?  A brief explanation would be beneficial here.  I thought that since this is a sythetic language, there are no exceptions to the rules! :) 
--[[User:Ralph walden|Ralph walden]] 02:22, 12 August 2006 (UTC)

:There are no exceptions; the rule is that to turn a root into an adverb, you add and -e. That's always true, but not all adverbs are formed from roots. There are some words that are purely adverbs, like {{lang eo|preskaŭ}} (&quot;almost&quot;). There is no &quot;{{lang eo|preska-}}&quot; root that this comes from (what would &quot;{{lang eo|preskao}}&quot; or &quot;{{lang eo|preskai}}&quot; mean?).

:But you're right - this really needs a bit more discussion. There is just too much crammed into this one lesson, and nothing is getting treated well. --[[User:Indiana|Indiana]] ([[User talk:Indiana|talk]]) 23:03, 10 February 2010 (UTC)

It seems a bit odd to say &quot;there is no verb conjugation in Esperanto.&quot; Vidi, vidas, vidis, vidos, vidus -- that's conjugation, buddy. If you are going to use grammatical terms please use them properly. [[User:Rikat|Rikat]] ([[User talk:Rikat|talk]]) 03:51, 16 May 2009 (UTC)

:Perhaps it would have been more constructive to edit the phrase in question to &quot;there is no verb conjugation in Esperanto for number or gender&quot;, rather than to criticize and do nothing else. --[[User:Indiana|Indiana]] ([[User talk:Indiana|talk]]) 23:03, 10 February 2010 (UTC)

The pronouns section seems to be incorrect. I think ''mi'' can only mean &quot;I&quot; not &quot;me&quot;. I'm pretty sure ''min'' is &quot;me&quot;. --[[User:Yair rand|Yair rand]] ([[User talk:Yair rand|talk]]) 20:36, 14 December 2009 (UTC)

:{{lang eo|Mi}} can mean &quot;me&quot;. If you point at a picture of yourself and say &quot;that's me&quot;, that would be &quot;{{lang eo|tio estas mi}}&quot;. This is not an inconsistency in Esperanto, but due to a quirk in English. In English you can use either &quot;I&quot; or &quot;me&quot; as the predicate for the copula in certain conditions: for example, when announcing yourself you can say &quot;it is I&quot; or &quot;it is me&quot;. --[[User:Indiana|Indiana]] ([[User talk:Indiana|talk]]) 23:03, 10 February 2010 (UTC)

== Restructuring ==

This first &quot;lesson&quot; is way too grammar heavy. How about starting with a sentence like &quot;My name is (Bob). I'm from (USA).&quot; rather than starting with a long grammatical reference? Amazingly people can learn languages without knowing anything explicitly about grammar. Introduce the nouns, verbs, etc later, or introduce them more gradually. [[User:Pengo|Pengo]] ([[User talk:Pengo|talk]]) 05:47, 1 June 2008 (UTC)

:I agree - I looked at what was being introduced in the first lesson (&quot;Nouns, Adjectives, Adverbs, Personal and possessive pronouns, Verbs - Present Tense, Objects&quot;) and went cross-eyed. This really needs to be scaled down and separated substantially. --[[User:Indiana|Indiana]] ([[User talk:Indiana|talk]]) 23:03, 10 February 2010 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>lxjg9lbd2mse6vt7ajn3simxrfwxw4s</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Physics Study Guide/Greek alphabet</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1854</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2628046</id>
      <parentid>2628045</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-04-08T15:15:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Defender</username>
        <id>621284</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/182.69.17.23|182.69.17.23]] ([[User talk:182.69.17.23|talk]]) to last version by 112.207.165.213</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{PSG}}

=About the ''Common uses in Physics''=
While these are indeed common usages, it should be pointed out that there are many other usages and that other letters are used for the same purpose. The reason is quite simple: there are only so many symbols in the Greek and Latin alphabets, and scientists and mathematicians generally do not use symbols from other languages. It is a common trap to associate a symbol exclusively with some particular meaning, rather than learning and understanding the physics and relations behind it.


{| align=&quot;center&quot; border cellspacing=0 cellpadding=5
|+'''Greek Alphabet'''
!Lower case !! Capital !! Name !! Common use in Physics
|-
| &lt;math&gt;\alpha\;&lt;/math&gt; || &lt;math&gt;\Alpha\;&lt;/math&gt;  || alpha
| Angular acceleration&lt;br/&gt;Linear expansion&lt;br/&gt;Coefficient&lt;br/&gt;Alpha particle (helium nucleus)&lt;br/&gt;Fine Structure Constant
|-
| &lt;math&gt;\beta\;&lt;/math&gt; || &lt;math&gt;\Beta\;&lt;/math&gt;  || beta
| Beta particle &amp;mdash; high energy electron&lt;br/&gt;Sound intensity
|-
| &lt;math&gt;\gamma\;&lt;/math&gt; || &lt;math&gt;\Gamma\;&lt;/math&gt;  || gamma
| Gamma ray (high energy EM wave)&lt;br&gt;Ratio of heat capacities (in an ideal gas)&lt;br&gt;Relativistic correction factor
|-
| &lt;math&gt;\delta\;&lt;/math&gt; || &lt;math&gt;\Delta\;&lt;/math&gt;  || delta
| &amp;Delta;=&quot;Change in&quot; &lt;br&gt; &amp;delta;=&quot;Infinitesimal change in&quot;
|-
| &lt;math&gt;\epsilon\;&lt;/math&gt; || &lt;math&gt;\Epsilon\;&lt;/math&gt;  || epsilon
| Emissivity&lt;br&gt;Strain&lt;br&gt;Permittivity&lt;br&gt;EMF
|-
| &lt;math&gt;\zeta\;&lt;/math&gt; || &lt;math&gt;\Zeta\;&lt;/math&gt;  || zeta
| (no common use)
|-
| &lt;math&gt;\eta\;&lt;/math&gt; || &lt;math&gt;\Eta\;&lt;/math&gt;  || eta
| Viscosity&lt;br&gt;Energy efficiency
|-
| &lt;math&gt;\theta\;&lt;/math&gt; || &lt;math&gt;\Theta\;&lt;/math&gt;  || theta
| Angle (&amp;deg;, rad)&lt;br&gt;Temperature
|-
| &lt;math&gt;\iota\;&lt;/math&gt; || &lt;math&gt;\Iota\;&lt;/math&gt;  || iota
| The lower case &lt;math&gt;\iota\;&lt;/math&gt; is rarely used, while &lt;math&gt;\Iota\;&lt;/math&gt; is sometimes used for the identity matrix or the moment of inertia.  Note that &lt;math&gt;\iota\;&lt;/math&gt; is not to be confused with the Roman character &lt;math&gt;i;&lt;/math&gt; (which has a dot and is much more widely used in mathematics and physics).
|-
| &lt;math&gt;\kappa\;&lt;/math&gt; || &lt;math&gt;\Kappa\;&lt;/math&gt;  || kappa
| Spring constant&lt;br&gt;Dielectric constant
|-
| &lt;math&gt;\lambda\;&lt;/math&gt; || &lt;math&gt;\Lambda\;&lt;/math&gt;  || lambda
| Wavelength&lt;br&gt;Thermal conductivity&lt;br&gt;Constant&lt;br&gt;Eigenvalue of a matrix&lt;br&gt;Linear density
|-
| &lt;math&gt;\mu\;&lt;/math&gt; || &lt;math&gt;\Mu\;&lt;/math&gt;  || mu
| Coefficient of friction&lt;br&gt;Electrical mobility&lt;br&gt;Reduced mass&lt;br&gt;Permeability
|-
| &lt;math&gt;\nu\;&lt;/math&gt; || &lt;math&gt;\Nu\;&lt;/math&gt;  || nu
| Frequency
|-
| &lt;math&gt;\xi\;&lt;/math&gt; || &lt;math&gt;\Xi\;&lt;/math&gt;  || xi
| Damping cofficient
|-
| &lt;math&gt;o\;&lt;/math&gt; || &lt;math&gt;O\;&lt;/math&gt;  || omicron
| (no common use)
|-
| &lt;math&gt;\pi\;&lt;/math&gt; || &lt;math&gt;\Pi\;&lt;/math&gt;  || pi
| Product symbol &lt;math&gt;\Pi&lt;/math&gt;&lt;br&gt; Circle number &lt;math&gt;\pi:=3.14159...&lt;/math&gt;
|-
| &lt;math&gt;\rho\;&lt;/math&gt; || &lt;math&gt;\Rho\;&lt;/math&gt;  || rho
| Volume density&lt;br&gt; Resistivity
|-
| &lt;math&gt;\sigma\;&lt;/math&gt; || &lt;math&gt;\Sigma\;&lt;/math&gt;  || sigma
| Sum symbol&lt;br&gt;Boltzmann constant&lt;br&gt;Electrical conductivity&lt;br&gt;Uncertainty&lt;br&gt;Stress&lt;br&gt;Surface density
|-
| &lt;math&gt;\tau\;&lt;/math&gt; || &lt;math&gt;\Tau\;&lt;/math&gt;  || tau
| Torque&lt;br&gt;Tau particle (a lepton)&lt;br&gt;Time constant
|-
| &lt;math&gt;\upsilon\;&lt;/math&gt; || &lt;math&gt;\Upsilon\;&lt;/math&gt;  || upsilon
| mass to light ratio
|-
| &lt;math&gt;\phi\;&lt;/math&gt; || &lt;math&gt;\Phi\;&lt;/math&gt;  || phi
| Magnetic/electric flux&lt;br&gt;Angle (&amp;deg;, rad)
|-
| &lt;math&gt;\chi\;&lt;/math&gt; || &lt;math&gt;\Chi\;&lt;/math&gt;  || chi
| Rabi frequency (lasers)&lt;br&gt;Susceptibility
|-
| &lt;math&gt;\psi\;&lt;/math&gt; || &lt;math&gt;\Psi\;&lt;/math&gt;  || psi
| Wave function
|-
| &lt;math&gt;\omega\;&lt;/math&gt; || &lt;math&gt;\Omega\;&lt;/math&gt;  || omega
| Ohms (unit of electrical resistance)&lt;br&gt;&amp;omega; Angular velocity
|}

=See Also=
[[w:Greek alphabet|Greek alphabet]] on the [[w:Main Page|Wikipedia]]
{{BookCat}}
missionaries of the sacred heart</text>
      <sha1>dmsadyyfdwclvci0alagwtsax44rur0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cascading Style Sheets</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1855</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2667090</id>
      <parentid>2632104</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-05-28T20:04:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Koavf</username>
        <id>16549</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>intro</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">__NOTOC__
This book is a guide to Cascading Style Sheets (CSS), a technique widely used in web pages including Wikipedia to describe their visual style and appearance. CSS can take [[HTML]] to new places creatively and functionally. Once you learn how to style mark-up, you can additionally learn [[JavaScript]] functions that make dynamic web pages.

==Contents==
{{Book Search}}
{{Print version|Cascading Style Sheets/Print version}}
{{wikipedia|Cascading Style Sheets}}
{{wikiversity|Topic:CSS}}
{{prerequisite|HyperText Markup Language}}
# [[/Introduction/]]
# [[/Applying CSS to HTML and XHTML/]]&amp;nbsp;— linking, embedding and inlining
# [[/Applying CSS to XML/]]
# CSS Construction
## [[/Syntax/]]
## [[/Defining Style Rules/]]
## [[/Lengths and Units/]]
## [[/Selectors/]]
## [[/Inheritance Rules/]]
## [[/Important/|The Important Keyword]]
# CSS Presentation
## [[/Color/]]
## [[/Fonts and Text/]]
## [[/Hyperlinks/]]
## [[/Pseudo Elements and Pseudo Classes/]]
## [[/Clipping/]]
## [[/Lists/]]
## [[/Box Model/]]&amp;nbsp;— setting the size and shape of elements
## [[/Borders/]]
## [[/Background/]]
## [[/Shorthand Properties/]]
## [[/Cursor/]]
## [[/Gradients/]]
## [[/Sprites/]]
# CSS Layout
## [[/Centering/]]
## [[/Positioning/]]
## [[/Tables/]]
## [[/Floating Elements/]]
## [[/Typography/]]
## [[/Media Types/]]
## [[/Multi-Column Layout/]]
## [[/z-index/]]
# CSS URI Schemes
## [[/MHTML URIs/]]
## [[/Data URIs/]]
# CSS Applications
## [[/CSS Menus/]]
## [[/Breadcrumbs/]]
## [[/User Style Sheets/]]
# Troubleshooting
## [[/Standards Mode and Quirks Mode/|Standards Mode and Quirks Mode]]
## [[/Compatibility/|Browser Compatibility]]
## [[/Troubleshoot Order/|CSS Source Order]] (Troubleshooting the cascade of repeated selectors)
# Appendices
## [[/Hacks and Filters/]]
## [[/Browser Extensions/]]
## [[/Links/]]
## [[/Index of Properties/]]
## [[/Index/]]
## [[/Glossary/]]
## [[/Detailed TOC/]]
## [[/Contributors/]]
## [[/To Do/]]

==Related Wikibooks==
* [[JavaScript]]
* [[XHTML]]
* [[The CSS Cascade]]
* [[Style Presentation Modes in Opera 12.16]]
{{Subject|Markup languages}}
{{alphabetical|C}}
{{status|75%}}

[[de:Websiteentwicklung: CSS]]
[[et:CSS]]
[[fr:Le langage CSS]]
[[gl:CSS]]
[[id:Pemrograman CSS]]
[[it:CSS]]
[[he:CSS]]
[[ms:Lembaran Gaya Lata]]
[[nl:Cascading Style Sheets]]
[[ja:CSS]]
[[ka:CSS]]
[[pl:CSS]]
[[zh:CSS]]
[[ru:CSS]]
[[uk:CSS]]</text>
      <sha1>l4bpmt2trzc7kqjj6pcw4ekut1rr8m0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>