<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>File:1,6-Dichloro-2,3,5-trimethy.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1427</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748785</id>
      <parentid>746337</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-02-09T19:37:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>lftdbfdb9bftwmpa42ewbdhqaw7jksr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>US History/World War I</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1431</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2714882</id>
      <parentid>2714872</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-18T13:55:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pittsburgh Poet</username>
        <id>1449338</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Increasing Racial Tension */ consistent capitalization</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">== Europe ==

In 1815, Europe had united to defeat French Emperor Napoleon. For a century since that time, there had been no major war in Europe. Countries had organized themselves in a complex system of alliances.

After Napoleon's defeat, the United Kingdom, France, Prussia, Russia, and Austria met in Vienna. These nations decided that if power in Europe was balanced, then no nation would become so powerful as to pose a threat to the others. The most important of these was the German Confederation. In 1871, after defeating France and Prussia, several small German nations merged into the German Empire. This upset the traditional balance of power. 

German Chancellor Otto von Bismarck began to construct a web of alliances to protect German dominance. Germany and the United Kingdom were on good terms, as Germany had not built a navy to rival British sea power. In 1873, Russia, the Austro-Hungarian Empire, and Germany formed the Three Emperors' League. Nine years later, Austria-Hungary, Italy, and Germany formed the Triple Alliance. In 1887, the Reinsurance Treaty ensured that Russia would not interfere in a war between France and Germany. 

During this time the British Queen Victoria built alliances in her own way. During years of relative peace, she had her children marry into many of the royal families of Europe, believing that this would solidify relations among the nations. In the first decade of the Twentieth century the Kaiser and the King of England were cousins through Victoria, as were the Tzar and Tzarina of Russia.

In 1890, Bismarck was fired by Kaiser Wilhelm II, who then began to undo many of Bismarck's policies. He decided to build up a German navy, antagonizing the United Kingdom. He did not renew German agreements with Russia. In 1894, this led Russia to form a new alliance with Germany's rival France.

In 1904, France and the United Kingdom decided to end centuries of bitter enmity by signing the Entente Cordiale. Three years later, those two nations and Russia entered the Triple Entente. Imperial Russia began to build its army, as did Germany and Austria-Hungary.

== War Breaks Out ==

Austria-Hungary was a patchwork of several nations ruled by the Habsburg family. Several ethnic groups resented rule by the Habsburgs. In June, 1914, the heir to the throne, Archduke Franz Ferdinand, traveled to Sarajevo in Bosnia and Herzegovina. A Serb nationalist named Gavrilo Princip, who hated Habsburg rule, assassinated the Archduke and his wife. This assassination triggered the First World War.
[[Image:Vierbund05h.jpg|thumb|250px|The Central Powers.]]
The Austro-Hungarian government decided to retaliate by crushing Serbian nationalism. They threatened the Serbian government with war. Russia came to the aid of the Serbs. To oppose this alliance, Austria-Hungary called on Germany. Kaiser Wilhelm II said his country would give Austria-Hungary whatever it needed to win the war; in effect, a &quot;blank check.&quot; In addition to these open agreements, any of these countries might have had secret agreements with other states. The result was almost all of Europe at war, with the largest battlefield ever seen before.   

In July, 1914, Austria-Hungary declared war on Serbia. Austria-Hungary, Russia, and Germany began to mobilize their troops. The conflict in Austria-Hungary quickly spread over Europe. In August, Germany declared war on France. The Germans demanded that Belgium allow German troops to pass through the neutral nation. When King Albert of Belgium refused, Germany violated Belgian neutrality and invaded. Belgium appealed to the United Kingdom for aid. The British House of Commons threatened that Great Britain would wage war against Germany unless it withdrew from Belgium. The Germans refused, and the United Kingdom joined the battle. The Central Powers, Germany and Austria-Hungary, were pitted against the Allies, the United Kingdom, Russia, and France.

== The Early Stages ==

German troops entered Belgium on August 4. By August 16, they had begun to enter France. The French Army met the Germans near the French border with Belgium. France lost tens of thousands of men in less than a week, causing the French Army to retreat to Paris. The Germans penetrated deep into France, attempting to win a quick victory.

On August 5, the United States formally declared their neutrality in the war. They also offered to mediate the growing conflict. In the United States, the opinions were divided. Some felt we should aid England, France, and Belgium because they were depicted as victims of barbarous German aggression and atrocities. Others felt we should avoid taking sides.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Don't Know Much About History&quot; by Kenneth C. Davis&lt;/ref&gt;

The Allies won a key battle at Marne, repelling the German offensive. The Germans lost especially due to a disorganized supply line and a weak communications network. The French Army, however, had not completely defeated the Germans. Both sides continually fought each other, to no avail. On the Western Front, Germany and France would continue to fight for more than three years without any decisive victories for either side.

Meanwhile, on the Eastern Front, Germany faced Russia. In the third week of August, Russian troops entered the eastern part of Germany. Germany was at a severe disadvantage because it had to fight on two different fronts, splitting its troops. However, despite Germany's disadvantage, no decisive action occurred for three years.

The United Kingdom used its powerful Royal Navy in the war against Germany. British ships set up naval blockades. The Germans, however, countered with submarines called U-boats. U-boats sank several ships, but could not, during the early stages of the war, seriously challenge the mighty Royal Navy.

The war spread to Asia when Japan declared war on Germany in August, 1914. The Japanese sought control of German colonies in the Pacific. Germany already faced a two-front war, and could not afford to defend its Pacific possessions. 

In October, 1914, the Ottoman Empire entered, allying itself with the Central Powers. The entry of the Ottoman Empire was disastrous to the Allies. The Ottoman Empire controlled the Dardanelles strait, which provided a route between Russia and the Mediterranean. The Ottoman sultan declared holy war- ''jihad''- against the Allies. Muslims in the British Empire and French Empire were thus encouraged to rebel against their Christian rulers.  However, the Allies' concerns were premature. Few Muslims accepted the sultan's proclamation. In fact, some Muslims in the Ottoman Empire supported the Allies so that the Ottoman Empire could be broken up, and the nations they ruled could gain independence.
 
== The Middle Stages ==

Between 1914 and 1917, the war was characterized by millions of deaths leading nowhere. Neither side could gain a decisive advantage on either front. 

In 1915, the Germans began to realize the full potential of Submarines. German Submarines engaged in official unrestricted warfare, engaging and sinking any ship found within the war zone regardless of the flag flown. Germany's justification for this use of force was that there was no certain method to ascertain the ultimate destination of the passengers and cargo carried by the ships in the war zone, and thus they were all taken as attempts at maintaining the anti-German blockade.

In May, 1915, Italy broke the Triple Alliance by becoming an Allied Power. In October, Bulgaria joined the Central Powers. Each side had induced their new partners to join by offering territorial concessions. Italy prevented Austria-Hungary from concentrating its efforts on Russia, while Bulgaria prevented Russia from having connections with other Allied Powers.

In May, 1916, one of the most significant naval battles in World War I occurred. The Royal Navy faced a German fleet during the Battle of Jutland. The Battle proved that the Allied naval force was still superior to that possessed by the Central Powers. The Germans grew even more dependent on U-boats in naval battle.

In August, 1916, Romania joined the Allies. Romania invaded Transylvania, a province of the Austro-Hungarian Empire. But when the Central Powers struck back, they took control of important Romanian wheat fields.

In 1917, the liberal-democratic government of Russia that was lead by Aleksander Kerensky was over thrown by V.I. Lenin. When Lenin took over in Russia one of the things he promised was to change world politics. The terms by which Lenin wanted to changed world politics challenged Woodrow Wilson's and Lenin's Bolshevik-style revolutions spreading world wide was something that western leaders did not want. &lt;ref&gt;A People and A Nation&lt;/ref&gt;

== The United States Declares War ==

Through all of this, America was neutral. It adopted the policy of '''isolationism''' because it felt that the increasing colonialism in Europe did not affect North America. There was a strong pacifist strain in American society, as evidenced by such popular songs as &quot;I Didn't Raise my Boy to be a Soldier,&quot; though at the same time many ethnic groups agitated for involvement. Economic links with the Allies also made neutrality difficult. The British were flooding America with new orders, many of them for arms. The sales were helping America get out of its recession. Although this was good for the economic health of the United States, Germany saw America becoming the Allied arsenal and bank.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;A People and A Nation&quot; the eighth edition&lt;/ref&gt; 

On May 7, 1915, the German navy sunk the Cunard Line passenger ship R.M.S. Lusitania, operating under the flag of Great Britain. Of the 1,959 passengers 1200 died, including one hundred twenty Americans. The ship's quick explosion was due to a hidden cargo of weaponry, a fact the American government denied. Woodrow Wilson's Secretary of State William Jennings Bryan, a pacifist, resigned over Wilson's responsibility for the placement of arms and the consequent inevitability of war. Various American citizens from different ethnic groups put pressure on their government to join the war. However, the US government was calmed by the Germans, who agreed to limit submarine warfare. In 1917, the Germans reinstated unrestricted submarine warfare in order to cripple the British economy by destroying merchant ships, and break the sea blockade of Britain.  

On February 24, 1917, the American ambassador received a telegram in London from the British. It enclosed a British-decoded message, originally sent as a cyphered telegram from the German foreign Secretary, Arthur Zimmerman, to the ambassador in Mexico. Zimmerman proposed that the event of the war with the United States, Germany and Mexico would join in alliance. Germany would fund Mexico's conflict with the US: victory achieved.  Mexico would then be able to gain their lost territories with Arizona. The message was published in American newspapers on March 1st.&lt;ref&gt;''Teaching With Documents: The Zimmermann Telegram.''
http://www.archives.gov/education/lessons/zimmermann/&lt;/ref&gt;

On the evening of April 4, 1917 at 8:30 P.M., President Wilson appeared before a joint session of Congress, asking for the declaration of war to make the world &quot;safe for democracy.&quot; He was hoping for a quick resolution of the conflict. Congress complied on April 6, 1917. The United States was at last at war with Germany.  

The last American war had been the minor Spanish-American War a generation before. A draft of men above the age of eighteen ensued, but many more volunteered. Men wanted to escape their lives and join the military for a job and an adventure. American business and industry became involved as men created more military supplies, and jobs opened for building and designing new materials to be used in battle.

The US had to mobilize its military before it could aid the Allies by sending troops. The cadre of the U.S. Army had experience in mobilizing and moving troops from its Mexican expedition, but the Army needed to expand to over one million men, most of which were untrained. In the same way, the Navy could send a battleship division to assist the British Grand Fleet, but needed to expand. To supply the American forces, new supply lines in France would be needed south of the British and French lines, which meant the U.S. would take over the southern part of the Western Front battle line. The US could and did help the Allies with monetary assistance. Increased taxes and the sale of war bonds allowed the US to raise enormous sums of money. Politicians and celebrities, as well as such movie stars as Charlie Chaplin and Mary Pickford, headed huge patriotic &quot;Bond Rallies,&quot; where people were encouraged to buy bonds.

A government committee to influence the public on the war was formed, the Committee on Public Information or CPI. Among its organs of publicity were the &quot;Four Minute Men,&quot; speakers who talked on pertinent subjects on Vaudeville stages, in movie theaters, and in public assemblies. There was also an organization of private citizens formed to root out German sympathizers, the American Protective League. A hit movie, &quot;The Kaiser, the Beast of Berlin,&quot; was one hit of 1918. To strengthen the United States in this time of stress, families were encouraged to grow Victory gardens, and American women and African Americans were encouraged to go into jobs the servicemen had left. This is the beginning of the Great Migration, when Southern African Americans began moving to Northern cities for jobs.

== Trench Warfare ==

The U.S. commander, General John J. &quot;Black Jack&quot; Pershing, faced immense pressure from the British and French governments to use American forces in small units to reinforce depleted British and French units. This was impossible politically. Pershing insisted to General Foch, the Generalissimo of the Allied armies, that the U.S. Army would fight as a single Army.  Pershing did not want to give his men to other Allied commanders, many of whose strategies he disagreed with. 

The European method of fighting, as it had been since the Boer War, was '''trench warfare'''. An army on the French battleground protected itself from the enemy with zigzag trenches, mines, barbed wire, and a line of rifles and machine guns. Between the enemy lines was a contested area, &quot;no man's land.&quot; An attempt to advance toward the enemy was met with gunfire. These trenches stalemated military advances, as any man who raised his head from the trenches would be shot. At the Battle of the Somme in 1916, for example, Allied troops suffered 600,000 dead and wounded to earn only 125 square miles; the Germans lost 400,000 men. Rain fell in the trenches. As one song put it, a soldier was &quot;Up to your waist in water, up to your eyes in slush.&quot; The damp produced a foot disease known as &quot;trench foot&quot;: if untreated, it could rot flesh from the bone. The close, unsanitary conditions of the front lines encouraged fleas and lice, and typhoid, typhus, and dysentery caused deaths unrelated to gunfire. Worst of all, perhaps, was that sometimes the enemy would gas your trench. There was no way to escape, and sometimes no masks to protect you.

First used by the Germans in April 1915, chlorine gas stimulated overproduction of fluid in the lungs, leading to death by drowning. One British officer tended to troops who had been gassed reported that, “quite 200 men passed through my hands . . . Some died with me, others on the way down . . . I had to argue with many of them as to whether they were dead or not.” Chlorine, mustard, and phosgene gas would continue in use throughout the war, sometimes blistering, sometimes incapacitating, and often killing.

== The End of the War ==

Despite the fact that the Germans could concentrate their efforts in one area, the Central Powers faced grim prospects in 1918. Encouraged by the United States joining the war, several nations joined the Allied Powers. The four Central Powers of Germany, the Austro-Hungarian Empire, the Ottoman Empire, and Bulgaria faced the combined might of the Allied Powers of the United Kingdom and the British Empire, Australia, New Zealand, Canada, South Africa, France, Belgium, Japan, Serbia, Montenegro, San Marino, Italy, Portugal, Romania, the United States, Cuba, Panama, Guatemala, Nicaragua, Honduras, Haiti, Costa Rica, Brazil, Liberia, Siam (Thailand) and China (some of the above nations did not support the war with troops, but did contribute monetarily.) The Germans launched a final, desperate attack on France, but it failed miserably. Due to Allied counterattacks, the Central Powers slowly began to capitulate.

Bulgaria was the first to collapse. A combined force of Italians, Serbs, Greeks, Britons, and Frenchmen attacked Bulgaria through Albania in September, 1918. By the end of September, Bulgaria surrendered, withdrawing its troops from Serbia and Greece, and even allowing the Allies to use Bulgaria in military operations.

British forces, led by T. E. Lawrence (Lawrence of Arabia), together with nationalist Arabs, were successful in the Ottoman Empire. About a month after Bulgaria's surrender, the Ottoman Empire surrendered, permitting Allies to use the Ottoman territory, including the Dardanelles Strait, in military operations.

The Austro-Hungarian Empire also decided to surrender in October. The royal family, the Habsburgs, and the Austro-Hungarian government desperately sought to keep the Empire of diverse nationalities united. Though Austria-Hungary surrendered, it failed to unite its peoples. The once-powerful Austro-Hungarian Empire was destroyed by the end of October, splitting into Austria, Hungary, Czechoslovakia, and Yugoslavia. 

Germany, remaining all alone, also decided to surrender. President Wilson required that Germany accede to the terms of the Fourteen Points, which, among other things, required Germany to return territory acquired by the Treaty of Brest-Litovsk to Russia and the provinces of Alsace and Lorraine to France. Germany found the terms too harsh, while the Allies found them too lenient. But when German Emperor Wilhelm II abdicated the throne, the new German government quickly agreed to Wilson's demands. On November 11, 1918, World War I had come to an end.

The war had been marked by millions and millions of casualties. The deaths were so wide-spread and so vast that people in England talked of &quot;The Lost Generation.&quot; Many died in battle, others died from disease and some even died after when hit with an influenza that spread throughout the whole world in 1918. Destruction of factories and farms, not to mention houses, created economic damage, and was one of the factors creating widespread European starvation during the winter of 1918-1919.&lt;ref&gt;A People and A Nation&lt;/ref&gt;

In contrast, damage was low in America. Although we had also suffered from the flu, the war had not touched our shores. For years afterward, in Germany, France, and even British Commonwealth countries such as Canada, you could see men wearing artificial tin faces to hide battle wounds, men who wheezed because of damage from poison gas, and &quot;war cripples&quot; begging with bowls on the street corner. But our men were by-and-large intact. Our factories had been fully supplied, and our country was on a sounder financial footing because of profit from the War.

At the end of the war, as American soldiers returned from Europe, employment rose. Some of the veterans returned to find themselves without homes or jobs. Overseas, some Black men were organized into a top fighting unit. However, Homeland outrage at the success helped to fuel riots in the notorious &quot;Red Summer&quot; of 1919. Each veteran returned with a certificate promising certain monies for their service; however, the certificate could not be cashed in until 1945.

== American After-Effects Of The War ==

===Suffrage For American Women===

An after-effect of the employment of women during the war was the Nineteenth Amendment, giving them the right to vote. There had been a '''Suffrage''' movement since the nineteenth century. President Wilson and his contemporaries were reluctant, but conceded it as a ''quid pro quo''. After the servicemen had returned, there were still two million more women in the workforce. However, instead of being in factory jobs, they were largely only permitted in &quot;women's work&quot;: the &quot;caring professions&quot; such as nurses or teachers, secretaries or &quot;stenographers,&quot; and waitresses, cooks, or washerwomen. These jobs paid little, and women were often expected to quit the job when they got married.&lt;ref&gt;A People and A Nation Eighth Edition&lt;/ref&gt;

Politically active women still remained excluded from local and national power structures. Their voluntary organizations used tactics that advanced modern pressure-group politics. Issues ranged from birth control, peace, education, Indian Affairs, or opposition to lynching. Women in these associations lobbied legislators to support their causes. At the state level women achieved rights such as the ability to serve on juries. &lt;ref&gt;Mary Beth Norton et al., “A People and A Nation: A History of the United States; The New Era; 1920-1929,” ed. Mary Beth Norton et al. (Boston: Cenage Learning 2009).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Increasing Racial Tension===

Racism was already part of the American landscape, as shown by Jim Crow and lynchings. In 1913, President Woodrow Wilson segregated the Civil Service. However, the war and the Great Migration sparked more oppression and more violence. When White Americans were drawn into the army or defense industries, their jobs were sometimes given to Black workers, for lower wages. The owners considered this a double good, keeping production going while destroying the workingman unions which agitated for higher pay. But while bosses were dependent, for the moment, on Black workers, they did not think they owed anything to these employees. 

An influx of unskilled Black strikebreakers into East St Louis, Illinois, heightened racial tensions in 1917. Rumors that Blacks were arming themselves for an attack on Whites resulted in numerous attacks by White mobs on Black neighborhoods. On July 1, Blacks fired back at a car whose occupants they believed had shot into their homes and mistakenly killed two policemen riding in a car. The next day, a full scale riot erupted which ended only after nine Whites and 39 Blacks had been killed and over three hundred buildings were destroyed. The anxieties of war helped fuel violence: Southern and Midwestern war vigilance committees formed the matrix for a revival of the Ku Klux Klan.

===The Great Experiment===

On August 1, 1917, the Senate voted to send the Eighteenth Amendment to the Constitution to the states for ratification. The vote was bi-partisan, 65 to 20. Section One read, in part, ''After one year from the ratification of this article the manufacture, sale, or transportation of intoxicating liquors [. . . ] is hereby prohibited.'' By 1919, the requisite number of states had ratified the Amendment. The Amendment actually came into effect, under its own terms, one year after ratification.

The Temperance movement had been in effect for more than a hundred years, since the Second Great Revival. The late 19th and early 20th century Anti-Saloon League had been successful in turning the discussion from social discouragement of alcohol to legal prohibition of the substance. It was not simply a creature of Protestant or Catholic Churches, but was &quot;united with Democrats and Republicans, Progressives, Populists, and suffragists, the Ku Klux Klan and the NAACP, the International Workers of the World, and many of America's most powerful industrialists including Henry Ford, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., and Andrew Carnegie – all of whom lent support to the ASL's increasingly effective campaign.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Roots of Prohibition. Web page in association of the Ken Burns documentary ''Prohibition.'' http://www.pbs.org/kenburns/prohibition/roots-of-prohibition/ Retrieved on August 17, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; 

But if '''Prohibition''' was not a simple reaction to World War I, it drew strength from the conflict. The War was funded by an income tax, thus unlocking saloon profits from the interests of the nation.&lt;ref&gt;Roots of Prohibition.&lt;/ref&gt; The Lever Act of 1917, with the aim of feeding soldiers, prohibited grain from being used for alcoholic beverages. There were nationalist concerns, too: the most famous brewers of beer had German last names.

== Treaty of Versailles ==
The Treaty of Versailles was the peace settlement signed after World War One had ended in 1918 and in the shadow of the Russian Revolution and other events in Russia. The treaty was signed at the vast Versailles Palace near Paris - hence its title - between Germany and the Allies. The three most important politicians there were David Lloyd George, Georges Clemenceau and Woodrow Wilson. The Versailles Palace was considered the most appropriate venue simply because of its size - many hundreds of people were involved in the process and the final signing ceremony in the Hall of Mirrors could accommodate hundreds of dignitaries. Many wanted Germany, now led by Friedrich Ebert, smashed - others, like Lloyd George, and were privately more cautious.
On June 28th 1919, the chief Allied Powers of the United Kingdom, the United States, France, Italy, and Japan met with the Central Powers in France to discuss a peace settlement.  There were men, David Lloyd George of Britain, Woodrow Wilson of America, and Clemenceau of France, who were known as the big three. Each of the Allied Powers had distinct interests during the talks. The UK wanted to keep the Royal Navy supreme by dismantling the German Navy, and also wished to end Germany's colonial empire, which might have proved to be a threat to the vast British Empire.David of Britain wanted to be hard on the Germans because if he looked soft people would not vote for him in the future&lt;ref&gt;http://www.historylearningsite.co.uk/treaty_of_versailles.htm&lt;/ref&gt;. Italy wanted the Allies to fulfill the promise of territory given to them at the beginning of the war.  Clemenceau wanted Germany to be brought to its knees so it could never start a war again France wanted Germany to compensate them for the damage caused to France during the War. Japan had already accomplished its interests by taking over German Pacific colonies. President Wilson's main goal for the conference was the creation of the League of Nations; he felt such an organization would be the only way to prevent future wars. Many historians believe that his concentration on the league, forcing him to sacrifice possible kindnesses to Germany, would lead to WWII.

The Treaty of Versailles forced Germany to cede Alsace and Lorraine to France, dismantle its Army and Navy, give up its colonial Empire, pay massive reparations to the Allies, and take full responsibility for causing the war. The conference also led to the creation of the League of Nations. The US Senate, however, did not consent to the Treaty, and the European powers were left to enforce its provisions themselves. This eventually led to violations of the treaty by Germany, which then led to the Second World War. The treaty crippled Weimar Germany and led to great bitterness in Germany. This bitterness eventually led to the rise of fascism and Adolf Hitler.

==Questions For Review==

1. What extended a conflict between Serbians and the Austro-Hungarian Empire into the globe-straddling World War I?

2. How did the advances of technology lead to trench warfare?

3. What in 1914-1915 led to an economic advantage for America from the War? What were the nation's post-war advantages?



==References==
{{reflist}}

{{chapnav|Advancements|Roaring Twenties and Prohibition}}</text>
      <sha1>lhfcgihha4t4rh82bl1wbh4wvu6xg4x</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Organic Chemistry/Templates</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1433</id>
    <revision>
      <id>961162</id>
      <parentid>663894</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-09-07T18:34:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>removing all sub-pages from [[Category:Chemistry]], reformatting book main pages to use {{Subject}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Go To Organic Chemistry Contents .png]]
----
==Review table ==


{| WIDTH=&quot;100%&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;background-color: #FFFFEE; border: solid 1px #FFC92E; padding: 1em;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; |
&lt;center&gt;&lt;H1&gt;Header&lt;H1&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
body goes here
|}

==Note table ==


{| WIDTH=&quot;75%&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;background-color: #FFF7F7; border: solid 1px #FFBDBD; padding: 1em;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; |
==Note==

note contents go here
|}

==Equations==

{| WIDTH=&quot;75%&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;background-color: #F3F3FF; border: solid 1px #D6D6FF; padding: 1em;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; |
==Title==

CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; Br&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; &amp;rarr; No reaction
|}

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>hrd277vynvonnbj7v3yjwse8knrhwic</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Etothex</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>1434</id>
    <revision>
      <id>153550</id>
      <parentid>7385</parentid>
      <timestamp>2003-11-17T01:35:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Etothex</username>
        <id>110</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>update</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Ok, first, I'm a student, so my time is very limited. But I try to check in here as often as possible.

I'm etothex, so what am I interested in? Math+science, but of course I'm not working on those, I'm working on [[US History]]. :)
*Update: Since [[User:Lord Emsworth|Lord Emsworth]] took over [[US History]], I haven't been able to add much to that. Then I started [[German]], though I don't speak it, and [[User:Marshman|Marsh]] is doing a great job there now. :)

So I'll try to do what I can. Hopefully I can do some stuff on math, too, since I'm at the level of having done most of the courses which have texts here and can write for pretty much all of them.</text>
      <sha1>s3zlcmcfbeeapf5elfmelw7cgr6qrv4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Discrete Mathematics/Polynomials</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1435</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2254110</id>
      <parentid>2065180</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-01-18T18:37:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>72.12.155.151</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Properties */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">In this section we look at the '''polynomial''' in some commutative ring with identity. What is interesting is that studying polynomials over some commutative ring with identity acts very much like numbers; the same rules often are obeyed by both.

== Definitions ==
A ''polynomial'' over some commutative ring with identity R is an expression in the form
: &lt;math&gt;\sum_{j=0}^n a_jx^j; \forall a_j \in R, a_n \not = 0&lt;/math&gt;
and n &amp;isin; '''N''', and ''x'' is some indeterminate (''not'' a variable).

== Terminology ==
Given the first nonzero term in the polynomial, i.e. the term ''a''&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;x&lt;sup&gt;n&lt;/sup&gt; above:
* ''a''&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt; is called the ''leading coefficient''
**Given 7''x''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;+2''x''+5 , 7 is the leading coefficient
* the polynomial has ''degree'' ''n''
**7''x''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;+2''x''+5 , 3 is the degree
* if ''a''&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;=1 the polynomial is termed ''monic''
**7''x''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;+2''x''+5 is ''not monic'', whereas ''x''&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; and ''x''&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;-3''x''+2 are ''monic''.

In the above, if ''a''&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;=0 for all i, the polynomial is the ''zero polynomial''.

== Properties ==
Let R[x] be the set of all polynomials of all degrees. Clearly R is closed under addition and multiplication (although in a non-straightforward way), and thus we have that R[x] is itself a commutative ring with identity.

Assume now R is a field F; we do this so we can define some useful actions on polynomials

=== Division algorithm ===
Firstly recall the [[Famous Theorems of Mathematics/Number Theory/Basic Results (Divisibility)|division algorithm for numbers]], that each number can be decomposed into the form
: n = ''qk''+''r''
where ''q'' is the quotient and ''r'' the remainder and r&amp;lt;n.

Now, since we have that F is a field, we can do something similar with the polynomials over F, F[x]. 

If f(''x''), g(''x'') &amp;isin; F[x], with g(''x'') nonzero:
: f(''x'') = q(''x'')g(''x'')+r(''x'')

Again, q(''x'') is known as the quotient polynomial and r(''x'') the remainder polynomial.  Furthermore, we have the degree of r(x) &amp;le; degree of f(x)

We perform divisions by polynomial long division. For brevity we omit the ''x''&lt;sup&gt;k&lt;/sup&gt; terms. Here's an example. We divide ''x''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;+''x''+2 by ''x''-1. First write:
:&lt;math&gt;
\begin{matrix}
  &amp;    &amp;   &amp;   &amp;   &amp;   &amp;   &amp; \\
1 &amp; -1 &amp; | &amp; 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 1 &amp; 2 &amp; \\
\end{matrix}
&lt;/math&gt;
Note we place a 0 in any polynomial not present. Now ''x''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;/''x'' = ''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, so we place a 1 in the second column to get
:&lt;math&gt;
\begin{matrix}
  &amp;    &amp;   &amp;   &amp; 1 &amp;   &amp;   &amp; \\
1 &amp; -1 &amp; | &amp; 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 1 &amp; 2 &amp; \\
\end{matrix}
&lt;/math&gt;
Multiply ''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; throughout the divisor ''x''-1 to get ''x''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;-''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, which is (1 -1), so write this below like the following:
:&lt;math&gt;
\begin{matrix}
  &amp;    &amp;   &amp;   &amp; 1 &amp;   &amp;   &amp; \\
1 &amp; -1 &amp; | &amp; 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 1 &amp; 2 &amp; \\
  &amp;    &amp; | &amp; 1 &amp;-1 &amp;   &amp;   &amp; \\
\end{matrix}
&lt;/math&gt;
Now subtract (1 0) and (1 -1), drop the third 1 to get:
:&lt;math&gt;
\begin{matrix}
  &amp;    &amp;   &amp;   &amp; 1 &amp;   &amp;   &amp; \\
1 &amp; -1 &amp; | &amp; 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 1 &amp; 2 &amp; \\
  &amp;    &amp; | &amp; 1 &amp; -1 &amp;   &amp;   &amp; \\
  &amp;    &amp; | &amp;   &amp; 1&amp; 1 &amp;   &amp; \\
\end{matrix}
&lt;/math&gt;
Now repeat, but divide by ''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; now (since we have subtracted and gotten (1 1) - ''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; + ''x''), and continue in the same fashion, to get:
:&lt;math&gt;
\begin{matrix}
  &amp;    &amp;   &amp;   &amp; 1 &amp; 1 &amp; 2 &amp; \\
1 &amp; -1 &amp; | &amp; 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 1 &amp; 2 &amp; \\
  &amp;    &amp; | &amp; 1 &amp; -1&amp;   &amp;   &amp; \\
  &amp;    &amp; | &amp;   &amp; 1 &amp; 1 &amp;   &amp; \\
  &amp;    &amp; | &amp;   &amp; 1 &amp; -1 &amp;  &amp; \\
  &amp;    &amp; | &amp;   &amp;   &amp; 2 &amp; 2 &amp; \\
  &amp;    &amp; | &amp;   &amp;   &amp; 2 &amp; -2 &amp; \\
  &amp;    &amp; | &amp;   &amp;   &amp;   &amp; 4 &amp; \\
\end{matrix}
&lt;/math&gt;
So the quotient is ''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;+''x''+2, and the remainder is 4.

=== Euclidean algorithm ===
Now we have a working division algorithm for polynomials, the Euclidean algorithm, and hence the gcd of two polynomials can readily be found. 

==== Examples ====
Let's use a similar example above: what is gcd(''x''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;+''x''+2, ''x''-1)?
We've shown already above that
''x''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;+''x''+2=(''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;+''x''+2)(''x''-1) + 4

Proceeding in the normal fashion in the Euclidean algorithm
:''x''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;+''x''+2=(''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;+''x''+2)(''x''-1) + 4
:gcd(''x''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;+''x''+2, ''x''-1) = gcd(''x''-1,4)

and the greatest common divisor of any monomial and an integer is clearly 1, so ''x''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;+''x''+2 and ''x''-1 are coprime.

For a second example, consider gcd(''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;-1,''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;+2''x''+1)

:''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;+2''x''+1=&lt;u&gt;(''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;-1)&lt;/u&gt;*1+&lt;u&gt;2''x''+2&lt;/u&gt;
:''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;-1=&lt;u&gt;(2''x''+2)&lt;/u&gt;*''x''/2+ &lt;u&gt;-(x+1)&lt;/u&gt;
:2''x''+2=&lt;u&gt;-(x+1)&lt;/u&gt;*(-2)+&lt;u&gt;0&lt;/u&gt;

Since factors of -1 make no difference, gcd(''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;-1,''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;+2''x''+1) is -(''x''+1)

=== Irreducibles===
We've seen that ''x''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;+''x''+2 and ''x''-1 are coprime; they have no factors in common. So, are we able to determine &quot;prime&quot; polynomials? Indeed we can - depending on the field that the polynomial lies in. We call these ''irreducibles'' instead of primes.

==== Example ====
Take p(''x'')=''x''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; + ''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; + 2 over '''Z'''&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;. Now we can factor this polynomial if it has a root - from the factor theorem (which also holds for polynomials over any commutative ring with identity) p(k)=0 means k is a root. So, let's look at the following:
Since we're in '''Z'''&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;, we luckily only need to check three values
p(0)=2
p(1)=1
p(2)=2
So we have p(''x'') having no roots - it is irreducible (&quot;prime&quot;).

Now observe an interesting fact. Take the exact same polynomial but instead over '''Z'''&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. The polynomial then is equivalent to 
: ''x''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;+''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;+0
and thus has root p(0)=0 and thus ''is reducible'' but ''over'' '''Z'''&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;

So the reducibility of the polynomial depends on the field it is in.

=== Showing irreducibility===
The general procedure to show a polynomial is irreducible is:
* observe its degree
* identify possible factorizations
* eliminate these factorizations
effectively a proof by cases.

For example, consider the polynomial q(''x'')=''x''&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;+''x''+2 in '''Z'''&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;. To prove it is irreducible, observe that q(''x'') could be factorized in the  following ways:
# linear, irreducible cubic
# linear, linear, irreducible quadratic
# linear, linear, linear, linear
# irreducible quadratic, irreducible quadratic

So we can prove 1, 2, 3 by showing it has no linear factors. 4 is a little more difficult. Let us proceed to show it has no linear factors:
Observe
: q(0)=2
: q(1)=1
: q(2)=2
So q has no linear factors. Now, we need to show that q is not the product of two irreducible quadratics. 

In '''Z'''&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;, we have the quadratics 
:{''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;,''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;+1,''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;+''x'',''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;+''x''+1,''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;+''x''+2,''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;+2,''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;+2''x'',''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;+2''x''+1,''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;+2''x''+2}
We can identify the irreducible quadratics easily by inspection. We then obtain
:{''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;+1, ''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;+''x''+2, ''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;+2''x''+2}

If we can show that neither of these polynomials divide q(''x'')=''x''&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;+''x''+2, we have shown q(''x'') is irreducible. 

Let us try ''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;+1 first.
:&lt;math&gt;\begin{matrix}
  &amp;   &amp;   &amp;   &amp;   &amp;   &amp; 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 2 \\
1 &amp; 0 &amp; 1 &amp; | &amp; 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 1 &amp; 2 \\
  &amp;   &amp;   &amp;   &amp; 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 1 &amp;   &amp;   \\
  &amp;   &amp;   &amp;   &amp;   &amp;   &amp; 2 &amp; 1 &amp; 2 \\
  &amp;   &amp;   &amp;   &amp;   &amp;   &amp; 2 &amp; 0 &amp; 2 \\
  &amp;   &amp;   &amp;   &amp;   &amp;   &amp;   &amp; 1 &amp; 0 \\
\end{matrix}&lt;/math&gt;
We have a remainder, so ''x''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;+1 doesn't divide q. 
On dividing the other polynomials, we all get a remainder. (''Verify this for yourself as practice'').

So q(''x'') is irreducible in '''Z'''&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;.

==Modular arithmetic and polynomials==
Since we have a working polynomial division and factor theorem, and that polynomials appear to mimic the behaviour of the integers - can we reasonably define some sort of modular arithmetic with polynomials?

We can indeed. If we have a field '''Z'''&lt;sub&gt;p&lt;/sub&gt;[''x''] and we wish to find all the remainders (remember, these remainders are polynomials) on dividing by some polynomial m(''x''), we can do so by polynomial long division. 

If m(''x'') is irreducible, then the set of remainders as above forms a field.

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>1at0oir9jz50c5w5ekabi2mugi16dta</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Abstract Algebra/Category theory</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1436</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2677119</id>
      <parentid>2677118</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-06-28T16:48:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>80.61.123.5</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Definitions &amp; Notations */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Category theory''' is the study of ''categories'', which are collections of objects and ''morphisms'' (or arrows), or from one object to another. It generalizes many common notions in Algebra, such as different kinds of products, the notion of kernel, etc. See [[Category Theory]] for additional information.

== Definitions &amp; Notations ==

'''Definition 1:''' A ''category'' &lt;math&gt;\mathcal{C}&lt;/math&gt; consists of

:A collection &lt;math&gt;\mathrm{Obj}(\mathcal{C})&lt;/math&gt; of ''objects''.

:For any &lt;math&gt;X,Y\in\mathrm{Obj}(\mathcal{C})&lt;/math&gt;, a set &lt;math&gt;\mathrm{Hom}(X,Y)&lt;/math&gt; of ''morphisms'' from &lt;math&gt;X&lt;/math&gt; to &lt;math&gt;Y&lt;/math&gt;.

These obey the following axioms:

:There is a notion of ''composition''. If &lt;math&gt;X,Y,Z\in\mathrm{Obj}(\mathcal{C})&lt;/math&gt;, &lt;math&gt;f\in\mathrm{Hom}(X,Y)&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;g\in\mathrm{Hom}(Y,Z)&lt;/math&gt;, then &lt;math&gt;f&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;g&lt;/math&gt; are called a composable pair. Their composition is a morphism &lt;math&gt;g\circ f\in\mathrm{Hom}(X,Z)&lt;/math&gt;.

:Composition is associative. &lt;math&gt;f\circ(g\circ h)=(f\circ g)\circ h&lt;/math&gt; whenever the composition is defined.

:For any object &lt;math&gt;X&lt;/math&gt;, there is an identity morphism &lt;math&gt;\mathrm{id}_X\in\mathrm{Hom}(X,X)&lt;/math&gt; such that if &lt;math&gt;Y,Z&lt;/math&gt; are objects, &lt;math&gt;f\in\mathrm{Hom}(X,Y)&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;g\in \mathrm{Hom}(Z,X)&lt;/math&gt;, then &lt;math&gt;\mathrm{id}_X\circ f=f&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;g\circ\mathrm{id}_X=g&lt;/math&gt;.


Note that we do not demand that &lt;math&gt;\mathrm{Obj}(\mathcal{C})&lt;/math&gt; be a set, if it is in fact a set, then we may call our category a ''small''.


'''Definition 2:''' A morphism &lt;math&gt;f&lt;/math&gt; has associated with it two functions &lt;math&gt;\mathrm{dom}&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\mathrm{cod}&lt;/math&gt; called ''domain'' and ''codomain'' respectively, such that &lt;math&gt;f\in\mathrm{Hom}(X,Y)&lt;/math&gt; if and only if &lt;math&gt;\mathrm{dom}\,f=X&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\mathrm{cod}\,f=Y&lt;/math&gt;. Thus two morphisms &lt;math&gt;f,g&lt;/math&gt; are composable if and only if &lt;math&gt;\mathrm{cod}\,f=\mathrm{dom}\,g&lt;/math&gt;.


'''Remark 3:''' Unless confusion is possible, we will usually not specify which Hom-set a given morphism belongs to. Also, unless several categories are in play, we will usually not write &lt;math&gt;X\in\mathrm{Obj}(\mathcal{C})&lt;/math&gt;, but just &quot;&lt;math&gt;X&lt;/math&gt; is an object&quot;. We may write &lt;math&gt;X\stackrel{f}{\longrightarrow}Y&lt;/math&gt; or &lt;math&gt;f:X\to Y&lt;/math&gt; to implicitly indicate the Hom-set &lt;math&gt;f&lt;/math&gt; belongs to. We may also omit the composition symbol, writing simply &lt;math&gt;gf&lt;/math&gt; for &lt;math&gt;g\circ f&lt;/math&gt;.

== Basic Properties ==

'''Lemma 4:''' Let &lt;math&gt;X&lt;/math&gt; be an object of a category. The the identity morphism for &lt;math&gt;X&lt;/math&gt; is unique.

''Proof'': Assume &lt;math&gt;i&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;j&lt;/math&gt; are identity morphisms for &lt;math&gt;X&lt;/math&gt;. Then &lt;math&gt;i=i\circ j=j&lt;/math&gt;.


'''Example 5:''' We present some of the simplest categories:

:i) &lt;math&gt;0&lt;/math&gt; is the ''empty category'', with no objects and no morphisms.

:ii) &lt;math&gt;1&lt;/math&gt; is the category containging only a single object and its identity morphism. This is the ''trivial category''.

:iii) &lt;math&gt;2&lt;/math&gt; is the category with two objects, &lt;math&gt;X&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;Y&lt;/math&gt;, their identity morphisms, and a single morphism &lt;math&gt;f\in\mathrm{Hom}(X,Y)&lt;/math&gt;.

:iv) We can also have a category like &lt;math&gt;2&lt;/math&gt;, but where we have two morphisms &lt;math&gt;f,g\in\mathrm{Hom}(X,Y)&lt;/math&gt; with &lt;math&gt;f\neq g&lt;/math&gt;. Then &lt;math&gt;f&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;g&lt;/math&gt; are called ''parallel morphisms''.

:v) &lt;math&gt;3&lt;/math&gt; is the category with three objects &lt;math&gt;X,Y,Z&lt;/math&gt;. We have &lt;math&gt;f\in\mathrm{Hom}(X,Y)&lt;/math&gt;, &lt;math&gt;g\in\mathrm{Hom}(Y,Z)&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;h=gf\in\mathrm{Hom}(X,Z)&lt;/math&gt;.


=== Initial and Final Objects ===
'''Definition''' An object &lt;math&gt;I&lt;/math&gt; in a category is called initial or cofinal, if for any object &lt;math&gt;X&lt;/math&gt; there exists a unique morphism &lt;math&gt;f:I\to X&lt;/math&gt;

'''Lemma''' If &lt;math&gt;I&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;J&lt;/math&gt; are initial objects, then they are isomorfic. 

''Proof'': Let &lt;math&gt;i:I\to J&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;j:J\to I&lt;/math&gt; be the unique morphisms between &lt;math&gt; I&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;J&lt;/math&gt;. Given that both &lt;math&gt; I&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;J&lt;/math&gt; have a unique endomorphism because of their initiality, this morphism must be the identity. Therefore &lt;math&gt;i\circ j&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;j\circ i&lt;/math&gt; are the respective identity morphisms, making &lt;math&gt; I&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;J&lt;/math&gt; isomorphic.


'''Definition''' An object &lt;math&gt;F&lt;/math&gt; in a category is called final or coinitial, if for any object &lt;math&gt;X&lt;/math&gt; there exists a unique morphism &lt;math&gt;f:X\to T&lt;/math&gt;

'''Lemma''' If &lt;math&gt;T&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;S&lt;/math&gt; are final objects, then they are isomorphic.

''Proof'' Pass to isomorphicness of initial objects in the cocategory.

== Some examples of categories ==

* &lt;math&gt;\mathbf{Set}&lt;/math&gt;: the category whose objects are sets and whose morphisms are maps between sets.

* &lt;math&gt;\mathbf{FinSet}&lt;/math&gt;: the category whose objects are finite sets and whose morphisms are maps between finite sets.

*The category whose objects are open subsets of &lt;math&gt;\mathbb{\R}^n&lt;/math&gt; and whose morphisms are continuous (differentiable, smooth) maps between them.

*The category whose objects are smooth (differentiable, topological) manifolds and whose morphisms are smooth (differentiable, continuous) maps.

*Let &lt;math&gt;k&lt;/math&gt; be a field.  Then we can define &lt;math&gt;k-\mathbf{Vect}&lt;/math&gt;: the category whose objects are vector spaces over &lt;math&gt;k&lt;/math&gt; and whose morphisms are linear maps between vector spaces over &lt;math&gt;k&lt;/math&gt;.

*&lt;math&gt;\mathbf{Group}&lt;/math&gt;: the category whose objects are groups and whose morphisms are homomorphisms between groups.

In all the examples given thus far, the objects have been sets with the morphisms given by set maps between them.  This is not always the case.  There are some categories where this is not possible, and others where the category doesn't naturally appear in this way.  For example:

*Let &lt;math&gt;\mathcal{G}&lt;/math&gt; be any category.  Then its opposite category &lt;math&gt;\mathcal{G}^{op}&lt;/math&gt; is a category with the same objects, and all the arrows reversed.  More formally, a morphism in &lt;math&gt;\mathcal{G}^{op}&lt;/math&gt; from an object &lt;math&gt;X&lt;/math&gt; to &lt;math&gt;Y&lt;/math&gt; is a morphism from &lt;math&gt;Y&lt;/math&gt; to &lt;math&gt;X&lt;/math&gt; in &lt;math&gt;\mathcal{G}&lt;/math&gt;.

*Let &lt;math&gt;M&lt;/math&gt; be any monoid.  Then we can define a category with a single object, with morphisms from that object to itself given by elements of &lt;math&gt;M&lt;/math&gt; with composition given by multiplication in &lt;math&gt;M&lt;/math&gt;.

*Let &lt;math&gt;G&lt;/math&gt; be any group.  Then we can define a category with a single object, with morphisms from that object to itself given by elements of &lt;math&gt;G&lt;/math&gt; with composition given by multiplication in &lt;math&gt;G&lt;/math&gt;.

*Let &lt;math&gt;\mathcal{C}&lt;/math&gt; be any small category, and let &lt;math&gt;\mathcal{D}&lt;/math&gt; be any category.  Then we can define a category &lt;math&gt;\mathcal{D}^\mathcal{C}&lt;/math&gt; whose objects are functors from &lt;math&gt;\mathcal{C}&lt;/math&gt; to &lt;math&gt;\mathcal{D}&lt;/math&gt; and whose morphisms are natural transformations between the functors from &lt;math&gt;\mathcal{C}&lt;/math&gt; to &lt;math&gt;\mathcal{D}&lt;/math&gt;.

*&lt;math&gt;\mathbf{Cat}&lt;/math&gt;: the category whose objects are small categories and whose morphisms are functors between small categories.

{{Subject|Abstract Algebra}}</text>
      <sha1>s7az5wx50fh6pvg8t6c6hn381hb5ic6</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>US History/Age of Invention and Gilded Age</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1437</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2714880</id>
      <parentid>2712664</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-18T13:50:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pittsburgh Poet</username>
        <id>1449338</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Racism */ Inserting 1898 riot (from 1920s section!) ~~~~</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Racism==
Racism was a major blight of the 1890s', largely unacknowledged by the government in Washington. The freedoms which had been given to the former slaves by Emancipation were taken away in Southern states. Every one of them passed laws which disenfranchised African Americans, including poll taxes and literacy tests. The notorious Jim Crow laws, named for an old minstrel show song, started to take effect even in some states which had not seceded. Blacks were barred from public drinking fountains, bathrooms, and train cars, and directed by sign to &quot;Negro only&quot; facilities which were often dirty and defective. A new set of photographic post cards started going through the mail. These showed the results of public lynchings, largely of African American men. Many of these postcards show large crowds, some including White children, and the hung, mutilated, or burnt body of the victim. These proud shows seldom resulted in any prosecution of the attackers, who sometimes included local public officials.

In 1898 white citizens of Wilmington, North Carolina, resenting African Americans’ involvement in local government and incensed by an editorial in an African American newspaper accusing white women of loose sexual behavior, rioted and killed dozens of blacks. In the fury’s wake, white supremacists overthrew the city government, expelling black and white office holders, and instituted restrictions to prevent blacks from voting.

== Industrialization ==

In the 1870's, the United States became a leading Industrial power. Advances in technology drove American Industrialization, as did access to the immense and untapped resources of the North American continent. Industrialization brought the growth of new American cities such as Chicago, and the arrival of a flood of immigrants from all over Europe to man the factories. The Civil War had transformed the North into one of the most heavily industrialized regions in the world, and during the Gilded Age, businessmen reaped enormous profits from this new economy. Powerful tycoons formed giant trusts to monopolize the production of goods that were in high demand. Andrew Carnegie, for one, built a giant steel empire using vertical integration, a business tactic that increased profits by eliminating middlemen from the production line. Though industrialization caused many long-term positives, it did cause problems in the short-term.&lt;ref&gt;“The Gilded Age &amp; the Progressive Era (1877–1917),” founded on January 15, 2011,  http://www.sparknotes.com/history/american/gildedage/summary.html&lt;/ref&gt;  Rich farmers who could afford new machinery grew even richer, while poorer farmers were forced to move into urban areas as they could not compete in the agricultural sector. 

In 1878 the U.S. had entered a time of success after a long downfall of the mid 1870's. The number of manufacturing plants and number of people doubled. Also, by the 1900's the South had consisted of more than 400 mills. Women and also children worked in bad conditions for long periods of time, mostly about 12-16 hours per day. They only made about a half a dollar per day, which was not much in that day of time.

In 1868 the typewriter was finally perfected by an editor by the name of Christopher Sholes. This invention would bring about a wave of new employment opportunities for women in America. This machine was made popular by several authors but none more so than Mark Twain when he was the first to make and send a typewritten manuscript, which was “The Adventures of Tom Sawyer”, to a printer. Writers loved the typewriter because it could fit so many words onto one page compared to what they could do in handwriting. Along with this new machine also came other inventions such as the telephone and the telegraph. Jobs for women went up substantially. In the 1890s, while the number of women telephone and telegraph operators went up 167 percent, the number of women stenographers and typists went up almost twice as much at 305 percent. 

This huge event, when women were getting more and more jobs, was during the era where white, middle-class women strove to branch out from the home. These women wanted to do more than just wash the clothes, keep the house clean, make all of the meals, and take care of the kids. These women wanted to be equal with men. This movement was referred to as “The Woman Movement.” In this movement women expanded their jobs, creating clubs and crusades, and receiving more rights such as voting. One of the motivations for women to begin this movement was that women believed that they were superior to men and that they should share their greatness with the rest of America instead of keeping it combined to the home. This later became one of their arguments for many things such as voting. Jane Addams argued that “If women have in any sense been responsible for the gentler side of life which softens and blurs some of its harsher conditions, may not they have a duty to perform in our American cities?” Arguments such as these would fuel the fire for women across America to continue to fight for rights and recognition.

Early innovations in the technology of the internal-combustion engine took place in Europe. In 1885 a German engineer, Gottlieb Daimler, built a lightweight engine driven by vaporized gasoline. This development inspired one of America's most visionary manufacturers, Henry Ford. In the 1880's, Ford, an electrical engineer in Detroit's Edison Company, experimented in his spare time using Daimler's engine to power a vehicle. George Selden, a Rochester, New York, lawyer, had already been tinkering with such technology, but Ford applied organizational genius to this invention and spawned a massive industry. &lt;ref&gt;Mary Beth Norton et al., “A People and A Nation: A History of the United States; The Machine Age: 1877-1920,” ed. Mary Beth Norton et al. (Boston: Cenage Learning 2009), 512.&lt;/ref&gt;

As industrialization boomed, more job opportunities than ever opened up.  Factory line jobs were perfect for women and children, mostly because the factory owners could pay the women less.  Despite terrible work conditions, increasing numbers of women began to move from purely domestic workers to factory help.  Although women now had a part in the workforce, sexual discrimination lasted.  Where women had the opportunity to take some low positions, virtually no women were trusted with responsibilities such as managing, or even handling money. The factories also took advantage of immigrants and used them as cheap labor. Immigrants from Ireland, Germany and other European countries were considered second class citizens and this was evident in the work place. Immigrants received extremely low wages and no benefits, it was common for a worker to suffer a serious injury and lose his job if he was unable to perform. 

Workers adjusted to mechanization as best they could. Some people submitted to the demands of the factory, machine, and time clock. Some tried to blend old ways of working into the new system. Others turned to resistance. Individuals challenged the system by ignoring management's orders, skipping work, or quitting. But also, anxiety over the loss of independence and a desire for better wages, hours, and working conditions drew disgruntled workers into unions. &lt;ref&gt; Mary Beth Norton et al., “A People and A Nation: A History of the United States; The Machine Age: 1877-1920,” ed. Mary Beth Norton et al. (Boston: Cenage Learning 2009), 522.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the cities, laborers and employers often clashed over wages, sanitary conditions, working hours, benefits, and several other issues. Laborers organized themselves into unions to negotiate with companies. The companies, however, attempted to shut down labor unions. Some imposed ''yellow dog contracts'', under which an employer could dismiss a worker who participated in union activity. 

In 1886, the American Federation of Labor was formed to fight for laborers in general. The AFL and other union groups employed as many tactics as possible to force employers to accede to their demands. One tactic was the strike. Some strikes escalated into riots, as with the Knights of Labor's strike in 1886 becoming the Haymarket Riots. The Haymarket Riots of 1886 occurred when an unknown person threw a dynamite bomb into a group of police officers. Eight officers were killed in the explosion and gunfight that ensued. As a result, eight anarchists were tried for murder -- four were sentenced to death and one committed suicide. 

The Pullman Strike occurred in 1894, in response to Pullman Company workers' wages being cut following the Panic of 1893, an economic depression which was caused in part by excessive railroad speculation.  Approximately 3,000 workers began the strike on May 11.  Many of the workers were members of the American Railway Union, and although the strike began without authorization from union officials (known as a &quot;wildcat strike&quot;), the ARU eventually supported the strike by launching a nationwide boycott of Pullman cars on June 26.  Within four days, approximately 125,000 ARU members had quit their jobs rather than switch Pullman cars.  On July 6, President Cleveland sent Army troops to break up the strike, ostensibly because it prevented delivery of mail and was considered a threat to public safety.

The companies sometimes retaliated against strikes by suing the unions. Congress had passed the Sherman Antitrust Act to prevent trusts, or corporations that held stock in several different companies, from obstructing the activities of competitors. Though the Sherman Act was intended to target trusts, the companies sued the union under it, claiming that unions obstructed interstate commerce.

During the machine age, there were a number of strikes that took place due to the demands from factories and time clocks. It was hard for individuals to adjust to that system, and as a result, they challenged the system by ignoring management's orders, skipping work, or quitting. The desire and longing for better wages let to anxiety and frustration. Like farming and mining, industry was massive in size and changed not only the nature of the work but the person doing it. Soon, all of these disgruntled individuals formed specialized groups into unions. The different jobs varied in not only skill, but other things as well that were non-related to worker conflict; race, sex, etc. These jobs were such as working on/in railroads, steel factories, and automobiles.  The outcome for many working in labor during the Gilded Age led to horrific labor violence. Industrialists and workers literally fought over control of the workplace. Many suffered due to the strikes and riots and it inevitably led to deaths, loss of jobs, and often continuous violence. For most American workers, the Machine age had varying results. At times there was no job stability and when costs of living would increase drastically there were even more problems.
&lt;ref&gt; Mary Beth Norton et al., “A People and A Nation: A History of the United States; The Machine Age: 1877-1920,” ed. Mary Beth Norton et al. (Boston: Cenage Learning 2009), &lt;/ref&gt;

Prices, and consequently wages, fell sharply in about the 1870s and stayed that way all the way through the 1970s. The prices of necessities in the late 1800s were: 4 pounds butter for $1.60, 1 bag of flour $1.80, a quart of milk for $0.56, vegetables $0.50, 2 bushels of coal $1.36, soap, starch, pepper, salt, vinegar, etc. $1.00, rent for $4.00 a week, and more. The average total of a person's wages was $16.00. By the time that person bought the necessities such as food and soap and rent, most, if not all, of the money would be gone.

== Urbanization ==
With industrialization came urbanization.  The increasing factory businesses created many more job opportunities in the cities.  Soon people began to flock from rural, farm areas, to large cities.  Minorities and immigrants added to these numbers.  Factory jobs were the only jobs some immigrants could get, and as more came to the cities to work, the larger the urbanization process became. In 1870 there were only two American cities with a population of more than 500,000, but by 1900 there were six, and three of these, New York, Chicago, and Philadelphia had over one million inhabitants. Roughly 40 percent of Americans lived in cities and the number was climbing. These large populations in the cities caused the crime rates to go up, and disease was rapidly spreading. Not only did urbanization cause cities to grow in population, it also caused cities to grow in building size. Skyscrapers were being built in the cities and the idea of mass transit had started.
With these mass transits being built it allowed people to commute to work from further distances. Suburbs were beginning to form and higher class families began to move to them to get out of the over crowded city but still gave them the ability to go into the city to work each day.
City living was for the lower class the upper class had enough money to get away from all of the pollution and the city stench. This still holds true today in larger cities a lot of the nicer homes are located further out from the center of the city. For example, in the city of Chicago, you will find a lot of the nicer homes away from the city, and more towards the suburbs. In this case, this is because there are a lot of violence in the inner city. Therefore, people try to live more further out from the city in order to stay away from the violence.

== Agriculture ==
In the late 1880s and early 1900s, a typical farm would be about 100 acres. Farmers could only plow with the aid of a horse or a mule. Later on the internal combustion engine was used to create tractors. Unlike Southern cotton plantations, most farms raised a variety of foodstuffs, breeding cows, pigs and chickens, and growing turnips, potatoes, carrots, wheat, and corn. They were often self-sufficient. Farmers made their bread from their own wheat, and killed the runt pig for their own table. 

While industry generally increased in importance, farmers struggled due to debt and falling prices. In the 1880s there were crop failures. Steamships and railways brought in wheat from abroad, lowering American farm prices still more. Economic transformation created industrial prosperity and new lifestyles, but in states still dominated by farming these changes also had a widespread negative effect. Crop diversification and a greater focus on cotton as a cash crop did not give many farmers any potential to get ahead.&lt;ref&gt;The Encyclopaedia of Arkansas History and Culture; “Post-Reconstruction through the Gilded Age, 1875 through 1900,” last modified on 12/17/2010, http://encyclopediaofarkansas.net/encyclopedia/entry-detail.aspx?entryID=402&lt;/ref&gt;

American farmers helped to create regulation of the railroads. When domestic farmers needed to transport their crops, they also had to rely on the railroad system. But railroads often charged outrageous prices. Farmers, small merchants, and reform politicians started to demand rate regulation. In 1877, in Munn v. Illinois, the Supreme Court upheld the principle of state regulation, declaring that grain warehouses owned by railroads acted in the public interest and therefore must submit to regulation for the common good. By 1880 fourteen states had established commissions to limit freight and storage charges of state-chartered lines. 

Between 1860 and 1905 the number of farms tripled from two million to six million. In 1905 the number of people living on farms grew to thirty-one million. The value of farms went from eight billion in 1860 to thirty billion in 1906. Then as now, wheat was a major crop, creating such common food as bread, a major source of both starch and protein for poorer people.

Farmers had to rise early, often at four or five in the morning. Cows and goats had to be milked twice a day, at morning and at evening. Chickens' eggs were gathered every morning, cleaned, and packed in cases. Because they laid eggs, female chickens or pullets were more important than the male chickens or roosters. Because of this, and to keep roosters from attacking each other, poultry farmers would have only one rooster with several hens. 

After the Civil War, more prosperous farmers gained more machinery to plant and harvest their crops. In 1879 the centrifugal cream separator was patented. In 1885, chicken raising became a lot more profitable due to the invention of the mechanized incubator. Complicated horse-drawn mechanical combines and threshers were used about this time. With the aid of machines a farmer could harvest about 135 acres of wheat; without them, he or she could only harvest about 7.5 acres of wheat in the same amount of time. The Montgomery Ward &amp; Company mail order catalogue of 1895 listed various grist mills, seeders and planters, a hay pitcher, a hay tedder, and nearly a full page of mechanical churns.&lt;ref&gt;Montgomery Ward &amp; Co. Catalogue and Buyers' Guide No. 57, Spring And Summer 1895. Unabridged reprint. Dover: NY, 1969.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Imperialism ==

As time progressed, Industrialization caused American businessmen to seek new international markets in which to sell their goods. In addition, the increasing influence of Social Darwinism led to the belief that the United States had the inherent responsibility to bring concepts like industry, democracy and Christianity to less scientifically developed, &quot;savage&quot; societies. The combination of these attitudes, along with other factors, led the United States toward Imperialism, the practice of of a nation increasing its sphere of influence. 

=== The Orient ===

In the Orient, Russia, Japan, the United Kingdom, France, and Germany all exercised influence.{{Citation needed}} US Secretary of State John Hay endorsed the ''Open Door Policy'', under which all foreign powers would exercise equal economic power in the Orient. The US thus protected its interests in China and maintained a balance of power there.

Chinese nationalists known as the &quot;Righteous Fists of Harmony&quot;, or &quot;Boxers&quot; in English, who resented foreign influence, promoted hatred of non-Chinese as well as Chinese Christians. In June 1900 in Beijing, Boxer fighters threatened foreigners and forced them to seek refuge in the Legation Quarter. In response, the initially hesitant Empress Dowager Cixi, urged by the conservatives of the Imperial Court, supported the Boxers and declared war on foreign powers. Diplomats, foreign civilians, soldiers, and Chinese Christians in the Legation Quarter were under siege by the Imperial Army of China and the Boxers for 55 days. The siege was raised when the Eight-Nation Alliance brought 20,000 armed troops to China, defeated the Imperial Army, and captured Beijing. The Boxer Protocol of 7 September 1901 specified an indemnity of 67 million pounds (450 million taels of silver), more than the government's annual tax revenue, to be paid over a course of thirty-nine years to the eight nations involved.&lt;ref&gt;Spence, ''In Search of Modern China'', pp. 230-235; Keith Schoppa, ''Revolution and Its Past'', pp. 118-123.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Spanish Territories ===

By 1825 Spain had acknowledged the independence of its possessions in the present-day United States. The only remnants of the Spanish Empire in the Western Hemisphere were Cuba, Puerto Rico, across the Pacific in the Philippines Islands, as well as the Carolina, Marshall, and Mariana Islands (including Guam) in Micronesia.

In 1898, the American battleship USS ''Maine'' was destroyed by an explosion in the Cuban Harbor of Havana. Although later investigations proved that an internal problem was to blame, at the time it was thought that Spanish forces had sunk it. On the advice of Assistant Secretary of the Navy Theodore Roosevelt, President William McKinley asked Congress to declare war on April 11, 1898. Senator Henry M. Teller of Colorado added an amendment to the proposed U.S. declaration of war against Spain on April 19, which proclaimed that the United States would not establish permanent control over Cuba. The amendment stated that the United States &quot;hereby disclaims any disposition of intention to exercise sovereignty, jurisdiction, or control over said island except for pacification thereof, and asserts its determination, when that is accomplished, to leave the government and control of the island to its people.&quot; 

At that time Spanish troops stationed on the island included 150,000 regulars and 40,000 irregulars and volunteers while rebels inside Cuba numbered as many as 50,000. Total U.S. army strength at the time totalled 26,000, requiring the passage of the Mobilization Act of April 22 that allowed for an army of at first 125,000 volunteers (later increased to 200,000) and a regular army of 65,000. 

On April 25, 1898 Congress declared war on Spain. The United States Navy won two decisive naval battles, destroying the Spanish Pacific Fleet at Manila in the Philippines and the Atlantic fleet at Santiago, Cuba. The U.S. then landed forces in Cuba, which fought the tropical climate and associated diseases as well as the Spanish forces. In the Battle of San Juan Hill (actually Kettle Hill), Lt. Colonel Theodore Roosevelt earned a reputation as a military hero by leading the attack on entrenched Spanish positions. The regiment to which Roosevelt belonged, the First U.S. Volunteers, was recruited throughout the United States and known as the ''Rough Riders'' because of the large number of cowboys to volunteer. The 10th Cavalry, a regiment of black soldiers, supported the Rough Riders in the attack.  Joseph Wheeler, a Confederate general of the Civil War, commanded U.S. forces in Cuba. Two of Robert E. Lee's nephews were also U.S. generals. The war ended eight months later with the signing of the Treaty of Paris on December 10, 1898. As a result Spain lost its control over the remains of its overseas empire. The treaty allowed the United States to purchase the Philippines Islands from Spain for $20 million. The war had cost the United States $250 million and 3,000 lives, of whom 90% had perished from infectious diseases. True to the letter of the Teller Amendment, American forces left Cuba in 1902.

The Spanish-American War was seen domestically as a sign of increasing national unity. 

=== Hawaii ===

The Kingdom of Hawaii was established in 1795 with the subjugation of the smaller independent chiefdoms of Oʻahu, Maui, Molokaʻi, Lānaʻi, Kauaʻi and Niʻihau by the chiefdom of Hawaiʻi (or the &quot;Big Island&quot;), ruled by the dynasty of King Kamehameha the Great. In 1887 the Honolulu Rifle Company, a paramilitary force also known as the Honolulu Rifles, deposed the Hawaiian monarchy, forcing the King to sign a new constitution at gunpoint. Bayonets were fixed to their guns, which led to the term Bayonet Constitution, referring to King David Kalākaua's resignation and the establishment of new voting rights. No voting rights were extended to Asiatics and the requirements for voting rights included land ownership, making the Bayonet Constitution one of the most controversial documents in history.

Native-born Hawaiian Sanford B. Dole, serving as a friend of both Hawaiian royalty and the elite immigrant community, advocated the westernization of Hawaiian government and culture. Dole was a lawyer and jurist in the Hawaiian Islands as a kingdom, protectorate, republic and territory. King Kalākaua appointed Dole a justice of the Supreme Court of the Kingdom of Hawaii on December 28, 1887, and to a commission to revise judiciary laws on January 24, 1888. After Kalākaua's death, his sister Queen Liliʻuokalani appointed him to her Privy Council on August 31, 1891. 

On January 17, 1893, the last monarch of the Kingdom of Hawaiʻi, Queen Lili'uokalani, was deposed in a coup d'état led largely by American citizens who were opposed to Lili'uokalani's attempt to establish a new Constitution. Dole was named president of the Provisional Government of Hawaii that was formed after the coup, and was recognized within 48 hours by all nations with diplomatic ties to the Kingdom of Hawaii, with the exception of the United Kingdom.
The Americans in Hawaii asked the US to annex the islands, but President Benjamin Harrison's annexation treaty was stalled in the Senate by Democrats until a Democratic President, Stephen Grover Cleveland, took office. With Grover Cleveland's election as President of the United States, the Provisional Government's hopes of annexation were derailed. In fact, Cleveland tried to directly help reinstate the monarchy, after an investigation led by James Henderson Blount. The Blount Report of July 17, 1893, commissioned by President Cleveland, concluded that the Committee of Safety conspired with U.S. ambassador John L. Stevens to land the United States Marine Corps, to forcibly remove Queen Liliʻuokalani from power, and declare a Provisional Government of Hawaii consisting of members from the Committee of Safety. Although unable to restore Lili'uokalani to her former position, Cleveland withdrew the treaty. 

The Territory of Hawaii or Hawaii Territory existed as a United States organized incorporated territory from July 7, 1898, until August 21, 1959, when its territory, with the exception of Johnston Atoll, was admitted to the Union as the fiftieth U.S. state, the State of Hawaii.

== President Grover Cleveland ==
In 1884, as the presidential campaign season approached, the Republican party chose former Speaker of the House James G. Blane as its candidate, with John Logan as the vice presidential candidate. Against them the Democrats ran New York governor Stephen Grover Cleveland for a presidential candidate and vice presidential candidate Thomas A. Hendricks.Cleveland and Hendricks won&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Super Review; United States History&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; with the combined support of Democrats and reform Republicans, the &quot;Mugwumps.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Biography of Cleveland at http://www.whitehouse.gov/about/presidents/grovercleveland24, noted on August 3, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;  

Grover Cleveland was the only Democrat elected to the presidency during the era of Republican political domination that lasted from 1860 to 1912. In fact, he won the popular vote for president three times, in 1884, 1888, and 1892. His last election in 1892 defeated Republican president Benjamin Harrison. He was thus the only president to serve two non-consecutive terms, and is the only individual to be counted twice in the numbering of the presidents. (In that last election, Cleveland's vice president was Adlai E. Stevenson; Harrison's Vice President was Whitelaw Reid.) Cleveland's conservative economic stand in favor of the gold standard brought him the support of various business interests. The democrats then won control of both houses of Congress.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Super Review; United States History&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}


{{chapnav|Reconstruction|Progressive Era}}</text>
      <sha1>ngfbme7e5qj323s9m4lv04s521zjtek</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>XHTML/Authors</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1438</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1636850</id>
      <parentid>551125</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-09-30T13:34:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sigma 7</username>
        <id>164862</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">Below are the authors of the XHTML tutorial:
*[[User:LittleDan|LittleDan]]
*The WikiBooks community

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>646xawecpug1a29haam64w8oyes7r40</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>US History/Progressive Era</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1441</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2682803</id>
      <parentid>2624610</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-07-19T22:57:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pittsburgh Poet</username>
        <id>1449338</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Movies, an aspect of American life &amp; culture ~~~~</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">== Progressivism ==

Industrialization led to the rise of big businesses at the expense of the worker. Factory laborers faced long hours, low wages, and unsanitary conditions. The large corporations protected themselves by allying with political parties. The parties, in turn, were controlled by party leaders, rather than by the members.  The Progressive movement was an effort to cure American of all its problems.  These problems included the idea of slavery, reconstruction from the American Civil War, and women’s rights.  Progressivism rejected the church as the main source of change throughout the country.  The main goals of Progressivism were to remove corrupt political machines from office and get more common people in the political process. Progressivism was not so much an organized movement as it was a general spirit of reform embraced by Americans with diverse goals and backgrounds during the early twentieth century  &lt;ref name=&quot;test&quot;&gt;http://www.u-s-history.com/pages/h1061.html&lt;/ref&gt; Progressivism was the belief that you could make the world a better place with a certain method to employ and achieve the goal.  Federal level, state, public and private. Local public safety, less corruption, efficiency, regulation, reform, specialization, social justice and social control of knowledge.  By activating this, brings equality for men and women no matter, gender or race; or social background.

== Local Reform ==

At the urban level, Progressivism mainly affected municipal government. The system whereby the city is governed by a powerful mayor and a council was replaced by the ''council-manager'' or the ''commission'' system. Under the council-manager system, the council would pass laws, while the manager would do no more than ensure their execution. The manager was essentially a weak mayor. Under the commission system, the executive would be composed of people who each controlled one area of government. The commission was essentially a multi-member, rather than single-member, executive.

At the state level, several electoral reforms were made. Firstly, the secret ballot was introduced. Prior to the secret ballot, the ballots were colored papers printed by the political parties. Due to the lack of secrecy, bribing or blackmailing voters became common. It was to prevent businessmen or politicians from thus coercing voters that the secret ballot was introduced.  Also, reforms were made to give voters more say in government.  The initiative allowed voters to propose new laws.  The referendum allowed certain laws (for example tax increases) to be approved by the voters first. Finally, the recall, allowed the voters to remove public officials for wrongdoing while in office.

In addition, Progressives sought to combat the power of party leaders over which candidates would be nominated.  The ''direct primary'' was instituted, under which the voters cast ballots to nominate candidates. Before the primary was introduced, the party leaders or party faithful were the only ones allowed to nominate candidates. The South pioneered some political reforms; &quot;the direct primarily originated in North Carolina; the city commission plan arose in Galveston  Texas; and the city manager plan began in Stanton-Virgina. Progressive governors introduced business regulation, educational expansion,and other reforms that duplicated actions taken by northern counterparts.

== Labor Reforms ==

Progressive movement also attempted to give more power over legislation to the general populace. Three practices - the ''referendum'', the ''initiative'', and the ''recall'' - were created. The referendum allowed the voters to vote on a bill at an election before it took force as law. The initiative permitted the voters to petition and force the legislature to vote on a certain bill. Finally, the recall permitted voters to remove elected officials from office in the middle of the term. State laws were formed to improve labor conditions. Many states enacted factory inspection laws, and by 1916 nearly two-thirds of  the states required compensation for the victims in industrial accidents.

In 1901, Jane Addams founded the Juvenile Protective Association, a non-profit agency dedicated to protecting children from abuse. In 1903, Mary Harris Jones organized the Children's Crusade, a march of child workers from Kensington, Pennsylvania to the home of President Theodore Roosevelt in Oyster Bay, New York, bringing national attention to the issue of child labor.  In 1909, President Roosevelt hosted the first White House Conference on Children, which continued to be held every decade through the 1970s.  In 1912, the United States Children's Bureau was created in order to investigate &quot;all matters pertaining to the welfare of children and child life among all classes of our people.&quot;  At the instigation of middle class coalitions, many states enacted factory inspection laws, and by 1916 two-thirds of the states required compensation for victims of industrial accidents. An alliance of labor and humanitarian groups induced some legislatures to grant aid to mothers with dependent children. Under pressure from the National Child Labor to Committee, nearly every state set a minimum age for employment and limited hours that employers could make children work.Families that needed extra income evaded child labor restrictions by falsifying their children's ages to employers.

States also regulated female labor by setting maximum work hours, especially when an accident at the Triangle Shirtwaist Factory resulted in the deaths of more than 100 women. The Supreme Court ruled in favor of regulated work hours for women in &quot;Muller v. Oregon&quot;. Finally, some minimum wage provisions were introduced (for men and women).

The Industrial Workers of the World (IWW) was founded in Chicago in 1905 at a convention of anarchist and socialist union members who were opposed to the policies of the American Federation of Labor (AFL).  Unlike the AFL, which was a group composed of separate unions for each different trade (craft unionism), the IWW supported the concept of industrial unionism, in which all workers in a given industry are organized in one union, regardless of each worker's particular trade.  They promoted the idea of &quot;One Big Union&quot; in the hopes that one large, centralized body would be better equipped to deal with similarly-large capitalist enterprises.

1881 The Great influx of Russian and Polish Jews. They formed an objectionable part of the population, because they couldn't speak English, lived closely crowded, and dirty.  Penniless and unfamiliar with industrial conditions.  They were apart of industrial, intellectual, and civil life.  Their willingness to work 18 hours obnoxiously was crazy compared to Americans who worked (part-time).  &quot;It's not the condition that the immigrant comes from that determines he's usefulness;But the power one shows to rise above the condition.&quot;

== President Theodore Roosevelt ==

At the national level, Progressivism centered on defeating the power of large businesses. President Theodore Roosevelt, who succeeded to the Presidency when President McKinley was assassinated in 1901, helped the Progressive movement greatly.

In early 1902, anthracite coal miners struck.  Their salaries had not been raised in over two decades.  Furthermore, they were paid with ''scrips''. Scrips were essentially coupons for goods from pricey company stores.

The president of the Reading Railroad, George F. Baer, said that the miners had erred by distrusting the owners. He declared that the mine owners were &quot;Christian men of property to whom God has given control of the property rights of the country,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.populist.com/03.03.castagnera.html Workers Don't Suffer by James O. Castagnera]&lt;/ref&gt; who could be trusted more than union leaders.

The owners and the miners refused to negotiate with each other. As autumn approached, many feared that the coal strike would cripple the economy. President Roosevelt intervened by asking the owners and miners to submit to arbitration. The miners accepted, but the owners refused Roosevelt's suggestion. Roosevelt then threatened to use the Army to take over the mines. The owners finally acquiesced; the strike was settled in 1903. Roosevelt's policy triumphed in 1904 when the Supreme Court, convinced by the government's arguments, created by J.P Morgan and his business allies. Roosevelt choose however , not to attack others trust, such as u.s steel another of Morgan's creations. Prosecution of northern securities began reportedly collared Roosevelt and offered &quot;if we have done anything wrong, send your man to my man and we can fix it up&quot;.  Roosevelt continued his Progressive actions when he revived the Sherman Antitrust Act. The Act sought to prevent companies from combining into trusts and gaining monopolies. A ''trust'' is formed when many companies loosely join together under a common board of directors to gain total control of an entire market so that prices can be raised without the threat of competitors. This total control of a market and subsequent price raising is a ''monopoly''. However, until Roosevelt's administration, the Act was rarely enforced. Roosevelt also enforced the Hepburn Act, which allowed the Interstate Commerce Commission to regulate railroads. The railroads had allied themselves with large businesses, charging higher rates to those business' competitors. Thus, the large businesses would gain even more power. The Hepburn Act prevented railroads from granting reduced rates to businesses. Roosevelt also championed the cause of conservation. He set aside large amounts of land as part of the national park system.

=== Conflicts with other Imperialist Nations ===

Imperialism was yet a common theme in the relations between nations in this era. It should be noted that although the US annexed Hawaii, Japan also had interests in the island and an aggressive foreign policy; Japan had already seized Taiwan from China in 1885 and would annex Korea in 1905. Imperial Germany was another aggressive power. The U.S. and Germany had conflicts over who would control Samoa, in the Pacific, as well as nearly faced a naval war with Germany in 1902 over German plans to seize the customs revenues of Venezuela. 

However, under the administration of President Theodore Roosevelt, the United States became more open in asserting international power. In 1905, Russia and Japan went to war over control of Korea and China. The Japanese won naval victories over two Russian fleets, in the Battles of the Yellow Sea and Tsushima. President Roosevelt offered to negotiate peace between the two nations, and in Portsmouth, New Hampshire, a peace treaty was signed.

To demonstrate the ability of the United States to project power around the world (unlike Russia), Roosevelt ordered a fleet of U.S. men-o'war to sail around the world. The fleet left the east coast of the U.S. in 1908 and returned in 1909, visiting ports in Europe, Australia, and Japan.

== President William Howard Taft == 
William Howard Taft, tried to win over the Filipino people by reforming education, transportation, and health care.  New railroads, bridges, and telegraph lines strengthened the economy.  A public school system was set up, and new health care policies virtually eliminated severe diseases such as cholera and smallpox.  These reforms slowly reduced Filipino hostility.
Roosevelt, following the tradition upheld by every reelected president before him, decided not to run for reelection for a third term in 1908. Republicans nominated William Howard Taft as their candidate for the 1908 election, and he easily defeated the Democratic candidate William Jennings Bryan, supporting the continuation of Roosevelt's progressive programs. Taft was somewhat more cautious and quiet than Roosevelt, and therefore, had less public attention.

Although Taft was less of an attention grabber than Roosevelt, he went far beyond what Roosevelt ever did. Taft used the Sherman Antitrust Act, a law passed in 1890 that made trusts and monopolies illegal, and they had to sue many large and economically damaging corporations. For comparison, Taft won more antitrust lawsuits in four years than Roosevelt won in seven.

Taft also pushed for the passing of the Sixteenth Amendment, which gave the federal government the right to tax citizens' incomes. The purpose of the amendment was to supply the government with cash to replace the revenue generated from tariffs, which progressives hoped that Taft would lower. Taft failed in getting a lower tariff, and in addition, he failed to fight for conservation and environmentalism, and actually weakened some conservation policies to favor business. When Roosevelt came back from an expedition to Africa in 1910, he was disappointed in Taft, and vigorously campaigned for progressive republicans in the congressional elections of 1910.

Because of Roosevelt's enormous popularity, he ran for reelection to a third term in 1912, but he failed to win the nomination for the Republican Party because Taft had connections to influential people in the party. Roosevelt and his supporters broke off from the Republicans and formed the Progressive Party, which later came to be known as the Bull Moose party after Roosevelt declared that he felt &quot;as strong as a bull moose!&quot; The split in the party came to hurt the two candidates, and Democratic candidate Woodrow Wilson gathered a 42 percent plurality of the popular votes and 435 out of 531 electoral votes.
===On the Supreme Court===
Taft would later become a member of the Supreme Court, making him the only former President to do so. In 1921, when Chief Justice Edward Douglass White died, President Warren G. Harding nominated Taft to take his place, thereby fulfilling Taft's lifelong ambition to become Chief Justice of the United States. Very little opposition existed to the nomination, and the Senate approved him 60-4 in a secret session, but the roll call of the vote has never been made public. He readily took up the position, serving until 1930. As such, he became the only President to serve as Chief Justice, and thus is also the only former President to swear in subsequent Presidents, giving the oath of office to both Calvin Coolidge (in 1925) and Herbert Hoover (in 1929). He remains the only person to have led both the Executive and Judicial branches of the United States government. He considered his time as Chief Justice to be the highest point of his career: he allegedly once remarked, &quot;I don't remember that I ever was President.&quot;

== President Woodrow Wilson ==

Although Woodrow Wilson was a Democrat, he still pushed for progressive reforms. One of the first successes of his administration was the lowering of tariffs, which he accomplished in 1913. Wilson believed that increased foreign competition would spur U.S. based manufacturers to lower prices and improve their goods. That same year, Wilson passed the Federal Reserve Act, which created twelve regional banks that would be run by a central board in the capitol. This system gave the government more control over banking activities.   A few years later he wrote: 
&quot;I am a most unhappy man. I have unwittingly ruined my country. A great industrial nation is controlled by its system of credit. Our system of credit is concentrated. The growth of the nation, therefore, and all our activities are in the hands of a few men. We have come to be one of the worst ruled, one of the most completely controlled and dominated Governments in the civilized world no longer a Government by free opinion, no longer a Government by conviction and the vote of the majority, but a Government by the opinion and duress of a small group of dominant men. -Woodrow  Wilson&quot;  

Wilson also pushed for governmental control over business. In 1914, a Democratic-controlled Congress established the Federal Trade Commission (FTC) to investigate companies that participated in suspected unfair and illegal trade practices. Wilson also supported the Clayton Antitrust Act, which joined the Sherman Antitrust Act as one the government's tools to fight trusts the same year.

By the end of Wilson's First term, progressives had won many victories. The entire movement lost steam, though, as Americans became much more interested in international affairs, especially the war that had broken out in Europe in 1914.

==The Supreme Court and Labor==

'''Upset workers had succeeded in lobbying Congress''' to pass legislation that improved work conditions.  However, the Supreme Court of the United States somewhat limited the range of these acts.  In [[wikipedia:Holden v. Hardy|Holden v. Hardy]] (1896), the Supreme Court ruled that miners' hours must be short because long hours made the job too dangerous.  However, in [[wikipedia:Lochner v. New York|Lochner v. New York]] laws ruled that bakery workers did not have a job dangerous enough to put restrictions on the free sale of labor.  Putting aside this decision, in 1908, the decision in [[wikipedia:Muller v. Oregon|Muller v. Oregon]] said that women's'' health must be protected &quot;to preserve the strength and vigor of the race.&quot;  This did,'' clearly, protect women's health, but it also locked them into menial jobs.


{{chapnav|Age of Invention and Gilded Age|Advancements}}


=Controlling Prostitution=
Moral outrage erupted when muckraking journalists charged that international gangs were kidnapping young women and forcing them into prostitution, a practice called white slavery. Accusations were exaggerated, but they alarmed some moralists who falsely perceived a link between immigration and prostitution. Although some women voluntarily entered &quot;the profession&quot; because it offered income and independence from their male counterparts, some women had very little option to a life where they had little if any amenities and many were forced into this profession and lifestyle. Reformers nonetheless believed they could attack prostitution by punishing both those who promoted it and those who practiced it. In 1910 Congress passed the White Slave Traffic Act (Mann Act), prohibiting interstate and international transportation of a woman for immoral purposes. By 1915 nearly all states outlawed brothels and solicitation of sex. Such laws ostensibly protected young women from exploitation, but in reality they failed to address the more serious problem of sexual violence that women suffered at the hands of family members, presumed friends, and employers.
&lt;ref&gt;Mary Beth Norton et al., “A People and A Nation: A History of the United States; The Progressive Era;1895-1920,” ed. Mary Beth Norton et al. (Boston: Cenage Learning 2009).&lt;/ref&gt;
  
==Football and the Formation of the NCAA==
By the turn of the century American football was already in the process of becoming a large national sport.  Originally formed and played at universities as an intercollegiate sport, it was seen as only for the upper class.  The size of the field depended on what the players agreed with, but it was almost always over 100 yards.  Once a player started a game, the player could not leave unless he/she became injured.  &lt;ref&gt;http://www.1890sweekend.com/19th-century-football.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Very soon the sport began to gain spectators, and with spectators came controversy.  With over 15 deaths in 1905 alone, many saw a need for change in the sport.  However, others liked the violence and would watch because of this.  President Roosevelt formed a group to reconstruct the rules of football and make it less violent.  Standard rules would not be made and used until 1894.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.1890sweekend.com/19th-century-football.htm&lt;/ref&gt;  The group was originally named the Intercollegiate Athletic Association, and in 1910 it was renamed to the National College Athletic Association.

== William Taft ==
William Howard Taft (September 15, 1857 – March 8, 1930) was the 27th President of the United States and later the tenth Chief Justice of the United States. He is the only person to have served in both offices. Born in 1857 in Cincinnati, Ohio, into the powerful Taft family, &quot;Big Bill&quot; graduated from Yale College Phi Beta Kappa in 1878, and from Cincinnati Law School in 1880. He worked in a number of local nondescript legal positions until he was tapped to serve on the Ohio Supreme Court in 1887. In 1890, Taft was appointed Solicitor General of the United States and in 1891 a judge on the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit. When Theodore Roosevelt decided not to run for office in the election of 1908, that opened the doors for William H. Taft. Taft decided to run for president and was chosen as the Republican nominee with James S. Sherman as his vice president. They ran against the democratic nominees, William Jennings Bryan and John Kern, and socialists nominees, Eugene V. Debs. Taft won the election by over a million votes and the Republicans retained control of both houses of Congress. During Taft's presidency, he had a few objectives. His two primary goals in 1909 were to continue Roosevelt's trust-busting policy and to reconcile the old guard conservatives and young progressive reformers in the Republican Party. &lt;ref&gt;&quot;Super Review; United States History&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Movies==

At the beginning of this era of silent movies, the vast majority of films came in from overseas, mainly from Great Britain and France. Thomas Edison had a monopoly on the American film industry. From his New Jersey film studio, The Black Maria, came any number of movies, showing boxers, lovers, comic interludes, and what we would call documentaries, though they were often staged. In 1903, Edison's studio released several movies, including &quot;The Life of An American Fireman&quot; and &quot;The Great Train Robbery,&quot; two of the first great American fictional movies. In France, in contrast, George Melies created elaborate pageants, often hand-tinted, and Ferdinand Zecca produced and directed a Life of Jesus Christ which was shown as a special event, in legitimate theaters across America.

In 1905, the first Nickelodeon was opened in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. Before this movies had either been seen in &quot;peep show&quot; arrangements or onstage as part of Vaudeville shows. A viewer could now pay a nickel to see a variety of movies projected on a screen in an atmosphere which was respectable, if not quite fireproof. (Early movie houses had a lackadasical attitude toward the fire code, and the nitrate base of film stock was very flammable.) 

Movies had became a money-making proposal. Increased demand begged for increased supply. A competitor to Edison Studios had arisen in 1893, and in 1903 Biograph Studios started making fictional movies, films often more complex than Edison's. In 1910 it moved as far away as possible from Edison and its lawsuits, to Hollywood, California. Other studios followed, and the American film industry began to gain momentum. 

==References==
{{reflist}}</text>
      <sha1>dleggvkbv4zhqxnj37pe8wq8r4xj627</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>US History/Roaring Twenties and Prohibition</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1444</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2717806</id>
      <parentid>2717805</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-24T20:00:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>76.79.199.130</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Technology */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{TOC right}}

==Technology==

Although there were innumerable technical innovations, the vast changes in American life about this time had two major technical bases, mass production (the assembly line), and mass testing.

In the vast steel factories and in cloth mills individuals had to move together with the machines. Any mistake could lead to an accident, perhaps a fatal one. Henry Ford's assembly line worked on the same principle, but went much further. A car went from station to station, from worker to worker. Each worker had one function -- tightening nuts, adding a component -- and only that function, as if he were himself a machine. His main interest was in doing those motions which would do his job and do it most efficiently. (In this respect the system drew upon work efficiency experts such as Frederick Winslow Taylor and the Gilbreths.) 

The advantages to this extreme systemization were fundamental. As with the cloth factories, the product was produced extremely quickly at all hours of the day or night. Very little training was needed for those jobs. The results of this system were extremely long-lasting. The Model T was seen as a durable car, and &quot;the tin Lizzie&quot; retained public affection even when it was superseded by cars with self-starters. The cars were also affordable, with results as seen below. Henry Ford raised his wages regularly, urging that the men who made the cars also buy them. 

A small demerit was that these new cars were extremely ugly. The Stanley Steamer had been sleek, with lines like what would later be called &quot;streamlining.&quot; Dusenbergs and Pierce-Arrows had a variety of hues and such extras as bud vases. Ford famously said that his purchasers could have any color they wanted, &quot;so long as it is black.&quot; As people became more prosperous, they could shop for colored paint jobs and detailing for their luxury cars. However, creating affordable and beautiful goods was a movement away from Ford's version of the market.

More importantly, working on the assembly line wore on the workers. Standing in one place and squinting, working with a few muscles for hours a day (or night) could be very fatiguing. Human beings weren't made to live like that. When there were a limited set of priorities for working, workers could be easily replaced, just like machines. Not every boss of the assembly line paid as well as Ford. 

Mass testing was a requirement for the assembly line -- a bad part made a bad product. But it had actually begun as a human policy, in the requirements for the late 19th Century census. It was accelerated in the desire to find sound men for the First World War. Psychologists were employed to create intelligence tests to weed out unfit soldiers. Their weapons had to be carefully inspected, for when shoddy goods reached the front lines, the result could be a disaster.

In the post-war world, Big Business began developing research and development departments. Before a change was implemented, there had to be a prototype, and the effects on the public had to be carefully measured. Economics became a matter, not merely of becoming prosperous, but of selling to the largest number possible. (The term ''mass market'' originated in the 1920s.)

== Politics and Government ==
A new sympathy toward business was shown in the election of Republican Warren G. Harding as President in 1920. His administration helped streamline federal spending with the Budgeting and Accounting Act of 1921, supported anti-lynching legislation (which was, however, rejected by Congress), and approved bills assisting farm cooperatives and liberalizing farm credit. The Harding administration was also known for its scandals. He had had an affair with the wife of an Ohio merchant: the resulting daughter was never officially acknowledged. He also appointed some cronies, who saw office as an invitation to personal gain. One of those men was Charles Forbes, head of the Veterans Bureau. He was convicted of fraud and bribery in connection with government contracts, and was sent to prison. Another crony, Attorney General Harry Daugherty, was involved with an illegal liquor scheme. He only escaped prosecution by refusing to testify against himself. The most notorious of these scandals was the revelation that the Secretary of the Inferior, Albert Fall, accepted bribes to lease government property to private oil companies in the Teapot Dome Scandal. The popular conservation legislation created by Harding's predecessors, presidents Teddy Roosevelt, William Taft, and Woodrow Wilson, had set aside naval petroleum reserves in Wyoming and California. Three naval oil fields, Elk Hills and Buena Vista Hills in California and Teapot Dome in Wyoming, were tracts of public land meant as emergency underground supplies to be used by the navy only when regular oil supplies diminished. Teapot Dome received its name because of a rock resembling a teapot above the oil-bearing land. Politicians and private oil interests had opposed the restrictions placed on the oil fields, claiming that the reserves were unnecessary, and that the American oil companies could provide for the U.S. Navy. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.montgomerycollege.edu/Departments/hpolscrv/jzeck.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mary Beth Norton et al., “A People and A Nation: A History of the United States; The New Era:1920-1929,” ed. Mary Beth Norton et al. (Boston: Cenage Learning 2009).&lt;/ref&gt;

Civil and criminal suits concerning Teapot Dome lasted through the 1920s. In 1927 the Supreme Court finally ruled that the oil leases had been corruptly obtained and invalidated the Elk Hills lease in February of that year and the Teapot lease in October of the same year. The navy regained control of  Teapot Dome and Elk Hills reserves. Albert Fall was found guilty of bribery in 1929, fined $100,000, and sentenced to one year in prison. Harry Sinclair refused to cooperate with the government investigators, was charged with contempt, and received a short sentence for jury tampering. Edward Doheny was acquitted in 1930 of attempts to bribe Fall.

The Teapot Dome scandal was a victory for neither political party. It became a major issue in the presidential election of 1924, but neither party could claim full credit for divulging the wrongdoing. It became the first true evidence of government corruption in America. The scandal revealed the problem of natural resource scarcity and the need to protect for the future against emergency depletion of resources. Vice President Calvin Coolidge, who assumed the presidency after Harding's death, handled the problem very systematically, and his administration avoided any damage to its reputation.

== The Automobile ==

In the 1920s, the United States automobile industry began an extraordinary period of growth by means of the assembly line in manufacturing. Cars began to alter the American lifestyle. In 1929, one out of every five Americans had a car. They began using their own automobiles instead of the street cars. Cars also replaced horses. This made the streets cleaner, because there wasn't as much horse manure. (However, this was replaced by other, more subtle forms of pollution. In the 1920s gasoline companies started adding lead to their fuel to increase engine efficiency.) 

The idea of &quot;homes on wheels&quot; was also created around this time. Americans were packing up food and camping equipment in order to get away from home. &lt;ref&gt;&quot;A People and A Nation&quot; the eighth edition&lt;/ref&gt; By the 1920s most automobiles gained cloth or steel roofs, offering a private space for courtship and sex. Women gained from the automobile revolution. Women who learned to drive achieved new-found independence, taking touring trips with female friends, conquering muddy roads, and making repairs when their vehicles broke down. Prosperous African-Americans for the first time obtained a limited freedom from local discrimination. A family could drive around and past &quot;closed&quot; White communities, and to beaches, camps, and other holiday destinations. However, the family car would have to carry its own food, drink and gas, and not stop before it reached its destination. (The largest-scale pamphlet for &quot;safe&quot; businesses African Americans could use, the Negro Motorist Green Book, was only published beginning in 1936.) The car was the ultimate social equalizer.  

There were 108 automobile manufacturers in 1923 and colors allowed owners to express personal tastes. An abundance of fuel fed these cars. In 1920, the United States produced sixty-five percent of the World's oil. Road construction was extensive. The first timed stop-and-go traffic light was in 1924.&lt;ref&gt;Mary Beth Norton et al., “A People and A Nation: A History of the United States; The New Era; 1920-1929,” ed. Mary Beth Norton et al. (Boston: Cenage Learning 2009).&lt;/ref&gt;  
 
Industries related to the manufacturing and use of automobiles also grew; petroleum, steel, and glass were in high demand, leading to growth and profitability in related sectors. State governments began to build roads and highways in rural areas. Gasoline stations were installed across the country, evidence of the sudden and continued growth of the petroleum industry. Automobile dealers introduced the installment plan, a financing concept that was adopted in many other parts of business. Thus, the automobile industry's growth had repercussions throughout the nation. With a perfected design of Henry Ford's assembly line automobiles began to be more affordable for the common US citizens all over the country. A lot of men were hired to work in car factories.

==Health and Life Expectancy==
The relation between food and health was long known. For example, since the 18th century it has been known how to fight scurvy, and mariners have taken fruit on long voyages. Yet the fact that scurvy is caused by lack of vitamin c was only discovered in 1932.  

From 1915 to the end of the &quot;Roaring Twenties&quot;, most vitamins were discovered. Food regulation began to ensure a safer food supply. People began to have access to and the possibility of choosing more and better food, due to faster transport and refrigeration. Technical information was also more easily transmitted, and by 1930 nutritionists began to emphasize to the public the need for consumption of certain foods, and their constituent vitamins and minerals, on a daily basis. Food companies began marketing their products, on how their products contain certain amounts of your daily vitamins and therefore healthy. However, the advertisements sometimes contained unusual ideas about nutrition. For example, some candy bars were advertised by their &quot;food value.&quot; And Welch's Grape Juice marketed their product as containing nutrients and vitamins, but failed to inform the reader of the large amount of sugar also included.  

But the emphasis on nutrition and good hygiene made many Americans healthier. This was the decade when penicillin and insulin were discovered. During this time the life expectancy at birth in the United States also increased from fifty-four to sixty percent, and infant mortality rate decreased by one-third. However this was not the case for nonwhites: the mortality rate for nonwhite children was about fifty to one hundred times that of whites during this era. (Rickets among the poor and among rural African Americans was seen as the result of poor genetics, &quot;bad blood.&quot; The American fad for Eugenics and the sterilization movement also grew in this era.) Accident fatalities also increased by roughly 150 percent, for the car was becoming faster and more common.

==Elderly Americans and Retirement==

With the increase of the elderly, the interest in pensions and other forms of old age assistance began to be put into effect. Although European countries had established state-supported pension systems, in 1923 the Chamber of Commerce in Pennsylvania. Stated that old-age assistance was “un-American &amp; socialistic”. During the &quot;Roaring Twenties&quot; one third of Americans sixty-five and older depended financially on someone else. Resistance to pension plans broke at the state level during the 1920’s. Isaac Max Rubinow and Abraham Epstein were the first to try and persuade associations such as labor unions, and legislators to endorse old-age assistance. It wasn’t until 1933 that almost every state minimal support to needy elderly.

==Social Values==

During this time period, new social values emerged. It became difficult to determine what was socially acceptable, as youth frequently took up smoking, drinking, and a new openness about sex. They were being influenced less by their parents and more by their peers and schoolmates. Schools in the cities geared up for mass education, segregating children with others of their same age. The rite of passage, dating without adult supervision, became more commonplace among these youth.

The Flapper was the female symbol of this change, as the raccoon-coated Sheik was the symbol among young men. The dresses then in fashion de-emphasized the bodice, with a flat abdomen, the so-called &quot;boyish figure.&quot; Flappers did not have the long hair of their mothers and grandmothers, but short, &quot;bobbed&quot; styles. They drank and smoked like men, knew all the latest dances and songs, and openly swore and talked of sex. It is unknown how frequent the Flapper really was. Bobbed hair was fashionable among women and girls, but there was never a standard measurement of this or any related trend. Movie actresses such as Louise Brooks and Clara Bow were shown drinking on the big screen. 

During the War, servicemen became used to lectures on preventing venereal disease, and thus became more comfortable with the idea of contraception. Condoms started to be made with latex instead of animal tissues, and became a product which could be mass-produced on an assembly line. Birth control became more available, and more respectable. With a greater chance for babies to survive infancy, and with the ability to time when they came into the world, the number of children in a middle-class family began to go from four or five to two or three. Unfortunately, this overlapped with the eugenics movement.

As the middle class became more mobile, it was much less able to rely on the advice of grandparents and family, and &quot;expert&quot; child care advice became popular. This advice was different from that commonly used nowadays. John B. Watson, who published his book in 1928, advised against picking up infants, holding them when they cried, or cossetting them or showing them too much affection.

== Radio ==

Radio had been used for ship-to-shore communication since the Titanic sent out a Morse code S-O-S. It was used by both sides during the First World War. Wilson considered nationalizing the medium, as Great Britain was later to nationalize the British Broadcasting Corporation, but corporate outcry overruled him.&lt;ref&gt;Jones, Gerard. ''Honey, I'm Home! Sitcoms: Selling the American Dream.'' First edition. New York: Grove Weidenfeld (Grove Press), 1992. p. 7&lt;/ref&gt; By 1920, thousands of curious machines produced screeches for the hobbyist, with an occasional, distant snatch of voices or music. In 1920 the assembly line did its work, producing an RCA &quot;Cat's Whisker&quot; receiver for under four dollars. In October of that year Westinghouse created the first radio station, KDKA. In November it provided running coverage of the Presidential elections.&lt;ref&gt;Jones, Gerard. p. 8&lt;/ref&gt; 

By the mid-'20s programming ran from morning till night. In 1924, the first radio network, the National Broadcasting Company, began operations between New York and Boston. In 1927, the Columbia Broadcasting System began. The Federal Radio Commission was set up in 1926, and organized in the Radio Act of 1927. Advertisers sponsored programs: one popular music program was The A &amp; P Gypsies, giving coast-to-coast coverage to the A &amp; P grocery stores. The news and entertainment provided was vetted by the sponsor, and anything which would offend sponsors was forbidden. But within those lines much was permitted. One could occasionally find high culture (though the Metropolitan Opera broadcasts only began at the end of 1931), but the aim was to air songs in the middle range of culture; &quot;The Lost Chord,&quot; or &quot;Drink to Me Only With Thine Eyes.&quot; They played popular music, but not much jazz: Paul Whiteman, the so-called &quot;King of Jazz,&quot; was not. (There were exceptions to this rule; some high-powered radio stations in Mexico poured out jazz, &quot;Black music,&quot; and ads for toxic patent medicines.) Much of the country's culture was not covered, though the Grand Ole Opry began its broadcasts in 1925. But as electrification expanded, the market for radio grew, and some stations experimented. A pair of white comedians, Freeman Gosden and Charles Correll, created a comic, sentimental serial drama, ''Amos 'n' Andy''. At a time when lynchings of African Americans occurred as far North as Ohio, this was a comedy about two stupid African Americans who mispronounced their words. But it also created sympathy for them. &quot;One episode ended with Amos and Andy in desperate need of a typewriter; nearly two thousand typewriters were immediately sent in by listeners.&quot; Yet &quot; ''Amos 'n' Andy'' 's popularity was no doubt due to excitement over this new national experience. For the first time Americans could all enjoy the same event at the same moment.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Jones, Gerard, p. 19&lt;/ref&gt;

== Movies ==

In the 1920s movies also grew into a popular recreation. By 1922, about 40 million people were going to the movies each week; that number jumped to about 100 million people by the end of the decade. Movie stars such as Douglas Fairbanks, Mary Pickford, and Charlie Chaplin became known around the world.  

Eight studios dominated the industry, consolidating and integrating all aspects of a film's development. By 1929, the film-making firms that were to rule and monopolize Hollywood for the next half-century were the giants or the majors, sometimes dubbed The Big Five. The Big Five studios were Warner Bros., RKO, Paramount, Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer, and Fox Film Corporation. They produced more than 90 percent of the fiction films in America and distributed their films both nationally and internationally. Each studio somewhat differentiated its products from other studios.

A movie house was only allowed to play the products of one studio. Thus, for example, the New York Paramount only played cartoons, newsreels, and fiction films created by Paramount Studios. Each division of the studio was contracted to make so many films each year. If a movie house wanted to get the films of a Gloria Swanson or a Rudolf Valentino, it had to accept a given number of films by a less-liked star. This &quot;block booking&quot; ensured that certain actors got publicity and kept the screens under the thumb of the studio. However, in return each theater was ensured of a weekly change of movies, with the full backing of the studio. In addition to the projectionist, ushers and candy and cigarette sellers, the Paramount Theater employed a grand musician to accompany the silent film on one of the largest theater organs ever created. Its halls were ornamented by hand-painted murals. The top-line theaters were called &quot;movie palaces.&quot;

The most popular studio movies often used sweepingly romantic stories set in exotic lands: Argentina in 1921's ''The Four Horsemen of the Apocalypse'', Persia in 1924's ''The Thief of Bagdad''. The 1925 movie ''Ben Hur'' was shot partially in Italy and partially on huge purpose-built sets in California. It had 42 cameras shooting the still-famous chariot race. Among the famous or yet-to-be-famous figures swelling the scenes as extras were the Barrymore brothers, Lillian and Dorothy Gish, comedian Harold Lloyd, William Randolph Hearst's love Marion Davies, and studio head Samuel Goldwyn. The religious sequences used two-tone technicolor. It was the most expensive film yet made.&lt;ref&gt;IMDB trivia page for ''Ben Hur: A Tale of the Christ'' (1925), http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0016641/trivia?ref_=tt_ql_2 Retrieved on August 15, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Prohibition ==

Although total alcohol consumption halved, some people blatantly disregarded Prohibition. There were loopholes in the Volstead Act, the twenty-two page law which defined Prohibition. Churches could use wine in their ceremonies, and alcohol drunk as a medicine (this was still part of the medical profession) was still allowed. The amount of &quot;religious&quot; and &quot;medicinal&quot; wine suddenly increased. 

Some illegal alcohol was imported from Canada, Cuba, and Mexico, which never made alcohol illegal. Some was home-made American. ''Bootleggers'' were found in many places throughout the country, from backwoods stills (illegal alcohol production had continued after the Whiskey Rebellion) to urban &quot;bathtub gin.&quot; The Volstead Act had said that personal consumption of alcohol in one's own home was legal, though it had prohibited public gatherings to drink. The occasional secret saloons called ''speakeasies'' which sprang up in cities were therefore illegal. These required money, and a new criminal underworld rose to fund them and profit from them. Some of this money funded pay-offs to police to stop enforcement of Prohibition. Gangs prospered in this hidden economy. Many jobs came out of Prohibition, both from alcohol and from the &quot;front&quot; legitimate businesses set up to launder speakeasy money. However, these jobs came with great risks, from blackmail and graft to outright violence. Some commentators felt that Prohibition was too harsh and that it made a criminal out of the average American man or woman, who would have bought alcohol legally if it were available.

==Gangs and Violence==

There was obviously a huge market for what in the 1920's was an illegal commodity. Gangsters provided this commodity. Major gangsters in this period included Charles &quot;Lucky&quot; Luciano, Mayer Lansky, and &quot;Dutch&quot; Schultz. Perhaps the most notorious was Chicago's Al Capone. Capone smuggled alcohol all over the Midwest. He was also responsible for drug smuggling and murder, and bribed both police and important politicians.  

Despite the deference given Capone by &quot;bought&quot; figures, he had enemies from other Chicago gangs. He rode in an armor-plated limousine, always accompanied by armed bodyguards. Violence was a daily occurrence in Chicago. 227 gangsters were killed in the space of four years. On St Valentine's Day, 1929, seven members of the O'Banion gang were shot dead by gangsters dressed as police officers.

In 1931, the government got around the corrupted regular police by arresting Capone for tax evasion, rather than for his many violent offenses. He got eleven years in jail, and left prison with his health broken.

==Bonnie and Clyde==
Bonnie and Clyde were also a famous pair of murderers and thieves in the 1920's during the prohibition era with their gang.  Clyde Champion Barrow and his companion, Bonnie Parker, were shot to death by officers in an ambush near Sailes, Bienville Parish, Louisiana on May 23, 1934, after one of the most colorful and spectacular manhunts the nation had seen up to that time. Barrow was suspected of numerous killings and was wanted for murder, robbery, and state charges of kidnapping.

The Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI), then called the Bureau of Investigation, became interested in Barrow and his paramour late in December 1932 through a singular bit of evidence. A Ford automobile, which had been stolen in Pawhuska, Oklahoma, was found abandoned near Jackson, Michigan in September of that year. At Pawhuska, it was learned another Ford car had been abandoned there which had been stolen in Illinois. A search of this car revealed it had been occupied by a man and a woman, indicated by abandoned articles therein. In this car was found a prescription bottle, which led special agents to a drug store in Nacogdoches, Texas, where investigation disclosed the woman for whom the prescription had been filled was Clyde Barrow's aunt.

Further investigation revealed that the woman who obtained the prescription had been visited recently by Clyde Barrow, Bonnie Parker, and Clyde's brother, L. C. Barrow. It also was learned that these three were driving a Ford car, identified as the one stolen in Illinois. It was further shown that L. C. Barrow had secured the empty prescription bottle from a son of the woman who had originally obtained it.

On May 20, 1933, the United States Commissioner at Dallas, Texas, issued a warrant against Clyde Barrow and Bonnie Parker, charging them with the interstate transportation, from Dallas, to Oklahoma, of the automobile stolen in Illinois. The FBI then started its hunt for this elusive pair.

==Scopes Trial==
In 1925 a teacher by the name of John Thomas Scopes was tried and convicted for teaching evolution in his public school classroom as an explanation to where man originated from, rather than Adam and Eve that is what the law at the time stated. This was a major dispute and caught the attention of many popular government officials such as William Jennings Bryan, who spoke on behalf of the prosecution. Although the modernists defending Scopes lost, they still were proud to have been able to put into question the illogical thinking behind the law enforcing the belief that no one can teach alternative methods for the origin of man, they were also proud hat this trial and conviction didn’t affect the expansion of fundamentalist ideals. The Southern Baptist Convention a protestant group was even one of the fastest growing denominations after the trial showing that it may have even gave popularity to the religious denomination. The beliefs of these groups resulted in the creation of an independent subculture within the U.S. and with their own schools, radio programs, and missionary societies. 

==Religious Revivalism==
With economic insecurity religion, faith became more popular through out the United States. The new revivalism condemned the new socially acceptable movies, dress styles, and dancing. Many religious organizations supported the prohibition movement, thinking drinking was a sinful unclean act.  

== Jazz == 
[[File:Louis Armstrong restored.jpg|thumb|right|Louis Armstrong]]
Jazz is an American musical art form which originated around the beginning of the 20th century in African American communities in the Southern United States from a confluence of African and European music traditions.  It was originated from African Americans.  The “hometown” of jazz is considered to be in New Orleans.  Early jazz musicians would called New Orleans their home even if they have never been there.  Jazz music started the whole jazz revolution from poetry, fashion, and industry.  Jazz spread through America very quickly&lt;ref&gt;http://www.d.umn.edu/cla/faculty/tbacig/studproj/is3099/jazzcult/20sjazz/upriver.html&lt;/ref&gt;.  The style's West African pedigree is evident in its use of blue notes, call-and-response, improvisation, polyrhythms, syncopation, and the swung note of ragtime. Beginning in 1922, Gennett Records began recording jazz groups performing in Chicago. The first group they recorded was the New Orleans Rhythm Kings, followed in 1923 by King Oliver’s Creole Jazz Band with Louis Armstrong. Another indie company in Chicago, Paramount Records, was competing with Gennett and Okeh for jazz talent.&lt;ref&gt;Some very famous jazz musicians include King Oliver, Louis Armstrong, Kid Ory, and Duke Ellington.  &lt;/ref&gt;

==Business Overseas==
After the war, many manufacturing companies faced hard times as they attempted to convert from wartime production of weapons and planes to what they had traditionally produced before the war. However, the pro-business policies put in place first by Harding, then Coolidge, allowed business to flourish. While business did well at home -- the raising of tariff rates from 27% (under the Underwood-Simmons Tariff) to 41% certainly helped in this regard -- many major companies did quite well overseas. Just as these companies had started to do before the war, they set up shop in a variety of countries based around the resources located there. Meat packers like Gustavus Swift went to Argentina; fruit growers went to Costa Rica, Honduras, and Guatemala; sugar plantation owners went to Cuba; rubber plantation owners to the Philippines, Sumatra, and Malaya; copper corporations to Chile; and oil companies to Mexico and Venezuela (which remains today a great source for oil). Steamships and telegraphs made for easy transport and communication.

==Organized Labor==
The Organized labor force during the 1920's suffered a great deal. During this time the country was fearful of the spread of communism in America, because of this widespread fear public opinion was against any worker who attempted to disrupt the order of the working class. The public was so anti-labor union that in 1922 the Harding administration was able to get a court injunction to destroy a railroad workers strike that was about 400,000 strong. Also in 1922 the government took part in putting to an end a nationwide miners strike that consisted of about 650,000 miners. The federal and state level of government had no toleration for strikes, and allowed for businesses to sue the unions for any damages done during a strike.  

== Major Cases and Laws ==
Several laws came into play during the 1920's because of things such as prohibition, voting rights, and women's rights. Our country has progressed a great deal since the 1920's, and of the laws that come into play dealt with what our country was going through at the time. On January 16, 1920 it was illegal to sell, make, or transport any type of alcoholic beverage with more than one and a half percent of alcohol. Also, the 19th Amendment was another monumental law passed during the 1920's.

Sacco-Vanzetti Trial, Leopold and Loeb, Scopes &quot;Monkey&quot; Trial, and Black Sox Trail  were all significant court cases during the 1920's. Each of these courts cases were unique and monumental in their own right, and set a precedent for the years to come especially in court looking back on these cases.  The 1920's was a very monumental time for the law and courts of the United States.

==Minority Women==
During the 1920's there were almost double the amount of nonwhite women than white in the workforce. Women, especially minorities, who held factory jobs held the least desirable and lowest paying jobs in factories. African American women mostly held domestic jobs such as cooking, cleaning, and laundry. There were many openings for educated African women in the social work, teaching, and nursing fields during this time, however they faced much discrimination. The Economic needs of the family brought thousands of minority women into having to work. Mexican women, mainly in the Southwest worked as domestic servants, operatives in garment factories, and as agricultural laborers. This was looked down upon because the Mexican culture traditionally was against women labor. Next to African women, Japanese women were the most likely to hold low paying jobs in the work force, they worked in the lowest paying jobs; they faced very strong racial biases and discrimination on a regular basis as well.

== African-Americans and the Ku Klux Klan ==
Southern states segregated public facilities (like buses). In half the South fewer than 10% of the blacks were allowed to vote. 

Another factor that ignited more hatred towards blacks was the Great Migration.  During the 1920s blacks began to move from rural areas in the South to large cities.  More than 1.5 million African Americans migrated to cities such as New York, Chicago, Detroit and the black population even grew in Western cities such as Los Angeles and San Diego.  Although most of the migrants were poor and lived in cheap urban housing, some were able to afford better housing in white neighborhoods.  This migration of African Americans created unrest within the white community as blacks began to buy and rent property in white neighborhoods.  The Great Migration ended in even more discrimination and violence against blacks.

To fight the increasing discrimination many black movement groups began to form.  The Universal Negro Improvement Association (UNIA) was formed Marcus Garvey, an immigrant from Jamaica living in Harlem.  Garvey preached a message of equality that many, including other black leaders, considered radical.  Garvey helped start companies and news papers directed towards the African American community.  Along the way he gained a substantial amount of followers around the US, especially in urban cities.  Some estimate that Garvey and the UNIA had over half a million followers.  Although Garvey created more racial unity and inspired the black community to stand up, many disagreed with his radical approach.  W.E.B. Du Bois, a prominent black figure, considered Garvey’s approach extreme and believed that it would only backfire in the movement for equal rights.  With the help up of other Black leaders, Du Bois petitioned the attorney general and had Garvey deported back to Jamaica.  Garvey is still considered by many as a successful figure in the fight for civil rights.  His message to fight back for equality lived on long after he was deported and he was one of the early inspirations of 1960’s civil rights leader Malcolm X.     

In New York City's Harlem and in half a dozen other Northern cities, a Black culture began to form as a result of the relative economic and educational advantages given through the Great Migration. Black businesses, legal and political systems, and arts societies flourished. Here &quot;the talented tenth&quot; had its own institutions. Poets Langston Hughes, Claude McKay, and Jean Toomer, and musicians such as Chick Webb and Duke Ellington were published in mainstream magazines and heard in White-frequented (though sometimes segregated) clubs. '''The Harlem Renaissance''' talked of the contemporary Black community's hopes and fears. 

The Ku Klux Klan flourished 1921-26 with a membership of millions of Protestants. Not only was the Ku Klux Klan big in the south, but it now fanned out to places such as Oregon and Indiana. Indiana's governor and an Oregon mayor were both members of the KKK. Along with the men in this group, there were now women too. The women consisted of about a half-million members. Klansmen argued for a purified nation and denounced African-Americans, Catholics, and Jews, as well as bootleggers and adulterers. They gained new support from nativists who had detested the mass immigration to the Northeast in the early 1900s.

The return of the Klan caused a split in the Democratic Party which allowed Calvin Coolidge, a conservative Republican, to take office in 1924.

In most cities, the only way blacks could relieve the pressure of crowding that resulted from increasing migration was to expand residential borders into surrounding previously white neighborhoods, a process that often resulted in harassment and attacked by white residents whose intolerant attitudes were intensified by fears that black neighbors would cause property values to decline. Moreover the increased presence of African Americans in cities, North and South, as well as their competition with whites for housing, jobs, and political influence sparked a series of race riots. The Tulsa Race Riots of 1921 and  the Rosewood Massacre of 1923 (where a town was wiped off the map by racist violence) were examples of this extreme of hatred. 

Although African Americans were widely persecuted by the Ku Klux Klan they were not the only group of people that the KKK targeted because they believed in “Native, white, Protestant supremacy.” They also targeted groups like Mexicans, Catholics and Jews. The Ku Klux Klan would also try and bring justice into their own hands when it came to dealing with bootleggers, wife beaters and adulterers, and even the Knights of Columbus. &lt;ref&gt;A People and A Nation Eighth Edition&lt;/ref&gt; A Klu Klux Klan newspaper ran a doggerel poem of a dialogue between the Pope and the Devil, with the latter saying the KKK &quot;will make it hotter than I can for you in hell.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Pope's Last Call,&quot; &quot;Elsie Thornton.&quot; Originally printed in Alabama KKK Newsletter, June 1926. p. 4. Box 16, Folder 11: Association Records, Ku Klux Klan, Alabama Department of Archives and History, Montgomery. Recalled on October 18, 2014: http://www1.assumption.edu/users/McClymer/his261/Pope'sLastCall.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==The End of Prosperity and the Stock Market Crash of 1929==

In the 1920s, farmers did not do so well. A lot of farms did not have running water or electricity, and pay was low due to surplus. World War I had disrupted farming in Europe and the warring European nations greatly depended on American farming for food.&lt;ref&gt;Shmoop Editorial Team. &quot;Economy in The 1920s&quot; Shmoop University, Inc..11 November 2008. http://www.shmoop.com/1920s/economy.html (accessed November 22, 2013).&lt;/ref&gt;  When peace came, demand for crops like cotton and grain suddenly fell but farmers kept planting at wartime rates&lt;ref&gt;Katers, Nicholas. &quot;The Roaring Twenties and the Struggles of Immigrants, Farmers, and Other Interest Groups.&quot; ''Yahoo! Voices''. Yahoo!, 30 Mar. 2006. Web. 22 Nov. 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;, so they were left without money to pay off their loans or new devices like tractors. 

A lot of farmers were dependent growing cotton. However, in the twenties the price of cotton plummeted because of new man-made materials that entered the market. Matters were made worse by the invasion of the boll weevil, an insect which planted its eggs in the boll (cotton blossom), and ate the cotton. The Southern economy was partially saved through following the urging of inventor George Washington Carver and planting peanuts instead of cotton. In 1925-1927 George Washington Carver patented two uses for peanuts, and hundreds of more inventions from soybeans, pecans, and even sweet potatoes. Some inventions he made from peanuts and soybeans are paper, instant coffee, shaving cream, mayonnaise, soap, and talcum powder. None of these procedures were ever recorded by him in a notebook.  

On October 24, 1929, today known as Black Thursday, the stock market began its downhill drop. After the first hour, the prices had gone down at an amazing speed. Some people thought that after that day, the prices would rise again just as it had done before. But prices kept dropping. On October 29, 1929, Black Tuesday, more than 16 million shares were sold, but by the end of the day, most stocks ended below their previous value, and some stocks became totally worthless. By November 13, the prices had hit rock bottom. The stock AT&amp;T had gone from 304 dollars to 197. Much of America had celebrated unheard of prosperity for eight years, but the Stock Market Crash put an end to that within a few weeks. 

== Questions For Review ==

1. Name the economic effects of one of the following: the automobile; mass production as a whole; the boll weevil.

← [[US History/World War I|World War I]] · '''[[US History]]''' · [[US History/Great Depression and New Deal|Great Depression and New Deal]] →

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{BookCat}}

{{chapnav|World War I|Great Depression and New Deal}}</text>
      <sha1>s0cwq8luoznuait14dtacip14kjhack</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>World History/Standards</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1451</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1110149</id>
      <parentid>1110127</parentid>
      <timestamp>2008-02-11T06:15:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Neoptolemus</username>
        <id>77154</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>fix links</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{WHP - page top 2}}

'''Please see [[COSTP World History Project]] for the parallel project based on California content standards (note that it has no content).'''

==Newly Adopted AP World History Standards==

[[World History/AP World History Standard]]

==Previous Standards==

===California standards===
[[World History/California Content Standard]]

http://www.cde.ca.gov/re/pn/fd/documents/hist-social-sci-frame.pdf

http://www.cde.ca.gov/be/st/ss/hstgrades9through12.asp

===Florida standards (Never put into effect)===
[[World History/Florida Instructional Materials Specifications]]

[[World History/Florida Course Description]]



{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>pzyyggbdn04jd0hxniykd8o3kp37mgx</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Patrick</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>1454</id>
    <revision>
      <id>153569</id>
      <parentid>137992</parentid>
      <timestamp>2005-06-10T08:12:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Patrick</username>
        <id>43</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;pre&gt;

*[[project:a (b)|]]
*[[m:project:a (b)|]]
*[[de:project:a (b)|]]
*[[w:project:a (b)|]]
*[[w:de:project:a (b)|]]
*[[:de:project:a (b)|]]
*[[wikibooks:project:a (b)|]]
*[[wikiquote:project:a (b)|]]
*[[m:wikisource:project:a (b)|]]

&lt;/pre&gt;

*[[project:a (b)|a]]
*[[m:project:a (b)|project:a]]
*[[de:project:a (b)|project:a]]
*[[w:project:a (b)|project:a]]
*[[w:de:project:a (b)|de:project:a]]
*[[:de:project:a (b)|:de:project:a]]
*[[wikibooks:project:a (b)|project:a]]
*[[wikiquote:project:a (b)|project:a]]
*[[m:wikisource:project:a (b)|wikisource:project:a]]


Image description page with redirect to Special:

http://wikibooks.org/w/wiki.phtml?title=Image:Textbookicons.png&amp;redirect=no

[[Image Textbookicons.png – go to redirect-to-Special page itself]]

[[Image Go To A Random Page .png – go to redirect-to-Special page itself]]

test:

&lt;center&gt;Centered text.&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;nowiki&gt;[[a (i)|]]
[[project:a|]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;
[[a (i)|a]]
[[project:a|a]]

[[en:Main Page]], [[Main Page (i)|Main Page]], etc.

[[m:Main Page]]

[[wiktionary:Main Page]]

[[wikibooks:Main Page]]

[[wikiquote:Main Page]]

[[Wikisource:Main Page]]

[[Wikisource:Constitution of the United States of America]]

[[m:Wikisource:Constitution of the United States of America]]

http://sources.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constitution_of_the_United_States_of_America

http://meta.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikisource:Constitution_of_the_United_States_of_America</text>
      <sha1>41ck5owl158p3gp0e9rlngc0kmox682</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>US History/World War II and Rise of Atomic Age</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1457</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2691997</id>
      <parentid>2690199</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-16T17:10:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>184.155.217.64</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Anti-Semitism and The Holocaust */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Economic Effects of World War One and the Great Depression==
* The Treaty of Versailles unrealistically addressed war reparations, causing a debt spiral between Germany, the Western Allies, and the United States.  The German nation felt humiliated by the Treaty's terms.
* This contributed significantly to the collapse of the world financial markets and led to an economic catastrophe that spawned a political vacuum which allowed new, more radical-than-traditional politicians to emerge on the world scene.  These included such men as Adolf Hitler, Joseph Stalin, Franklin Roosevelt, Hideki Tojo, and Chiang Kai-shek.
* Also with many of the men being shipped overseas to fight in the war, many employment opportunities opened up for women. Thousands of women began to support the war efforts by getting employed in many different factories producing tanks and planes and other sorts of weaponry. The start of World War Two brought the end of the &quot;Great Depression&quot; due to all of the supplies and men it takes to win a war.

==Conflict in Europe==
[[Image:Mussolini&amp;Hitler1.gif|thumb|Mussolini and Hitler greet the people]]
In 1933, German president Paul von Hindenberg named Adolf Hitler chancellor; he then disbanded the Weimar Republic and then began the rise of the &quot;Third Reich&quot;, which was also known as &quot;Großdeutsches Reich&quot;. Hitler had outlined his aims years earlier, in his book ''Mein Kampf''(My Struggle). He noted Germany's problems after its defeat in World War I. The nation had been damaged economically and morally, cut off from the raw materials, land, and resources needed to help it develop as a nation. Hitler blamed &quot;sub human&quot; peoples such as the Jews for his country's defeat. The superior German people needed &quot;living room,&quot; and had a right to claim it. In fact, the book was a blueprint for the Nazi party's planned extermination of the Jews (the &quot;Holocaust&quot; or &quot;Shoah&quot;), and the elemination of homosexuals, the mentally ill, and other &quot;undesirable&quot; elements of German society. Hitler also used this opinion regarding German superiority, as well as the viewpoint that Germans were unfairly treated after World War I, to justify the attempt to terminate the Treaty of Versailles.

Hitler began a buildup of the German military. In 1936, he tested German might by supporting a rebellion in Spain. Then, Hitler and Benito Mussolini, the Fascist Dictator of Italy, as well as Japan, began to create a coalition between their three countries. The coalition later came to be known as the Axis.

In 1938, Hitler annexed Austria. Other nations were reluctant to interfere because of Hitler's claim that the relation between Germany and Austria was an internal German concern that had little or nothing to do with the rest of Europe. Then, Hitler took control of a part of Czechoslovakia. This time, British Prime Minister Neville Chamberlain did interfere, signing an agreement with Hitler that ensured that Germany would keep any territory already conquered, but would not attempt to take any further Czechoslovakian territory. The policy which sought to prevent another World War at almost any cost, including the cost of allowing the tyrant Hitler to gain more power, was known as ''appeasement''.

Hitler had no intention of keeping his agreement. In 1939, he took over the remainder of Czechoslovakia and turned his sights to Poland, demanding the Polish Corridor. France and the United Kingdom agreed to come to Poland's aid, but Germany signed the Nazi-Soviet Pact, which ensured the neutrality of the Soviet Union (formerly Russia).
Hitler also signed a Non-Aggression Pact with the Soviets. This would prevent Germany to have to fight the all so dreaded two front war. Both countries agreed to take parts of Poland, Russia like the idea of gaining control of the Baltic Sea ports. Germany, on the other hand was just on one of its small steps in taking over Europe. A few years after the treaty was signed Hitler discarded the treaty, therefore making the Soviet Union an allied force.

== The Beginning of the War ==

On the first day of September in 1939, Germany declared war on Poland; the British and French responded by declaring war on Germany two days later.

The Germans used the tactic of ''blitzkrieg'' (lightning war) in Poland, defeating the Polish Army at lightning speed. By the end of the first week of October, the Germans had gained control of half of Poland. The British and French had done little to aid Poland, fearing a repeat of the First World War. Meanwhile, the Soviets invaded from the east ending any hope for Poland. The last troops surrendered in early October. This new method of fighting known as the Blitzkreig method had never been seen before; unlike the previous World War, soldiers didn't dig deep into the trenches and fight for months trying to hold a certain position. Hitlers armored divisions and air force attacked Poland all at once with little warning. This made it difficult for the Polish, as well as every other country that Germany invaded, to gather up enough troops and support to defend themselves from invasion.

In the spring of 1940, Hitler continued his attempt to create a German Empire by attacking the nations of Denmark and Norway. Denmark surrendered, but British and French troops did, originally at least, come to Norway's aid. 

Meanwhile, Hitler planned to take control of France and other nations. Germany entered Belgium and the Netherlands on May 10, 1940. The Netherlands surrendered on May 15 (Zeeland held out until the 18); Belgium followed on May 28. On the same day, France recalled its troops from Norway, leaving Norway's fate to Germany.

On June 5, the Germans began their attack on France. To make matters worse, Mussolini declared war on France and Britain on June 10. The French government, meanwhile was taken over by a new Premier, who signed an armistice with Germany on June 17. Germany gained control of the northern part of France, and the Vichy French Government (so called because of the new French capital at Vichy) retained the south. The Italians had a small zone of occupation near the Franco-Italian border.

Hitler's Germany was the supreme power on Continental Europe. Only the United Kingdom offered resistance. The Germans intended to invade the United Kingdom, but they first had to contend with the British Royal Air Force. The German Luftwaffe (Air Force) commenced the Battle of Britain in 1940. However, the British used the new technology of radar (Radio Detection and Ranging) to combat the Germans. In September, 1940, the Germans ended the Battle of Britain by indefinitely delaying all plans for invasion. Nonetheless, German airplanes continued to bomb several British cities until the middle of the next year.

Hitler expanded the Axis in the winter of 1940-1941 with the additions of Hungary, Romania, and Bulgaria. In April, 1941, Germany and Italy then attacked Yugoslavia, which surrendered within one week of invasion. Then, Hitler and Mussolini turned to Greece, which collapsed by the end of April. By the end of 1942, most of Europe was under control of the Nazis or the Italians.  Meanwhile, the Japanese gained control of Indochina (Southeast Asia), which had formerly belonged to Vichy France. The United States retaliated by attempting to prevent Japanese purchases of oil and steel. Tensions between Japan and the United States began to grow.

In early 1941, the United States abandoned its neutrality and began to aid the British. The Lend-Lease Act, for example, allowed the President to lend or lease weapons worth over seven billion dollars to other nations.  The first two years of the war overseas saw the American public broadly divided on the issue of potential involvement.  Though the danger posed by Germany and Japan was generally recognized, millions of Americans felt that a strong, armed neutrality and oceanic defense without entering the war was the safest course.  President Roosevelt, on the other hand, made it quite clear to those around him that he felt the United States would have to intervene on the Allied side, and planned and acted accordingly, initiating a war industrial buildup and proposing that the US become the &quot;arsenal of democracy.&quot;  The Allied powers consisted of the Soviet Union, United States, Great Britain, France, Poland, Canada, Norway, Netherlands, Belgium, and Greece.  The main Axis powers consisted of Germany, Italy, and Japan.  The estimated death total for the Allied powers is around 61 million people, while the Axis power casualties is estimated to be around only 12 million.

==Conflict in the Pacific==

On June 22, 1941, the Germans invaded the Soviet Union. Originally, Germany predicted a quick victory. The Americans were very reluctant to start any conflict with Germany. Even in the fall of 1941, when shooting took place in the Atlantic between German U-boats and US ships, Roosevelt avoided escalation.  Soon however, momentous events in the Pacific changed the course of the war.

The Empire of Japan was active in the Pacific.  In order to secure resources and sea lanes for the Japanese islands, they intended to neutralize the American Pacific Fleet, which had been stationed at Pearl Harbor in Hawaii. On December 7, 1941, the Japanese Air Force bombed the large American naval base, destroying or severely damaging over nineteen ships and 292 aircraft. This naval base was the Pearl Harbor located in Hawaii. Fortunately for the US Navy, its aircraft carriers were at sea and survived the attack, but there was 2,403 American soldiers, sailors, and civilians that were killed by the attack. Defying the expectations of the United States, Japan also made simultanious strikes on Guam, Midway, and British bases.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Don't Know Much About History&quot; by Kenneth C. Davis&lt;/ref&gt; The next day, the United States Congress declared war on Japan, prompting Germany and Italy to in turn declare war on the United States. 

Japan continued with its Pacific operations by taking the American territories of the Philippines, Guam, and Wake Island, the British territories of Burma, Singapore, Malaya, Borneo, and the Dutch territory of the East Indies. An emboldened Japanese navy then committed a blunder by attacking Midway Island. American carrier-based planes defeated the Japanese ships at  Midway Island so badly that Japan's navy never recovered from the battle. Starving and weakening by disease, they held on for another month before surrendering. Those who survived long enough to surrender faced worse horror.
In June of 1942 the battle over Midway took place in the Pacific and it lasted several days. It was mainly areial attacks on naval ships. The United States destroyed a majority of Japans naval fleet, therefore bringing a turning point for the United States. From this point on the United States were able to island hop their way across the Pacific.

In February 1942, the War Relocation Authority began to establish centers where Japanese-Americans, including those born in the United States, were interned. Though this was clearly racial discrimination that violated constitutional due process requirements, the Supreme Court ruled that such internment was lawful in 1944, when it decided ''Korematsu v. United States''.

==Turning back the European Axis==
During the summer and fall of 1941, the Germans kept up their amazing pace into the heart of Russia. By December they had reached Moscow, and Leningrad was under siege. The Soviets sent in reserve troops from Siberia, and launched a counter attack. It succeeded, and Moscow was saved.

In the spring of 1942, Hitler ordered an attack into the Caucus Mountains, and Stalingrad. As they had done before, the Germans quickly advanced, breaking through the Russian lines. In Stalingrad, there was street to street, and house to house fighting. The Germans controlled over 90% of the city, but the Russians refused to surrender. A Russian reserve division encircled the Germans into the city, and 250,000 German soldiers were captured. It was one of the bloodiest battles in history.

In 1943, the President of the United States for an unprecedented third term, Franklin D. Roosevelt, and the Prime Minister of the United Kingdom, Winston Churchill held a Conference at Casablanca. The two nations then set up a plan of action for the next stages of the war. Meanwhile, the Russians continued to hold back the Germans, inflicting a crucial and massive defeat on Hitler's armies at the battle of Stalingrad in the winter of 1942-43. After a further major Russian victory at Kursk the following summer, the Germans were forced into retreat back towards Europe. 

In Africa, Axis troops led by Erwin Rommel had pushed into Egypt, just 70 miles west of Alexandria. However, British troops led by General Montgomery decisively defeated the Italian and German troops at the Battle of El Alamein. They were pushed out of Egypt, all the way across Libya, and into Tunisia. In November 1942, the Americans launched operation Torch and drove the French troops out of Algeria and Morrocco. After a long battle with Axis troops in Tunisia, they were driven out of Africa in May 1943.

The Allies then decided to invade Sicily, in hope of knocking Italy out of the war. In early July the invasion began. For the next month, the British and Americans led a bloody campaign in which Sicily was finally taken in early August. During the invasion Mussolini was overthrown and arrested. Hitler had him rescued and put him in charge of the new Italian Social Republic. Following the Invasion of mainland Italy in early September, the Italian government signed an armistice with the Allies. The fall of Italy signaled the beginning of the end of World War II. However, Mussolini was rescued by the Germans and had established an Italian Social Republic.
Near the end of the War, Germany tries to fight for a last stand with the Allies. It became to be Germany's only hope for turning the war around. The battle took place in a 60 mile deep 40 mile wide &quot;Bulge&quot;. Therefore giving the name of the battle, battle of the Bulge. After weeks of fighting in the cold winters the Allied forces came out victorious. Months after this battle the Allied forces had the Germans pushed all the way back into Berlin.

==Anti-Semitism and The Holocaust==
The Protocols of the Elders of Zion (Russian: &quot;Протоколы сионских мудрецов&quot;, or &quot;Сионские протоколы&quot;, see also other titles) is an antisemitic and anti-Zionist plagiarism and literary forgery first published in 1903 in Russian, in Znamya; it alleges a Jewish and Masonic plot to achieve world domination.

&quot;The Protocols&quot; (the most brief title by which the text is known) is an early example of contemporary conspiracy theory literature,[1] and takes the form of a speech describing how to dominate the world, the need to control the media, finance, replace traditional social order, etc. It is one of the best known and discussed examples of literary forgery, and a hoax.

The text was popularized by those opposed to Russian revolutionary movement, and was disseminated further after the revolution of 1905, becoming known worldwide after the 1917 October Revolution. It was widely circulated in the West in 1920 and thereafter. The Great Depression and the rise of Nazism were important developments in the history of the Protocols, and the hoax continued to be published and circulated despite its debunking.

Hitler mentioned in his book Mein Kampf that the book ''Protocols'' was up to date, indicating that he saw it as justification for his deeds against the Jews.

The Holocaust is known as one of the most ghastly episodes in the modern history of mankind. In April of 1933, three months after Hitler took power, the Nazis issued a decree ordering the compulsory retirement of &quot;non-Aryans&quot; from the civil service. This is known as the spark of the Holocaust. Before Germany was defeated, there were some eleven million people that had been slaughtered in the name of Nazi racial purity. Although the Jews were the favored targets and are the victims we most hear about when talking about the Holocaust, they were not the only victims. There were also millions of Russians, Poles, gypsies and others that were also murdered. Although the deprivation of the Jews started in the years following 1933, the mass killings didn't begin until 1941.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;WWII&quot; by Eric Sevareid&lt;/ref&gt;

	There were huge amounts of deaths involved in the Holocaust.  One of the main concentration camps, Auschwitz, claimed the lives of over 1.4 million people.  The Belzec camp killed over 600,000 people, Chelmno killed 320,000 people, and various others killed up to over 800,000 people.  The main way of extermination was through the gas chambers.  Many different types were used and once the people were dead, they were sent into the fire pit.

== Operation Overlord ==

In November, 1943, Prime Minister Churchill and President Roosevelt held another Conference at Tehran. Joseph Stalin, who held the title of General Secretary of the Communist Party of the USSR, but was actually a Dictator of the Soviet Union, joined them there. The three leaders agreed to a plan codenamed Operation Overlord, under which an attack would be launched on the northern coast of France from the English Channel. In preparation for an invasion of France, Hitler cut off all support for the German armies remaining in the Soviet Union. Thus disabled, the German Army was forced to withdraw from Russia in the winter of 1943-1944.

On June 6, 1944 (&quot;D-Day,&quot;) in the early morning hours, American and British paratroopers were dropped into Normandy. Hours later, American, British, French and Canadian soldiers landed at Normandy on the north coast of France. The troops landed near Caen, but Hitler wrongly felt that they would attack at a location to the north of that city. The Allies took advantage of Hitler's miscalculation; by the end of the month, the Allies had over eight hundred thousand soldiers in Normandy.

Meanwhile, Russian troops, which had been on the defensive, began their offensive on German-controlled territories. In the middle of July, the Soviets won their first major victory by taking the territory of Belorussia.  At this time, concern began to grow in the West about Soviet domination replacing German in eastern Europe, especially in Poland.  Despite these worries, Roosevelt felt that he had little influence in that area over Stalin, whose armies were bearing a huge brunt of the fight.  

By the end of July, the Allies expanded their base at Normandy by breaking out into the rest of France. Pushing through the nation, the Allies had gone far enough to liberate the city of Paris on August 25. On September 11, some Allied troops entered Germany, taking Antwerp, Belgium on the way.  German resistance then hardened, however. British Field Marshall Montgomery attempt to &quot;end the war by '44&quot; with Operation Market Garden, a plan to liberate Holland and bypass the German border defenses, failed. The British and American armies would make little more progress for the rest of 1944. 

Meanwhile, Russian troops pushed toward Germany, defeating Germany's Axis partners on the way. In August, Romania surrendered, followed by Bulgaria and Finland in September.

== Yalta and German Surrender ==

Allied air bombing of German industries and cities had been ongoing and savage since 1943, but did not have the intended effect of crushing the German will to fight. Indeed, Hitler was able to field new advanced weapons in 1943-45, such as the world's first jet fighter aircraft, the V-1 flying bomb, the V-2 ballistic missile, and new types of tanks and submarines.  The new weapons, however, proved of little use against Allied numbers and economic superiority, with American industrial production for the war effort massive and untouched by Axis attack.  Germany forced millions of prisoners into slave labor, under the most brutal conditions, to keep its own war effort going.  

In December 1944, Germany launched a massive counter-attack on the light defended American positions in Belgium. The Germans hoped to cut off the Allied supply lines, however, after reinforcements arrived, the &quot;Bulge&quot;(today it is know as the Battle of the Bulge) was flattened out. Meanwhile, the Soviets were on the verge of entering Germany from the east en masse, having taken control of Poland.  Hitler's troops were exhausted, millions dead or captured, and with the fall of the Romanian oil fields, German armies were running out of gasoline.  A final callup began of old men and boys for a last-ditch defense of Germany. Many German civilians fled, fearing the revenge the Russians would put on them after what the Germans had done in Russia. Thousands of German Civilians were killed and/or raped. 

To plan for the end of the war, Roosevelt, Churchill, and Stalin met at Yalta in February.When they met at the Yalta conference each different country had their own ideas of what they wanted to do with Germany. Churchill and Britain wanted to protect their colonial possessions and to also keep the Soviet Union from having to much power. The Stalin and the Soviet Union wanted Germany to pay them money in order to help them start the rebuilding of their country. The United States along with the other countries wanted to influence Germany and to also keep peace.&lt;ref&gt;A People and A Nation&lt;/ref&gt; The Yalta conference suggested the division of Germany into &quot;zones&quot; after the war for the purpose of reconstruction. Also, the leaders decided to punish Nazis who had participated in war crimes such as the Holocaust.  The Allies first attempted to reach the Rhine River in their quest to take over Germany.  In March, this goal accomplished, the Americans and British opposed the Soviets in the ''Race for Berlin''. The Race determined who would control Berlin, a city that would prove important in the reconstruction of Germany.

The Americans allowed the Soviets to win the Race for Berlin.  Fierce fighting erupted in and around the city as motley German units made their last stand against the powerful army groups of Russian marshals Zhukov and Koniev.  His capital surrounded and his loyal minions deserting him, Adolf Hitler killed himself in his Berlin command bunker on April 30, 1945, also  American President Franklin Roosevelt had died on April 12, and Benito Mussolini was executed by Italian Partisans on April 28. The new leader of Germany, Karl Doenitz, agreed to surrender. On May 8, Germany formally signed an unconditional surrender, dissolving the Axis and leaving only Japan to be defeated.

== The Atomic Bomb and the End of World War II ==
{{Wikipedia|Atomic bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki}}
Meanwhile, the United States dramatically improved its position in the Pacific. The Japanese continued to fight, though it was in a hopeless situation. The suicidal Japanese spirit was exemplified by kamikaze, the practice of Japanese pilots who intentionally drove their own planes into American ships. 

The Manhattan project was a two billion dollar project that offered many jobs to the American people. The purpose of this project was to build a nuclear weapon that can produce mass destruction. The project offered jobs to mainly scientists and other educated individuals. With the completion of the atomic bomb however our nation was able to end the war a lot sooner than expected. The bomb itself used fission which is the splitting of a highly electronegative atom such as uranium into smaller ones which gives off ten times as much power, which is why the two bombs where so destructive.
The Japanese resistance grew stronger and stronger as the Allies advanced to Japan. One million American deaths and two more years of war were not uncommon predictions. President Harry Truman, the Vice President who rose to the Presidency upon Roosevelt's death, chose to use the Atomic Bomb instead of the invasion. In the 1930's, physicists began to understand the power of the fission, or splitting, of atoms. This advance of knowledge meant that nuclear power and atomic weapons were indeed possible. On October 11, 1939 the president received a letter signed by Albert Einstein explaining the developments in the nuclear chain reactions that would generate lots of power.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;WWII&quot; by Eric Severeid&lt;/ref&gt; In 1942, the US secretly created the Manhattan Project to develop a weapon which could utilize the concept of the fission of uranium atoms, which, according to the conclusions of physicists, would create a massive explosion. The very costly Manhattan Project needed a lot of help getting the bomb created. At the peak of the project more than 600,000 Americans had worked on this project, most of them not realizing what they were really working for. After America spent more than two billion dollars on this project, the first atomic bomb was created. This bomb was named &quot;fat man.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;WWII&quot; by Eric Sevareid&lt;/ref&gt; On July 16, 1945, the atomic bomb was successfully tested in New Mexico.
{{Wikipedia|Albert Einstein}}
The atomic bomb works on the principles of transmutation, accelerated nuclear decay, nuclear chain reaction, and the law of the conservation of mass. Since mass is lost in the accelerated decay of the nuclei, this mass must be accounted for. According to Albert Einstein's Theory of Relativity, this missing mas is converted into energy, according to the relationship, E=mc&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, where ''E'' is the rest energy, ''m'' is the missing mass, and ''c'' is the speed of light in a vacuum.

On August 6, the atomic bomb was dropped on Hiroshima, Japan by a B-29 aircraft piloted by Col. Paul Tibbets.  This deadly bomb was given the name “Little Boy”. Still, Japan refused to give up. On August 9, another bomb was dropped on Nagasaki.  This deadly bomb was given the name “Fat Man”. Together, the bombs killed over one hundred thousand people (though the Japanese suggested a number twice as high).  Just about everybody who died was a civilian. In between the attacks on Hiroshima and Nagasaki, meanwhile, the Soviet Union joined in the war on Japan.  Six days after the Nagasaki bomb was dropped, Japan surrendered. On August 14, with the Americans threatening a third atomic bomb on the way for Tokyo (though in reality the United States had no more atomic bombs at the time) Japan agreed to surrender; the formalities were completed on September 2, 1945 aboard the USS Missouri. When the A-bomb was dropped, it exploded forming a mushroom cloud.  Dust and debris is shot into the sky and can be seen from miles away.

== Franklin D. Roosevelt ==
Franklin Delano Roosevelt (January 30, 1882 – April 12, 1945), also known by his initials, FDR) was the 32nd President of the United States and a central figure in world events during the mid-20th century, leading the United States during a time of worldwide economic crisis and world war. The only American president elected to more than two terms, he forged a durable coalition that realigned American politics for decades. FDR defeated incumbent Republican Herbert Hoover in November 1932, at the depths of the Great Depression. FDR's combination of optimism and activism contributed to reviving the national spirit.  Starting in his &quot;first hundred days&quot; in office, which began March 4, 1933, Roosevelt launched major legislation and a profusion of executive orders that gave form to the New Deal—a complex set of programs designed to produce relief (especially government jobs for the unemployed), recovery (of the economy), and reform (through regulation of Wall Street, banks and transportation). As World War II loomed after 1938, with the Japanese invasion of China and the aggressions of Nazi Germany, FDR gave strong diplomatic and financial support to China and Britain, while remaining officially neutral. His goal was to make America the &quot;Arsenal of Democracy&quot; which would supply ammunition to the Allies. Working closely with Winston Churchill and Joseph Stalin in leading the Allies against Germany and Japan in World War II, he died just as victory was in sight. After FDR's death Harry Truman became president. The day after Roosevelt's death Truman sought out old friends to ask for their help in this &quot;terrible job&quot;.

==Links==
*[http://www.archives.gov/research/ww2/photos/ National Archives]
*[http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761563737/world_war_ii.html Encarta encylopedia]
*[http://memory.loc.gov/learn/features/timeline/depwwii/wwarii/wwarii.html Library of Congress]
*[http://teacher.scholastic.com/ACTIVITIES/wwii/ahf/index.htm Scholastic, Inc.]
==References==
{{reflist}}


{{chapnav|Spanish Civil War|Truman and Cold War}}</text>
      <sha1>pwejxhagju87hz02zd4lbqujbdzz0wz</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>US History/Eisenhower Civil Rights Fifties</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1458</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2666360</id>
      <parentid>2666343</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-05-27T14:11:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Harrybrowne1986</username>
        <id>430968</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rejected the last 2 text changes (by [[Special:Contributions/38.117.84.204|38.117.84.204]]) and restored revision 2377007 by QuiteUnusual</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">== Civil Rights Movement under Eisenhower and Desegregation ==

The first events that would spark off the entire Civil Rights movement happened during the Eisenhower administration. In the south, there were many statewide laws that segregated many public facilities ranging from buses to water fountains. Southern African Americans now felt that their time had come to enjoy American democracy and they fought hard to end southern segregation policies.

===''Brown v. Board of Education''===

In 1952, seven year old Linda Brown, of Topeka, Kansas, wasn't permitted to attend a white-only elementary school that was only a few blocks from her house. In order to attend her coloreds-only school, Brown had to cross dangerous railroad tracks and take a bus for many miles. Her family sued the Topeka school board and lost, but appealed the case all the way to the Supreme Court. ''Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka, Kansas'' came to the Supreme Court in December 1952. In his arguments, head lawyer for the NAACP, Thurgood Marshall, challenged the &quot;Separate But Equal&quot; doctrine established in ''Plessy v. Ferguson'' in 1896. He argued that schools could be separate, but never equal. On May 17, 1954, the Court gave its opinion. It ruled that it was unconstitutional to segregate schools, and ordered that schools integrate &quot;with all deliberate speed.&quot;

====Central High Confrontation====

Integration would not be easy. Many school districts accepted the order without argument, but some, like the district of Little Rock, Arkansas, did not. On September 2, 1957, the day before the start of the school term the Arkansas Governor, Orval Faubus, instructed the National Guard to stop any black students entering the school. He claimed this was to protect the property against violence planned by integration protesters. 

The federal authorities intervened and an injunction was granted preventing the National Guard from blocking the school and they were withdrawn on September 20. School restarted on 23 September, with the building surrounded by local police officers and nearly one thousand protesters. The police escorted nine black students, later known as the Little Rock Nine, into the school via a side door. When the crowd discovered the students had entered the building, they tried to storm the school and the black students were hurried out around lunch time.

Congressman Brooks Hays and the Little Rock mayor, Woodrow Mann, asked the federal government for more help. On September 24, Mann sent a message to President Eisenhower requesting troops. Eisenhower responded immediately and the 101st Airborne Division was sent to Arkansas. In addition, the President brought the Arkansas National Guard under federal control to prevent its further use by the Governor. 

On September 25, 1957, the nine black students finally began their education properly, protected by 1,000 paratroopers.

===Montgomery Bus Boycott===

On December 1, 1955, Rosa Parks, a seamstress and secretary of the Montgomery, Alabama, chapter of the NAACP, boarded a city bus with the intention of going home. She sat in the first row of seats in the &quot;colored&quot; section of the segregated bus. At the next stop, whites were among the passengers waiting to board but all seats in the &quot;white&quot; front section of the bus were filled. Drivers had the authority, under local custom and the segregated-seating ordinance, to shift the line dividing the black and white sections to accommodate the racial makeup of the passengers at any given moment. So he ordered the four blacks sitting in the first row of seats in the &quot;colored&quot; section to stand and move to the rear of the bus so the waiting whites could have those seats. Three of the passengers complied; Mrs. Parks did not. Warned again by the driver, she still refused to move, at which point the driver exited the bus and located a policeman, who came onto the bus, arrested Mrs. Parks, and took her to the city jail. She was booked for violating the segregation ordinance, and was shortly released on bail posted by E. D. Nixon, the leading local civil rights activist. She was scheduled to appear in municipal court on December 5, 1955.

Mistreatment of African Americans on Montgomery's segregated buses was not uncommon, and several other women had been arrested in similar situations in the months preceding Parks's. However, Mrs. Parks was especially well-known and well-respected within the black community, and her arrest particularly angered the African Americans of Montgomery. In protest, community leaders quickly organized a one-day boycott of the buses to coincide with her December 5 court date. An organization, the Montgomery Improvement Association, was also created, and the new minister of the Dexter Avenue Baptist Church, the 26-year-old Martin Luther King, Jr., was selected as the MIA's president. Word of the boycott spread effectively through the city over the weekend of December 3–4, aided by mimeographed fliers prepared the Women's Political Council, by announcements in black churches that Sunday morning, and by an article in the local newspaper about the pending boycott, which had been &quot;leaked&quot; to a reporter by E. D. Nixon.

On the morning of Mrs. Parks's trial, King, Nixon, and other leaders were pleasantly surprised to see that the boycott was almost 100 percent effective among blacks. And since African Americans made up 75% of Montgomery's bus riders, the impact was significant. In city court, Mrs. Parks was convicted and was fined $10. Her attorney, the 24-year-old Fred D. Gray, announced an appeal. That night, more than 5,000 blacks crowded into and around the Holt Street Baptist Church for a &quot;mass meeting&quot; to discuss the situation. For most in the church (and listening outside over loudspeakers), it was their first time to hear the oratory of Martin Luther King, Jr. He asked the crowd if they wanted to continue the boycott indefinitely, and the answer was a resounding yes. For the next 381 days, African Americans boycotted the buses, while the loss of their fares drove the Chicago-owned bus company into deeper and deeper losses. However, segregationist city officials prohibited the bus company from altering its seating policies, and negotiations between black leaders and city officials went nowhere.

With bikes, carpools, and hitchhiking, African Americans were able to minimize the impact of the boycott on their daily lives. Meanwhile, whites in Montgomery responded with continued intransigence and rising anger. Several black churches and the homes of local leaders and ministers, including those of Nixon and King, were bombed, and there were numerous assaults by white thugs on African Americans. Some 88 local black leaders were also arrested for violating an old anti-boycott law.

Faced with the lack of success of negotiations, attorney Gray soon filed a separate lawsuit in federal court challenging the constitutionality of the segregated seating laws. The case was assigned to and testimony was heard by a three-judge panel, and the young Frank M. Johnson, Jr., newly appointed to the federal bench by Republican President Dwight D. Eisenhower, was given the responsibility for writing the opinion in the case. Johnson essentially ruled that in light of the 1954 Brown v. Board of Education decision by the U.S. Supreme Court, there was no way to justify legally the segregation policies, and the district court ruling overturned the local segregation ordinance under which Mrs. Parks and others had been arrested. The city appealed, but the U.S. Supreme Court affirmed the lower court ruling, and in December 1956, city officials had no choice but to comply. The year-long boycott thus came to an end.

The Montgomery Bus Boycott made Mrs. Parks famous and it launched the civil rights careers of King and his friend and fellow local minister, Ralph Abernathy. The successful boycott is regarded by many historians as the effective beginning of the twentieth century civil rights movement in the U.S.

==Vietnam==

In the early 50's, Vietnam was rebelling against French rule. America saw Vietnam as a potential source of trouble, as rebels (known as the Vietnamese) led by Communist leader Ho Chi Minh were gaining strength. America loaned France billions of dollars to aid in the war against the Vietnamese rebels, but despite the aid, France found itself on the verge of defeat, and appealed to America for troops, but America refused, fearing entanglement in another costly Korean War, or even a war with all of communist Asia.

France surrendered, and the VietMinh and France met in Geneva, Switzerland to negotiate a treaty. Vietnam was divided into two countries: the Vietminh in control of the North and the French-friendly Vietnamese in control of the South. In 1956, the two countries would be reunited with free elections.

Eisenhower worried about South Vietnam. He believed that if it also fell to the Communists, many other Southeast Asian countries would follow, in what he called the ''domino theory''. He aided the Southern government and set up the Southeast Asia Treaty Organization (SEATO) in 1954. The nations included in the alliance were America, Great Britain, France, Australia, Pakistan, the Philippines, New Zealand and Thailand, and they all pledged to fight against &quot;Communist aggressors&quot;.

==The Warsaw Pact and NATO==

1955 saw the division of Europe into two rival camps. The westernized countries of the free world had signed NATO 1949 and the eastern European countries signed the Warsaw pact.

===NATO===

The North Atlantic Treaty Organization was created as a response to the crisis in Berlin. The United States, Britain, Canada, France, Portugal, Italy, Belgium, Luxembourg, Norway, Denmark, Iceland, and the Netherlands founded NATO in April 1949, and Greece, Turkey and West Germany had joined by 1955. The countries agreed that &quot;an armed attack against one or more of [the member states] in Europe or North America shall be considered an attack against them all,&quot; and was created so that if the Soviet Union eventually did invade Europe, the invaded countries would have the most powerful army in the world (the United States' Army) come to their defense.  When the Korean War broke out, NATO drastically raised its threat level because of the idea that all the communist countries were working together.  As the number of communist countries grew and grew, so did the NATO forces.  Greece and Turkey eventually joined NATO in 1952.  The USSR eventually decided to join NATO so that there would be peace, but NATO declined them because they thought that the USSR would try to weaken them from the inside.

===The Warsaw Pact===

The Soviet Union responded in to the addition of West Germany to NATO 1955 with its own set of treaties, which were collectively known as the Warsaw Pact.  Warsaw Pact was also known as “The Treaty of Friendship”.  The Warsaw Pact allowed East Germany, Poland, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Albania, Romania, and Bulgaria to function in the same way as the NATO countries did.  The Soviet Union used this Warsaw Pact to combine the military forces unified under it.  The Pact was supposed to make all the countries in it, equal.  However, the Soviet Union took a little advantage of this by using the allied countries military wherever they wanted.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.warsaw-life.com/poland/warsaw-pact&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike NATO, Warsaw forces were used occasionally.

==Suez Canal==

Back in 1948, Israel was created as a sanctuary of sorts for the displaced Jews of the Holocaust. At the same time, many Arabs living in the area were displaced. Tensions had been high in the Middle East ever since Israel had been attacked just after its founding. The stage was set for superpower involvement in 1956; the United States backed Israel, the Soviet Union backed the Arabs, and the Egyptian president Gamal Abdel Nasser had nationalized, or brought under Egypt's control, the Suez Canal, which had previously belonged to Britain. 

France and Britain worried that Egypt would decide cut off oil shipments between the oil-rich Middle East and western Europe, so that October they invaded Egypt, hoping to overthrow Nasser and seize the canal. Israel, upset by earlier attacks by Arab states, agreed to help in the invasion.

U.S. and Soviet reactions to the invasions were almost immediate. The Soviets threatened to launch rocket attacks on British and French cities, and the United States sponsored a United Nations resolution for British and French withdrawal. Facing pressures from the two powers, the three invaders pulled out of Egypt. To ensure stability in the area, United Nations troops were sent to patrol the Egypt-Israel border.

==Rock and Roll==

The term “rock and roll” was originally a nautical phrase referring to the motion of a ship at sea.  In the early 20th century, it gained a religious connotation (referring to the sense of rapture felt by worshippers) and was used in spirituals.  After this, “rocking and rolling” increasingly became used as a metaphor for sex in blues and jazz songs.  

The origins of rock and roll lie primarily in electric blues from Chicago in the late 1940s, which was distinguished by amplification of the guitar, bass, and drums.  Electric blues was played by artists like Muddy Waters, Willie Dixon, and Buddy Guy, who were recorded by Leonard and Phil Chess at Chess Records in Chicago.  They inspired electric blues artists in Memphis like Howlin’ Wolf and B.B. King, who were recorded by a Memphis-based record producer named Sam Phillips, also the owner of Sun Records. He later discovered Elvis Presley in 1954, and he also recorded early songs by Jerry Lee Lewis, Johnny Cash, Roy Orbison, and Carl Perkins.

Rhythm and blues artists such as Little Richard, Chuck Berry, Bo Diddley, and Ray Charles incorporated electric blues as well as gospel music.  In the early 50s, R&amp;B was more commonly known by the blanket term “race music”, which was also used to describe other African-American music of the era such as jazz and blues.  Billboard didn’t replace the “race records” category with “rhythm and blues” until 1958.  Doo-wop was a mainstream style of R&amp;B, with arrangements favoring vocal harmonies.  Other types of music that contributed to early rock and roll include African-American spirituals, also known as gospel music, and country/folk, which was primarily made by poor whites in the South.

Arguably, the first rock and roll song ever made is “Rocket 88”, recorded at Sam Phillip’s studio in Memphis in March 1951.  It was credited to “Jackie Brenston and his Delta Cats,” a band that didn’t actually exist—the song was put together by Ike Turner and his band, the Kings of Rhythm.  Jackie Brenston was the vocalist on the song, who also played saxophone in the band.  What really sets “Rocket 88” apart is the distorted guitar sound: it was one of the first examples of fuzz guitar ever recorded.  The amplifier they used to record the song was damaged on the way from Mississippi to Memphis.  They tried to hold the cone in place by stuffing the amplifier with newspaper, which created the distortion. Sam Phillips liked the sound and decided to keep it in the song.  Although “Rocket 88” was recorded by Sam Phillips, it wasn’t released by Sun Records, which didn’t exist until 1952.  From 1950-1952, Phillips ran the Memphis Recording Service, where he would let amateurs perform and then sell the recordings to large record labels.  He sold “Rocket 88” to Chess Records, which released predominately blues, gospel, and R&amp;B.  The Chess brothers started Checker Records in 1952, because radio stations would only play a certain number of tracks from each label.

Alan Freed (also known as “Moondog”) was a radio DJ who started playing R&amp;B records on WJW in Cleveland in 1951.  He is credited with introducing rock and roll to a wide audience for the first time, as well as being the first to use the phrase “rock and roll” as the name of the genre.  He also promoted and helped organize the first major rock and roll concert, The Moondog Coronation Ball, which occurred on March 21, 1952.  The concert was so successful that it became massively overcrowded – there was a near-riot and it had to be shut down early.   Freed’s popularity soared, and he was immediately given more airtime by the radio station.  His promotion of rock ‘n’ roll is one of the main reasons it became successful, and in recognition of his contributions to the genre, the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame was built in Cleveland.

“Payola” refers to the practice of record company promoters paying radio DJs to play their recordings in order to boost their sales.  Payola had been commonplace since the Vaudeville era in the 1920s, but it became a scandal in the 1950s due to a conflict between the American Society of Composers, Authors, and Publishers (ASCAP) and radio stations.  Prior to 1940, ASCAP had made huge amounts of money from the sales of sheet music, but when radio started gaining popularity, recorded music became more profitable than sheet music.  ASCAP demanded large royalty payments from radio stations that played their recordings.  Instead, stations boycotted ASCAP recordings and created their own publishing company called Broadcast Music Incorporated (BMI).  ASCAP tended to ignore music composed by black musicians or “hillbillies”, which gave BMI control of these areas.  When rock ‘n’ roll became more and more popular, BMI became more and more successful.  ASCAP (in addition to many others) believed that rock ‘n’ roll was the music of the devil, that it was brainwashing teenagers, and that it would never have been successful without payola.  This was just after the quiz show scandal (when it was found that certain shows were rigged), and ASCAP urged the House Legislative Committee which had investigated that scandal to look into payola.  The hearings that followed destroyed Alan Freed’s career, although it didn’t eliminate rock ‘n’ roll altogether as ASCAP had hoped.

Several factors contributed to the decline of early rock and roll.  Chuck Berry and Jerry Lee Lewis were both prosecuted in scandals involving young women.  Elvis Presley was inducted into the U.S. Army in 1958, and after training at Fort Hood, he joined the 3rd Armored Division in Germany, where he would remain until 1960.  Three rock and roll musicians –- Buddy Holly, Ritchie Valens, and “The Big Bopper” –- died in a plane crash on February 3, 1959 (“The Day the Music Died”).  Little Richard retired from secular music after a religious experience.  He ran a ministry in Los Angeles, preached across the country, and recorded gospel music exclusively until 1962.

Rock and roll music is associated with the emergence of a teen subculture among baby boomers.  Teenagers bought records and were exposed to rock and roll via radio, jukeboxes, and television shows like American Bandstand, which featured teenagers dancing to popular music.  It also affected movies, fashion trends, and language.  The combination of white and black music in rock and roll –- at a time when racial tensions were high and the civil rights movement was in full-swing –- provoked strong reactions among the older generation, many of whom worried that rock and roll would contribute to social delinquency among teenagers.  However, it actually encouraged racial cooperation and understanding to some extent—rock and roll was a combination of diverse styles of music made by different races, and it was enjoyed by both African-American and Caucasian teens.

==Space Race==

“The Space Race” has its origins in an arms race between the United States and the Soviet Union.  After the Soviet Union tested its first atomic bomb in September 1949, the fear of nuclear war began to spread.  The ensuing arms race led to the creation of intercontinental ballistic missiles (ICBMs), long-range rockets designed to deliver nuclear warheads from land- or submarine-based launch sites.  The first successful ICBM test flight was on August 21, 1957, when the USSR launched an ICBM with a dummy payload over 4,000 miles to an isolated peninsula on Russia’s east coast that had been declared a military zone (Kamchatka Peninsula, which remained closed to civilians from 1945–1989).  

On October 4, 1957, the Soviets successfully put the first man-made satellite, ''Sputnik'', into orbit. Americans were horrified. They feared that the Soviets were using the satellite to spy on Americans, or even worse, that the Soviet Union might attack America with nuclear weapons from space. America responded with the launch of its own satellite, ''Vanguard''. Hundreds of spectators gathered, only to watch the satellite rise only a few feet off the launch pad, and then explode.

The failure spurred the government to create a space agency, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA). NASA succeeded in launching the ''Explorer'' in 1958, and thus, the '''Space Race''' was initiated. With the creation of Project Mercury, a program to put an astronaut in space, America was pulling ahead. Nonetheless, the USSR was the first to put a man in space, when Yuri Gagarin was launched into orbit in 1961. For the next 14 years, the U.S and the Soviet Union would continue to compete in space.

Many Americans were frightened during the start of the space race because this gave the Soviet Union a better ability to launch a surprise attack on the states. The United States of course immediately jumped on the bandwagon and did its best to become the first country to land on the moon.

===Enos the Chimp===
Enos (died November 4, 1962) was a chimpanzee that was launched into space.

Enos was purchased from the Miami Rare Bird Farm in April 3, 1960. He completed more than 1,250 hours of training for his mission at the University of Kentucky and Holloman Air Force Base. His training was more intense than that of Ham, the Americans' first chimp in space, because Enos would be exposed to weightlessness and a higher g for longer periods of time. His training included psychomotor training and aircraft flights.

Enos was selected to make the first orbital animal flight only three days before the launch. Two months before allowing a chimp to be launched into orbit, NASA had launched Mercury Atlas 4 on September 13, 1961, to conduct the same mission with a &quot;crewman simulator&quot; in the spacecraft. Enos flew into space on board Mercury Atlas 5 on November 29, 1961. He completed his first orbit in 1 hour, 28.5 minutes.
===Spider webs in space===
Spider webs in space were spun in 1973 aboard Skylab, involving two female European garden spiders (cross spiders) called Arabella and Anita. As part of an experiment, the two spiders were taken into low earth orbit on the Skylab 3 mission. The aim of the experiment was to test whether the two spiders would spin webs in space, and, if so, whether these webs would be the same as those that spiders produced on Earth. The experiment was a student project of Judy Miles of Lexington, Massachusetts. A similar experiment was conducted on board Columbia's ill fated final mission using Australian spiders provided to NASA by various institutions in Melbourne.

When scientists were given the opportunity to study the webs, they discovered that the space-webs were finer than normal Earth webs, and although the patterns of the web were not totally dissimilar, variations were spotted, and there was a definite difference in the characteristics of the web. Additionally, while the webs were finer overall, the space-web had variations in thickness in places, some places were slightly thinner, and others slightly thicker. This was unusual, because Earth webs have been observed to have uniform thickness.

==Cuban Revolution==

In 1958 and 1959, anti-American feeling became a part of the growing Cuban revolution. In January 1959, the dictator of Cuba, Fulgenicio Batista, was overthrown by the rebel leader Fidel Castro, who promptly became the leader of Cuba.

At first, America supported Castro because of his promises of democratic and economic reforms. But relations between the two countries became strained when Cuba began seizing foreign-owned land (which was mostly U.S. owned) as a part of its reforms. Soon, Castro's government was a dictatorship, and was being backed by the Soviet Union. In 1961, Eisenhower cut diplomatic ties with Cuba, and relations with the island nation have been difficult ever since.
===Che===
Ernesto Guevara de la Serna (June 14, 1928 – October 9, 1967), commonly known as Che Guevara, El Che or just Che was an Argentine-born Marxist revolutionary, international political figure, author, social philosopher, medical physician, and leader of Cuban and internationalist guerrillas.

As a young man studying medicine, Guevara traveled throughout South America bringing him into direct contact with the impoverished conditions in which many people (particularly the indigenous peasantry) lived. His experiences and observations during these trips led him to the conclusion that the region's socio-economic inequalities were a result of capitalism, colonialism, neo-colonialism, and imperialism and thus could only be remedied by socialism through revolution, prompting him to intensify his study of Marxism and travel to Guatemala to learn about the reforms being implemented there by President Jacobo Arbenz Guzmán.
===Rise of the Middle Class===
In the late 1940s and 1950’s led to a rise of the middle class in the United States.  With troops coming home from the war soldiers were quick to start families.  The GI bill allowed for upward mobility for veterans.  With free college and over four billion dollars given to trips the economy continued to succeed.  With war savings and a host of new consumer goods on the market, America quickly turned into a consumer market.  The best example of this would be automobiles and the television.  In 1955, $65 billion was spent on automobiles.  This represented 20% of the Gross National Product.  In 1950 50% of American homes had a television.  By 1960 this number was raised to 90%.

{{chapnav|Truman and Cold War|Kennedy and Johnson}}
==References==
{{Reflist}}</text>
      <sha1>gwqx68q2xwj1o97n0y0ltrqubd3x8n3</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Geometry/Topology</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1464</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1001556</id>
      <parentid>509549</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-10-12T20:15:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mike's bot account</username>
        <id>67847</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>re-categorization for Subject: pages</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">A topological space is a set X, and a collection of subsets of X, C such that both the empty set and X are contained in C and the union of any subcollection of sets in C and the intersection of any finite subcollection of sets in C are also contained within C. The sets in C are called open sets. Their complements relative to X are called closed sets.

Given two topological spaces, X and Y, a map f from X to Y is continuous if for every open set U of Y, f&lt;sup&gt;&amp;minus;1&lt;/sup&gt;(U) is an open set of X.

[[Category:Geometry (book)]]</text>
      <sha1>k4gbq30j795glzdpduztgew51xstgev</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Go To Organic Chemistry Contents .png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1474</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1117740</id>
      <parentid>1108205</parentid>
      <timestamp>2008-02-18T04:29:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Webaware</username>
        <id>27565</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Karl Wick images are GFDL, see his [[User:Karl Wick|user page]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Organic Chemistry]]

==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>dpj7c5bbfln0wrh0mmzkqm4gaogkbgp</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Linear Algebra/Vectors</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1475</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1607245</id>
      <parentid>1480171</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-08-14T12:15:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>137.56.140.136</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Definitions */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Vectors''' are commonly used in physics and other fields to express quantities that cannot be accurately described by a scalar. '''Scalars''' are simply the value of something in a single dimension - a real number. For example, one might say that they have driven 5 kilometers, that an hour has elapsed, or that something's mass is 20 kilograms. In every one of these cases, there has been exactly one value stated. 

However, we might have more information we wish to give. Take the example of driving 5 kilometers. In this case, it may be useful to know how far you drove, but it might also be equally important which ''direction'' you drove, such as 5 kilometers due east. Now, given your starting point, exactly where you drove can be determined.

== Definitions ==

Vectors can be described mathematically by using [[Algebra/Trigonometry|trigonometry]]. 
&lt;div style=&quot;float:right;margin:0 0 1em 1em;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;[[image:Vector_example.PNG|Sample Vector]]&lt;/div&gt;
We can define a vector to be an ordered pair consisting of a '''magnitude''' and a '''direction'''. In this diagram, ''r'' is the magnitude of this vector and &amp;theta; is the direction. Notice, now, that we have moved horizontally ''r'' cos(&amp;theta;) and vertically ''r'' sin(&amp;theta;). These are called the ''x-component'' and the ''y-component'', respectively. 

We can also write a vector conveniently in terms of the x and y component. We write &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} x \\ y\end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt; for vectors. In some texts, you may see the vector written sideways, like (''x'', ''y''), but when you write it will help ''greatly'' to write them downwards in columns. In print we commonly use bold vectors, but since you probably don't have a pen that writes in bold print, underline your vectors, i.e. write &lt;u&gt;v&lt;/u&gt;, or put a tilde underneath your vectors. Occasionally in Physics, you may see vectors written with an arrow pointing right.

Notice that vectors need not have two components. We can have 2 or 3 or ''n'' or an infinite number of components.

We write the set of all vectors with 2 real number components as '''R'''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;; likewise for 3, ''n'', or infinite number of components. For components with complex numbers, we write '''C'''. Polynomials are &quot;vectors&quot; too - we'll look at notation for the set of polynomials later. For a reason why we do this, see [[Discrete mathematics/Set theory|Set theory]] for an explanation.

== Stretching and shrinking ==
We can define some actions on vectors. What will happen if we extend the vector? Or what will happen if we shrink the vector? The vector's ''direction'' doesn't change, only its length -- its magnitude. The action we perform to stretch or shrink a vector is that we multiply its magnitude by some amount. We refer to doing this as ''scalar multiplication'': we multiply the ''vector'' by a ''scalar'' real number.

=== Scalar multiplication ===
For scalar multiplication, we simply multiply each component by the scalar. We commonly use Greek letters for scalars, and English letters for vectors.


So for a scalar value of &amp;lambda; and a vector '''v''' defined by ''r'' and &amp;theta;, the new vector is now &amp;lambda;''r'' and &amp;theta;. Notice how the direction does not change.

==== Example ====
Say we have &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} 2 \\ 3 \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt; and we wish to double the magnitude. So, &lt;math&gt;2 \begin{pmatrix} 2 \\ 3 \end{pmatrix} = \begin{pmatrix} 4 \\ 6 \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;.

== Addition of vectors ==

Simply, to add two vectors, you must add the respective x-components together to obtain the new x-component, and likewise add the two y-components together to obtain the new y-component.

=== Example ===
Say we have &lt;math&gt;\mathbf{v_1}=\begin{pmatrix} 2 \\ 3 \end{pmatrix}, \mathbf{v_2}=\begin{pmatrix} 4 \\ 6 \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt; and we wish to add these. So, &lt;math&gt;\mathbf{v_1}+\mathbf{v_2}=\begin{pmatrix} 6 \\ 9 \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;.

== Subtraction of vectors ==

The operation of subtraction on two vectors, '''a''' and '''b''', '''a'''-'''b''', can also be written as '''a'''+(-1)'''b'''. Therefore, we can use scalar multiplication to find the value of (-1)'''b''', then use vector addition to find our solution.

== Complex numbers as vectors ==
^
[[../Complex numbers/]] can be represented in the form &lt;math&gt;r(cos(\theta) + isin(\theta))&lt;/math&gt; or equivalently &lt;math&gt;re^{i\theta}&lt;/math&gt; , or in other words, a vector with magnitude &lt;math&gt;r&lt;/math&gt; and direction &lt;math&gt;\theta&lt;/math&gt;. On the complex plane, this vector has a ''real'' x-component and an ''imaginary'' y-component. See [[../Complex numbers/]] for more information.

== Lines and planes ==
We can form the equations of lines and planes using vectors. Let's see how we can do this.

=== Vector equation of the line ===
Consider a vector &lt;math&gt;\mathbf{v}=\begin{pmatrix} 1 \\ 2 \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;. Let's consider the following:
: &lt;math&gt;2\mathbf{v}=\begin{pmatrix} 2 \\ 4 \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;
: &lt;math&gt;-\mathbf{v}=\begin{pmatrix} -1 \\ -2 \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;
: &lt;math&gt;3\mathbf{v}=\begin{pmatrix} 3 \\ 6 \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;

If we have the equation &amp;lambda;'''v''', it is clear that for each choice of &amp;lambda; we choose, we get a different point on the line ''y''=2''x''. 

We can now generalize this idea into the ''vector equation of the line'' (and it is not restricted to 2 dimensions either).

The vector equation of a line is given by
: '''x'''=&amp;lambda;'''v''' (for a scalar &amp;lambda;)
where '''v''' is a vector parallel (which then, could lie) on the line. &amp;lambda; then, is the unknown in the equation. '''x''' is then the dependant vector variable.

=== Vector equation of the plane ===
Now consider a plane. If we have two nonparallel vectors lying on the plane and we add them, we can add a linear combination (that is, add the two vectors, which are multiplied only by scalars) to choose some other vector. The set of all vectors under linear combinations of these two vectors form a plane.
&lt;!-- a picture speaks a thousand words --&gt;

More simply, if we have two nonparallel vectors '''a''' and '''b''' we can form any other vector parallel to '''a''' and '''b''' by:
: &amp;lambda;&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;'''a'''+&amp;lambda;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;'''b'''='''x'''
where &amp;lambda;&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; and &amp;lambda;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; are both scalars.

== Further algebra and geometry of vectors ==
There are other operations on vectors which we can perform. These operations we will consider have very real and significant geometric meanings.

=== Magnitude ===
The ''magnitude'' of a vector is its length in '''R'''&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;

=== The dot product===
The ''dot product'' of two vectors is defined as the sum of the products of the components. Symbolically we write
: &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} a_1 \\ a_2 \\ \vdots \\ a_n \end{pmatrix}\cdot\begin{pmatrix}b_1 \\ b_2 \\ \vdots \\b_n \end{pmatrix} = a_1b_1 + a_2b_2 + \ldots + a_nb_n&lt;/math&gt;

For example,
: &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} 3 \\ 5 \end{pmatrix}\cdot\begin{pmatrix} 1 \\ -2 \end{pmatrix}=3-10=-7&lt;/math&gt;

==== Properties of the dot product ====
If we have '''a''' and '''b''' as vectors,
: '''a''' &amp;middot; '''b''' = '''b''' &amp;middot; '''a'''
: ''c''('''a''' &amp;middot; '''b''') = '''ca'''&amp;middot;'''b''' = '''a'''&amp;middot;'''cb'''
where ''c'' is a scalar.

==== Geometry of the dot product ====
&lt;!-- Need a nice pictorial proof of the equivalence of the forms --&gt;
The dot product of two vectors has an alternate form:
: &lt;math&gt; \mathbf{a}\cdot\mathbf{b}=|\mathbf{a}||\mathbf{b}|\cos{\theta}&lt;/math&gt;
If we pick a vector '''c'''='''a'''-'''b''' to form a triangle, we can show that these two forms are indeed equivalent by trigonometry.

The angle &amp;theta; then is important, as it shows that the dot product of two vectors is related to the angle between them. More specifically, we can calculate the dot product of two vectors - if the dot product is zero we can then say that the two vectors are perpendicular.

For example, consider simply
: &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} 1 \\ 1 \end{pmatrix}\cdot\begin{pmatrix}1 \\ -1\end{pmatrix}=1-1=0&lt;/math&gt;
Plot these vectors on the plane and verify for yourself that these vectors are perpendicular.

=== Cross product ===
The ''cross product'' is a more complicated product to define, but has a nice geometric property. We will only look at the cross product in three dimensions, since it is the most commonly used in three dimensions and it is difficult to define in greater dimensions.

For a vector with three components, the cross product is defined as
: &lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix} a_1 \\ a_2 \\ a_3 \end{pmatrix}\times\begin{pmatrix}b_1 \\ b_2 \\ b_3 \end{pmatrix} = 
\begin{vmatrix} 
\mathbf{i} &amp; \mathbf{j} &amp; \mathbf{k} \\
a_1 &amp; a_2 &amp; a_3 \\
b_1 &amp; b_2 &amp; b_3 \\ \end{vmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;

where
:&lt;math&gt;\mathbf{i}=\begin{pmatrix} 1 \\ 0 \\ 0 \end{pmatrix}, \mathbf{j}=\begin{pmatrix} 0 \\ 1 \\ 0 \end{pmatrix}, \mathbf{k}=\begin{pmatrix} 0 \\ 0 \\ 1 \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;

If you have not done Matricies before, here is a formula to work out from above...

=  '''i''' &lt;math&gt;(a_2 b_3 - a_3 b_2)&lt;/math&gt;  - '''j'''&lt;math&gt; (a_1 b_3 - a_3 b_1)&lt;/math&gt;+ '''k''' &lt;math&gt;(a_1 b_2 - a_2 b_1)&lt;/math&gt;

==== Properties of the cross product ====
The cross product has some properties
: '''a'''&amp;times;'''b''' = -'''b'''&amp;times;'''a'''
which is easily verified from the above definition, and
: '''c'''&amp;times;('''a'''+'''b''') = '''c'''&amp;times;'''a'''+'''c'''&amp;times;'''b'''
 

==== Geometric properties of the cross product ====
The cross product has some interesting geometric properties. 

If '''a''' and '''b''' are two vectors, '''a'''&amp;times;'''b''' is the vector perpendicular to both. Now if we have two vectors, we have ''two'' choices of vector perpendicular to '''a''' and '''b''' - if we switch the order of the cross product we obtain the other vector.

The magnitude of the cross product of two vectors is the area of the parallelogram formed by these two vectors.

The ''scalar triple product'', '''a'''&amp;middot;('''b'''&amp;times;'''c''') is the volume of the paralleliped formed by these three vectors. &lt;!-- needs a pic --&gt;

== See also==
* [[w:Vector (spatial)|Vectors at Wikipedia]]

[[Category:Linear Algebra|{{SUBPAGENAME}}]]</text>
      <sha1>beokfhzzvwkuvsit36ruxgqnzsvbiok</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Organic Chemistry/Introduction to reactions/Review of nucleophilic substitution</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1477</id>
    <revision>
      <id>961171</id>
      <parentid>646678</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-09-07T18:34:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>removing all sub-pages from [[Category:Chemistry]], reformatting book main pages to use {{Subject}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{| WIDTH=&quot;75%&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;background-color: #FFF7F7; border: solid 1px #FFBDBD; padding: 1em;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; |
&lt;H2&gt;Mechanism shared by S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;1 and S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;2 &lt;/H2&gt;

R-X (electrophile) + Nu- (nucleophile) -&gt; Nu-R (product) + X- (leaving group)
|}

Remeber, S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;1 and S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;2 are the same reaction just undergoing a different mechanism.


{| WIDTH=&quot;75%&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;background-color: #FFF7F7; border: solid 1px #FFBDBD; padding: 1em;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; |
&lt;H2&gt;S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;1 quick sheet &lt;/H2&gt;

*rate-determining step is '''unimolecular'''
*has carbocation intermediate
*favored by tertiary carbons that can support carbocation
*works better in a polar protic solvent (solvation effect)
* tertiary &gt;&gt; secondary electrophile
|}


{| WIDTH=&quot;75%&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;background-color: #FFF7F7; border: solid 1px #FFBDBD; padding: 1em;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; |
&lt;H2&gt;S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;2 quick sheet &lt;/H2&gt;

*rate-determining step is '''bimolecular'''
*no carbocation intermediate
*nucleophile assists leaving group
*works better in a polar aprotic solvent 
*methyl &gt; primary &gt;&gt; secondary elecrophile
*steric effects important, favoring small nucleophiles
|}

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>0o96qx2tz2jsyw7kl9p2zuqbwsoleba</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Organic Chemistry/Alcohols</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1478</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2625032</id>
      <parentid>2625029</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-04-02T16:51:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>1.38.21.200</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Synthesis from an Aldehyde */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Alcohols''' are the family of compounds that contain one or more '''hydroxyl (-OH)''' groups attached to a single bonded alkane. Alcohols are represented by the general formula R-OH. Alcohols are important in organic chemistry because they can be converted to and from many other types of compounds. Reactions with alcohols fall into two different categories. Reactions can cleave the R-O bond or they can cleave the O-H bond.

Ethanol (ethyl alcohol, or grain alcohol) is found in alcoholic beverages, CH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;CH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;OH.

=Preparation=

In the [[Organic_Chemistry/Alkenes|Alkenes]] section, we already covered a few methods for synthesizing alcohols. One is the hydroboration-oxidation of alkenes and the other is the oxymercuration-reduction of alkenes. But there are a great many other ways of creating alcohols as well.

A common source for producing alcohols is from carbonyl compounds. The choice of carbonyl type (ketone, aldehyde, ester, etc.) and the type of reaction (Grignard addition or Reduction), will determine the product(s) you will get. Fortunately, there are a number of variations of carbonyls, leading to a number of choices in product.

There are primarily two types of reactions used to create alcohols from carbonyls: Grignard Addition reactions and Reduction reactions. We'll look at each type of reaction for each type of carbonyl.

===Grignard Addition Reactions===

As we learned previously, [[Organic_Chemistry/Haloalkanes#Grignard_reagents|Grignard reagents]] are created by reacting magnesium metal with an alkyl halide (aka [[Organic Chemistry/Haloalkanes|haloalkanes]]). The magnesium atom then gets between the alkyl group and the halogen atom with the general reaction:

R-X + Mg &amp;rarr; R-Mg-X

In our examples, we'll be using bromine in our Grignard reagents because it's a common Grignard halogen and it will keep our examples a little clearer without the need for X.

[[Image:Grignard-Reaction_Mechanism.png|thumb|600px|center|Mechanism of Grignard reagent reacting with a carbonyl]]

The general mechanism of a Grignard reagent reacting with a carbonyl (except esters) involves the creation of a 6-membered ring transition state. The pi bond of the oxygen attacks a neighboring magnesium bromide which in turn, releases from its R group leaving a carbocation. At the same time, the magnesium bromide ion from another Grignard molecule is attacked by the carbocation and has its magnesium bromide ion stolen (restoring it to its original state as a Grignard reagent). The second molecule's carbocation is then free to attack the carbanion resulting from the vacating pi bond, attaching the R group to the carbonyl.

At this point, there is a magnesium bromide on the oxygen of what was a carbonyl. The proton from the acidic solvent easily displaces this magnesium bromide ion and protonates the oxygen, creating a primary alcohol with formaldehyde, a secondary alcohol with an aldehyde and a tertiary alcohol with a ketone.

With esters, the mechanism is slightly different. Two moles of Grignard are required for each mole of the ester. Initially, the pi bond on the carbonyl oxygen attacks the magnesium bromide ion. This opens up the carbon for attack from the R group of the Grignard. This part of the reaction is slow because of the dual oxygens off of the carbon providing some resonance stabilization. The oxygen's pi bond then re-forms, expelling the O-R group of the ester which then joins with the magnesium bromide, leaving R-O-MgBr and a ketone. The R-O-MgBr is quickly protonated from the acidic solution and the ketone is then attacked by Grignard reagent via the mechanism described earlier.

====Synthesis from Formaldehyde====

[[Image:Alcohols_from_formaldehyde_via_grignard.png|thumb|600px|center|Synthesis of alcohol from formaldehyde and Grignard reagent]]

The image above shows the synthesis of an alcohol from formaldehyde reacted with a Grignard reagent. When a formaldehyde is the target of the Grignard's attack, the result is a primary alcohol.

====Synthesis from an Aldehyde====

[[Image:Alcohols_from_aldehyde_via_grignard.png|thumb|600px|center|Synthesis of alcohol from an aldehyde and Grignard reagent]]

The image above shows the synthesis of an alcohol from an aldehyde reacted with a Grignard reagent. When an aldehyde is the target of the Grignard's attack, the result is a secondary alcohol.

====Synthesis from a Ketone====

[[Image:Alcohols_from_ketone_via_grignard.png|thumb|600px|center|Synthesis of alcohol from an ketone and Grignard reagent]]

The image above shows the synthesis of an alcohol from a ketone reacted with a Grignard reagent.
When a ketone is the target of the Grignard's attack, the result is a tertiary alcohol.

====Synthesis from an Ester====

[[Image:Alcohols_from_ester_via_grignard.png|thumb|600px|center|Synthesis of alcohol from an ester and Grignard reagent]]

The image above shows the synthesis of an alcohol from an ester reacted with a Grignard reagent.
When an ester is the target of the Grignard's attack, the result is a tertiary alcohol and a primary alcohol. The primary alcohol is always from the -O-R portion of the ester and the tertiary alcohol is the other R groups of the ester combined with the R group from the Grignard reagent.

====Synthesis from an Epoxide====

[[Image:Alcohols_from_epoxides_via_grignard.png|thumb|600px|center|Synthesis of alcohol from an epoxide and Grignard reagent]]

We will discuss reactions with Epoxides later when we cover epoxides, but for now, we'll briefly discuss the synthesis of an alcohol from an epoxide. The nature of the reaction is different than with the carbonyls, as might be expected. The reaction of Grignard reagents with epoxides is regioselective. The Grignard reagent attacks at the least substituted side of the carbon-oxygen bonds, if there is one. In this case, one carbon has 2 hydrogens and the other has 1, so the R group attacks the carbon with 2 hydrogens, breaking the bond with oxygen which is then protonated by the acidic solution. leaving a secondary alcohol and a concatenated carbon chain. The R group can be alkyl or aryl.


====Organolithium Alternative====

As an alternative to Grignard reagents, organolithium reagents can be used as well. Organolithium reagents are slightly more reactive, but produce the same general results as Grignard reagents, including the synthesis from epoxides.

===Reduction===

====Synthesis from an Aldehyde====

[[Image:Alcohols_from_aldehyde_via_reduction.png|thumb|600px|center|Synthesis of alcohol from an aldehyde by reduction.]]

The image above shows the synthesis of an alcohol from an aldehyde  by reduction.

====Synthesis from a Ketone====

[[Image:Alcohols_from_ketone_via_reduction.png|thumb|600px|center|Synthesis of alcohol from an aldehyde by reduction]]

The image above shows the synthesis of an alcohol from a ketone  by reduction.


====Synthesis from an Ester====

[[Image:Alcohols_from_ester_via_reduction.png|thumb|600px|center|Synthesis of alcohol from an ester by reduction]]

The image above shows the synthesis of an alcohol from an ester  by reduction.  Esters can be hydrolysed to form an alcohol and a carboxylic acid.

====Synthesis from a Carboxylic Acid====

[[Image:Alcohols_from_carboxylic_acid_via_reduction.png|thumb|600px|center|Synthesis of alcohol from a carboxylic acid by reduction]]

The image above shows the synthesis of an alcohol from a carboxylic acid reacted  by reduction.

=Properties=

==Naming alcohols==
Follow these rules to name alcohols the IUPAC way:

#find the longest carbon chain containing at least one OH group, this is the parent
##if there are multiple OH groups, look for the chain with the most of them, and the way to count as many carbons in that chain
##name as an alcohol, alkane diol, triol, etc.
#number the OH groups, giving each group the lowest number possible when different numbering possibilities exist
#treat all other groups as lower priority substituents (alcohol / hydroxy groups are the highest priority group for naming)

===Example alcohols===

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!  
! IUPAC name
! Common name
|-
| CH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;CH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;OH || Ethanol
| Ethyl alcohol
|-
| CH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;CH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;CH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-OH
| 1-Propanol || n-Propyl alcohol
|-
| (CH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;CH-OH || 2-Propanol
| Isopropyl alcohol (Note: Isopropanol would be incorrect. Cannot mix
and match between systems.)
|-
|
 || 2-Ethylbutan-1-ol || 2-Ethylbutanol
|-
|
 || 3-Methyl-3-pentanol ||
|-
|
 || 2,2-Dimethylcyclopropanol ||
|-
| Multiple OH functional groups || ||
|-
|
 || 1,2-Ethanediol || Ethylene glycol
|-
|
 || 1,1-Ethanediol || Acetaldehyde hydrate
|-
|
 || 1,4-Cyclohexanediol ||
|-
| (form that body fat is stored as) || 1,2,3-Propanetriol
| Glycerol
|-
| &lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;OH can be named as a substituent hydroxyl group (hydroxyalkanes)
|
 ||
|-
|
 || 1,2-Di(hydroxymethyl)cyclohexane
|
|-
|
 || 2-(hydroxymethyl)-1,3-propanediol
|
|-
| Find the longest chain of carbons containing the maximum number of
&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;OH groups
|
 ||
|-
|
| 1-(1-hydroxyethyl)-1-methylcyclopropane
|
|-
|
 || 2-(1-methylcyclopropyl)ethanol ||
|-
|
| 2-(2-hydroxyethyl)-2-methylcyclopropanol
|
|-
|
| 3-(2-hydroxyethyl)-3-methyl-1,2-cyclopropanediol
|
|}

==Acidity==
&lt;!-- Review general topics of acidity and basicity [[Organic Chemistry/Foundational concepts of organic chemistry/Acids and bases|here]]. --&gt;

In an O-H bond, the O steals the H's electron due to its electronegativity, and O can carry a negative charge (R-O&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;). This leads to '''deprotonation''' in which the nucleus of the H, a proton, leaves completely. This makes the -OH group (and alcohols) Bronsted acids.  Alcohols are weak acids, even weaker than water. Ethanol has a pKa of 15.9 compared to water's pKa of 15.7. The larger the alcohol molecule, the weaker an acid it is.

On the other hand, alcohols are also weakly basic.  This may seem to be contradictory--how can a substance be both an acid and a base?  However, substances exist that can be an acid or a base depending on the circumstances.  Such a compound is said to be amphoteric or amphiprotic.  As a Bronsted base, the oxygen atom in the -OH group can accept a proton (hydrogen ion.) This results in a positively-charged species known as an oxonium ion.  Oxonium ions have the general formula ROH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;, where R is any alkyl group.

==Alkoxides==

When O becomes deprotonated, the result is an '''alkoxide'''. Alkoxides are anions. The names of alkoxides are based on the original molecule. (Ethanol=ethoxide, butanol=butoxide, etc.)
Alkoxides are good nucleophiles due to the negative charge on the oxygen atom.

===Producing an alkoxide===

R-OH -&gt; H&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; + R-O&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;

In this equation, R-O&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; is the alkoxide produced and is the conjugate base of R-OH
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

Alcohols can be converted into alkoxides by reaction with a strong base (must be stronger than OH&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;) or reaction with metallic sodium or potassium. Alkoxides themselves are basic. The larger an alkoxide molecule is, the more basic it is.

=Reactions=

==Conversion of alcohols to haloalkanes==

Recall that haloalkanes can be converted to alcohols through nucleophilic substitution.


{| WIDTH=&quot;75%&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;background-color: #F3F3FF; border: solid 1px #D6D6FF; padding: 1em;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; |
&lt;H2&gt;Conversion of a haloalkane to an alcohol&lt;/H2&gt;
R-X + OH&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; &amp;rarr; R-OH + X&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;
|}

This reaction proceeds because X (a halogen) is a good leaving group and OH&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; is a good nucleophile. OH, however, is a poor leaving group. To make the reverse reaction proceed, OH must become a good leaving group. This is done by protonating the OH, turning it into H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;, which is a good leaving group. H&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; must be present to do this. Therefore, the compounds that can react with alcohols to form haloalkanes are HBr, HCl, and HI. Just like the reverse reaction, this process can occur through S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;2 (backside attack) or S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;1 (carbocation intermediate) mechanisms.


{| WIDTH=&quot;75%&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;background-color: #F3F3FF; border: solid 1px #D6D6FF; padding: 1em;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; |

&lt;H2&gt;S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;2 conversion of an alcohol to a haloalkane&lt;/H2&gt;
R-O-H + H&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; + X&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; &amp;rarr; R-O&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;-H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; + X&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; &amp;rarr; R-X + H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O
|}


{| WIDTH=&quot;75%&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;background-color: #F3F3FF; border: solid 1px #D6D6FF; padding: 1em;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; |
&lt;H2&gt;S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;1 conversion of an alcohol to a haloalkane&lt;/H2&gt;
R-O-H + H&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; + X&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; &amp;rarr; R-O&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;-H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; + X&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; &amp;rarr; R&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; + H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O + X&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; &amp;rarr; R-X + H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O
|}

As stated in the haloalkane chapter, the two mechanisms look similar but the mechanism affects the rate of reaction and the stereochemistry of the product.

==Oxidation of alcohols==

Oxidation in organic chemistry always involves either the addition of oxygen atoms (or other highly electronegative elements like sulfur or nitrogen) or the removal of hydrogen atoms. Whenever a molecule is oxidized, another molecule must be reduced. Therefore, these reactions require a compound that can be reduced. These compounds are usually inorganic. They are referred to as ''oxidizing reagents''.

With regards to alcohol, oxidizing reagents can be strong or weak. Weak reagants are able to oxidize a primary alcohol group into a aldehyde group and a secondary alcohol into a ketone.  Thus, the R-OH (alcohol) functional group becomes R=O (carbonyl) after a hydrogen atom is removed.  Strong reagents will further oxidize the aldehyde into a carboxylic acid (COOH). Tertiary alcohols cannot be oxidized.

An example of a strong oxidizing reagent is chromic acid (H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;CrO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;). An example of a weak oxidizing reagent is pyridinium chlorochromate (PCC) (C&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;NCrO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;Cl).

&lt;noinclude&gt;
----
[[Organic Chemistry/Haloalkanes|&lt;&lt; Haloalkanes]] | Alcohols | [[Organic Chemistry/Alkenes|Alkenes &gt;&gt;]]
&lt;/noinclude&gt;

{{BookCat}}
[[id:Kimia Organik/Alkohol]]</text>
      <sha1>6f4lkp43edxdblcnu4z3t6k4bgrl2af</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Organic Chemistry/Introduction to reactions/Free-radical halogenation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1481</id>
    <revision>
      <id>961193</id>
      <parentid>616072</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-09-07T18:35:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>removing all sub-pages from [[Category:Chemistry]], reformatting book main pages to use {{Subject}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">__NOTOC__
==Free-radical halogenation==
Free-radical halogenation is &quot;a way to do a substitution other than by nucleophilic substitution.&quot;


{| WIDTH=&quot;75%&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;background-color: #F3F3FF; border: solid 1px #E7E7FF; padding: 1em;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; |
RH (hydrocarbon) + X&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; (halogen) -&gt; RX (haloalkane) + HX (byproduct)
|}

''or, simplified:''


{| WIDTH=&quot;75%&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;background-color: #F3F3FF; border: solid 1px #E7E7FF; padding: 1em;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; |
RH + X&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;rarr; RX + HX
|}

H's come off as H&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; not H&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;, making nucleophilic substitution impossible.


{| WIDTH=&quot;75%&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;background-color: #F3F3FF; border: solid 1px #E7E7FF; padding: 1em;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; |
CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; Br&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;/-&gt; No reaction
|}

We must first remove a H&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; to perform the reaction.

Free radicals as a rule violate the octet rule and are highly reactive, reacting even with strong bonds.


{| WIDTH=&quot;75%&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;background-color: #F3F3FF; border: solid 1px #E7E7FF; padding: 1em;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; |
&lt;H2&gt;Creating a free radical&lt;/H2&gt;

Br&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; heat or light/-&gt; 2Br&amp;deg; free radicals
|}


{| WIDTH=&quot;75%&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;background-color: #F3F3FF; border: solid 1px #E7E7FF; padding: 1em;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; |
&lt;H2&gt;Bromine radical reacting with (relatively unreactive) methane&lt;/H2&gt;

Br&amp;deg; + CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; -&gt; HBR + H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;C&amp;deg;
|}

''then''


{| WIDTH=&quot;75%&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;background-color: #F3F3FF; border: solid 1px #E7E7FF; padding: 1em;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; |
&lt;H2&gt;&lt;/H2&gt;
H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;C&amp;deg;  + Br&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; -&gt; CH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;Br + Br&amp;deg;
(and radical produced continues reacting with surrounding molecules)
|}

The reaction continues happening in a chain mechanism called a '''free radical chain reaction.'''

==Free radical chain reaction==
This has three steps:

#'''Initiation step:''' this generates radicals
#'''Propagation step:''' this is where the bulk of the action lies. Chain carriers generate reaction products.
#'''Termination step:''' anything that consumes the free radicals. 


{| WIDTH=&quot;75%&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;background-color: #F3F3FF; border: solid 1px #E7E7FF; padding: 1em;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; |
&lt;H2&gt;Termination step examples&lt;/H2&gt;


Br + CH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;Br -&gt; BrCH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; + Br

&lt;H2&gt;Note&lt;/H2&gt;

Fluorine gas is too reactive and does not undergo this sort of reaction as it explodes. Iodine doesn't work very well either as it is too unreactive. So the reaction works only for Cl and Br, the reaction with Cl running a bit faster than with Br.
|}

Running free radical chain reactions with Chlorine and Bromine yield their respective end products in different proportions, a quality that can be useful in the laboratory.

(insert image here)

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>hl3jh4syge5ej2bzqqbhdo6l93622qb</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>