<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>Spanish/Exercises/Regular Verbs - Solutions</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1171</id>
    <revision>
      <id>532392</id>
      <parentid>482817</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-07-22T07:35:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">Soluciones a los [[Spanish/Exercises/Regular_Verbs|ejercicios]].
''Solutions to the [[Spanish/Exercises/Regular_Verbs|exercises]]''

--------
=== Rellena los espacios en blanco ===

=== ''Fill in the blank'' ===

Por favor, rellena los espacios en blanco con la forma correcta del verbo:
''Please, fill in the blank with the correct form of the verb:''

1. Nosotros '''aprendemos''' español.
''We learn Spanish.''

2. Yo '''compro''' un libro.
''I buy a book.''

3. Carmen y Roberto '''viajan''' a Mexico.
''Carmen and Roberto travel to Mexico.''

4. Ana '''habla''' ingles.
''Ana speaks English.''

5. Tú '''bebes''' una cerveza.
''You drink a beer.''

6. Susana '''escribe''' una carta.
''Susana writes a letter.''

7. Los niños '''estudian''' para el examen.
''The children study for the exam.''

8. Fernando y Lucas '''cantan''' una cancion.
''Fernando and Lucas sing a song.''

9. Tú '''lees''' un libro.
''You read a book.''

10. Vosotros '''subís''' las escaleras.
''You (plural) climb the stairs.''
----------------------------------------
[[Spanish/Exercises/Regular_Verbs|Enlace a los Ejercicios]] ''Link to exercices''


[[Spanish/Lesson_3|Enlace a la lección 3]] ''Link to the lesson 3.''

[[Category:Spanish]]</text>
      <sha1>3etxqboa9najtdtjc5k7j2un83v75gt</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Botany/Introduction discussion</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1195</id>
    <revision>
      <id>489689</id>
      <parentid>489688</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-06-17T15:16:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[Botany:Introduction discussion]] moved to [[Botany/Introduction discussion]]: naming convention</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">== Further Discussion ==
The questions posed in '''Chapter 1. Introduction''' are discussed further on this page. Remember, some questions are intended to be thought-provoking and more than one answer may be &quot;correct&quot;. Users are encouraged to expand upon the discussions here.   

 1-1. ''Do you think the ''scientific method'' is something only a scientist would use?''

The ''scientific method'' is something that is taught, so we might question just how natural or intuitive an approach it is. Think about how you discovered answers to interesting or difficult questions as a child. You might have first sought the opinion of an expert (like your dad, right?). That is the first step used by a scientist as well.  Scientists learn to seek the expertise of others that have asked similar questions and come up with at least partial answers. This does not require contacting other scientists; more often it is a matter of becoming very familiar with the literature (the written and published record) on the subject of interest. Scientists rarely formulate ''hypotheses'' without first learning all they can about a subject from what has been published already. In effect, they learn how to put their question at the very forefront of knowledge about a subject.  There are so many questions to be answered in science that no one would want to expend a lot of energy asking and answering questions to mysteries already solved. Of course learning is different.  Asking questions and seeking answers from books, journals, and other sources is a valid approach to this first step of learning, and one you and any scientist would have in common.

Formulating a proper question or a hypothesis is perhaps the most difficult step. Recall that the '''hypothesis''' is not really a question but an answer.  The question is the wonder about something; the hypothesis is a testable answer to that question. It is not THE answer, just a reasonable one posed in such a way that an experiment can be conducted to ascertain its validity.  You may see this step expressed as ''making a guess''; but consider that after he or she has completed the step described above&amp;mdash;learning everything written about a subject&amp;mdash;the scientist is in a position to make a pretty good guess. This step could be difficult for the scientist because he or she must have in mind one or more experiments to conduct to test the hypothesis. This step may be difficult for you for the same reason, and because it probably feels odd to answer a question before investigating it. The hypothesis step is included in the scientific method to promote intellectual honesty and to allow others to better understand a scientist's reasoning when reviewing what was done and how a conclusion was reached.
Compare these scenarios:
:&lt;tt&gt;Conversation over a radio from technician defusing a bomb&lt;/tt&gt; &amp;ndash;

::''OK. I have the device out. There are two black wires and a red one to the timer. Let me try this''...&lt;BOOM&gt;!

&lt;center&gt;Or&lt;/center&gt;

::''OK. I have the device out. There are two black wires and a red one to the timer.''
::''I think the red one controls the detonation'' (Hypothesis: An intact red wire is necessary for detonation)
::''I am going to cut the red wire'' (Testing the hypothesis)
::''oops'' &lt;BOOM&gt;

In the absence of any further report from this technician, only the second procedure provides any information to the next technician faced with a second, similar bomb. He at least knows what not to do! Note also that the hypothesis is '''falsifiable'''. Testing demonstrated whether an intact red wire was or was not needed for detonation (apparently it controlled the undetonated state).  Framing the hypothesis thusly: ''the red wire serves a purpose'' cannot be proven false; what test could you devise to satisfactorily demonstrate it has no purpose? It may in fact have no purpose (not in the example above), but eliminating by testing every possible purpose under the sun is an unsatisfactory approach.    
                         
----

  1-3. When you catch a cold a virus has infected your body.
       ''Why do you think there is reason to question whether the virus is living or not?''
       After all, if you took some ricinin (a plant poison), you would get very sick,
       but no one would suggest the toxin were alive or that the plant had entered your body.

Ricinin is an alkaloid and, along with the toxalbumin ricin (a plant protein), constitute extremely toxic substances found in the seeds of the castor bean (''Ricinus communis'')  plant. Were you to ingest several raw seeds, you would experience nausea and vomiting, stomachache, bloody diarrhea, headache, cold sweat, sleepiness, disorientation, fever, shortage of breath, seizures, and possibly collapse and death. While there are a number of different ways that a virus could enter your body, the most common would be breathing in virus particles while in the presence of an infected person. The outcome of such exposure could be pretty much the same as that described for ricinin ingestion, depending upon the type of virus and your body's ability to respond appropriately to the &quot;infection&quot;.  Or, perhaps the infection you &quot;catch&quot; is cholera&amp;mdash;the ''Vibrio cholerae'' bacterium. These bacteria are typically ingested in drinking water contaminated by improper sanitation.  Again, you might display many of the same symptoms described, including the really unpleasant part about dying. The point here is to consider which of these problems constitute an &quot;attack&quot; by another living organism and which represent simply a poisoning of your living body by a non-living chemical.  You cannot use the resulting symptoms as an indication because....; well, because they are just symptoms: what you &quot;feel&quot; as your body reacts to the chemical or biological attack.

In the case of ricin, this protein inhibits protein synthesis within the cells of the body.  Organ damage results. ''Vibrio cholerae'' in the body produce a chemical that results in a loss of fluid and salts across the lining of the gut. The resulting diarrhea allows the bacterium to spread to other people under unsanitary conditions, and can result in death due to dehydration (an inability to retain water). So both the non-living chemical and the living bacterium cause illness by toxicity to our bodily functions.

You should recognize one pretty significant difference between an illness caused by a living organisms and an illness caused by a non-living, but toxic, chemical.  In the latter case, the severity of our symptoms will be pretty much dependent upon the dose of toxin we ingest. There will be just so much chemical entering the body, and the damage should be proportional to that amount.  In the case of the bacterium, something like a million cells need to be ingested to result in an infection, but once established, the living organism is a tiny factory that cranks out toxin and reproduces more identical factories (more cells) that themselves produce toxin.  So the dose of toxin we get from the bacterial infection is not obviously limited.  Living cells metabolize (break down and produce chemicals for various purposes) and reproduce (increase their numbers).  

In essence, this is what is meant by an '''infection''': another life form has taken up residence in or on our body, and is utilizing organic substances that are a part of our life processes to carry out its life functions, to further its existence and numbers. In the case of chlorea, the bacterium has some nasty habits that make us very ill; but there are a number of other bacteria (''Escherichi coli'', for example) that live in perfect harmony within or digetive tract and help us digest food.  So not every &quot;alien&quot; that invades our body necessarily causes an infection.

              
           
----
&lt;&lt; [[Botany/Introduction_Botany|Chapter 1]]

[[Category:Botany]]</text>
      <sha1>0kf5yuxevct0bz2rv7rbmdtx2t7p07y</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Lojban/Dates</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1200</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518435</id>
      <parentid>461003</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-07-11T21:26:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">There are two systems of naming months in use: one based on the zodiac, and one based on numbers. The place structure is &quot;x1 is foomonth in year x2 in calendar x3&quot;; this is not according to jvojva but makes it easy to specify dates as &quot;the day nth of the foomonth of the year mmmm&quot;. 

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!English name!!Zodiac name!!Number name
|-
|January||kanbyma'i||pavma'i
|-
|February||jaurbeima'i||relma'i
|-
|March||fipma'i||cibma'i
|-
|April||lanma'i||vonma'i
|-
|May||bakma'i||mumyma'i
|-
|June||matsi'uma'i||xavma'i
|-
|July||mlajukma'i||zelma'i
|-
|August||cinfyma'i||bivma'i
|-
|September||xlima'i||sozma'i
|-
|October||laxma'i||pavnonma'i
|-
|November||rebjukma'i||pavypavma'i
|-
|December||celma'i||pavrelma'i
|}

There are also systems of naming the days of the week based on Oriental elements and numbers. 

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!English name!!Oriental el. name!!Number name
|-
|Monday||lurdei||pavdei
|-
|Tuesday||fagdei||reldei
|-
|Wednesday||jaurdei||cibdei
|-
|Thursday||mudydei||vondei
|-
|Friday||jimdei||mumdei
|-
|Saturday||tedydei||xavdei
|-
|Sunday||soldei||zeldei ''or'' nondei
|}

Note that Sunday in Lojban is either day seven or day zero, depending on your perspective.

[[Category:Lojban]]</text>
      <sha1>57jyus5xym99xnc6u1b04wk3qw71r1d</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Lojban/Directions</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1201</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1154901</id>
      <parentid>518437</parentid>
      <timestamp>2008-04-02T22:48:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>98.27.163.188</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt; [[Lojban]]

 N       north                 berti               B       0°00'
 NbE     north by east         bersunberberti      BDBB    11°15'
 NNE     north northeast       bersunberti         BDB     22°30'
 NEbN    northeast by north    bersunberstuna      BDBD    33°45'
 NE      northeast             berstuna            BD      45°00'
 NEbE    northeast by east     bersunsunberti      BDDB    56°15'
 ENE     east northeast        bersunstuna         BDD     67°30'
 EbN     east by north         bersunsunstuna      BDDD    78°45'
 &lt;font color=white&gt;|&lt;/font&gt;
 E       east                  stuna               D       90°00'
 EbS     east by south         nansunsunstuna      NDDD    101°15'
 ESE     east southeast        nansunstuna         NDD     112°30'
 SEbE    southeast by east     nansunsunsnanu      NDDN    123°45'
 SE      southeast             nanstuna            ND      135°00'
 SEbS    southeast by south    nansunynanstuna     NDND    146°15'
 SSE     south southeast       nansunsnanu         NDN     157°30'
 SbE     south by east         nansunynansnanu     NDNN    168°45'
 &lt;font color=white&gt;|&lt;/font&gt;
 S       south                 snanu               N       180°00'
 SbW     south by west         nansicnansnanu      NVNN    191°15'
 SSW     south southwest       nansicysnanu        NVN     202°30'
 SWbS    southwest by south    nansicnanstici      NVNV    213°45'
 SW      southwest             nanstici            NV      225°00'
 SWbW    southwest by west     nansicysicysnanu    NVVN    236°15'
 WSW     west southwest        nansicystici        NVV     247°30'
 WbS     west by south         nansicysicystici    NVVV    258°45'
 &lt;font color=white&gt;|&lt;/font&gt;
 W       west                  stici               V       270°00'
 WbN     west by north         bersicysicystici    BVVV    281°15'
 WNW     west northwest        bersicystici        BVV     292°30'
 NWbW    northwest by west     bersicysicyberti    BVVB    303°45'
 NW      northwest             berstici            BV      315°00'
 NWbN    northwest by north    bersicyberstici     BVBV    326°15'
 NNW     north northwest       bersicyberti        BVB     337°30'
 NbW     north by west         bersicyberberti     BVBB    348°45'

[[Category:Lojban]]</text>
      <sha1>3nfajregjhb6zzqd5a630bbnv8ora0u</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Lojban/Le ninmu cu te dunda le ninmu le gerku</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1202</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518441</id>
      <parentid>408261</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-07-11T21:27:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Lojban==
le ninmu cu te dunda le gerku&lt;br&gt;

.uinaicaidai zo'e na prami le ninmu&lt;br&gt;
.i .a'ucu'idai le ninmu cu na junri zo'e&lt;br&gt;
.i .u'icu'idai le ninmu na cmila&lt;br&gt;
.i .iucu'idai le ninmu cu na prami zo'e&lt;br&gt;

.i .a'odai le nanmu cu klama le ninmu la kentykis.&lt;br&gt;
.i .i'odai le nanmu cu dunda le gerku le ninmu&lt;br&gt;
.i .oidai le nanmu cu klama la kentykis. le ninmu&lt;br&gt;

.i .uiru'edai le gerku cu prami le ninmu&lt;br&gt;
.i .a'uru'edai le ninmu cu junri le gerku&lt;br&gt;
.i .u'idai le ninmu cu cmila&lt;br&gt;
.i .iucaidai le ninmu cu prami le gerku&lt;br&gt;

==English==
The Woman Receives a Dog&lt;br&gt;

Sadness! The woman is not loved.&lt;br&gt;
Disinterest! The woman doesn't have a gravity for anything.&lt;br&gt;
No amusement! The woman doesn't laugh.&lt;br&gt;
No love! The woman doesn't love.&lt;br&gt;

Hope! The man goes to the woman from Kentucky.&lt;br&gt;
Appreciation! The man gives the dog to the woman.&lt;br&gt;
Complaint! The man goes to Kentucky from the woman.&lt;br&gt;

A little happiness! The dog loves the woman.&lt;br&gt;
A little interest! The woman has a gravity for the dog.&lt;br&gt;
Amusement! The woman laughs.&lt;br&gt;
Lots of love! The woman loves the dog.

[[Category:Lojban]]</text>
      <sha1>5nge7gt21h5t08kbjvdrnvjz4anpyrn</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>US History/New Nation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1203</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2691983</id>
      <parentid>2584625</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-16T16:34:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Rotlink</username>
        <id>761486</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>fixing dead links</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">== The Articles of Confederation ==

''(The following text is taken from Wikipedia)''

The '''Articles of Confederation and Perpetual Union''', also the '''Articles of Confederation''', was the governing constitution of the alliance of thirteen independent and sovereign states styled &quot;United States of America.&quot; The Article's ratification (proposed in 1777) was completed in 1782, legally uniting the states by compact into the &quot;United States of America&quot; as a union with a confederation government. Under the Articles (and the succeeding Constitution) the states retained sovereignty over all governmental functions not specifically deputed to the confederation. 

The final draft of the Articles was written in the summer of 1777 and adopted by the Second Continental Congress on November 15, 1777 in York, Pennsylvania after a year of debate. In practice the final draft of the Articles served as the ''de facto'' system of government used by the Congress (&quot;the United States in Congress assembled&quot;) until it became ''de jure'' by final ratification on March 1, 1781; at which point Congress became the Congress of the Confederation. The ''Articles'' set the rules for operations of the &quot;United States&quot; confederation. The confederation was capable of making war, negotiating diplomatic agreements, and resolving issues regarding the western territories; it could mint coins and borrow inside and outside the United States. An important element of the Articles was that Article XIII stipulated that &quot;their provisions shall be inviolably observed by every state&quot; and &quot;the Union shall be perpetual.&quot; This article was put to the test in the American Civil War.

The Articles were created by the chosen representatives of the states in the Second Continental Congress out of a perceived need to have &quot;a plan of confederacy for securing the freedom, sovereignty, and independence of the United States.&quot; Although serving a crucial role in the attainment of nationhood for the thirteen states, a group of reformers, known as &quot;federalists&quot;, felt that the Articles lacked the necessary provisions for a sufficiently effective government. Fundamentally, a federation was sought to replace the confederation. The key criticism by those who favored a more powerful central state (i.e. the federalists) was that the government (i.e. the Congress of the Confederation) lacked taxing authority; it had to request funds from the states. Another criticism of the Articles was that they did not strike the right balance between large and small states in the legislative decision making process. Due to its ''one-state, one-vote'' plank, the larger states were expected to contribute more but had only one vote. The Articles were replaced by the United States Constitution on June 21, 1788. 

===Background===
The political push for the colonies to increase cooperation began in the French and Indian Wars in the mid 1750s.  The opening of the American Revolutionary War in 1775 induced the various states to cooperate in seceding from the British Empire. The Second Continental Congress starting 1775 acted as the confederation organ that ran the war. Congress presented the Articles for enactment by the states in 1777, while prosecuting the American Revolutionary war against the Kingdom of Great Britain.

===Ratification===
Congress began to move for ratification of the Articles in 1777:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
''The articles can always be candidly reviewed under a sense of the difficulty of combining in one general system the various sentiments and interests of a continent divided into so many sovereign and independent communities, under a conviction of the absolute necessity of uniting all our councils and all our strength, to maintain and defend our common liberties...''&lt;ref name=ratificationletter&gt;[http://memory.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/r?ammem/hlaw:@field(DOCID+@lit(jc00941)) Monday, November 17 1777], Journals of the Continental Congress, 1774–1789. [http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/amlaw/lawhome.html A Century of Lawmaking, 1774-1873]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The document could not become officially effective until it was ratified by all of the thirteen colonies. The first state to ratify was Virginia on December 16, 1777. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
   |url=http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ho/time/ar/91719.htm
   |title=Articles of Confederation, 1777-1781
   |publisher=U.S. Department of State
   |accessdate=2008-01-26
|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20070915075849/http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ho/time/ar/91719.htm|archivedate=2007-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; The process dragged on for several years, stalled by the refusal of some states to rescind their claims to land in the West. Maryland was the last holdout; it refused to go along until Virginia and New York agreed to cede their claims in the Ohio River valley. A little over three years passed before Maryland's ratification on March 1, 1781.

===Article summaries===
Even though the Articles of Confederation and the Constitution were established by many of the same people, the two documents were very different. The original five-paged Articles contained thirteen articles, a conclusion, and a signatory section.  The following list contains short summaries of each of the thirteen articles.

#Establishes the name of the confederation as &quot;The United States of America.&quot;
#Asserts the precedence of the separate states over the confederation government, i.e. &quot;Each state retains its sovereignty, freedom, and independence, and every power, jurisdiction, and right, which is not by this Confederation expressly delegated.&quot;
#Establishes the United States as a league of states united &quot;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;. for their common defense, the security of their liberties, and their mutual and general welfare, binding themselves to assist each other, against all force offered to, or attacks made upon them .&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&quot;
#Establishes freedom of movement&amp;ndash;anyone can pass freely between states, excluding &quot;paupers, vagabonds, and fugitives from justice.&quot; All people are entitled to the rights established by the state into which he travels. If a crime is committed in one state and the perpetrator flees to another state, he will be extradited to and tried in the state in which the crime was committed.
#Allocates one vote in the Congress of the Confederation (United States in Congress Assembled) to each state, which was entitled to a delegation of between two and seven members. Members of Congress were appointed by state legislatures; individuals could not serve more than three out of any six years.
#Only the central government is allowed to conduct foreign relations and to declare war.  No states may have navies or standing armies, or engage in war, without permission of Congress (although the state militias are encouraged).  
#When an army is raised for common defense, colonels and military ranks below colonel will be named by the state legislatures.
#Expenditures by the United States will be paid by funds raised by state legislatures, and apportioned to the states based on the real property values of each.
#Defines the powers of the central government: to declare war, to set weights and measures (including coins), and for Congress to serve as a final court for disputes between states. 
#Defines a Committee of the States to be a government when Congress is not in session.
#Requires nine states to approve the admission of a new state into the confederacy; pre-approves Canada, if it applies for membership.
#Reaffirms that the Confederation accepts war debt incurred by Congress before the Articles.
#Declares that the Articles are perpetual, and can only be altered by approval of Congress with ratification by ''all'' the state legislatures.

Still at war with the Kingdom of Great Britain, the colonists were reluctant to establish another powerful national government. Jealously guarding their new independence, members of the Continental Congress created a loosely-structured unicameral legislature that protected the liberty of the individual states. While calling on Congress to regulate military and monetary affairs, for example, the Articles of Confederation provided no mechanism to force the states to comply with requests for troops or revenue. At times, this left the military in a precarious position, as George Washington wrote in a 1781 letter to the governor of Massachusetts, John Hancock.



===The end of the war===
The Treaty of Paris (1783), which ended hostilities with Great Britain, languished in Congress for months because state representatives failed to attend sessions of the national legislature. Yet Congress had no power to enforce attendance. Writing to George Clinton in September 1783, George Washington complained:

:''Congress have come to no determination &lt;em&gt;yet&lt;/em&gt; respecting the Peace Establishment nor am I able to say when they will. I have lately had a conference with a Committee on this subject, and have reiterated my former opinions, but it appears to me that there is not a sufficient representation to discuss &lt;em&gt;Great&lt;/em&gt; National points.''&lt;ref name=washingtonclinton&gt;[http://memory.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/r?ammem/mgw:@field(DOCID+@lit(gw270170)) Letter George Washington to George Clinton], September 11 1783. [http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/gwhtml/gwhome.html The George Washington Papers, 1741-1799]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Function===
The Articles supported the Congressional direction of the Continental Army, and allowed the 13 states to present a unified front when dealing with the European powers. As a tool to build a centralized war-making government, they were largely a failure, but since guerrilla warfare was correct strategy in a war against the British Empire's army, this &quot;failure&quot; succeeded in winning independence.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;While Washington and Steuben were taking the army in an ever more European direction, Lee in captivity was moving the other way — pursuing his insights into a fullfledged and elaborated proposal for guerrilla warfare. He presented his plan to Congress, as a &quot;Plan for the Formation of the American Army.&quot;

Bitterly attacking Steuben's training of the army according to the &quot;European Plan,&quot; Lee charged that fighting British regulars on their own terms was madness and courted crushing defeat: &quot;If the Americans are servilely kept to the European Plan, they will … be laugh'd at as a bad army by their enemy, and defeated in every [encounter]… . [The idea] that a decisive action in fair ground may be risqued is talking nonsense.&quot; Instead, he declared that &quot;a plan of defense, harassing and impeding can alone succeed,&quot; particularly if based on the rough terrain west of the Susquehannah River in Pennsylvania. He also urged the use of cavalry and of light infantry (in the manner of Dan Morgan), both forces highly mobile and eminently suitable for the guerrilla strategy.

This strategic plan was ignored both by Congress and by Washington, all eagerly attuned to the new fashion of Prussianizing and to the attractions of a &quot;real&quot; army.&quot; - Murray N. Rothbard, [http://mises.org/story/2885 Generalissimo Washington: How He Crushed the Spirit of Liberty] excerpted from Conceived in Liberty, Volume IV, chapters 8 and 41.{{relevance|date=June 2008|rather long &amp; agenda driven quote, with little relevance to article's main topic}} &lt;/ref&gt;
Under the articles, Congress could make decisions, but had no power to enforce them.  There was a requirement for unanimous approval before any modifications could be made to the Articles.  Because the majority of lawmaking rested with the states, the central government was also kept limited.

Congress was denied the power of taxation: it could only request money from the states. The states did not generally comply with the requests in full, leaving the confederation chronically short of funds. Congress was also denied the power to regulate commerce, and as a result, the states fought over trade as well.{{Fact|date=February 2008}} The states and the national congress had both incurred debts during the war, and how to pay the debts became a major issue. Some states paid off their debts; however, the centralizers favored federal assumption of states' debts.

Nevertheless, the Congress of the Confederation did take two actions with lasting impact. The Land Ordinance of 1785 established the general land survey and ownership provisions used throughout later American expansion. The Northwest Ordinance of 1787 noted the agreement of the original states to give up western land claims and cleared the way for the entry of new states.

Once the war was won, the Continental Army was largely disbanded. A very small national force was maintained to man frontier forts and protect against Indian attacks. Meanwhile, each of the states had an army (or militia), and 11 of them had navies. The wartime promises of bounties and land grants to be paid for service were not being met. In 1783, Washington defused the Newburgh conspiracy, but riots by unpaid Pennsylvania veterans forced the Congress to leave Philadelphia temporarily.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
   |url=http://www.fullbooks.com/George-Washington-Vol-I4.html
   |title=George Washington, Vol. I
   |author=Henry Cabot Lodge
   |publisher=
   |volume=I
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Signatures===
The Second Continental Congress approved the Articles for distribution to the states on November 15 1777. A copy was made for each state and one was kept by the Congress. The copies sent to the states for ratification were unsigned, and a cover letter had only the signatures of Henry Laurens and Charles Thomson, who were the President and Secretary to the Congress.

But, the ''Articles'' at that time were unsigned, and the date was blank. Congress began the signing process by examining their copy of the ''Articles'' on June 27 1778. They ordered a final copy prepared (the one in the National Archives), and that delegates should inform the secretary of their authority for ratification.

On July 9, 1778, the prepared copy was ready. They dated it, and began to sign. They also requested each of the remaining states to notify its delegation when ratification was completed. On that date, delegates present from New Hampshire, Massachusetts, Rhode Island, Connecticut, New York, Pennsylvania, Virginia and South Carolina signed the Articles to indicate that their states had ratified. New Jersey, Delaware and Maryland could not, since their states had not ratified. North Carolina and Georgia also didn't sign that day, since their delegations were absent.

After the first signing, some delegates signed at the next meeting they attended. For example, John Wentworth of New Hampshire added his name on August 8. John Penn was the first of North Carolina's delegates to arrive (on July 10), and the delegation signed the ''Articles'' on July 21 1778.

The other states had to wait until they ratified the ''Articles'' and notified their Congressional delegation. Georgia signed on July 24, New Jersey on November 26, and Delaware on February 12 1779. Maryland refused to ratify the ''Articles'' until every state had ceded its western land claims. 

[[Image:Act of Maryland to ratify Articles.jpg|thumb|253px|left|The Act of the Maryland legislature to ratify the Articles of Confederation on February 2, 1781]]
On February 2, 1781, the much-awaited decision was taken by the Maryland General Assembly in Annapolis&lt;ref name=lawsofmaryland&gt;[http://aomol.net/megafile/msa/speccol/sc2900/sc2908/000001/000203/html/am203--265.html Friday, February 2 1781], Laws of Maryland, 1781. [http://aomol.net/megafile/msa/speccol/sc2900/sc2908/000001/000203/html/am203--265.html An ACT to empower the delegates]&lt;/ref&gt;. As the last piece of business during the afternoon Session, &quot;among engrossed Bills&quot; was &quot;signed and sealed by Governor Thomas Sim Lee in the Senate Chamber, in the presence of the members of both Houses… an Act to empower the delegates of this state in Congress to subscribe and ratify the articles of confederation&quot; and perpetual union among the states. The Senate then adjourned &quot;to the first Monday in August next.&quot; The decision of Maryland to ratify the Articles was reported to the Continental Congress on February 12. The formal signing of the ''Articles'' by the Maryland delegates took place in Philadelphia at noon time on March 1, 1781 and was celebrated in the afternoon. With these events, the Articles entered into force and the United States came into being as a united, sovereign and national state.

Congress had debated the ''Articles'' for over a year and a half, and the ratification process had taken nearly three and a half years. Many participants in the original debates were no longer delegates, and some of the signers had only recently arrived. The ''Articles of Confederation and Perpetual Union'' were signed by a group of men who were never present in the Congress at the same time. 

The signers and the states they represented were:
* New Hampshire: Josiah Bartlett and John Wentworth Jr.
* Massachusetts Bay: John Hancock, Samuel Adams, Elbridge Gerry, Francis Dana, James Lovell, and Samuel Holten
* Rhode Island and Providence Plantations: William Ellery, Henry Marchant, and John Collins
* Connecticut: Roger Sherman¹, Samuel Huntington, Oliver Wolcott, Titus Hosmer, and Andrew Adams
* New York: James Duane, Francis Lewis, William Duer, and Gouverneur Morris
* New Jersey: John Witherspoon and Nathaniel Scudder
* Pennsylvania:Robert Morris², Daniel Roberdeau, Jonathan Bayard Smith, William Clingan, and Joseph Reed
* Delaware: Thomas McKean, John Dickinson³, and Nicholas Van Dyke
* Maryland: John Hanson and Daniel Carroll³
* Virginia: Richard Henry Lee, John Banister, Thomas Adams, John Harvie, and Francis Lightfoot Lee
* North Carolina: John Penn, Cornelius Harnett, and John Williams
* South Carolina: Henry Laurens, William Henry Drayton, John Mathews, Richard Hutson, and  Thomas Heyward Jr.
* Georgia: John Walton, Edward Telfair, and Edward Langworthy
&lt;br /&gt;
:¹ The only person to sign all four great state papers of the United States: the Articles of Association, the United States Declaration of Independence, the Articles of Confederation and the United States Constitution.
:² One of only 2 people to sign three of the great state papers of the United States: the United States Declaration of Independence, the Articles of Confederation and the United States Constitution.
:³ One of only 4 people to sign both the Articles of Confederation and the United States Constitution.

===Presidents of the Congress===
The following list is of those who led the Congress of the Confederation under the ''Articles of Confederation'' as the Presidents of the United States in Congress Assembled. Under the Articles, the president was the presiding officer of Congress, chaired the Cabinet (the Committee of the States) when Congress was in recess, and performed other administrative functions.  He was not, however, a ''chief'' executive in the way the successor President of the United States is a chief executive, but all of the functions he executed were under the auspices and in service of the Congress. 

* Samuel Huntington (March 1, 1781 &amp;ndash; July 9, 1781)
* Thomas McKean (July 10, 1781 &amp;ndash; November 4, 1781)
* John Hanson (November 5, 1781 &amp;ndash; November 3, 1782)
* Elias Boudinot (November 4, 1782 &amp;ndash; November 2, 1783)
* Thomas Mifflin (November 3, 1783 &amp;ndash; October 31, 1784)
* Richard Henry Lee (November 30, 1784 &amp;ndash; November 6, 1785)
* John Hancock (November 23, 1785 &amp;ndash; May 29, 1786)
* Nathaniel Gorham (June 6, 1786 &amp;ndash; November 5, 1786)
* Arthur St. Clair (February 2, 1787 &amp;ndash; November 4, 1787)
* Cyrus Griffin (January 22, 1788 &amp;ndash; November 2, 1788)
''For a full list of Presidents of the Congress Assembled and Presidents under the two Continental Congresses before the Articles, see President of the Continental Congress.''


===Revision and replacement===
In May 1786, Charles Pinckney of South Carolina proposed that Congress revise the Articles of Confederation. Recommended changes included granting Congress power over foreign and domestic commerce, and providing means for Congress to collect money from state treasuries. Unanimous approval was necessary to make the alterations, however, and Congress failed to reach a consensus.

In September, five states assembled in the Annapolis Convention to discuss adjustments that would improve commerce. Under their chairman, Alexander Hamilton, they invited state representatives to convene in Philadelphia to discuss improvements to the federal government. Although the states' representatives to the Constitutional Convention in Philadelphia were only authorized to amend the Articles, the representatives held secret, closed-door sessions and wrote a new constitution.  The new Constitution gave much more power to the central government,  but characterization of the result is disputed. Historian Forrest McDonald, using the ideas of James Madison from ''Federalist 39'', describes the change this way:

{{quote|The constitutional reallocation of powers created a new form of government, unprecedented under the sun. Every previous national authority either had been centralized or else had been a confederation of sovereign states.  The new American system was neither one nor the other; it was a mixture of both.&lt;ref&gt;McDonald pg. 276&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Historian Ralph Ketcham comments on the opinions of Patrick Henry, George Mason, and other antifederalists who were not so eager to give up the local autonomy won by the revolution:

{{quote|Antifederalists feared what Patrick Henry termed the &quot;consolidated government&quot; proposed by the new Constitution. They saw in Federalist hopes for commercial growth and international prestige only the lust of ambitious men for a &quot;splendid empire&quot; that, in the time-honored way of empires, would oppress the people with taxes, conscription, and military campaigns. Uncertain that any government over so vast a domain as the United States could be controlled by the people, Antifederalists saw in the enlarged powers of the general government only the familiar threats to the rights and liberties of the people.&lt;ref&gt;Ralph Ketcham, [http://books.google.com/books?id=QlDPAtJXQu0C&amp;pg=PA381&amp;lpg=PA381&amp;dq=ralph+ketcham+%22anti+federalist%22&amp;source=web&amp;ots=BQZCnGjA9c&amp;sig=rVp_ZBF9cEFFN8R5yJsW2xTMyf0#PPA381,M1 Roots of the Republic: American Founding Documents Interpreted, pg. 383]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

According to their own terms for modification (Article XIII), the Articles would still have been in effect until 1790, the year in which the last of the 13 states ratified the new Constitution. The Congress under the Articles continued to sit until November 1788,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
   |url=http://libertariannation.org/a/f11e1.html#3
   |title=The Articles of Confederation
   |last=Emory
   |first=Bobby
   |publisher=Libertarian Nation Foundation
   |date=1993
   |accessdate=2008-01-26
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
   |url=http://www.loc.gov/exhibits/religion/rel04.html
   |title=Religion and the Congress of the Confederation, 1774-89 (Religion and the Founding of the American Republic, Library of Congress Exhibition)
   |date=2003-10-27
   |publisher=Library of Congress
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
   |url=http://www.archives.gov/research/guide-fed-records/groups/360.html#360.2
   |title=Records of the Continental and Confederation Congresses and the Constitutional Convention
   |publisher=U.S. National Archives and Records Administration
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/collections/continental/constit.html Documents from the Continental Congress and the Constitutional Convention, 1774-1789 - To Form a More Perfect Union: The Work of the Continental Congress &amp; the Constitutional Convention (American Memory from the Library of Congress)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; overseeing the adoption of the new Constitution by the states, and setting elections.

Historians have given many reasons for the perceived need to replace the articles in 1787. Jillson and Wilson (1994) point to the financial weakness as well as the norms, rules and institutional structures of the Congress, and the propensity to divide along sectional lines. 

Rakove (1988) identifies several factors that explain the collapse of the Confederation. The lack of compulsory direct taxation power was objectionable to those wanting a strong centralized state or expecting to benefit from such power. It could not collect customs after the war because tariffs were vetoed by Rhode Island. Rakove concludes that their failure to implement national measures &quot;stemmed not from a heady sense of independence but rather from the enormous difficulties that all the states encountered in collecting taxes, mustering men, and gathering supplies from a war-weary populace.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Rakove 1988 p. 230&lt;/ref&gt; The second group of factors Rakove identified derived from the substantive nature of the problems the Continental Congress confronted after 1783, especially the inability to create a strong foreign policy.  Finally, the Confederation's lack of coercive power reduced the likelihood for profit to be made by political means, thus potential rulers were uninspired to seek power.

When the war ended in 1783, certain special interests had incentives to create a new &quot;merchant state,&quot; much like the British state people had rebelled against. In particular, holders of war scrip and land speculators wanted a central government to pay off scrip at face value and to legalize western land holdings with disputed claims. Also, manufacturers wanted a high tariff as a barrier to foreign goods, but competition among states made this impossible without a central government.

===Historical importance===
The Articles are historically important for two major reasons: ''i)'' they were the first constitution or governing document for the United States of America and ''ii)'' they legally established a union of the thirteen founding states; a Perpetual Union. Early on, tensions developed surrounding the Union, not least because of the fact that with the US Constitution the basis of government was changed from that of confederation to federation. Thomas Jefferson and John C. Calhoun were in their time leading proponents of guaranteeing the constitutional rights of states in federal legislation. Over time, a legal view developed that if the union violated the constitutional rights of states they might rightfully seceed.&lt;ref&gt;In his book Life of Webster Sen. Henry Cabot Lodge writes, &quot;It is safe to say that there was not a man in the country, from Washington and Hamilton to Clinton and Mason, who did not regard the new system as an experiment from which each and every State had a right to peaceably withdraw.&quot; A textbook used at West Point before the Civil War, A View of the Constitution, written by Judge William Rawle, states, &quot;The secession of a State depends on the will of the people of such a State.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; A significant tension in the 19th century surrounded the expansion of slavery (which was generally supported in agricultural Southern states and opposed in industrial Northern states). As the secessionist view gained support in the South, the opposing view in the North was that since the U.S. Constitution declared itself to be &quot;a more perfect union&quot; than the Articles, it too must be perpetual, and also could not be broken without the consent of the other states. This view was promoted by Daniel Webster and Abraham Lincoln. In 1861, these constitutional contracts were cited by President Lincoln against any claims by the seceding states that unilaterally withdrawing from the Union and taking federal property within those states was legal.&lt;!-- Lincoln, in inaugural, does not say he would take force to prevent secession--&gt;&lt;ref name=inauguraladdress&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/presiden/inaug/lincoln1.htm |title=First Inaugural Address of Abraham Lincoln, Monday, March 4, 1861| quote=...no State upon its own mere motion can lawfully get out of the Union; that resolves and ordinances to that effect are legally void, and that acts of violence within any State or States against the authority of the United States are insurrectionary or revolutionary, according to circumstances.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== The Northwest Ordinance ==

The Congress established the Northwest Territory around the Great Lakes between 1784 and 1787. In 1787, Congress passed the Northwest Ordinance banning slavery in the new Territory. Congressional legislation divided the Territory into ''townships'' of six square miles each and provided for the sale of land to settlers. The Northwest Territory would eventually become the states of Ohio, Wisconsin, Indiana, Illinois and Michigan.

== Problems with the Confederation ==

The Confederation faced several difficulties in its early years. Firstly, Congress became extremely dependent on the states for income. Also, states refused to require its citizens to pay debts to British merchants, straining relations with Great Britain. France prohibited Americans from using the important port of New Orleans, crippling American trade down the Mississippi river.

== Shays' Rebellion ==

Due to the post-revolution economic woes, agitated by inflation, many worried of social instability.  This was especially true for those in Massachusetts. The legislature's response to the shaky economy was to put emphasis on maintaining a sound currency by paying off the state debt through levying massive taxes.  The tax burden hit those with moderate incomes dramatically.  The average farmer paid a third of their annual income to these taxes from 1780 to 1786.  Those who couldn't pay had their property foreclosed and were thrown into crowded prisons filled with other debtors.

But in the summer of 1786, a revolutionary war veteran named Daniel Shays began to organize western communities in Massachusetts to stop foreclosures, with force, by prohibiting the courts from holding their proceedings.  Later that fall, Shays marched the newly formed &quot;rebellion&quot; into Springfield to stop the state supreme court from gathering.  The state responded with troops sent to suppress the rebellion.  After a failed attempt by the rebels to attack the Springfield arsenal, and other small skirmishes, the rebels retreated and then uprising collapsed.  Shays retreated to Vermont by 1787.

While Daniel Shays was in hiding, the government condemned him to death on the charge of treason.  Shays pleaded for his life in a petition which was finally granted by John Hancock on June 17, 1788.  With the threat of treason behind him, Shays moved to New York and died September 25, 1825

==US Presidents before George Washington==
Who was the first president of the United States? Ask any school child and they will readily tell you &quot;George Washington.&quot;  And of course, they would be correct—at least technically. Washington was inaugurated on April 30, 1789, and yet, the United States continually had functioning governments from as early as September 5, 1774 and operated as a confederated nation from as early as July 4, 1776. During that nearly fifteen year interval, Congress—first the Continental Congress and then later the Confederation Congress—was always moderated by a duly elected president.  This officer was known as the &quot;[[w:President of the Continental Congress|President of the Continental Congress]]&quot;, and later as the &quot;President of the United States, in Congress Assembled&quot;.

However, the office of President of the Continental Congress had very little relationship to the office of President of the United States beyond the name.  The President of the United States is the head of the executive branch of government, while the President of the Continental Congress was merely the chair of a body that most resembled a legislature, although it possessed legislative, executive, and judicial powers.  The following brief biographies profile these &quot;forgotten presidents.&quot; 

'''Peyton Randolph of Virginia (1723-1775)'''
[[Image:PeytonRandolph.jpeg|thumb|left|A portrait of Peyton Randolph.]]
When delegates gathered in Philadelphia for the first Continental Congress, they promptly elected the former King's Attorney of Virginia as the moderator and president of their convocation. He was a propitious choice. He was a legal prodigy—having studied at the Inner Temple in London, served as his native colony's Attorney General, and tutored many of the most able men of the South at William and Mary College—including the young Patrick Henry. His home in Williamsburg was the gathering place for Virginia's legal and political gentry—and it remains a popular attraction in the restored colonial capital. He had served as a delegate in the Virginia House of Burgesses, and had been a commander under William Byrd in the colonial militia. He was a scholar of some renown—having begun a self-guided reading of the classics when he was thirteen. Despite suffering poor health served the Continental Congress as president twice, in 1774 from September 5 to October 21, and then again for a few days in 1775 from May 10 to May 23. He never lived to see independence, yet was numbered among the nation's most revered founders. 

'''Henry Middleton (1717-1784)'''

America's second elected president was one of the wealthiest planters in the South, the patriarch of the most powerful families anywhere in the nation. His public spirit was evident from an early age. He was a member of his state's Common House from 1744-1747. During the last two years he served as the Speaker. During 1755 he was the King's Commissioner of Indian Affairs. He was a member of the South Carolina Council from 1755-1770. His valor in the War with the Cherokees during 1760-1761 earned him wide recognition throughout the colonies—and demonstrated his leadership abilities while under pressure. He was elected as a delegate to the first session of the Continental Congress and when Peyton Randolph was forced to resign the presidency, his peers immediately turned to Middleton to complete the term. He served as the fledgling coalition's president from October 22, 1774 until Randolph was able to resume his duties briefly beginning on May 10, 1775. Afterward, he was a member of the Congressional Council of Safety and helped to establish the young nation's policy toward the encouragement and support of education. In February 1776 he resigned his political involvements in order to prepare his family and lands for what he believed was inevitable war—but he was replaced by his son Arthur who eventually became a signer of both the Declaration of Independence and the Articles of Confederation, served time as an English prisoner of war, and was twice elected Governor of his state. 

'''John Hancock (1737-1793)'''
[[Image:John_Hancock_painting.jpg|thumb|right|John Hancock, signer of the Declaration of Independence.]]
The third president was a patriot, rebel leader, merchant who signed his name into immortality in giant strokes on the Declaration of Independence on July 4, 1776. The boldness of his signature has made it live in American minds as a perfect expression of the strength and freedom—and defiance—of the individual in the face of British tyranny. As President of the Continental Congress during two widely spaced terms—the first from May 24 1775 to October 30 1777 and the second from November 23 1785 to June 5, 1786—Hancock was the presiding officer when the members approved the Declaration of Independence. Because of his position, it was his official duty to sign the document first—but not necessarily as dramatically as he did. Hancock figured prominently in another historic event—the battle at Lexington: British troops who fought there April 10, 1775, had known Hancock and Samuel Adams were in Lexington and had come there to capture these rebel leaders. And the two would have been captured, if they had not been warned by Paul Revere. As early as 1768, Hancock defied the British by refusing to pay customs charges on the cargo of one of his ships. One of Boston's wealthiest merchants, he was recognized by the citizens, as well as by the British, as a rebel leader—and was elected President of the first Massachusetts Provincial Congress. After he was chosen President of the Continental Congress in 1775, Hancock became known beyond the borders of Massachusetts, and, having served as colonel of the Massachusetts Governor's Guards he hoped to be named commander of the American forces—until John Adams nominated George Washington. In 1778 Hancock was commissioned Major General and took part in an unsuccessful campaign in Rhode Island. But it was as a political leader that his real distinction was earned—as the first Governor of Massachusetts, as President of Congress, and as President of the Massachusetts constitutional ratification convention. He helped win ratification in Massachusetts, gaining enough popular recognition to make him a contender for the newly created Presidency of the United States, but again he saw Washington gain the prize. Like his rival, George Washington, Hancock was a wealthy man who risked much for the cause of independence. He was the wealthiest New Englander supporting the patriotic cause, and, although he lacked the brilliance of John Adams or the capacity to inspire of Samuel Adams, he became one of the foremost leaders of the new nation—perhaps, in part, because he was willing to commit so much at such risk to the cause of freedom. 

'''Henry Laurens (1724-1792)'''
[[Image:Henry_laurens.jpg|thumb|left|Henry Laurens, &quot;father of our country.&quot;]]
The only American president ever to be held as a prisoner of war by a foreign power, Laurens was heralded after he was released as &quot;the father of our country,&quot; by no less a personage than George Washington. He was of Huguenot extraction, his ancestors having come to America from France after the revocation of the Edict of Nantes made the Reformed faith illegal. Raised and educated for a life of mercantilism at his home in Charleston, he also had the opportunity to spend more than a year in continental travel. It was while in Europe that he began to write revolutionary pamphlets—gaining him renown as a patriot. He served as vice-president of South Carolina in1776. He was then elected to the Continental Congress. He succeeded John Hancock as President of the newly independent but war beleaguered United States on November 1, 1777. He served until December 9, 1778 at which time he was appointed Ambassador to the Netherlands. Unfortunately for the cause of the young nation, he was captured by an English warship during his cross-Atlantic voyage and was confined to the Tower of London until the end of the war. After the Battle of Yorktown, the American government regained his freedom in a dramatic prisoner exchange—President Laurens for Lord Cornwallis. Ever the patriot, Laurens continued to serve his nation as one of the three representatives selected to negotiate terms at the Paris Peace Conference in 1782. 

'''John Jay (1745-1829)'''
[[Image:John Jay (Gilbert Stuart portrait).jpg|thumb|right|John Jay, Chief Justice.]]
America's first Secretary of State, first Chief Justice of the Supreme Court, one of its first ambassadors, and author of some of the celebrated Federalist Papers, Jay was a Founding Father who, by a quirk of fate, missed signing the Declaration of Independence—at the time of the vote for independence and the signing, he had temporarily left the Continental Congress to serve in New York's revolutionary legislature. Nevertheless, he was chosen by his peers to succeed Henry Laurens as President of the United States—serving a term from December 10, 1778 to September 27, 1779. A conservative New York lawyer who was at first against the idea of independence for the colonies, the aristocratic Jay in 1776 turned into a patriot who was willing to give the next twenty-five years of his life to help establish the new nation. During those years, he won the regard of his peers as a dedicated and accomplished statesman and a man of unwavering principle. In the Continental Congress Jay prepared addresses to the people of Canada and Great Britain. In New York he drafted the State constitution and served as Chief Justice during the war. He was President of the Continental Congress before he undertook the difficult assignment, as ambassador, of trying to gain support and funds from Spain. After helping Franklin, Jefferson, Adams, and Laurens complete peace negotiations in Paris in 1783, Jay returned to become the first Secretary of State, called &quot;Secretary of Foreign Affairs&quot; under the Articles of Confederation. He negotiated valuable commercial treaties with Russia and Morocco, and dealt with the continuing controversy with Britain and Spain over the southern and western boundaries of the United States. He proposed that America and Britain establish a joint commission to arbitrate disputes that remained after the war—a proposal which, though not adopted, influenced the government's use of arbitration and diplomacy in settling later international problems. In this post Jay felt keenly the weakness of the Articles of Confederation and was one of the first to advocate a new governmental compact. He wrote five Federalist Papers supporting the Constitution, and he was a leader in the New York ratification convention. As first Chief Justice of the Supreme Court, Jay made the historic decision that a State could be sued by a citizen from another State, which led to the Eleventh Amendment to the Constitution. On a special mission to London he concluded the &quot;Jay Treaty,&quot; which helped avert a renewal of hostilities with Britain but won little popular favor at home—and it is probably for this treaty that this Founding Father is best remembered.
 
'''Samuel Huntington (1732-1796)'''
An industrious youth who mastered his studies of the law without the advantage of a school, a tutor, or a master—borrowing books and snatching opportunities to read and research between odd jobs—he was one of the greatest self-made men among the Founders. He was also one of the greatest legal minds of the age—all the more remarkable for his lack of advantage as a youth. In 1764, in recognition of his obvious abilities and initiative, he was elected to the General Assembly of Connecticut. The next year he was chosen to serve on the Executive Council. In 1774 he was appointed Associate Judge of the Superior Court and, as a delegate to the Continental Congress, was acknowledged to be a legal scholar of some respect. He served in Congress for five consecutive terms, during the last of which he was elected President. He served in that office from September 28, 1779 until ill health forced him to resign on July 9, 1781. He returned to his home in Connecticut—and as he recuperated, he accepted more Councilor and Bench duties. He again took his seat in Congress in 1783, but left it to become Chief Justice of his state's Superior Court. He was elected Lieutenant Governor in 1785 and Governor in 1786. According to John Jay, he was &quot;the most precisely trained Christian jurists ever to serve his country.&quot; 

'''Thomas McKean (1734-1817)'''
During his astonishingly varied fifty-year career in public life he held almost every possible position—from deputy county attorney to President of the United States under the Confederation. Besides signing the Declaration of Independence, he contributed significantly to the development and establishment of constitutional government in both his home state of Delaware and the nation. At the Stamp Act Congress he proposed the voting procedure that Congress adopted: that each colony, regardless of size or population, has one vote—the practice adopted by the Continental Congress and the Congress of the Confederation, and the principle of state equality manifest in the composition of the Senate. And as county judge in 1765, he defied the British by ordering his court to work only with documents that did not bear the hated stamps. In June 1776, at the Continental Congress, McKean joined with Caesar Rodney to register Delaware's approval of the Declaration of Independence, over the negative vote of the third Delaware delegate, George Read—permitting it to be &quot;The unanimous declaration of the thirteen United States.&quot; And at a special Delaware convention, he drafted the constitution for that State. McKean also helped draft—and signed—the Articles of Confederation. It was during his tenure of service as President—from July 10, 1781 to November 4, 1782—when news arrived from General Washington in October 1781 that the British had surrendered following the Battle of Yorktown. As Chief Justice of the supreme court of Pennsylvania, he contributed to the establishment of the legal system in that State, and, in 1787, he strongly supported the Constitution at the Pennsylvania Ratification Convention, declaring it &quot;the best the world has yet seen.&quot; At sixty-five, after over forty years of public service, McKean resigned from his post as Chief Justice. A candidate on the Democratic-Republican ticket in 1799, McKean was elected Governor of Pennsylvania. As Governor, he followed such a strict policy of appointing only fellow Republicans to office that he became the father of the spoils system in America. He served three tempestuous terms as Governor, completing one of the longest continuous careers of public service of any of the Founding Fathers. 

'''John Hanson (1715-1783)'''
He was the heir of one of the greatest family traditions in the colonies and became the patriarch of a long line of American patriots—his great grandfather died at Lutzen beside the great King Gustavus Aldophus of Sweden; his grandfather was one of the founders of New Sweden along the Delaware River in Maryland; one of his nephews was the military secretary to George Washington; another was a signer of the Declaration; still another was a signer of the Constitution; yet another was Governor of Maryland during the Revolution; and still another was a member of the first Congress; two sons were killed in action with the Continental Army; a grandson served as a member of Congress under the new Constitution; and another grandson was a Maryland Senator. Thus, even if Hanson had not served as President himself, he would have greatly contributed to the life of the nation through his ancestry and progeny. As a youngster he began a self-guided reading of classics and rather quickly became an acknowledged expert in the juridicalism of Anselm and the practical philosophy of Seneca—both of which were influential in the development of the political philosophy of the great leaders of the Reformation. It was based upon these legal and theological studies that the young planter—his farm, Mulberry Grove was just across the Potomac from Mount Vernon—began to espouse the cause of the patriots. In 1775 he was elected to the Provincial Legislature of Maryland. Then in 1777, he became a member of Congress where he distinguished himself as a brilliant administrator. Thus, he was elected President in 1781. He served in that office from November 5, 1781 until November 3, 1782. He was the first President to serve a full term after the full ratification of the Articles of Confederation—and like so many of the Southern and New England Founders, he was strongly opposed to the Constitution when it was first discussed. He remained a confirmed anti-federalist until his untimely death. 

'''Elias Boudinot (1741-1802)'''
He did not sign the Declaration, the Articles, or the Constitution. He did not serve in the Continental Army with distinction. He was not renowned for his legal mind or his political skills. He was instead a man who spent his entire career in foreign diplomacy. He earned the respect of his fellow patriots during the dangerous days following the traitorous action of Benedict Arnold. His deft handling of relations with Canada also earned him great praise. After being elected to the Congress from his home state of New Jersey, he served as the new nation's Secretary for Foreign Affairs—managing the influx of aid from France, Spain, and Holland. The in 1783 he was elected to the Presidency. He served in that office from November 4, 1782 until November 2, 1783. Like so many of the other early presidents, he was a classically trained scholar, of the Reformed faith, and an anti-federalist in political matters. He was the father and grandfather of frontiersmen—and one of his grandchildren and namesakes eventually became a leader of the Cherokee nation in its bid for independence from the sprawling expansion of the United States. 

'''Thomas Mifflin (1744-1800)'''
By an ironic sort of providence, Thomas Mifflin served as George Washington's first aide-de-camp at the beginning of the Revolutionary War, and, when the war was over, he was the man, as President of the United States, who accepted Washington's resignation of his commission. In the years between, Mifflin greatly served the cause of freedom—and, apparently, his own cause—while serving as the first Quartermaster General of the Continental Army. He obtained desperately needed supplies for the new army—and was suspected of making excessive profit himself. Although experienced in business and successful in obtaining supplies for the war, Mifflin preferred the front lines, and he distinguished himself in military actions on Long Island and near Philadelphia. Born and reared a Quaker, he was excluded from their meetings for his military activities. A controversial figure, Mifflin lost favor with Washington and was part of the Conway Cabal—a rather notorious plan to replace Washington with General Horatio Gates. And Mifflin narrowly missed court-martial action over his handling of funds by resigning his commission in 1778. In spite of these problems—and of repeated charges that he was a drunkard—Mifflin continued to be elected to positions of responsibility—as President and Governor of Pennsylvania, delegate to the Constitutional Convention, as well as the highest office in the land—where he served from November 3, 1783 to November 29, 1784. Most of Mifflin's significant contributions occurred in his earlier years—in the First and Second Continental Congresses he was firm in his stand for independence and for fighting for it, and he helped obtain both men and supplies for Washington's army in the early critical period. In 1784, as President, he signed the treaty with Great Britain which ended the war. Although a delegate to the Constitutional Convention, he did not make a significant contribution—beyond signing the document. As Governor of Pennsylvania, although he was accused of negligence, he supported improvements of roads, and reformed the State penal and judicial systems. He had gradually become sympathetic to Jefferson's principles regarding State's rights, even so, he directed the Pennsylvania militia to support the Federal tax collectors in the Whiskey Rebellion. In spite of charges of corruption, the affable Mifflin remained a popular figure. A magnetic personality and an effective speaker, he managed to hold a variety of elective offices for almost thirty years of the critical Revolutionary period. 

'''Richard Henry Lee (1732-1794)'''
His resolution &quot;that these United Colonies are, and of right ought to be, free and independent States,&quot; approved by the Continental Congress July 2, 1776, was the first official act of the United Colonies that set them irrevocably on the road to independence. It was not surprising that it came from Lee's pen—as early as 1768 he proposed the idea of committees of correspondence among the colonies, and in 1774 he proposed that the colonies meet in what became the Continental Congress. From the first, his eye was on independence. A wealthy Virginia planter whose ancestors had been granted extensive lands by King Charles II, Lee disdained the traditional aristocratic role and the aristocratic view. In the House of Burgesses he flatly denounced the practice of slavery. He saw independent America as &quot;an asylum where the unhappy may find solace, and the persecuted repose.&quot; In 1764, when news of the proposed Stamp Act reached Virginia, Lee was a member of the committee of the House of Burgesses that drew up an address to the King, an official protest against such a tax. After the tax was established, Lee organized the citizens of his county into the Westmoreland Association, a group pledged to buy no British goods until the Stamp Act was repealed. At the First Continental Congress, Lee persuaded representatives from all the colonies to adopt this non-importation idea, leading to the formation of the Continental Association, which was one of the first steps toward union of the colonies. Lee also proposed to the First Continental Congress that a militia be organized and armed—the year before the first shots were fired at Lexington; but this and other proposals of his were considered too radical—at the time. Three days after Lee introduced his resolution, in June of 1776, he was appointed by Congress to the committee responsible for drafting a declaration of independence, but he was called home when his wife fell ill, and his place was taken by his young protégé, Thomas Jefferson. Thus Lee missed the chance to draft the document—though his influence greatly shaped it and he was able to return in time to sign it. He was elected President—serving from November 30, 1784 to November 22, 1785 when he was succeeded by the second administration of John Hancock. Elected to the Constitutional Convention, Lee refused to attend, but as a member of the Congress of the Confederation, he contributed to another great document, the Northwest Ordinance, which provided for the formation of new States from the Northwest Territory. When the completed Constitution was sent to the States for ratification, Lee opposed it as anti-democratic and anti-Christian. However, as one of Virginia's first Senators, he helped assure passage of the amendments that, he felt, corrected many of the document's gravest faults—the Bill of Rights. He was the great uncle of Robert E. Lee and the scion of a great family tradition. 

'''Nathaniel Gorham (1738-1796)'''
Another self-made man, Gorham was one of the many successful Boston merchants who risked all he had for the cause of freedom. He was first elected to the Massachusetts General Court in 1771. His honesty and integrity won his acclaim and was thus among the first delegates chose to serve in the Continental Congress. He remained in public service throughout the war and into the Constitutional period, though his greatest contribution was his call for a stronger central government. But even though he was an avid federalist, he did not believe that the union could—or even should—be maintained peaceably for more than a hundred years. He was convinced that eventually, in order to avoid civil or cultural war, smaller regional interests should pursue an independent course. His support of a new constitution was rooted more in pragmatism than ideology. When John Hancock was unable to complete his second term as President, Gorham was elected to succeed him—serving from June 6, 1786 to February 1, 1787. It was during this time that the Congress actually entertained the idea of asking Prince Henry—the brother of Frederick II of Prussia—and Bonnie Prince Charlie—the leader of the ill-fated Scottish Jacobite Rising and heir of the Stuart royal line—to consider the possibility of establishing a constitutional monarch in America. It was a plan that had much to recommend it but eventually the advocates of republicanism held the day. During the final years of his life, Gorham was concerned with several speculative land deals which nearly cost him his entire fortune. 

'''Arthur St. Clair (1734-1818)'''
Born and educated in Edinburgh, Scotland during the tumultuous days of the final Jacobite Rising and the Tartan Suppression, St. Clair was the only president of the United States born and bred on foreign soil. Though most of his family and friends abandoned their devastated homeland in the years following the Battle of Culloden—after which nearly a third of the land was depopulated through emigration to America—he stayed behind to learn the ways of the hated Hanoverian English in the Royal Navy. His plan was to learn of the enemy's military might in order to fight another day. During the global conflict of the Seven Years War—generally known as the French and Indian War—he was stationed in the American theater. Afterward, he decided to settle in Pennsylvania where many of his kin had established themselves. His civic-mindedness quickly became apparent: he helped to organize both the New Jersey and the Pennsylvania militias, led the Continental Army's Canadian expedition, and was elected Congress. His long years of training in the enemy camp was finally paying off. He was elected President in 1787—and he served from February 2 of that year until January 21 of the next. Following his term of duty in the highest office in the land, he became the first Governor of the Northwest Territory. Though he briefly supported the idea of creating a constitutional monarchy under the Stuart's Bonnie Prince Charlie, he was a strident Anti-Federalist—believing that the proposed federal constitution would eventually allow for the intrusion of government into virtually every sphere and aspect of life. He even predicted that under the vastly expanded centralized power of the state the taxing powers of bureaucrats and other unelected officials would eventually confiscate as much as a quarter of the income of the citizens—a notion that seemed laughable at the time but that has proven to be ominously modest in light of our current governmental leviathan. St. Clair lived to see the hated English tyrants who destroyed his homeland defeated. But he despaired that his adopted home might actually create similar tyrannies and impose them upon themselves. 

'''Cyrus Griffin (1736-1796)'''
Like Peyton Randolph, he was trained in London's Inner Temple to be a lawyer—and thus was counted among his nation's legal elite. Like so many other Virginians, he was an anti-federalist, though he eventually accepted the new Constitution with the promise of the Bill of Rights as a hedge against the establishment of an American monarchy—which still had a good deal of currency. The Articles of Confederation afforded such freedoms that he had become convinced that even with the incumbent loss of liberty, some new form of government would be required. A protégé of George Washington—having worked with him on several speculative land deals in the West—he was a reluctant supporter of the Constitutional ratifying process. It was during his term in the office of the Presidency—the last before the new national compact went into effect—that ratification was formalized and finalized. He served as the nation's chief executive from January 22, 1788 until George Washington's inauguration on April 30, 1789.

==Notes==

{{reflist}}

==References==
* R. B. Bernstein, &quot;Parliamentary Principles, American Realities: The Continental and Confederation Congresses, 1774-1789,&quot; in  ''Inventing Congress: Origins &amp; Establishment Of First Federal Congress'' ed by Kenneth R. Bowling and Donald R. Kennon (1999) pp 76-108
*   Burnett, Edmund Cody. ''The Continental Congress: A Definitive History of the Continental Congress From Its Inception in 1774 to March, 1789'' (1941)  
* Barbara Feinberg, ''The Articles Of Confederation'' (2002). [for middle school children.]
* Robert W. Hoffert, ''A Politics of Tensions: The Articles of Confederation and American Political Ideas'' (1992).
* Lucille E. Horgan. ''Forged in War: The Continental Congress and the Origin of Military Supply and Acquisition Policy'' (2002)  
* Merrill Jensen, ''The Articles of Confederation: An Interpretation of the Social-Constitutional History of the American Revolution, 1774-1781'' (1959). 
* Merrill Jensen: &quot;The Idea of a National Government During the American Revolution&quot;, ''Political Science Quarterly,'' 58 (1943), 356-79. [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0032-3195%28194309%2958%3A3%3C356%3ATIOANG%3E2.0.CO%3B2-M  online at JSTOR]
* Calvin Jillson and Rick K. Wilson. ''Congressional Dynamics: Structure, Coordination, and Choice in the First American Congress, 1774-1789.'' (1994)
* Forest McDonald.''Novus Ordo Seclorum: The Intellectual Origins of the Constitution.'' (1985) 
* Andrew C. Mclaughlin, ''A Constitutional History of the United States'' (1935) [http://www.constitution.org/cmt/mclaughlin/chus.htm online version]
* Pauline Maier, ''American Scripture: Making the Declaration of Independence'' (1998).
* Jackson T. Main, ''Political Parties before the Constitution.'' University of North Carolina Press, 1974
* Jack N. Rakove, ''The Beginnings of National Politics:  An Interpretive History of the Continental Congress '' (1982).
* Jack N. Rakove, “The Collapse of the Articles of Confederation,” in ''The American Founding: Essays on the Formation of the Constitution.'' Ed by J. Jackson Barlow, Leonard W. Levy and  Ken Masugi. Greenwood Press. 1988. Pp  225-45 ISBN 0313256101

==Further reading==
*{{cite book |title = President Who? Forgotten Founders|last = Klos|first = Stanley L.  |work = |publisher = Evisum, Inc. |location = Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania |pages = 261|year = 2004 |id= ISBN 0-9752627-5-0}}


==External links==

* [http://www.law.ou.edu/hist/artconf.html Text Version of the Articles of Confederation]
* [http://earlyamerica.com/earlyamerica/milestones/articles/cover.html Articles of Confederation and Perpetual Union]
* [http://www.loc.gov/rr/program/bib/ourdocs/articles.html Articles of Confederation and related resources], Library of Congress
* [http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/today/nov15.html Today in History: November 15], Library of Congress
* [http://www.usconstitution.net/articles.html United States Constitution Online - The Articles of Confederation]
* [http://www.mp3books.com/shop/audio_item.aspx?id=819 Free Download of Articles of Confederation Audio]
* Audio narration (mp3) of the [http://www.americanaphonic.com/pages/Articles.html Articles of Confederation] at Americana Phonic
* [http://www.mises.org/books/conceived4.pdf The Articles of Confederation], Chapter 45 (see page 253) of Volume 4 of ''Conceived in Liberty'' by Murray Rothbard, in PDF format.


{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>s8msbdxnar6vtk8c15hevi0ryty9zv7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Spanish/Exercises/Articles</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1205</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2607654</id>
      <parentid>2607174</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-02-08T23:33:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Recent Runes</username>
        <id>66908</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/Ariebombarie123|Ariebombarie123]] ([[User talk:Ariebombarie123|talk]]) to last version by Think Fast</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Spanish/Lesson 2| ^Lesson 2^]]
----

=== Rellena los espacios en blanco ===

=== ''Fill in the blank'' ===

Por favor, rellena los espacios en blanco con el articulo correcto:
''Please, fill in the blank with the correct article:''

1. ____ mesa ''(a table)''

2. ____ caballos ''(some horses)''

3. ____ gato ''(the cat)''

4. ____ ciudad ''(the city)''

5. ____ casas ''(some houses)''

6. ____ hijos ''(the sons)''

7. ____ hijas ''(the daughters)''

8. ____ perro ''(a dog)''


----------------------------------------
[[Spanish/Exercises/Articles - Solutions|Soluciones a los ejercicios]] ''Solutions to exercices''

[[Spanish/Lesson 2| ^Lesson 2^]]

[[Category:Spanish]]</text>
      <sha1>511yv05kigi62sqnc39gw3ky4lijpoz</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Spanish/Exercises/Telling Time</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1208</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2658670</id>
      <parentid>2658618</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-05-21T17:59:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Harrybrowne1986</username>
        <id>430968</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/66.208.143.3|66.208.143.3]] ([[User talk:66.208.143.3|talk]]) to last version by 66.131.86.83</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Spanish/Lesson 2|^Lesson 2^]]

==Translate the following into Spanish==
# It's quarter past one.
# It's two o'clock.
# It's twenty minutes after five.
# It's midnight.
# It's six o'clock.
# It's half past ten.
# It's five minutes to eleven.
# It's ten minutes to noon.
----
[[Spanish/Exercises/Telling Time - Solutions|Soluciones a los ejercicios]] ''Solutions to exercices''

[[Spanish/Lesson 2|^Lesson 2^]]

[[Category:Spanish]]

translation:
#Es la una y cuarto
#son las dos en punto
#son las cinco y veinte
#es las medianoche
#son las seis en punto
#son las dies y media
#son las once menos cinco
#son las doce menos diez</text>
      <sha1>46zj19gsrjtsiiwm5xual917d8kpfj2</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>GCSE Science/Three useful components</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1209</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2320668</id>
      <parentid>2066285</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-05-03T05:51:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>220.233.143.242</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Questions */ spelling correction</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[GCSE Science/Electricity]]
----
This page looks at three components that are used in electrical circuits. The three components in question are: The diode, the thermistor, and the light dependent resistor. You will see how the components work and how they are used.

==The Diode==

{| align=&quot;right&quot;
|-
| [[Image:Diode_circuit_symbol.png]]
|} 

A diode is a device that allows current to flow in one direction but not in the reverse direction. Its circuit symbol consists of a triangle pointing in the direction that current ''is'' allowed to flow with a line at the point, inside a circle. Diodes are useful for stopping current flowing in the &quot;wrong&quot; direction.

[[Image:V-I_diode.png]] 

Above is a current voltage graph for a typical diode. Note that the diode needs a small voltage (about 0.6V) to work. Below 0.6V in the  forward direction very little current flows. At or above 0.6V the resistance drops dramatically and a huge current can flow. In the reverse direction, virtually no current flows no matter how large the voltage is. (Eventually, when the voltage gets high enough, the diode &quot;breaks down&quot; and current is able to flow in the  reverse direction. For normal diodes however this &quot;break down voltage&quot; is very high and can be ignored.  A diode that is connected in reverse to use the break down effect is called a Zener diode.  It is used to provide voltage control in power supplies (called the Zener voltage).)

Diodes are useful for turning AC current into DC current (AC/DC converters are called rectifiers). In AC the electricity flows back and forth in cycles. Mains electricity is AC. It cycles 50 times every second. This is fine for something like a lightbulb, where the bulb does not care in which direction the electricity flows. Some devices however can only work off DC. A toy electric train for example would not go with AC. The current would be saying &quot;go forwards&quot;, &quot;go backwards&quot; over and over again 50 times a second! With a diode in the circuit the ''negative'' part of the cycle is stopped.

[[Image:AC_current_through_a_diode.png]]

The graph on the left shows AC current. Note that the current cycles positive, negative, positive, and so on. The electricity is flowing to and fro. Putting the current through a diode has the result seen on the right. The positive part of the cycle in unaffected, but the negative is wiped out. The current goes positive, zero, positive and so on.

==The Thermistor==
[[Image:R_against_T_for_a_thermistor.png]] 

A thermistor is a just a resistor whose resistance depends on temperature. Most thermistors have lower resistance when the temperature is high. They are used in circuits which are temperature dependent. For example, fire alarms, the temperature gets too high; the alarm sounds.

==The LDR==
A light dependent resistor is a resistor whose resistance depends on the amount of light shining on it. Its resistance gets less the more light shines on it. It can be used in circuits that are light dependent. For example, switching circuits for street lights. The ambient light gets too low; the lamp turns on. It is also known as a photoresistor from photo, the Latin for light.

==Questions==


{| bgcolor=&quot;ffeeaa&quot;
|-
| '''Summary'''
|-
| A ''Diode'' allows electricity to flow in one direction, but not the other&lt;br&gt;
A ''thermistor'' is a resistor that has a lower resistance the higher the temperature&lt;br&gt;
A ''Light dependent resistor'' has a lower resistance the higher the light level shining on it'''
|}
----

[[GCSE Science/Safety in Mains circuits|Safety in Mains circuits&gt;&gt;]]

[[Category:GCSE Science]]</text>
      <sha1>eagrfnnd7cgihcq4peaui6d0pvsm1s7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:V-I diode.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1210</id>
    <revision>
      <id>636310</id>
      <parentid>153336</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-11-04T10:50:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Theresa knott</username>
        <id>93</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>tag</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">voltage current charachteristics of a diode ( simplified to a ppropriate level) Drawn by Theresa Knott


{{GFDL}}
{{Cc-by-sa-2.5}}</text>
      <sha1>f1v0l45b6ejmctjmjmfo08863gndam4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Allowed mapping for a function.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1211</id>
    <revision>
      <id>729125</id>
      <parentid>703702</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-01-21T19:56:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Theresa knott</username>
        <id>93</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>tagging</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Diagram drawn by Theresa Knott
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>c8y9tk21yd6acikrnrj9wk400b7lfud</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Diode circuit symbol.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1212</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2693072</id>
      <parentid>2313941</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-20T00:58:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Hyju</username>
        <id>184362</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Diagram drawn by Theresa Knott

{{GFDL}}
{{Cc-by-sa-2.5}}
{{Move to Wikimedia Commons}}

{{NowCommons}}</text>
      <sha1>dc0nk76ntbsjkuzk0f4jp1uayl3fqpv</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:AC current through a diode.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1213</id>
    <revision>
      <id>636435</id>
      <parentid>153339</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-11-04T11:04:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Theresa knott</username>
        <id>93</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Drawn by Theresa Knott

{{GFDL}}
{{Cc-by-sa-2.5}}</text>
      <sha1>fmeelzb8uvpie3ty7eth8xx1b2szbo9</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:R against T for a thermistor.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1214</id>
    <revision>
      <id>636430</id>
      <parentid>153340</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-11-04T11:02:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Theresa knott</username>
        <id>93</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Graph of how rsistance depends on temperature for a thermistor. Drawn by Theresa knott

{{GFDL}}
{{Cc-by-sa-2.5}}</text>
      <sha1>2nojba72ffp656qg6i72f0ria9vwd6e</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>GCSE Science/Safety in Mains circuits</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1216</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2684639</id>
      <parentid>2674890</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-07-25T10:42:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>FF-UK</username>
        <id>1637552</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Corrected misinformation.  Both Line and Neutral are LIVE WIRES!  The purpose of the fuse is to protect the flexible lead NOT THE APPLIANCE.  Corrected description of shutters (in socket, NOT PLUG)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[GCSE Science/Electricity]]
----
Mains electricity is potentially dangerous. There are, however, safety features included in plugs. This module looks at how to wire a plug correctly. 


==The three pin plug==

Nowadays most appliances are sold with moulded plugs already fitted. Nevertheless, it is still important to understand the correct wiring of a plug because enough of the old plugs still exist. It is also the case when you bring in equipments overseas. British Standard compliant adaptors are not always available for such non-UK plugs. You are very likely to need to change a plug at some time in your life. In the UK mains electricity is 230V. (In Hong Kong, it is 220V.) If you were to touch a live wire a current would flow through your body to the ground. This current may be enough to kill you. 

The cable from the appliance usually consist of three wires, an earth and two live wires (line and neutral) which carry the current (people often think that only the line wire is called live, but both neutral and line are live wires). The wires are made of copper surrounded by a plastic sheath. The sheath is made of plastic and is coloured:

*The line wire is &lt;font color=&quot;brown&quot;&gt;'''brown'''&lt;/font&gt;
*The neutral wire is &lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;'''blue'''&lt;/font&gt;
*The earth wire is &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;'''green'''&lt;/font&gt; and &lt;font color=&quot;eedd00&quot;&gt;'''yellow'''&lt;/font&gt;

The three wires are covered by an outer sheath made of plastic.

'''Q1)''' Use your knowledge of insulators and conductors to explain
:Why the wires are insulated&lt;s&gt;&lt;/s&gt;.
:Why the sheaths are made of plastic.


[[Image:Plug_diagram.png]]

The plug has the following features:
* A cable grip, to grip the ''outer sheath'' of cable and prevent it being pulled out of the plug
* Three pins made of brass, one of which is the earth pin.
* A fuse.
* A case made of plastic.

'''Q2)''' Why are the pins made of brass and why is the case plastic?

==The purpose of the parts of a plug==
===The line and neutral wires===
The line and neutral wires carry the current around the circuit. Mains current is A.C. (alternating current); this means that it is going backward and forwards in cycles (clockwise and anticlockwise around the circuit). The frequency of the cycle is 50 hertz (50 times per second). This cycling of current is achieved by varying the voltage on the line wire from about +325V to - you to the earth. This is where the earth wire is included, for your safety. The earth wire connects the case of the appliance out  down the flex to the earth pin on its plug. This connection goes into the socket, then inside the wiring of your house down to the earth through the earthing system (not necessarily plumbing). 

If the line wire were to touch the case a huge current would flow through the earth wire. This would probably blow the fuse and break the circuit (see next section). However even if the fuse doesn't blow the current would still prefer to flow through a wire with low resistance than a human body with relatively higher resistance. 

Thus the earth wire helps protect you if you touch the case of an appliance that is &quot;live&quot;. 

The earth pin on a plug is longer than the line and neutral pins. This ensures that the earth pin always connects with the socket first. All sockets have shutters which prevent access to the live contacts when there is no plug in the socket.  On some sockets these shutters are operated by the earth pin pushing the shutter mechanism down to uncover the line and neutral socket contacts, on other sockets there is a mechanism which opens the shutters when the two live pins are inserted simultaneously, and on other sockets when all three pins are inserted simultaneously.

===The fuse===
A fuse is simply a very thin wire. The wire has a quite low melting point. As current flows through the wire it heats up. If too large a current flows it melts, breaking the circuit. Fuses are used to protect the flexible lead between the plug and the appliance. If too large a current flows through an lead it may overheat or catch fire. Fuses are unlikely to act quickly enough to prevent human electrocution &amp;ndash; their main purpose is to prevent fires due to large currents.

Fuses are rated according to how much current they can carry before melting. In plugs fuses are usually 3A (red), 5A (black), or 13A (brown). The correct fuse is the one that matches the current rating of the lead.

All plug fuses must comply to British Standard BS1362. The rating and &quot;BS1362&quot; should be explicitly marked on such fuses. 

'''Q4)''' A table lamp usually carries a current of 0.5A. What fuse should be put in the plug: 3A, 5A, or 13A?

'''Q5)''' An iron usually carries a current of 5.2A. What fuse should be put in the plug: 3A, 5A, or 13A?

'''Q6)'''  A kettle is protected by an earth wire and a 13A fuse. The line wire comes loose and touches the side of the kettle. The fuse blows. Explain why.

'''Q7)''' Explain why the fuse is always located on the line wire and not the neutral wire?

'''Q8)''' Describe and Explain what happens in the following scenarios:
        a) The earth and line wire switch terminals on the plug
        b) The line and neutral wire switch terminals on the plug
        c) The neutral and earth wire switch terminals on the plug
        d) When the earth wire is removed


{| bgcolor=&quot;ffeeaa&quot;
|-
| '''Summary of this topic'''
|-
| The ''line wire'' is brown, and has A.C. voltage of 230V&lt;br&gt;
The ''neutral wire'' is blue  and has A.C. voltage of approximately zero.&lt;br&gt;
The ''earth wire'' is green and yellow and is a safety device designed to protect people from shocks.&lt;br&gt;
The ''fuse'' is a device that melts and breaks the circuit when the current gets too high.&lt;br&gt;
The case is made of plastic (an insulator) for safety.
|}
----
[[GCSE Science/Safety in Mains circuits answers|Answers]] | [[GCSE Science/Three useful components|&lt;&lt;Three useful components]] | [[GCSE Science/Electrical Power|Power&gt;&gt;]]

[[Category:GCSE Science]]</text>
      <sha1>f1o7zj8tpz3jsft4ammtn2l8wr4jzar</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Plug diagram.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1217</id>
    <revision>
      <id>636313</id>
      <parentid>153343</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-11-04T10:51:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Theresa knott</username>
        <id>93</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">
{{GFDL}}
{{Cc-by-sa-2.5}}
Drawn by theresa knott using microsoft word and paint shop pro</text>
      <sha1>fu7ea4d2urf7z6v0w2h2ik28zlz9nld</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Botany/Plant structure laboratory</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1218</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1278186</id>
      <parentid>1278183</parentid>
      <timestamp>2008-09-15T00:57:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mike.lifeguard</username>
        <id>55262</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Image:Leaves opposite.jpg|400px</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">''I'm experimenting here with the practicality of having laboratory excercises as part of the Botany Study Guide'' Comments invited.

== Chapter 3. Plant Structure Laboratory ==

=== Leaves ===

&lt;div style=&quot;float:right;margin:0 0 1em 0;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;[[Image:Leaves opposite.jpg||400px|Sessile joyweed]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;Ludwigia palustris'' (Onagraceae)([[media:leaves_opposite.jpg|2x Enlarge]])''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Examine this 'marsh purslane' plant and determine the following about its leaves:

'''3-1'''. ''Leaf arrangement is'':
:a) opposite
:b) alternate
:c) whorled
:d) entire
:e) smooth 
&lt;br&gt;
'''3-2'''. ''Which of the following describes the leaves'':
:a) sessile, margin toothed
:b) peltate, margin entire
:c) sessile, margin entire
:d) petiolate, margin crenate
:e) petiolate and hirsute

'''3-3'''. ''Only one of the following statements is true'':
:a) A ''monocot'' with clasping leaves
:b) A ''dicot'' with hairy, waxy leaves to reduce water loss
:c) A ''monocot'' growing in relatively wet areas
:d) A ''dicot'' with leaves opposite, leaf bases attenuate
:e) A wetland plant with compound leaves

&lt;&lt; [[Botany/Plant_structure|Chapter 3]]
----
''Answers to Laboratory Questions:''
:'''3-1''' ~ a
:'''3-2''' ~ d (but tricky, as ''petiole'' is about 1 mm long and margins weakly crenate).
:'''3-3''' ~ d

[[Category:Botany]]</text>
      <sha1>4wchd6gimo0hmg3veeozsjfredzti9n</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Discrete Mathematics/Number theory</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1223</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2685958</id>
      <parentid>2562852</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-07-30T15:44:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>180.214.139.126</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* An example */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Number theory''' is a large encompassing subject in its own right. Here we will examine the key concepts of number theory. 

== Introduction ==
Unlike real analysis and calculus which deals with the dense set of real numbers, number theory examines mathematics in discrete sets, such as '''N''' or '''Z'''. If you are unsure about sets, you may wish to revisit [[../Set theory/]].

Number Theory, the study of the integers, is one of the oldest and richest branches of mathematics.  Its basic concepts are those of divisibility, prime numbers, and integer solutions to equations -- all very simple to understand, but immediately giving rise to some of the best known theorems and biggest unsolved problems in mathematics.  The Theory of Numbers is also a very interdisciplinary subject.  Ideas from combinatorics (the study of counting), algebra, and complex analysis all find their way in, and eventually become essential for understanding parts of number theory.  Indeed, the greatest open problem in all mathematics, the Riemann Hypothesis, is deeply tied into Complex Analysis.  But never fear, just start right into ''Elementary Number Theory'', one of the warmest invitations to pure mathematics, and one of the most surprising areas of applied mathematics!

== Divisibility ==
Note that in '''R''', '''Q''', and '''C''', we can ''divide'' freely, except by zero. This property is often known as ''closure'' -- the quotient of two rationals is again a rational, etc..  However, if we move to performing mathematics purely in a set such as '''Z''', we come into difficulty. This is because, in the integers, the result of a division of two integers might not be another integer. For example, we can of course divide 6 by 2 to get 3, but we ''cannot'' divide 6 by 5, because the fraction 6/5 is not in the set of integers.

However we can introduce a new relation where division '''is''' defined. We call this relation ''divisibility'', and if &lt;math&gt;\frac{b}{a}&lt;/math&gt; is an integer, we say:
* &lt;math&gt;a&lt;/math&gt; divides &lt;math&gt;b&lt;/math&gt;
* &lt;math&gt;a&lt;/math&gt; is a factor of &lt;math&gt;b&lt;/math&gt;
* &lt;math&gt;b&lt;/math&gt; is a multiple of &lt;math&gt;a&lt;/math&gt;
* &lt;math&gt;b&lt;/math&gt; is divisible by &lt;math&gt;a&lt;/math&gt;

Formally, if there exists an integer &lt;math&gt;q&lt;/math&gt; such that &lt;math&gt;b = qa&lt;/math&gt; then we say that &lt;math&gt;a&lt;/math&gt; '''divides''' &lt;math&gt;b&lt;/math&gt; and write &lt;math&gt;a \mid b&lt;/math&gt;.  If &lt;math&gt;a&lt;/math&gt; does not divide &lt;math&gt;b&lt;/math&gt; then we write &lt;math&gt;a \nmid b&lt;/math&gt;:

'''Proposition.'''  The following are basic consequences of this definition.  Let a, b, and c be integers:
* (a) If a|b then a|(bc).
* (b) If a|b and b|c, then a|c.
* (c) If a|b and a|c, then for any integers x and y, a|(xb+yc) -- in other words a divides any ''linear combination'' of its multiples.
* (d) If both a|b and b|a, then a = b or a = -b.
* (e) If c is not 0, then a|b is equivalent to ca|cb.

== Quotient and divisor theorem ==
For any integer ''n'' and any ''k'' &amp;gt; 0, there is a unique ''q'' and ''r'' such that:

:''n'' = ''qk'' + ''r'' (with 0 &amp;le; ''r'' &amp;lt; ''k'')



We call ''q'' the ''quotient'', ''r'' the ''remainder'', and ''k'' the ''divisor''.

It is probably easier to recognize this as division by the algebraic re-arrangement:

:''n/k'' = ''q'' + ''r/k'' (0 &amp;le; ''r/k'' &amp;lt; 1)

== Modular arithmetic==
What can we say about the numbers that divide another? Pick the number 8 for example. What is the remainder on dividing 1 by 8? Using the division theorem above

: 0 = 8*0 + 0
: 1 = 8*0 + 1
: 2 = 8*0 + 2
: :
: 8 = 8*1 + 0
: 9 = 8*1 + 1
: 10 = 8 * 1 + 2
: : 
: ''and so on''

We have a notation for the remainders, and can write the above equations as 

:0 mod 8 = 0
:1 mod 8 = 1
:2 mod 8 = 2
:3 mod 8 = 3
:4 mod 8 = 4
:5 mod 8 = 5
:6 mod 8 = 6
:7 mod 8 = 7
:8 mod 8 = 0
:9 mod 8 = 1
:10 mod 8 = 2
: :

We can also write
:1 &amp;equiv; 1 (mod 8)
:2 &amp;equiv; 2 (mod 8)
:3 &amp;equiv; 3 (mod 8)
:4 &amp;equiv; 4 (mod 8)
:5 &amp;equiv; 5 (mod 8)
:6 &amp;equiv; 6 (mod 8)
:7 &amp;equiv; 7 (mod 8)
:8 &amp;equiv; 0 (mod 8)
:9 &amp;equiv; 1 (mod 8)
:10 &amp;equiv; 2 (mod 8)
: :



These notations are all short for

: ''a'' = 8''k''+''r'' for some integer ''k''.

So ''x'' &amp;equiv; 1 (mod 8), for example, is the same as saying

: ''x'' = 8''k''+1

Observe that the remainder here, in comparing it with the division algorithm is 1. ''x'' &amp;equiv; 1 (mod 8) asks what numbers have the remainder 1 on division by 8? Clearly the solutions are ''x''=8&amp;times;0+1, 8&amp;times;1+1,... = 1, 9, ...  

Often the entire set of remainders on dividing by ''n'' - which we say ''modulo n'' - are interesting to look at. We write this set '''Z'''&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;. Note that this set is finite. The remainder on dividing 9 by 8 is 1 - the same as dividing 1 by 8. So in a sense 9 is really &quot;the same as&quot; 1. In fact, the relation &quot;&amp;equiv;&quot; 

: ''x'' &amp;equiv; ''y'' iff ''x'' mod ''n'' = ''y'' mod ''n''.

is an equivalence relation. We call this relation ''congruence''.
Note that the equivalence classes defined by congruence are precisely the elements of '''Z'''&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;.

We can find some number ''a'' modulo ''n'' (or we say ''a'' congruent to ''n'') by finding its decomposition using the division algorithm. 

Addition, subtraction, and multiplication work in '''Z'''&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt; - for example 3 + 6 (mod 8) = 9 (mod 8) = 1 (mod 8). The numbers do look strange but they follow many normal properties such as commutativity and associativity. 

If we have a number greater than ''n'' we often reduce it modulo ''n'' first - again using the division algorithm. For example if we want to find 11+3 mod 8, its often easier to calculate 3 + 3 (mod 8) rather than reducing 14 mod 8. A trick that's often used is that, say, if we have 6 + 7 (mod 8) we can use ''negative'' numbers instead so the problem becomes -2 + -1 = -3 = 5 (mod 8).

We often use the second notation when we want to look at equations involving numbers modulo some ''n''.  For example, we may want to find a number ''x'' such that
: 3''x'' &amp;equiv; 5 (mod 8)

We can find solutions by trial substitution (going through all the numbers 0 through 7), but what if the moduli are very large? We will look at a more systematic solution later.

'''Note''': we often say that we are working in '''Z'''&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt; and use equals signs throughout. Familiarize yourself with the three ways of writing modular equations and expressions.
== Number Bases ==

Converting between various number bases is one of the most tedious processes in [[mathematics]]. 

The numbers that are generally used in transactions are all in base-10. This means that there are 10 digits that are used to describe a number. These ten digits are {0,1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9}. 

Similarly, base-4 has 4 digits {0,1,2,3} and base-2 has two digits {0,1}. Base two is sometimes referred to as Binary.

There are also bases greater than 10. For these bases, it is customary to use letters to represent digits greater than 10. An example is Base-16 (Hexadecimal). The digits used in this base are {0,1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,A,B,C,D,E,F}. 

In order to convert between number bases, it is critical that one knows how to divide numbers and find remainders. 

To convert from decimal to another base one must simply start dividing by the value of the other base, then dividing the result of the first division and overlooking the remainder, and so on until the base is larger than the result (so the result of the division would be a zero). Then the number in the desired base is the remainders read from end to start.

The following shows how to convert a number (105) which is in base-10 into base-2.


{| border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; cellpadding=&quot;10&quot;
! Operation
! Remainder
|- 
| 105 / 2 = 52
| 1
|-
| 52 / 2 = 26
| 0
|-
| 26 / 2 = 13
| 0
|-
| 13 / 2 = 6
| 1
|-
| 6 / 2 = 3
| 0
|-
| 3 / 2 = 1
| 1
|-
| 1 / 2 = 0
| 1
|}


Answer : 1101001


After finishing this process, the remainders are taken and placed in a row (from bottom to top) after the final quotient (1101001, in this example) is shown as the base-2 equivalent of the number 105. 

To sum up the process, simply take the original number in base 10, and divide that number repeatedly, keeping track of the remainders, until the quotient becomes less than the numerical value of the base.

This works when converting any number from base-10 to any base. If there are any letters in the base digits, then use the letters to replace any remainder greater than 9. For example, writing 11(of base-10) in base 14.


{| border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; cellpadding=&quot;10&quot;
! Operation
! Remainder
|-
| 11 / 14 = 0
| B (=11)
|}


Answer: B


As 11 is a single remainder, it is written as a single digit. Following the pattern {10=A, 11=B, 12=C...35=Z}, write it as B. If you were to write &amp;quot;11&amp;quot; as the answer, it would be wrong, as &quot;11&quot; Base-14 is equal to 15 in base-10!

In order to convert from a number in any base back to base ten, the following process should be used:

Take the number 3210 (in base-10). In the units place (10&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt;), there is a 0. In the tens place (10&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;), there is a 1. In the hundreds place (10&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;), there is a 2. In the thousands place (10&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;), there is a 3.

The formula to find the value of the above number is:

3×10&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; + 2×10&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; + 1×10&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; + 0×10&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt; = 3000 + 200 + 10 + 0 = '''3210'''.

The process is similar when converting from any base to base-10. For example, take the number 3452 (in base-6). In the units place (6&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt;), there is a 2. In the sixths place (6&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;) there is a 5. In the thirty-sixths place (6&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;), there is a 4. In the 216th place (6&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;), there is a 3.

The formula to find the value of the above number (in base-10) is:

3×6&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; + 4×6&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; + 5×6&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; + 2×6&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt; = 648 + 144 + 30 + 2 = '''824'''.

The value of 3452 (base-6) is '''824''' in base-10.

A more efficient algorithm is to add the left-most digit and multiply by the base, and repeat with the next digit and so on.

((3 * 6 + 4) * 6 + 5) * 6 + 2 = 824

The processes to convert between number bases may seem difficult at first, but become easy if one practices often.

== Prime numbers ==
Prime numbers are the building blocks of the integers. A prime number is a positive integer greater than one that has only two divisors: 1, and the number itself. For example, 17 is prime because the only positive integers that divide evenly into it are 1 and 17. The number 6 is not a prime since more than two divsors 1, 2, 3, 6 divide 6. Also, note that 1 is not a prime since 1 has only one divisor.

=== Some prime numbers ===
The prime numbers as a sequence begin
: 2, 3, 5, 7, 11, 13, 17, 19, 23, ...

=== Euclid's Proof that There are Infinitely Many Primes ===
The Greek mathematician [[w:Euclid|Euclid]] gave the following elegant proof that there are an infinite number of primes. It relies on the fact that all non-prime numbers --- composites --- have a unique factorization into primes.

Euclid's proof works by contradiction: we will assume that there are a finite number of primes, and show that we can derive a logically contradictory fact.

So here we go. First, we assume that that there are a finite number of primes:

: p&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;, p&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, ... , p&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;

Now consider the number M defined as follows:

: M = 1 +  p&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; *  p&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; * ... *  p&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;

There are two important --- and ultimately contradictory --- facts about the number M:

# It cannot be prime because p&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt; is the biggest prime (by our initial assumption), and M is clearly bigger than p&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;. Thus, there must be some prime p that divides M.
# It is not divisible by any of the numbers p&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;, p&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, ..., p&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;.   Consider what would happen if you tried to divide M by any of the primes in the list p&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;, p&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, ... , p&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;.  From the definition of M, you can tell that you would end up with a remainder of 1. That means that p --- the prime that divides M --- must be bigger than any of p&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;, ..., p&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;.

Thus, we have shown that M is divisible by a prime p that is not on the finite list of all prime. And so there must be an infinite number of primes.


These two facts imply that M must be divisible by a prime number bigger than p&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;. Thus, there cannot be a biggest prime.

Note that this proof does not provide us with a direct way to generate arbitrarily large primes, although it always generates a number which is divisible by a new prime. Suppose we know only one prime: 2.  So, our list of primes is simply p&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;=2. Then, in the notation of the proof, M=1+2=3.  We note that M is prime, so we add 3 to the list.  Now, M = 1 +2 *3 = 7.  Again, 7 is prime.  So we add it to the list.  Now, M = 1+2*3*7 = 43: again prime.  Continuing in this way one more time, we calculate M = 1+2*3*7*43 = 1807 =13*139.  So we see that M is not prime. 

Viewed another way: note that while 1+2, 1+2*3, 1+2*3*5, 1+2*3*5*7, and 1+2*3*5*7*11 are prime, 1+2*3*5*7*11*13=30031=59*509 is not.

=== Testing for primality ===
There are a number of simple and sophisticated primality tests. We will consider some simple tests here. In upper-level courses we will consider some faster and more sophisticated methods to test whether a number is prime.

====Inspection====
The most immediate and simple test to eliminate a number n as a prime is to inspect the units digit or the last digit of a number. 

If the number n ends in an even number 0, 2, 4, 6, 8 we can show that number n cannot be a prime. For example, take n = 87536 = 8753(10) + 6. Since 10 is divisible by 2 and 6 is divisible by 2 then 87536 must be divisible by 2. In general, any even number can be expressed in the form n = a*10 + b, where b = 0, 2, 4, 6, 8. Since 10 is divisible by 2 and b is divisible by 2 then n = a*10 + b is divisible by 2. Consequently, any number n which ends in an even number such as 7777732 or 8896 is divisible by 2 so n is not a prime.

In a similar type of argument, if a number n ends in a 5 we can show the number n cannot be a prime. If the last digit of n, call it b, is a 5 we can express n in the form n = a*10 + b, where b = 5. Since 10 is divisible by 5 and b = 5 is divisible by 5 then n = a*10 + b is divisible by 5. Hence, any number n which ends in a 5 such as 93475 is divisible by 5 so n is not a prime. 

Thus, if a number greater than 5 is a prime it must end with either a 1, 3, 7, or 9. Note that this does not mean all numbers that end in a 1, 3, 7, or 9 are primes. For example, while the numbers 11, 23, 37, 59 are primes, the numbers 21 = 3*7, 33 = 3*11, 27 = 3*9, 39 = 3*13 are not primes. Consequently, if a number ends in a 1, 3, 7, or 9 we have to test further.

====Trial Division Method====
To test if a number n that ends in a 1, 3, 7, or 9 is prime, we could simply try the smallest prime number and try to divide it in n. If that doesn't divide, we would take the next largest prime number and try again etc. Certainly, if we took all primes numbers in this manner that were less than n and we could not divide n then we would be justified in saying n is prime. However, it can be shown that you don't have to take all primes smaller than n to test if n is prime. We can stop earlier by using the Trial Division Method.

The justification of the Trial Division Method is if a number n has no divisors less than or equal to &lt;math&gt;\sqrt{n}&lt;/math&gt; then n must be a prime. We can show this by contradiction. Let us assume n has no divisors less than or equal to &lt;math&gt;\sqrt{n}&lt;/math&gt;. If n is not a prime, there must be two numbers a and b such that &lt;math&gt;a*b = n&lt;/math&gt;. In particular, by our assumption &lt;math&gt;\sqrt{n} &lt; a &lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\sqrt{n} &lt; b &lt;/math&gt;. But then &lt;math&gt;n = \sqrt{n}\sqrt{n} &lt; a*b = n&lt;/math&gt;. Since a number can not be greater than itself the number n must be a prime.

Trial Division Method is a method of primality testing that involves taking a number n and then sequentially dividing it by primes up to &lt;math&gt;\sqrt{n}&lt;/math&gt;.

For example, is 113 prime? &lt;math&gt;\sqrt{113}&lt;/math&gt; is approximately 10.63...
We only need to test whether 2, 3, 5, 7 divide 113 cleanly (leave no remainder, i.e., the quotient is an integer).
:113/2 is not an integer since the last digit is not even.
:113/3 (=37.666...) is not an integer.
:113/5 is not an integer since the last digit does not end in a 0 or 5.
:113/7 (=16.142857...) is not an integer.

So we need not look at any more primes such as 11, 13, 17 etc. less than 113 to test, since 2, 3, 5, 7 does not divide 113 cleanly, 113 is prime.

Notice that after rejecting 2 and 3 as a divisor, we next considered the next prime number 5 and not the next number 4. We know not to consider 4 because we know 2 does not divide 113. If 2 cannot divide 113 then certainly 4 cannot because if 4 divided 113 and since 2 divides 4 then 2 would divide 113. So we only use the next cheapest available prime to test not the next consecutive number.

If we test 91 we get,

:91/2 is not an integer since that last digit is not even.
:91/3= (30.333) is not an integer.
:91/5= is not an integer since the last digit does not end in a 0 or 5.
:91/7=13 is an integer

So we know since 7 divides 91, 91 is not a prime.

Trial division is normally only used for relatively small numbers due to its inefficiency. However this technique has the two advantages that firstly once we have tested a number we know for sure that it is prime and secondly if a number is not prime it also gives us the number's factors.

To obtain a few small primes, it may be best to use the [[w:Sieve of Eratosthenes|Sieve of Eratosthenes]] than to test each number sequentially using trial division. The Sieve of Eratosthenes method is basically a process of finding primes by elimination. We start by taking a list of consecutive numbers say 1 to 100. Cross out the number 1 because the number is not prime. Take the next least uncrossed off number which is 2 and circle it. Now cross out all multiples of 2 on the list. Next take the next least uncircled number which is 3. Circle the number 3 and cross out all multiples of 3. The next least uncircled number should be 5 since 4 is a multiple of 2 and should have been crossed off. Circle the number 5 and cross out all multiples of 5. The next least uncircled number should be a 7 since 6 is a multiple of 2. Circle the 7 and mark off all multiples of 7. Now the next uncrossed off number should be 11 since 8,9,10 is a multiple of 2, 3, and 2. If we continue in this manner what is left is the circled numbers which are primes. But notice we can actually stop now and circle all the unmarked numbers after crossing off multiples of 7 because of the result that since &lt;math&gt;\sqrt{100} = 10&lt;/math&gt; any number less than 100 which is not prime must be divisible by 2, 3, 5, or 7.

== The Fundamental Theorem of Arithmetic ==
'''The Fundamental Theorem of Arithmetic''' is an important theorem relating to the factorization of numbers. The theorem basically states that every positive integer can be written as the product of prime numbers in a unique way (ignoring reordering the product of prime numbers).

In particular, '''The Fundamental Theorem of Arithmetic''' means any number such as 1,943,032,663 is either a prime or can be factored into a product of primes. If a number such as 1,943,032,663 can be factored into primes such as 11&amp;times;13&amp;times;17&amp;times;19&amp;times;23&amp;times;31&amp;times;59 it is futile to try to find another different combination of prime numbers that will also give you the same number.

To make the theorem work even for the number 1, we think of 1 as being the product of zero prime numbers.

More formally,
:For all ''n''&amp;isin;'''N'''
::''n''=p&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;p&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;p&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;...
:where the p&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; are all prime numbers, and can be repeated.

Here are some examples.
: 4 = 2 &amp;times; 2 = 2&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
: 12 = 2 &amp;times; 2 &amp;times; 3 = 2&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; &amp;times; 3
: 11 = 11.
A proof of the Fundamental Theorem of Arithmetic will be given after Bezout's identity has been established.

== LCM and GCD ==
Two characteristics we can determine between two numbers based on their factorizations are the ''lowest common multiple'', the ''LCM'' and ''greatest common divisor'', the ''GCD'' (also ''greatest common factor'', ''GCF'')

=== LCM===
The lowest common multiple, or the least common multiple, for two numbers a and b is the smallest number designated by LCM(a,b) that is divisible by both the number a and the number b. We can find LCM(a,b) by finding the prime factorization of a and b and choosing the maximum power for each prime factor.

In another words, if the number a factors to &lt;math&gt;p_1^{\alpha_1}p_2^{\alpha_2}\cdots p_n^{\alpha_n}&lt;/math&gt;, and the number b factors to &lt;math&gt;p_1^{\beta_1}p_2^{\beta_2}\cdots p_n^{\beta_n}&lt;/math&gt;, then LCM(a,b) = &lt;math&gt;p_1^{\gamma_1}p_2^{\gamma_2}\cdots p_n^{\gamma_n}&lt;/math&gt;  
where &lt;math&gt;\gamma_i = Maximum (\alpha_i, \beta_i)&lt;/math&gt; for ''i'' = ''1 to n''.

An example, let us see the process on how we find lowest common multiple for 5500 and 450 which happens to be 49500. First, we find the prime factorization for 5500 and 450 which is
:5500=2&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; 5&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; 11  
:450=2 3&lt;sup&gt; 2&lt;/sup&gt; 5&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; 

Notice the different primes we came up for both the number 5500 and the number 450 are 2, 3, 5, and 11. Now let us express 5500 and 450 completely in a product of these primes raised to the appropriate power.
:5500=2&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; 5&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; 11 = 2&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; 3&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt; 5&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; 11&lt;sup&gt;1 
:450=2 3&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; 5&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 2&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; 3&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; 5&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; 11&lt;sup&gt;0

The LCM(5500,450) is going to be in the form 2&lt;sup&gt;?&lt;/sup&gt; 3&lt;sup&gt;?&lt;/sup&gt; 5&lt;sup&gt;?&lt;/sup&gt; 11&lt;sup&gt;?&lt;/sup&gt;. All we now have to do is find what the powers of each individual prime will be.

So now we compare the power of each prime for 5500 and 450. Let us consider the powers of the first prime 2. In the number 5500, the prime 2 is raised to the second power and in the number 450, prime 2 is raised to the first power. Since the maximum between 2 and 1 for the power of the prime 2 is 2, we use 2 for the power of the prime 2.

Now let us consider the powers of the prime 3. In the number 5500, the prime 3 is raised to the zero power and in the number 450 the prime 3 is raised to the second power. Since the maximum between 0 and 2 for the power of the prime 3 is 2, we use 2 for the power of the prime 3.

Similarly, let us consider the powers of the next prime 5. In the number 5500, the prime 5 is raised to the third power and in the number 450 the prime 5 is raised to the second power. Since the maximum between 3 and 2 for the power of the prime 5 is 3, we use 3 for the power of the prime 5.

Finally, let us consider the powers of the prime 11, the last prime on our list. In the number 5500, the prime 11 is raised to the first power and in the number 450 the prime 11 is raised to the zero power. Since the maximum between 1 and 0 for the power of the prime 11 is 1, we use 1 for the power of the last prime 11.

Consequently, the product of our results is LCM(5500,450)=2&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; 3&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; 5&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; 11&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; = 49500.

=== GCD===
The greatest common divisor for two numbers a and b is the biggest number designated by GCD(a,b) that divides both the number a and the number b. In a similar process to finding LCM(a,b), we can find GCD(a,b) by finding the prime factorization of a and b but choosing the minimum power for each prime factor instead.

In other words, if the number a factors to &lt;math&gt;p_1^{\alpha_1}p_2^{\alpha_2}\cdots p_n^{\alpha_n}&lt;/math&gt;, and the number b factors to &lt;math&gt;p_1^{\beta_1}p_2^{\beta_2}\cdots p_n^{\beta_n}&lt;/math&gt;, then GCD(a,b) = &lt;math&gt;p_1^{\gamma_1}p_2^{\gamma_2}\cdots p_n^{\gamma_n}&lt;/math&gt;  
where &lt;math&gt;\gamma_i = Minimum (\alpha_i, \beta_i)&lt;/math&gt; for ''i'' = ''1 to n''.

An example, let us see the process on how we find the greatest common divisor for 5500 and 450 which happens to be 50. First, we find the prime factorization for 5500 and 450 which is
:5500=2&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; 5&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; 11  
:450=2 3&lt;sup&gt; 2&lt;/sup&gt; 5&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; 

Notice the different primes we came up for both the number 5500 and the number 450 are 2, 3, 5, and 11. Now let us express 5500 and 450 completely in a product of these primes raised to the appropriate power.
:5500=2&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; 5&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; 11 = 2&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; 3&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt; 5&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; 11&lt;sup&gt;1 
:450=2 3&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; 5&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 2&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; 3&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; 5&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; 11&lt;sup&gt;0

The GCD(5500,450) is going to be in the form 2&lt;sup&gt;?&lt;/sup&gt; 3&lt;sup&gt;?&lt;/sup&gt; 5&lt;sup&gt;?&lt;/sup&gt; 11&lt;sup&gt;?&lt;/sup&gt;. All we now have to do is find what the powers of each individual prime will be.

So now we compare the power of each prime for 5500 and 450. Let us consider the powers of the first prime 2. In the number 5500, the prime 2 is raised to the second power and in the number 4&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;
50, prime 2 is raised to the first power. Since the minimum between 2 and 1 for the power of the prime 2 is 1, we use 1 for the power of the prime 2.

Now let us consider the powers of the prime 3. In the number 5500, the prime 3 is raised to the zero power and in the number 450 the prime 3 is raised to the second power. Since the minimum between 0 and 2 for the power of the prime 3 is 0, we use 0 for the power of the prime 3.

Similarly, let us consider the powers of the next prime 5. In the number 5500, the prime 5 is raised to the third power and in the number 450 the prime 5 is raised to the second power. Since the minimum between 3 and 2 for the power of the prime 5 is 2, we use 2 for the power of the prime 5.

Finally, let us consider the powers of the prime 11, the last prime on our list. In the number 5500, the prime 11 is raised to the first power and in the number 450 the prime 11 is raised to the zero power. Since the minimum between 1 and 0 for the power of the prime 11 is 0, we use 0 for the power of the last prime 11.

Consequently, the product of our results is GCD(5500,450)=2&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; 3&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt; 5&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; 11&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt; = 50.

==== Properties ====
*gcd(''a'',''b'')=gcd(''b'',''a'')
*gcd(''a'',''b'') = gcd(''b'',''q''), where ''q'' is the remainder of a divided by b
*gcd(''a''/''d'', ''b''/''d'')=1, where ''d'' is gcd(''a'',''b'')

== The Euclidean algorithm ==
The Euclidean algorithm is such that we can find the gcd of two numbers without finding the factorization&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;. The Euclidean algorithm consists of only addition and multiplication, and uses the above properties of gcd as its basis.

&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt; Factorization is a &quot;hard&quot; process, that is, to factor a number takes a long time depending on the length of the number. This is why later, when you need to find the gcd of a pair of numbers, you will most likely ''never'' factorize the numbers and use the properties of the primes but will use the Euclidean algorithm instead.

=== An example ===
We will see how this works by calculating gcd(11,17)
&lt;!-- Chosen so the k and r below are different to each other --&gt;

First, divide 458 by 44 and obtain the remainder: 
: 458 = 44 &amp;times; 10 + 18

Now suppose that a number is a common divisor of 458 and 44.  Then it must also be a divisor of 18.  To see this, rearrange the above equation to:
:458 - 44&amp;times;10 =18

When this equation is divided by a common divisor of 44 and 458, an integer is obtained on the left, and so must also be obtained on the right.  This, by definition, means that the number is also a divisor of 18.  By the same reasoning, any common divisor of 18 and 44 is also a divisor of 458.  Since all of the common divisors of 458 and 44 are equal to common divisors of 44 and 18, then in particular the greatest common divisors are equal. So we have gcd(458,44)=gcd(44,18)

The next step in the algorithm is to divide 44 by 18 and find the remainder.
: 44 = 18 &amp;times; ''k'' + ''r''
: 44 = 18 &amp;times; 2 + 8
Repeat this process; keep dividing the previous divisor by the previous remainder:
: 18 = 8 &amp;times; 2 + 2
: 8 = 2 &amp;times; 4 + 0

Our gcd is the last remainder before the zero, in this case, 2.  This is because the reasoning that proved gcd(458,44)=gcd(44,18) applies at every step, so gcd(458,44)=gcd(44,18)=gcd(18,8)=gcd(8,2)=gcd(2,0)=2.

=== The Matrix Method ===

We can construct a matrix that provides an alternative method for calculating the greatest common divisor.  In its general form, the matrix is

&lt;math&gt;
\begin{bmatrix}
   1 &amp; 0 &amp; b \\
   0 &amp; 1 &amp; a \\
\end{bmatrix}
&lt;/math&gt;

Recall that one way to write the gcd of two numbers is as an '''integral linear combination'''.  If we are finding the gcd, for example, we could represent it as ''as + bt'', where ''a'' and ''b'' are the two numbers we are comparing, and ''s'' and ''t'' are integers.  We also know that ''b = aq + r'' where ''r'' is the remainder upon division of ''b'' by ''a''.  After we subtract row 2 from row 1, we get

&lt;math&gt;
 \begin{bmatrix}
   1 &amp; -q_{1} &amp; r_{1} \\
   0 &amp; 1 &amp; a \\
 \end{bmatrix}
&lt;/math&gt;

If r_2 is nonzero, we must continue the process; this time, subtracting row 1 from row 2.  We continue this process until one of the '' r's '' has been reduced as far as possible.  We now have our gcd.  The numbers that are in that row, where the 1 and the 0 used to be, represent ''t'' and ''s'', respectively.

Let us now look at a computational example.

&lt;math&gt;
 \begin{bmatrix}
   1 &amp; 0 &amp; 99 \\
   0 &amp; 1 &amp; 7 \\
 \end{bmatrix} \rightsquigarrow 
\begin{bmatrix}
   1 &amp; 0 &amp; 99 \\
   0 &amp; 14 &amp; 98 \\
   \end{bmatrix} \rightsquigarrow
 \begin{bmatrix}
   1 &amp; -14 &amp; 1 \\
   0 &amp; 14 &amp; 98 \\
   \end{bmatrix}
&lt;/math&gt;

We see that it would be trivial at this point to go any further; we would just end up with row-2 containing a zero where ''a'' used to be.  So we look at row-1 and remember that the ''1'' represents our remainder, 1(=t) multiplies ''b'' and -14(=s) multiplies ''a'' such that


&lt;math&gt;1 = 99 \times 1 + -14 \times 7 &lt;/math&gt;

This can be checked by the Euclidean algorithm that gcd(7,99)=1.

== The extended Euclidean algorithm ==
What happens if we try and reverse the process of the Euclidean algorithm by substituting back? &lt;!-- note to self: give example. --&gt;Back-substitution is rather tedious and prone to error, so here is a faster method. 

Draw up a table with four columns, label these from left to right ''q'', ''r'', ''u'', ''v''. For convenience label a column ''i'' representing the step we're currently up to. Place ''a'' and ''b'' with the greater of these on top in the column ''r'', and place 1s and 0s accordingly:

&lt;math&gt;
\begin{matrix}
i &amp; q &amp; r &amp; u &amp; v \\
-1 &amp; . &amp; b &amp; 0 &amp; 1\\
0 &amp; . &amp; a &amp; 1 &amp; 0 \\
\end{matrix}
&lt;/math&gt;

Now iterate downwards by taking the quotient of ''b''/''a'' and putting it in the next space in the ''q'' column, then of ''b''-''aq'' in the ''r'' column. 

To update ''u'' and ''v'', take 
:''u''&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; = ''u''&lt;sub&gt;i-2&lt;/sub&gt;-''u''&lt;sub&gt;i-1&lt;/sub&gt;''q''&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;
:''v''&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; = ''v''&lt;sub&gt;i-2&lt;/sub&gt;-''v''&lt;sub&gt;i-1&lt;/sub&gt;''q''&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;

Indeed, you are looking for ''u'' and ''v'' such that a''u'' + b''v'' = gcd (a,b).
At some point, gcd (a,b) is in fact the remainder at the
ith stage, so you might as well compute u&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; and v&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; such
that a''u''&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; + b''v''&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; = r&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;, at EACH stage.

Deriving the recurrences found above results from these three
equations (the second equation is Euclid's algorithm's basic property, the other two are constraints we set to attain our desired goal):

:a''u''&lt;sub&gt;i-1&lt;/sub&gt; + b''v''&lt;sub&gt;i-1&lt;/sub&gt; = r&lt;sub&gt;i-1&lt;/sub&gt;
:r&lt;sub&gt;i-2&lt;/sub&gt; = q&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;r&lt;sub&gt;i-1&lt;/sub&gt; + r&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;
:a''u''&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; + b''v''&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; = r&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;

The trick is to then appropriately express r&lt;sub&gt;i-2&lt;/sub&gt;. 

Stop writing when you obtain a 0 in the ''r'' column. 

Finding then, gcd(450,44) (this is the same as gcd(44,450) )

&lt;!-- unroll this --&gt;
&lt;math&gt;
\begin{matrix}
i  &amp; q  &amp; r   &amp; u  &amp; v \\
-1 &amp; .  &amp; 450 &amp; 0  &amp; 1 \\
0  &amp; .  &amp; 44  &amp; 1  &amp; 0 \\
1  &amp; 10 &amp; 10  &amp; -10  &amp; 1 \\
2  &amp; 4  &amp; 4   &amp; 41 &amp; -4 \\
3  &amp; 2  &amp; \mathbf{2}   &amp; -92  &amp; 9 \\
4  &amp; 2  &amp; 0   &amp; -  &amp; - \\
\end{matrix}
&lt;/math&gt;

The bold number is the gcd. Observe (9)&amp;times;450+(-92)&amp;times;44=2
Clearly these ''u'' and ''v'' are very special. What can we say about the general case?

=== Bezout's identity ===
In the above case we have 9&amp;times;450+(-92)&amp;times;44=gcd(450,44). So the greatest common divisor of 450 and 44 can be written as a linear combination of 450 and 44 with integer coefficients.  This turns out to be true of any pair of integers.  This result is known as &quot;Bezout's Identity&quot; and can be stated as follows:
: For any pair of nonzero integers, ''a'' and ''b'', there exists integers ''u'' and ''v'' such that
:: ''au''+''bv''=''gcd(a,b)''
''Proof''
:If ''a'' and ''b'' are any pair of integers, not both 0, then clearly there exist integers ''u'' and ''v'' such that ''au''+''bv'' is positive (just match the signs of ''u'' and ''v'' to those of ''a'' and ''b'', respectivly, for instance), and for all integer ''u'' and ''v'', ''au''+''bv'' is also an integer (because the integers are closed under addition and multiplication).  So there is a non-empty set of positive integers consisting of numbers of the form ''au''+''bv''; call it S.  Since S is a non-empty set of positive integers, it must have a smallest element (this is the so called  [[w:Well-ordering principle|Well-ordering principle]]).  Call this number ''d''.  The claim is that &lt;math&gt;d=gcd(a,b)&lt;/math&gt;.  Since ''d'' belongs to S, then 

:(1)&lt;math&gt;d=ua + vb&lt;/math&gt; 

:for suitable ''u'' and ''v''.  Let ''n'' be any positive common divisor of ''a'' and ''b''.  Since ''n'' divides the right side of (1), it also divides d.  So &lt;math&gt;d=qn&lt;/math&gt; for some integer &lt;math&gt;q\geq 1&lt;/math&gt;.  So any common divisor of ''a'' and ''b'' is less than or equal to ''d''.  Therefore, if ''d'' is a common divisor of ''a'' and ''b'', it is the greatest one.  It only remains to show that ''d'' is in fact a common divisor.  

:To prove this, it will be shown that any element of S is divisible by ''d''.  This will prove that ''d'' is a common divisor of ''a'' and ''b'' because ''a'' and ''b'' are both elements of S  (because ''a'' = 1&amp;times;a + 0&amp;times;b and''b'' = 0&amp;times;a + 1&amp;times;b). Let ''t'' be any element of S.  Then, by the division algorithm 
:&lt;math&gt;t=qd+r&lt;/math&gt;

:for some  &lt;math&gt;0\leq r&lt;d&lt;/math&gt;.  If ''r'' is not 0, then it is in S.  This is because ''d'' and ''t'' are in S, so
:&lt;math&gt;r=t-qd=(u_1a+v_1b)-q(u_2a+v_2b)=(u_1-qu_2)a+(v_1-qv_2)b=u'a+v'b&lt;/math&gt; 
:But, since &lt;math&gt;r&lt;d&lt;/math&gt; and ''d'' is the least element of S, this is impossible.  The only other possibility is that ''r=0''.  Therefore any element, ''t'', of S is divisible by ''d''.  Since this includes both ''a'' and ''b'', ''d'' is a common divisor.  Combining this with the previous result establishes Bezout's Identity.

The numbers ''u'' and ''v'' can either be obtained using the tabular methods or backsubstitution in the Euclidean Algorithm.

== Proof of the Fundamental Theorem of Arithmetic ==
One use of Bezout's identity is in a proof of the Fundamental Theorem of Arithmetic.  Before this is proven, two other results are needed:
Lemma 1: If a prime number, ''p'', divides a product of two integers, &lt;math&gt;ab&lt;/math&gt;, then it must divide ''a'' or ''b'' (or both).
:''Proof:'' If ''p'' divides both ''a'' and ''b'', there is nothing to prove.  Assume ''p'' does not divide ''a''.  If it can be proven under that assumption that ''p'' does divide ''b'', the lemma will be proven.  
:Since ''p'' does not divide ''a'', then ''gcd(a,p)''=1 (because the only divisors of ''p'' are 1 and ''p'', but ''p'' is not a common divisor).  Therefore, by Bezout's Identity, there exist integers ''u'' and ''v'' such that
:&lt;math&gt;1=ua+vp&lt;/math&gt;
:Multiply this equation by ''b'' to obtain:
:&lt;math&gt;b=uab+vbp&lt;/math&gt;
:''p'' divides both terms on the right hand side and, therefore, divides the left hand side.  Hence, ''p'' divides ''b'', as was to be shown.
Lemma 2: If a prime number, ''p'', divides a product of integers, &lt;math&gt;a_1a_2...a_n&lt;/math&gt;, then it must divide at least one of the factors.
:''Proof'': The proof is by [[w:mathematical induction|induction]] on ''n'', the number of factors.  The statement is true for n=2, by Lemma 1.  Assume the statement is true for ''n=k'' and consider a product of ''k''+1 factors.  If ''p'' divides more than one of the factors, once again there is nothing to prove.  Assume that ''p'' does not divide any of the factors &lt;math&gt;a_1, a_2, ... a_k&lt;/math&gt;.  It will be shown that ''p'' must divide &lt;math&gt;a_{k+1}&lt;/math&gt;.  Since the statement is true for n=k, then since ''p'' does not divide any of the factors in &lt;math&gt;a_1a_2...a_k&lt;/math&gt;, it must not divive the product (by [[w:Contrapositive|Contrapositive]]).  Let &lt;math&gt;a_1a_2...a_k=b&lt;/math&gt;.  Then &lt;math&gt;a_1a_2...a_ka_{k+1}=ba_{k+1}&lt;/math&gt;.  The conclusion then follows by Lemma 1.
'''Fundamental Theorem of Arithmetic''':Any positive integer, ''n'', can be expressed as a product of primes.  This product is unique up to the order in which the terms appear.
:''Proof'':  The proof of the first part of the theorem is by induction on ''n''.  If ''n''=1, it is the product of 0 primes.  Assume all positive integers less than ''n'' can be expressed as a product of primes.  If ''n'' is prime, then it is the product of 1 prime.  Assume ''n'' is not prime or 1.  Then &lt;math&gt;n=ab&lt;/math&gt;,for some positive integers ''a'' and ''b'' both less than ''n''.  Since ''a'' and ''b'' are both less than ''n'', they can be written as a product of primes by the induciton hypothesis.  Combining these products gives ''n'' as a product of primes as required.
:Now to prove the second part.  Assume there are two prime factorizations of ''n'', 
:&lt;math&gt;n=p_1p_2...p_k=q_1q_2...q_s&lt;/math&gt;
:&lt;math&gt;p_1&lt;/math&gt; divides the left side and so must also divide the right side.  By Lemma 2, this means that &lt;math&gt;p_1&lt;/math&gt; must divide one of the &lt;math&gt;q_i&lt;/math&gt;.  But these are all prime, so the only way &lt;math&gt;p_1&lt;/math&gt; can divide &lt;math&gt;q_i&lt;/math&gt; is if &lt;math&gt;p_1=q_i&lt;/math&gt; for some ''i''.  Canceling &lt;math&gt;p_1&lt;/math&gt; from both sides of the equation forms another equation of the same form.  So it can likewise be proven that &lt;math&gt;p_2=q_i&lt;/math&gt; for some other ''i'', and so on until all the factors on the left are exhausted.  After this, there must not be any factors remaining on the right side since it must equal 1.  This proves that any two prime factorizations consist of the same prime factors, as was to be shown.

== Solving linear modular equations - back to Bezout ==
Bezout's identity above provides us with the key to solving equations in the form
: ''ax'' &amp;equiv; ''b'' (mod ''m'')

=== Coprime case - gcd(''a'', ''m'') is 1 ===
Consider the case where 
: ''ax'' &amp;equiv; ''b'' (mod ''m'')
but with gcd(''a'', ''m'')=1

Because of Bezout's identity 
: 1 = ''au''+''mv''
When we calculate ''u'', this number is special.

Say if we have the equation
: 4''x''=11 (mod 21)
4 and 21 are coprime since gcd(4,21)=1. Now 1=4*16+(-3)*(21). Our ''u'' in this case is 16. Observe now that 4*16=64. 64 (mod 21) = 1. This number ''u'' is very special - it is known as the ''multiplicative inverse''. It is the number ''u'' on multiplication by ''a'' gives 1 mod ''m''. Bezout's identity on calculating gcd(''a'', ''m'') will always give you the multiplicative inverse of ''a'' modulo ''m''. The multiplicative inverse of ''a'' is often written ''a''&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; but note that this does '''''not''''' mean 1/''a'' since we have seen in the first sections that we can not always divide in the integers.

Note that in '''Z'''&lt;sub&gt;''p''&lt;/sub&gt; there is one number ''without'' a multiplicative inverse - 0. It may be useful to exclude 0 when considering modular arithmetic, so instead of having to say '''Z'''&lt;sub&gt;''p''&lt;/sub&gt;\{0} all the time, we merely write '''Z'''&lt;sub&gt;''p''&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;.

Now since we have the magic multiplicative inverse, our problem becomes relatively easy to solve. 4&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;=16 in '''Z'''&lt;sub&gt;21&lt;/sub&gt; and now, on multiplying throughout by 16
: ''x'' = 11 &amp;times; 16 (mod 21)
(since 4&amp;times;16=1 because 16 is 4's multiplicative inverse mod 21). 11&amp;times;16=176 and using a calculator or using the division theorem we obtain
: ''x'' = 8 (mod 21)

which is our solution! Verify - 8&amp;times;4 = 32 = 11 (mod 21).

=== The general case ===
Consider the general case where 
: ''ax'' &amp;equiv; ''b'' (mod ''m'')
with no restrictions on ''a'', ''b'' and ''m''.

Firstly we calculate 
== gcd ==
gcd(''a'', ''m'') again to obtain ''d''. Now ''d'' is a ''divisor'' since the ''d'' in gc''d'' means greatest common divisor. So we can now divide ''a'' and ''m'' - but what about ''b''? Since we have calculated the gcd of ''a'' and ''m'' '''but not ''b''''' we have no guarantees that ''d'' will divide ''b''. This then becomes a condition that the equation has no solution.

Now we have reduced the problem to the previous coprime case because gcd(''a''/''d'', ''m''/''d'')=1 with ''d'' as above. However we do not have 1 solution any more - this is true because we have reduced the solution to being ''x'' = ''c'' (mod ''m''/''d'') and we must bring the solution back mod ''m''. This will be come clearer in the examples.

Let's work through some examples.

'''Example 1.''' Solve 4''x'' &amp;equiv; 3 (mod 20).
Firstly, gcd(4, 20) = 4. 4 does not divide 3 and we have no solution.

'''Example 2.''' Solve 9''x'' &amp;equiv; 6 (mod 15).
gcd(9, 15) = 3 and 3 does divide 6 and we have 3 solutions. 

Now, divide through by 3 to obtain
: 3''x'' &amp;equiv; 2 (mod 5)
gcd(3, 5) = 1 = 3 &amp;times; 2 + -1 &amp;times; 5
So the inverse of 3 mod 5 is 2. Now we obtain the solution
: ''x'' &amp;equiv; 4 (mod 5) 
Now in '''Z'''&lt;sub&gt;15&lt;/sub&gt; we must obtain the two extra solutions 9 and 14 mod 15 - 9 mod 5 = 4 and 14 mod 5 = 4.

Generally we can say that if we have the solution to the reduced equation ''x'', the general solution is ''x''+(''m''/''d'')''k'' for ''k''={0, 1, .., ''d''-1}.

{{wikipedia|Number theory}}

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>qm3v0251modampput1imstmne29t2p2</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Botany/Plant structure laboratory</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1225</id>
    <revision>
      <id>489719</id>
      <parentid>153350</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-06-17T15:26:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[Talk:Botany:Plant structure laboratory]] moved to [[Talk:Botany/Plant structure laboratory]]: naming convention</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Marshman this image is beautiful ! I want to make it into a big poster and hang it over my bed. Do you have more like it ? --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]</text>
      <sha1>21cfdupfftx55uplkq98yx334wmci66</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Algebra/Complex Numbers</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1226</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1888749</id>
      <parentid>902195</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-07-14T14:49:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Thenub314</username>
        <id>38087</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>moved [[Talk:Intermediate Algebra/Complex Numbers]] to [[Talk:Algebra/Complex Numbers]] over redirect: It is becoming more and more part of the new book, so it should be there.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">

Are we planning to add complex vector notation (polar notation) here or add that on a separate page?

(Descriptions provided for people inexperienced with complex math)

Essentially: R''e''^(&amp;theta;''i''), where R = the absolute value of the complex number and theta is the angle from the (1,0''i'') in the counterclockwise direction.

To convert R''e''^(&amp;theta;''i'') to rectangular notation or complex number format, multiply R times sin(&amp;theta;) for the imaginary and R times cos(&amp;theta;) for the real dimension.  Ergo, from this method of calculation we can determine that ''e''^(&amp;pi;&lt;sup&gt;r&lt;/sup&gt;''i'') = -1.

Additionally, what about hypercomplex numbers, such as [[w:quaternions|quaternions]] and [[w:octonions|octonions]]?

Quaternion = a + b''i'' + c''j'' + d''k''&lt;br&gt;
where ''i'' = (-1)^(1/2); ''j'' = (-1)^(1/2); ''k'' = (-1)^(1/2)&lt;br&gt;
and ''ijk'' = -1; ''ij'' = ''k''; ''ji'' = -''k''; et al...

-- [[User:Emperorbma|Emperorbma]] 23:34, 20 Sep 2003 (UTC)

Yes yes, you'll get polar notation and a whole lot more, just wait till I add it! I'm trying to expound this in a logical manner, don't worry :) Quaternions and octonions won't be in complex numbers because they are hypercomplex. [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 01:19, 21 Sep 2003 (UTC)

:Just seeing if you needed help, that's all.  BTW, should we start a hypercomplex number article, then? -- [[User:Emperorbma|Emperorbma]] 20:47, 21 Sep 2003 (UTC)
:: Sorry about the belatedness...sure, why not? :) [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 11:58, 29 Sep 2003 (UTC)
:::It looks like hypercomplex numbers would best go in [[Discrete mathematics]] so I think I'll add it there... -- [[User:Emperorbma|Emperorbma]] 17:38, 29 Sep 2003 (UTC)

==Introduction Section Editing==
Guys, I just edited the introduction section by adding the last para which makes the concept of complex numbers more coherent. - HellKing
==i==
It is a common mistake to define
:&lt;math&gt;i=\sqrt{-1}&lt;/math&gt;.
The right definition is to introduce a new number i such that:
:&lt;math&gt;\,i^2=-1&lt;/math&gt;.
which is not equivalent to the first!

==Complex numbers==
Better than considering complex numbers as matrices, it is more didactical considering them as pairs of real numbers.

== Engineering notation ==

A suggestion: maybe it would be interesting to add the fact that in engineering notation the imaginary part of a complex number is usually referred to as j instead of &lt;math&gt;i&lt;/math&gt; (because electric current is also referred to as I). Of course, I don't know about American engineering standards, but as a (European) engineering student I was told to adapt to this convention, even though I of course surely also do understand what is meant by using &lt;math&gt;i&lt;/math&gt; as a means to indicate the complex part of a complex number.






There's also a convention (in some old engineering texts), to use cis &amp;theta; instead of (cos&amp;theta; + &lt;i&gt;i&lt;/i&gt;sin&amp;theta;). --[[User:Fephisto|Fephisto]] 19:31, 17 April 2006 (UTC)

== Euler's formula ==

How come one prove that
: ''r''e&lt;sup&gt;i&amp;theta;&lt;/sup&gt; = r (cos &amp;theta; + i sin &amp;theta;)
if ''r''e&lt;sup&gt;i&amp;theta;&lt;/sup&gt; is not even defined?


''i'' is defined, and so is e&lt;sup&gt;z&lt;/sup&gt; via Taylor series.  If you want, you can define ''r''e&lt;sup&gt;i&amp;theta;&lt;/sup&gt; through a Taylor series, and see that this has the same radius of convergence of e&lt;sup&gt;z&lt;/sup&gt; and equate them.  --[[User:Fephisto|Fephisto]] 19:34, 17 April 2006 (UTC)

== Cauchy ==

Is stuff about Cauchy's Line integral theorem &amp;c. with line integrals under the Argand Plane, going to be included here?  --[[User:Fephisto|Fephisto]] 19:39, 17 April 2006 (UTC)


== Wow ==

I think this page goes way too far. Half this stuff deserves to be in Calculus, not Algebra. We all learned primary ideas about Complex Numbers in Algebra, but this definitely will confuse most readers</text>
      <sha1>hwi561mjjl7i3dazw6pfbmo9hss95pv</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>