<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>File:Dibromomethylcyclohexane2.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1401</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748786</id>
      <parentid>746336</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-02-09T19:37:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>lftdbfdb9bftwmpa42ewbdhqaw7jksr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>US History/Civil War</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1402</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2718165</id>
      <parentid>2716067</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-25T23:15:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pittsburgh Poet</username>
        <id>1449338</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>I wish the new edits had been sensible: reverting to the previous edits. ~~~~</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">== Causes of the Civil War ==

The immediate cause of the Civil War was '''the election of Abraham Lincoln'''. Four other and more fundamental causes include '''deep disagreement between advocates of slave ownership and abolitionists''', the '''conflict between North and South over the rights of a state in the Union''', '''social and economic differences''' between North and South, and '''whether it was constitutional to secede''' from the Union. &lt;ref&gt;http://americanhistory.about.com/od/civilwarmenu/a/cause_civil_war.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

== Dixie's Constitution ==
By the end of March, 1861, the Confederacy had created a constitution and elected its first and only president, Jefferson Davis. The Constitution of the Confederate States of America was the supreme law of the Confederate States of America, as adopted on March 11, 1861 and in effect through the conclusion of the American Civil War. The Confederacy also operated under a Provisional Constitution from February 8, 1861 to March 11, 1861.

In regard to most articles of the Constitution, the document is a word-for-word duplicate of the United States Constitution. The original, hand-written document is currently located in the University of Georgia archives at Athens, Georgia. The major differences between the two constitutions was the Confederacy's greater emphasis on the rights of individual member states, and an explicit support of slavery.
{{wikisource|Constitution of the Confederate States of America}}

== Fort Sumter and the Beginning of the War ==
Several federal forts were seized and converted to Confederate strongholds. By the time of Lincoln's inauguration, only two major forts had not been taken. On April 11, Confederate General P. G. T. Beauregard demanded that Union Major Robert Anderson surrender Fort Sumter in Charleston, South Carolina, which was an important fort because of its strategic position, which was to defend Charleston's harbor. The supplies of the besieged forts would only last a few weeks. The Union unsuccessfully sent ships to resupply the fort. Beauregard's troops surrounded the fort which was located on an island outside the bay and opened fire on the fort. A tremendous cannon firefight ensured that remarkably claimed no casualties.  By April 14, Anderson was forced to surrender the fort, and tragically the first casualties of the War occurred when a Union cannon misfired while the flag was being lowered.

On the very next day, President Lincoln declared formally that the US faced a rebellion. Lincoln called up state militias and requested volunteers to enlist in the Army. In response to this call and to the surrender of Fort Sumter, four more states, Virginia, Arkansas, Tennessee, and North Carolina all seceded. The Civil War had begun.

Each side proceeded to determine its strategies. The Confederate Army had a defensive-offensive strategy. The Confederacy only needed to defend itself and win to gain independence, but occasionally when the conditions were right, they would strike offensively into the North. Three people who had important roles in Confederate plans, had different strategies. General Robert Lee claimed that they had to fight the Union head on. Davis however, argued that they had to fight a solely defensive war. Jackson claimed that they needed to invade Union's important cities first and defeat the enemy that tires to reclaim the cities. 

Meanwhile, the strategy of aging Union General Winfield Scott became popularly known as the ''Anaconda Plan''. The Anaconda Plan, so named after the South American snake that strangles its victims to death, aimed to defeat the Confederacy by surrounding it on all sides with a blockade of Southern ports and the swift capture of the Mississippi River.

== First Battle of Bull Run and the Early Stages of the War ==

Four slave states remained in the Union: Delaware, Maryland, Kentucky, and Missouri. The four border states were all important, and Lincoln did not want them to join the Confederacy. Missouri controlled parts of the Mississippi River, Kentucky controlled the Ohio river, and Delaware was close to the important city of Philadelphia. Perhaps the most important border state was Maryland. It was close to the Confederate capital, Richmond, Virginia, and the Union capital, Washington, was located between pro-Confederate sections of Maryland and seceded Virginia. Lincoln knew that he had to be cautious if he did not want these states to join the Confederacy. But they did anyway (with the exception of Maryland) after the Battle of Fort Sumter. 

Both sides had advantages and weaknesses. The North had a greater population, more factories, supplies and more money than the South. The South had more experienced military leadership, better trained armies, and the advantage of fighting on familiar territory. Robert E. Lee is a good example because he was called on by president Lincoln before the civil war began to lead the Union army. But Lee refused and joined the Confederate army because he couldn't fight against his homeland, Virginia after they seceded.   

However, the Confederacy faced considerable problems. Support for secession and the war was not unanimous, and all of the southern states provided considerable numbers of troops for the Union armies. Moreover, the presence of slavery acted as a drain of southern manpower, as adult males who might otherwise join the army were required to police the slaves and guard against slavery. 

On July 21, 1861, the armies of General Beauregard and Union General Irvin McDowell met at Manassas, Virginia. At the ''Battle of Bull Run'', the North originally had the upper hand, but Confederate General Thomas Jackson and his troops blocked Northern progress, Jackson's men began to retreat but Jackson stayed, standing &quot;as a stone wall&quot; (the origin of the nickname &quot;Stonewall Jackson&quot;). As Confederate reinforcements arrived, McDowell's army began to retreat in confusion and was defeated thoroughly, causing the North to discard their overly optimistic hopes for quick victory over the Confederacy. Even though the Confederates achieved victory, General Beauregard did not chase stragglers. So he was replaced by General Robert E. Lee. Also, General McDowell,who was defeated by Confederates was replaced by McClellan.

The Union even faced the threat of complete defeat early in the war. The Confederacy appointed two persons as representatives to the United Kingdom and France. Both of them decided to travel to Europe on a British ship, the ''[[w: RMS_Trent|Trent]]''. A Union Captain, Charles Wilkes, seized the ship and forced the Confederate representatives to board the Union ship. However, Wilkes had violated the neutrality of the United Kingdom. The British demanded apologies, and Lincoln eventually complied, even releasing the Confederate representatives. Had he failed to do so, the United Kingdom might have joined with the Confederacy and the Union might have faced a much more difficult fight.

==Technology==

The Civil War was affected by technological innovations that changed the nature of battle. The most lethal change was the introduction of rifling to muskets. In previous wars, the maximum effective range of a musket was between 70 to 110 meters. Muskets, which were smooth bore firearms, weren't accurate beyond that. Tactics involved moving masses of troops to musket range, firing a volley, and then charging the opposing force with the bayonet, which is a sword blade attached to a firearm. However, a bullet from an aimed rifled musket could hit a soldier more than 1300 meters away. This drastically improved any defense. Massed attacks were easier to stop from a longer distance. The standardization of the rifle during the revolutionary war was extended to these new armaments, and to other military supplies.

Some other key changes on land dealt with logistics -- the art of military supply -- and communications. By 1860, there were approximately 30,000 miles of railroad track, mostly in the Northern states. The railroads meant that supplies need not be obtained from local farms and cities, and that armies could operate for extended periods of time without fear of starvation. The advances in food preservation created during the Napoleonic Wars brought a wider variety of food to the soldier. In addition, armies could be moved across the country within days, without marching. Doctors could move to the wounded.  

The telegraph is the third of the key technologies that changed the nature of the war.  Washington City and Richmond, the capitals of the two opposing sides, could stay in touch with commanders in the field, passing on updated intelligence and orders. President Lincoln used the telegraph frequently, as did his chief general, Halleck, and field commanders such as Grant. 

At sea, the greatest innovation was the introduction of ironclad warships. In 1862, the Confederate Navy built the CSS ''Virginia'' on the half-burned hull of the USS Merrimack. This ship, with iron armor, was impervious to cannon fire that would drive off or sink a wooden ship. The Virginia sank the U.S. frigate ''Cumberland''. It might have broken the blockade of the Federal fleet if it had not been for the arrival of the ironclad USS ''Monitor'', built by Swedish-American John Ericsson. The two met in May 1862 off Hampton Roads, Virginia.  The battle was a draw, but this sufficed for the Union to continue its blockade of the Confederacy. The Virginia'had retreated into a bay where it could not be of much use, and the Confederacy later burned it to prevent Union capture.

The U.S. Civil War introduced the first American railroad artillery; a successful submarine; a &quot;snorkel&quot; breathing device; the periscope for trench warfare; field trenches, land-mine fields, and wire entanglements, as battles began to take place for days at a time; American use of flame throwers and naval torpedoes; aerial reconnaissance, using hot-air balloons and cameras, and antiaircraft fire; resultant camouflage and blackouts; repeating rifles; telescopic sights for rifles for the aid of snipers, fixed ammunition, and long-range rifles for general use; electronic exploding bombs and torpedoes; revolving gun turrets on boats; and a workable machine gun. As part of the organization of men and materiel, the Civil War introduced foreign social innovations such as incorporation of female and civilian support in the Northern Sanitation Fairs, an organized medical and nursing corps with bandages, opium, and other anesthetics, hospital ships, and an army ambulance corps. To supply newspapers and magazines, with their sophisticated new engraving devices, there arose a wide-range corps of press correspondents in war zones. New aids in communication included the bugle call, &quot;Taps,&quot; and other new calls, and the wigwag signal code in battle. To enable the federal prosecution of the war, the North inaugurated American conscription, legal voting for servicemen, The U.S. Secret Service, the income, withholding, and tobacco (cigarette) taxes, and the Medal of Honor. The Southern forces created a Confederate Department of Justice. The North created the first U.S. Navy admiral. Both sides commissioned Army Chaplains. The North commissioned African-American fighters, and its first African-American U.S. Army Officer, Major M.R. Delany.

== Shiloh and Ulysses Grant ==

While Union military efforts in the East were frustrated and even disastrous, West of the Appalachians, the war developed differently resulting in the first significant battlefield successes for the North. 

Kentucky, on the border between the Union and Confederacy, was divided in its sentiments toward the two sides and politically attempted to pursue a neutral course. By autumn 1861, the state government decided to support the Union despite being a slave state. Kentucky's indecision and the divided loyalties of that state's population greatly influenced the course of military operations in the West as neither side wished to alienate Kentucky.

Below the confluence of the Ohio and Mississippi Rivers where the Kentucky, Tennessee and Missouri borders come together, Union Brigadier General Ulysses S. Grant, under command of Major General Henry W. Halleck, conducted a series of operations that would bring him national recognition. It was just across the Mississippi from Kentucky in Columbus, Missouri that Grant, later President of the United States, fought his first major battle.  

The western campaigns continued into 1862 under Halleck's overall direction with Grant continuing into Western Tennessee along the Mississippi. In February, Grant attacked and captured the Tennessean Fort Donelson, providing a significant (though not necessarily major) victory for the North. 

About two months after the victory at Fort Donelson, Grant fought an even more important battle at Shiloh. 

Confederate generals, A.S Johnston and P.G.T Beauregard, made a surprise attack towards the Union army. The attack was pretty successful. However the Union made a counter attack and the Confederate army was defeated in the end.

After the Union took Fort Donelson, Grant wanted to push onto into Charleston and Memphis. But General Helleck denied it. If they had pushed and held the area, they would have gained control of the eastern railroad.

Grant's troops killed Confederate General Albert Johnston and defeated the Confederate troops, but at a steep price. Approximately thirteen thousand Union soldiers and eleven thousand Confederate soldiers died, and Grant lost a chance of capturing the West quickly.

== Peninsular Campaign ==

General Stonewall Jackson threatened to invade Washington. To prevent Jackson from doing so, Union General George McClellan left over fifty-thousand men in Washington. Little did he know that the deceptive Jackson did not even have 5000 men in his army. McClellan's unnecessary fear caused him to wait over half a year before continuing the war in Virginia, earning him the nickname &quot;Tardy George&quot; and allowing enough time for the Confederates to strengthen their position. Jackson's deceptions succeeded when General McClellan led Union troops in the Peninsular Campaign, the attempt to take the Confederate capital Richmond, ''without'' the aid of the force remaining in Washington.

In early April 1862, McClellan began the Peninsular Campaign. His troops traveled over sea to the peninsula formed by the mouths of the York and James Rivers, which included Yorktown and Williamsburg and led straight to Richmond. (The Union strategy for a quick end to the war was capturing Richmond, which appeared easy since it was close to Washington.) In late May, McClellan was a few miles from Richmond, when Robert E. Lee took control of one of the Confederate Armies. After several battles, it appeared that McClellan could march to Richmond. But McClellan refused to attack, citing a lack of reinforcements. The forces that he wanted were instead defending Washington. During the last week of June, Confederate General Robert E. Lee initiated the Seven Days' Battles that forced McClellan to retreat. By July, McClellan had lost over fifteen thousand men for no apparent reason; there was little consolation in the fact that Lee had lost even more.

During the Peninsular Campaign, other military skirmishes occurred. Flag Officer David Farragut of the Union Navy easily took control of the Mississippi River when he captured the key port of New Orleans in April, providing a key advantage to the Union and practically depriving the Confederacy of the river.

== Total War ==

If Richmond had indeed been captured quickly and the war had ended, slavery and the Southern lifestyle would probably not have changed significantly. After the unsuccessful Union attacks in Virginia, Lincoln began to think about the Emancipation Proclamation, and the Union changed its strategy, from a quick capture of Richmond, to the destruction of the South through total war. Total war is a war strategy in which both military and non-military resources that are important to a state's ability to make war are destroyed by the opposing power. General William Sherman used total war in his &quot;March  to the Sea&quot; November and December in 1864. This destroyed the South so much that it could not make war. It may involve attacks on civilians or the destruction of civilian property.

The Union strategy finally emerged with six parts:
* blockade the Confederate coastlines, preventing trade;
* free the slaves, destroying the domestic economy;
* disconnect the Trans-Mississippi by controlling the Mississippi River;
* further split the Confederacy by attacking the Southeast coast (Georgia, South Carolina, and North Carolina), denying access to foreign supply
* capture the capital of Richmond, which would severely incapacitate the Confederacy; and
* engage the enemy everywhere, weakening the armies through attrition.

== Second Bull Run and Antietam ==

Meanwhile, a new Union Army under General John Pope was organized. Pope attempted to combine his army with McClellan's to create a powerful force. Stonewall Jackson attempted to prevent this danger by surrounding Pope's Army in Manassas. Both sides fought on August 29, and the Confederates won against a much larger Union force.

Pope's battered Army did eventually combine with McClellan's. But the Second Battle of Bull Run had encouraged General Lee to invade Maryland. In Sharpsburg, Maryland, McClellan and Lee led their armies against each other. On September 17, 1862, the Battle of Antietam (named for a nearby creek) led to the deaths of over ten thousand soldiers from each side; no other one-day battle led to more deaths in one day. This day is called &quot;Bloodiest day of American History&quot;. McClellan's scouts had found Lee's battle plans with a discarded packet of cigars, but he did not act on the intelligence immediately. The Union technically won the Pyrrhic victory; McClellan lost about one-sixth of his Army, but Lee lost around one-third of his. Even though they could march and end the war, McClellan didn't go forward because he thought he's already lost too many soldiers. This was the victory needed for Lincoln's Emancipation Proclamation, so that it did not appear as an act of desperation.

== The Emancipation Proclamation ==
Meanwhile, General McClellan seemed too defensive to Lincoln, who replaced McClellan with General Ambrose Burnside. Burnside decided to go on the offensive against Lee.  In December 1862, at Fredricksburg, Virginia, Burnside's Army of the Potomac assaulted built-up Confederate positions and suffered terrible casualties to Lee's Army of Northern Virginia. The Federal superiority in numbers was matched by Lee's use of terrain and modernized firepower. &quot;Burnside's Slaughter Pen&quot; resulted in over ten thousand Union casualties, largely due to the ill-considered use of Napoleonic tactics against machine guns. Burnside then tried another attempt to move to capture Richmond, but the movement was foiled by winter weather.  The &quot;Mud March&quot; forced the Army of the Potomac to return to winter quarters.


President Lincoln liked men who did not campaign on the abolition of slavery. He only intended to prevent slavery in all new states and territories. On the 22'nd of August, 1862, Lincoln was coming to the decision that abolishing slavery might help the Union, in a letter from that time he wrote &quot;My paramount object in this struggle is to save the Union, and is not either to save or destroy slavery. If I could save the Union without freeing any slave, I would do it; and if I could save it by freeing all the slaves, I would do it; and if I could do it by freeing some and leaving others alone, I would also do that.&quot;. Doing so would especially disrupt the Confederate economy. In September, 1862, after the Battle of Antietam, Lincoln and his Cabinet agreed to emancipate, or free, southern slaves. On January 1, 1863, Lincoln issued the Emancipation Proclamation, which declared all slaves in rebel states &quot;forever free.&quot;

The constitutional authority for the Emancipation Proclamation cannot be challenged. The Proclamation did not abolish slavery everywhere; it was restricted to states &quot;still in rebellion&quot; against the Union on the day it took effect. The Proclamation, technically, was part of a military strategy against states that had rebelled; this was to prevent internal conflict with the border states. Still, all the border states except Kentucky and Delaware had abolished slavery on their own. Naturally, the proclamation had no way of being enforced: the Executive in the form of military action was still trying to force the Confederacy to rejoin. Nonetheless, many slaves who had heard of the Proclamation escaped when Union forces approached.

The Proclamation also had another profound effect on the war: it changed the objective from forcing the Confederacy to rejoin the Union to eliminating slavery throughout the United States. The South had been trying too woo Great Britain (which relied on its agricultural exports, especially cotton, for manufacturing) into an alliance; now all hopes for one were eliminated. Great Britain was firmly against the institution of slavery, and it had been illegalized throughout the British Empire since 1833. In fact, many slaves freed via the Underground Railroad were taken to Britain, since it was safe from bounty hunters (Canada was too close to the U.S. for some).

Although the Union initially did not accept black freedmen for combat, it hired them for other jobs. When troops became scarce, the Union began enlisting blacks. At the end of the war, the 180,000 enlisted blacks made up about 10% of the Union Army, and 29500 enlisted blacks to Navy. Until 1864, the South refused to recognize captured black soldiers as prisoners of war, and executed several of them at Fort Pillow as escaped slaves. Lincoln believed in the necessity of black soldiers: in August 1864, he said if the black soldiers of the Union army all joined the Confederacy, &quot;we would be compelled to abandon the war in three weeks.&quot; See [[#Black Americans and the Civil War|Black Americans and the Civil War]] below for more on this subject.

== Fredericksburg and Chancellorsville ==


In 1863, Lincoln again changed leadership, replacing Burnside with General Joseph Hooker. Hooker had a reputation for aggressiveness; his nickname was &quot;Fighting Joe&quot;.  From May 1 to May 4, 1863, &lt;!--my book says 2-4, this used to say 1-3--&gt; near Chancellorsville, Virginia, General Lee, again outnumbered, used audacious tactics &amp;mdash; he divided his smaller force in two in the face of superior numbers, sending Stonewall Jackson to the Union's flank, and defeated Hooker. Again, the Confederacy won, but at a great cost. Shortly after the battle of Chancellorsville, Stonewall Jackson was accidentally shot by Confederate soldiers who didn't recognize him in the poor evening light, dying soon after.

== Vicksburg ==

The North already held New Orleans. If they could take control over the entire Mississippi River, the Union could divide the Confederacy in two, making transportation of weapons and troops by the Confederates more difficult. The Vicksburg and the Fort Hudson was the only way that confederate can reach the Mississippi river. General Winfield Scott's strategic &quot;Anaconda Plan&quot; was based on control of the Mississippi; however, planning control was easier than gaining the control.  

The city of Vicksburg, Mississippi, was located on high bluffs on the eastern bank of the river.  At the time, the Mississippi River went through a 180-degree U shaped bend by the city. (It has since shifted course westward and the bend no longer exists.) Guns placed there could prevent Federal steamboats from crossing.  Vicksburg was also on one of the major railroads running east-west through the Confederacy. Vicksburg was therefore the key point under Confederate control.

Major General Ulysses Grant marched on land from Memphis, Tennessee, while Union General William Tecumseh Sherman and his troops traveled by water. Both intended to converge on Vicksburg. Both failed, at least for the time being in December, 1862, when Grant's supply line was disrupted and Sherman had to attack alone.

Since Vicksburg did not fall to a frontal assault, the Union forces made several attempts to bypass Vicksburg by building canals to divert the Mississippi River, but these failed. 

Grant decided to attack Vicksburg again in April. Instead of approaching from the north, as had been done before, his army approached Vicksburg from the south.  Grant's Army of the Tennessee crossed from the western bank to the Eastern at Big Bluff on April 18, 1863 and then in a series of battles, including Raymond and Champion's Hill, defeated Confederate forces coming to the relief of Confederate general Pemberton.  Sherman and Grant together besieged Vicksburg. Two major assaults were repelled by the defenders of Vicksburg, including one in which a giant land mine was set off under the Confederate fortifications.

From May to July, Vicksburg remained in Confederate hands, but on July 3, 1863, one day before Independence Day, General Pemberton finally capitulated. Thirty thousand Confederates were taken prisoner, but released after taking an oath to not participate in fighting the United States unless properly exchanged (a practice called parole}. 

This victory cut the Confederate States in two, accomplishing one of the Union total war goals. Confederate forces would not be able to draw on the food and horses previously supplied by Texas.

This victory was very important in many ways. 
* The Union now controlled all of the Mississippi River. 
* Controlling the Mississippi meant that the Union had now split the Confederacy into two, depriving Confederate forces of the food and supplies of Texas. 

The people of Vicksburg would not celebrate Independence Day on July 4th for another 81 years.

== Gettysburg ==

[[Image:Battle of Gettysburg.jpg|thumb|right|400px|''A Harvest of Death'': dead soldiers await burial following the Battle of Gettysburg. NARA, public domain.]]

Concurrent with the opening of the Vicksburg Campaign, General Lee decided to march his troops into Pennsylvania for several reasons:
* He intended to win a major victory on Northern soil, increasing Southern morale, encouraging Northern peace activists, and increasing the likelihood of political recognition by England and France.
* He intended to feed his army on Northern supplies, reducing the burden on the Confederate economy. 
* He intended to pressure Washington, DC, forcing the recall of Federal troops from the Western Theater and relieving some of the pressure on Vicksburg.

Using the Blue Ridge Mountains to screen his movements, Lee advanced up the Shenandoah Valley into West Virginia and Maryland before ultimately marching into south-central Pennsylvania.  The Union forces moved north on roads to Lee's east.  However, Lee did not know of the Federal movement, because his cavalry commander and chief scout, Jeb Stuart, had launched a raid eastward intending to &quot;ride around&quot; the Union army.  On July 1, 1863, a Confederate division (Henry Heth's) ran into a Federal cavalry unit (Buford's) west of the city of Gettysburg. Buford's two brigades held their ground for several hours, until the arrival of the Union 1st Corps, and then withdrew through the town. The Confederates occupied Gettysburg, but by then the Union forces had formed a strong defensive line on the hills south of the town. 

For the next three days, the Confederate Army of Northern Virginia faced the Union Army of the Potomac, now under the command of General George G. Meade, a Pennsylvanian who replaced Hooker, who had resigned as commander. (Hooker was given a corps command in the Army of the Cumberland, then in eastern Tennessee, where he performed satisfactorily for the remainder of the war.)

South of Gettysburg are high hills shaped like an inverted letter &quot;J&quot;.  At the end of the first day, the Union held this important high ground, partially because the Confederate left wing had dawdled moving into position. One July 2, Lee planned to attack up Emmitsburg Road from the south and west, hoping to force the Union troops to abandon the important hills and ridges. The attack went awry, and some Confederate forces, including Law's Alabama Brigade, attempted to force a gap in the Federal line between the two Round Tops, dominant heights at the extreme southern end of the Union's fish hook-shaped defensive line.  Colonel Joshua Lawrence Chamberlain, commander of the 20th Maine Regiment, anchored this gap.  He and the rest of his brigade, commanded by Colonel Strong Vincent, held the hill despite several hard-pressed attacks, including launching a bayonet charge when the regiment was low on ammunition. 

Meanwhile, north of the Round Tops, a small ridge immediately to the west of the Federal line drew the attention of Union General Daniel Sickles, a former New York congressman, who commanded the Third Corps.  He ordered his corps to advance to the peach-orchard crested ridge, which led to hard fighting around the &quot;Devil's Den,&quot; Wheatfield, and Peach Orchard. Sickles lost a leg in the fight.

On the third day of the Battle of Gettysburg, Lee decided to try a direct attack on the Union and &quot;virtually destroy their army.&quot; Putting Lieutenant General James Longstreet in charge of the three-division main assault, he wanted his men, including the division of Major General George Pickett, to march across a mile and a half up a gradual slope to the center of the Union line.  Lee promised artillery support, but any trained soldier who looked across those fields knew that they would be an open target for the Union soldiers--much the reverse of the situation six months before in Fredericksburg. However, the choice was either to attack or withdraw, and Lee was a naturally aggressive soldier.

By the end of the attack, half of Longstreet's force was dead, wounded or captured and the position was not taken. George Pickett never forgave Lee for &quot;slaughtering&quot; his men. Pickett's Charge, called the &quot;High Water Mark of the Confederacy,&quot; was practically the last hope of the Southern cause at Gettysburg. 

Lee withdrew across the Potomac River.  Meade did not pursue quickly, and Lee was able to reestablish himself in Virginia.  He offered to Confederate President Jefferson Davis to resign as commander of the Army of Northern Virginia, saying, &quot;''Everything, therefore, points to the advantages to be derived from a new commander, and I the more anxiously urge the matter upon Your Excellency from my belief that a younger and abler man than myself can readily be attained.''&quot;  Davis did not relieve Lee; neither did Lincoln relieve Meade, though he wrote a letter of censure, saying &quot;''Again, my dear general, I do not believe you appreciate the magnitude of the misfortune involved in Lee's escape. He was within your easy grasp, and to have closed upon him would, in connection with our other late successes, have ended the war. As it is, the war will be prolonged indefinitely.''&quot;

The battle of Gettysburg lasted three days. Both sides lost nearly twenty-five thousand men each. After Gettysburg, the South remained on the defensive.'''''

On November 19, 1863 Lincoln delivered his most famous speech in the wake of this battle. '''The Gettysburg Address''' is often cited for its brevity (it followed a two-hour speech by Edward Everett) and its masterful rhetoric. As with other early Republican documents, it placed its justification in the Founding Fathers. Unlike them, it did not place the justification of emancipation in the Constitution, but in the Declaration of Independence: &quot;All men are created equal.&quot; 
{{wikisource|The Gettysburg Address}}

== Black Americans and the Civil War ==

The view of the Union towards blacks had changed during the previous two years.  At the beginning of hostilities, the war was seen as an effort to save the Union, not free slaves.  Several black slaves who reached Federal lines were returned to their owners. This stopped when Major General Benjamin F. Butler, a New Jersey lawyer and prominent member of the Democratic party, announced that slaves, being the property of persons in rebellion against the United States, would be seized as &quot;contraband of war&quot; and the Fugitive Slave Act could not apply.  &quot;Contrabands&quot; were, if not always welcome by white soldiers, not turned away.

However, as the struggle grew more intense, abolition became a more popular option.  Frederick Douglas, a former slave, urged that the war aim of the Union include the emancipation of slaves and the enlistment of black soldiers in the Union Army. This was done on a nationwide basis in 1863, though the state of Massachusetts had raised two regiments (the 54th and 55th Massachusetts) before this.

The 54th Massachusetts Regiment was the first black regiment recruited in the North. Col. Robert Gould Shaw, the 25 year old son of very wealthy abolitionist parents, was chosen to command. On May 28, the well equipped and drilled 54th paraded through the streets of Boston and then boarded ships bound for the coast of South Carolina. Their first conflict with Confederate soldiers came on July 16, when the regiment repelled an attack on James Island. But on July 18 came the supreme test of the courage and valor of the black soldiers; they were chosen to lead the assault on Battery Wagner, a Confederate fort on Morris Island at Charleston. In addressing his soldiers before leading them in charge across the beach, Colonel Shaw said, &quot;I want you to prove yourselves. The eyes of thousands will look on what you do tonight.&quot;

While some blacks choose to join the military fight others fought by other means.  An American teacher named Mary S. Peake worked to educate the freedmen and &quot;contraband&quot;. She spent her days under a large oak tree teaching others near Fort Monroe in Virginia. (This giant tree is now over 140 years old and called Emancipation Oak). Since Fort Monroe remained under Union control this area was some what of a safe location for refugees and runaways to come to.  Soon Mary began teaching in the Brown Cottage. This endeavor, sponsored by the American Missionary Association, became the basis from which Hampton University would spawn.  Mary's school would house around 50 children during the day and 20 adults at night.  This remarkable American died from tuberculosis on Washington's birthday in 1862.

Confederate President Jefferson Davis reacted to the raising of black regiments by passing General Order No. 111, which stated that captured black Federal soldiers would be returned into slavery (whether born free or not) and that white officers who led black soldiers would be tried for abetting servile rebellion.  The Confederate Congress codified this into law on May 1, 1863.  President Lincoln's order of July 30, 1863 responded:
&lt;blockquote&gt;It is therefore ordered that for every soldier of the United States killed in violation of the laws of war, a rebel soldier shall be executed; and for every one enslaved by the enemy or sold into slavery, a rebel soldier shall be placed at hard labor on the public works and continued at such labor until the other shall be released and receive the treatment due to a prisoner of war. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

Eventually the Federal forces had several divisions' worth of black soldiers.  Their treatment was not equal to white soldiers: at first, for example, black privates were paid $10 a month, the same as laborers, while white privates earned $13 a month.  In addition, blacks could not be commissioned officers.  The pay difference was settled retroactively in 1864.

The issue of black prisoners of war was a continual contention between the two sides.  In the early stages of the war, prisoners of war would be exchanged rank for rank.  However, the Confederates refused to exchange any black prisoner.  The Union response was to stop exchanging any prisoner of war.  The Confederate position changed to allowing blacks who were born free to be exchanged, and finally to exchange all soldiers, regardless of race.  By then, the Federal leadership understood that the scarcity of white Confederates capable of serving as soldiers was an advantage, and there were no mass exchanges of prisoners, black or white, until the Confederate collapse.

== Chickamauga and Chattanooga ==

In September 1863, Union Major General William Rosecrans decided to attempt the takeover of Chattanooga, a Confederate rail center in the eastern part of Tennessee.  Controlling Chattanooga would provide a base to attack Georgia.  The Confederates originally gave up Chattanooga, thinking that they could launch a devastating attack as the Union Army attempted to take control of it. Rosecrans did not, in the end, fall into such a trap.  However, on November 23, 1863, the Union and Confederate Armies met at Chickamauga Creek, south of Chattanooga, upon which a rail line passed into Georgia.

The battle of Chickamauga was a Confederate victory.  The Army of the Cumberland was forced to withdraw to Chattanooga, but Union General George Thomas, &quot;the Rock of Chickamauga,&quot; and his troops prevented total defeat by standing their ground.

After Rosecrans withdrew to Chattanooga, the Confederates under General Braxton Bragg decided to besiege the city. Rosecrans was relieved of command; Lincoln's comment was that he appeared &quot;stunned and confused, like a duck hit on the head.&quot;  Meanwhile, by great effort, the Federal forces kept a &quot;cracker line&quot; open to supply Chattanooga with food and forage.  Ulysses Grant replaced Rosecrans. 

Grant's forces began to attack on November 23, 1863.  On November 24 came the Battle of Lookout Mountain, an improbable victory in which Union soldiers, without the initiative of higher command, advanced up this mountain, which overlooks Chattanooga, and captured it.  One of the authors of this text had an ancestor in the Confederate forces there; his comment was when the battle started, he was on top of the hill throwing rocks at the Yankees, and when it was over, the Yankees were throwing rocks at him.

By the end of November, Grant and his troops had pushed the Confederates out of East Tennessee and begun operations in Georgia.

== Ulysses Grant As General-in-Chief ==

Lincoln recognized the great victories won by Ulysses Grant. In March, 1864, the President made Grant the general-in-chief of Union Forces, with the rank of Lieutenant General (a rank only previously held by George Washington). Grant decided on a campaign of continual pressure on all fronts, which would prevent Confederate forces from reinforcing each other.  

He went east and made his headquarters with General Meade's Army of the Potomac (although Grant never took direct command of this Army).  The Army of the Potomac's chief mission would be to whittle down the manpower of the Army of Northern Virginia, Lee's army. In May 1864, the two sides met in Virginia near site of the previous year's Battle of Chancellorsville.  The terrain was heavily wooded and movement to attack or reinforce was particularly difficult.  

During the Battle of the Wilderness, the Union lost eighteen thousand soldiers, while the Confederates lost eleven thousand. Nevertheless, the Union pushed on. The two Armies fought each other again at Spotsylvania Court House and at Cold Harbor.  In each case, the Union again lost large numbers of soldiers. Grant then hatched a plan to go ''around'' rather than through the Confederate Army in order to capture Richmond. At the last second, due to a hesitation by Major General &quot;Baldy&quot; Smith, the Army of Northern Virginia blocked the Union troops at Petersburg. Grant then decided to siege the city (and Lee's forces) and force it to surrender; if Lee could not move, he could not help other Confederate armies.  

The siege took almost one year.

== The Georgia Campaign ==

=== Battles for Atlanta ===
This victory had a significant effect on the election of 1864. Without it, there might have been more support for his Copperhead opponent General McClellan.

=== The March to the Sea ===

Once Atlanta was taken, General Sherman and four army corps disconnected themselves from any railroad or telegraphic communications with the Union and headed through the state of Georgia. Their objective was Savannah, Georgia, a major seaport. Sherman's strategy was to inflict as much damage on the civilian population of Georgia, short of killing people, as possible. This strategy was known as &quot;Total War&quot;. To accomplish this, he issued orders to &quot;forage liberally on the country.&quot; Many of his soldiers saw this as a license to loot any food or valuable property they could. Sherman officially disapproved of this. 

Sherman's army destroyed public buildings and railroad tracks wherever they went. One way to do this was through &quot;Sherman's neckties&quot;, caused by heating a railroad section to red heat and twisting them around a tree.  Sherman carved a path of destruction 300 miles long and over 60 miles wide from Atlanta to the coastal city of Savannah.  His technique not only supported his regiments without supply lines, but destroyed supply caches for Confederate forces in the area as well.

The Confederate forces were unable to take on Sherman's forces, which, though separated from the Union army, had plenty of arms and ammunition. He reached the city of Savannah on December 24, 1864, and telegraphed President Lincoln &quot;I present to you the city of Savannah as a Christmas present.&quot;

=== Moving through the Carolinas ===

Sherman's forces then moved north into South Carolina, while faking an approach on Augusta, Georgia; the general's eventual goal was to coordinate his forces with those of General Grant in Virginia and entrap and destroy Lee's Army of Northern Virginia. The pattern of destruction by the Union soldiers continued, often with a more personal feeling of vengeance. A Federal soldier said to his comrades, &quot;Here is where treason began and, by God, here is where it will end!&quot;

On February 17, 1865, Sherman's forces reached Columbia, the capital of South Carolina. After a brief bombardment, the city surrendered. However, a large stock of whiskey was left behind as the Confederates retreated. Drunken soldiers broke discipline; convicts were let loose from the city jail, and somehow fires broke out, destroying much of the city.

== Hood's Invasion of Tennessee and the Battle of Nashville ==

=== Spring Hill ===
The battle of Spring Hill was fought on November 29, 1864, at Spring Hill, Tennessee.  The Confederates attacked the Union as it retreated from Columbia.  The Confederates were not able to inflict significant damage to the retreating Union force. So the Union Army was still able to make it safely north to Franklin during the night.  The following day the Confederates decided to follow the Union and attack a much more fortified group at the Battle of Franklin.  This did not prove to be a wise decision, as the Confederates suffered many casualties.

=== Franklin ===
The Battle of Franklin was fought on November 30, 1864 at Franklin, Tennessee.  This battle was a devastating loss for the Confederate Army.  It detrimentally shut down their leadership.  Fourteen Confederate Generals were extinguished with 6 killed, 7 wounded and 1 captured. 55 Regimental Commanders were casualties as well.  After this battle the Confederate Army in this area was effectively handicapped.

=== Nashville ===

In one of the decisive battles of the war, two brigades of black troops helped crush one of the Confederacy's finest armies at the Battle of Nashville on December 15-16, 1864.  Black troops opened the battle on the first day and successfully engaged the right of the rebel line.  On the second day Col. Charles R. Thompson's black brigade made a brilliant charge up Overton Hill.  The 13th US Colored Troops sustained more casualties than any other regiment involved in the battle.

=== Fort Pillow ===

The Battle of Fort Pillow was fought on was fought on April 12, 1864, at Fort Pillow on the Mississippi River at Henning, Tennessee.  The battle ended with a massacre of surrendered Union African-American troops under the direction of Confederate Brigadier General Nathan Bedford Forrest.

== The End of the Confederacy ==

=== The Siege of Petersburg ===
The Siege of Petersburg, also known as The Richmond Petersburg Campaign, began on June 15, 1864 with the intent by the Union Army to take control of Petersburg which was Virginia's second largest city and the supply center for the Confederate capital at Richmond. The campaign lasted 292 days and concluded with the occupation of Union forces on April 3, 1865. Thirty-two black infantry and cavalry regiments took part in the siege.

=== First Battle of Deep Bottom===
The First Battle of Deep Bottom is also known as Darbytown, Strawberry Plains, New Market Road, and Gravel Hill. It was part of The Siege of Petersburg, and was fought July 27-29, 1864, at Deep Bottom in Henrico County, Virginia.

=== The Crater ===
The Battle of the Crater was part of the Siege of Petersburg and took place on July 30, 1864. The battle took place between the Confederate Army of Northern Virginia and the Union Army of Potomac. The battle was an unusual attempt by the Union to penetrate the Confederate defenses south of Petersburg, VA. The battle showed to be a Union disaster. The Union Army went into battle with 16,500 troops, under the direct command of Ulysses S. Grant; the Confederate Army was commanded by Robert E. Lee and entered battle with 9,500 troops. Pennsylvania miners in the Union general Ambrose E. Burnside's Ninth Corps, worked for several weeks digging a long tunnel, and packing it with explosives. The explosives were then detonated at 3:15 on the morning of July 30, 1864. Burnside originally wanted to send a fresh division of black troops against the breach, but his superiors, Ulysses S. Grant, ruled against it. The job, chosen by short straw, went to James H. Ledlie. Ledlie watched from behind the lines as his white soldiers, rather than go around, pile into the deep crater, which was 170 feet long, 60 feet across, and 30 feet deep. They were not able to escape making the Union soldiers easy targets for the Confederates. The battle was marked by the cruel treatment of black soldiers who took part in the fight, most of them were captured and murdered. The battle ended with a confederate victory. The Confederacy took out 3,798 Union soldiers, while the Union were only able to defeat 1,491 Confederate soldiers. The United States Colored Troops suffered the most with their casualties being 1,327 which would include 450 men being captured.

===Second Deep Bottom===
The Second Battle of Deep Bottom was fought August 14-20, 1864, at Deep Bottom in Henrico County, Virginia; it was part of the Siege of Petersburg. The battle is also known as Fussell's Mill, Kingsland Creek, White's Tavern, Bailey's Creeks, and Charles City Road. General Winfield Scott Hancock came across the James River at Deep Bottom where he would threaten Richmond, Virginia. This would also cause the Confederates to leave Peterburgs, Virginia and the trenches and Shenandoah Valley.

=== Retreat from Richmond ===

== Appomattox ==

Sherman did not stop in Georgia. As he marched North, he burnt several towns in South Carolina, including Columbia, the capital. (Sherman's troops felt more anger towards South Carolina, the first state to secede and in their eyes responsible for the war.) In March 1865, Lincoln, Sherman, and Grant all met outside Petersburg. Lincoln called for a quick end to the Civil War. Union General Sheridan said to Lincoln, &quot;If the thing be pressed I think Lee will surrender.&quot; Lincoln responded, &quot;Let the thing be pressed.&quot;

On April 2, 1865, the Confederate lines of Petersburg, Richmond's defense, which had been extended steadily to the west for 9 months, broke.  General Lee informed President Davis he could no longer hold the lines; the Confederate government then evacuated Richmond.  Lee pulled his forces out of the lines and moved west; Federal forces chased Lee's forces, annihilated a Confederate rear guard defense, and finally trapped the Army of Northern Virginia.  General Lee requested terms.  The two senior Army officers met each other near Appomattox Courthouse in Virginia on April 9th,1865. The men met at the home of Wilmer McLean. The gathering lasted about two and half hours. Grant offered extremely generous terms, requiring only that Lee's troops surrender and swear not to bear arms till the end of the War. This meeting helped to nearly end the bloodiest war in American history.

General Sherman met with Confederate General Joseph E. Johnston to discuss the surrender of Confederate troops in the South. Sherman initially allowed even more generous terms than Grant. However, the Secretary of War refused to accept the terms because of the assassination of Abraham Lincoln by the Confederate John Wilkes Booth. By killing Lincoln at Ford's Theater, Booth made things worse for the Confederacy. Sherman was forced to offer harsher terms of surrender than he originally proposed, and General Johnston surrendered on April 26 under the Appomattox terms. All Confederate armies had surrendered by the end of May, ending the Civil War.

Side note: A Virginian named Wilmer McLean had no luck escaping the Civil War. The first battle of the war, Bull Run, was fought right in front of his house, and the generals slept there, too. Hoping to get away from the war, he then moved to Appomattox. It was in his parlor that Lee surrendered to Grant.

==Besides the Fighting==

Not all the important events of the Civil War took place on the battlefield.

On May 20, 1862, the United States Congress passed the Homestead Act, which had been delayed by Southern legislators before secession.  According to the provisions of the Act, any adult American citizen, or a person intending to become an American citizen, who was the head of a household, could qualify for a grant of 160 acres (67 hectares) of land by paying a small fee and living on the land continuously for 5 years.  If a person was willing to pay $1.25 an acre, the time of occupation dwindled to six months.

Other vital legislation included the Pacific Railway Acts of 1862 and 1864, which enabled the United States Government to make a direct grant of land to railway companies for a transcontinental railroad, as well as a payment of $48,000 for every mile of track completed and lower-than-prime rate loans for any railway company who would build such a railway.  Two railways, the Central Pacific and the Union Pacific, began to construct lines.  The two railways finally met 4 years after the war, in Promontory Point, Utah, in 1869.

The federal government started a draft lottery in July, 1863. Men could avoid the draft by paying $300, or hiring another man to take their place. This caused resentment amongst the lower classes as they could not afford to dodge the draft.  On Monday, July 13, 1863, between 6 and 7 A.M., the Civil War Draft Riots began in New York City. Rioters attacked the Draft offices, the Bull's Head Hotel on 44th Street, and more upscale residences near 5th Avenue.  They lynched black men, burned down the Colored Orphan Asylum on 5th Avenue between 43rd and 44th Streets, and forced hundreds of blacks out of the city. Members of the 7th New York Infantry and 71st New York Infantry subdued the riot.

On April 22, 1864 the U.S. Congress passes the Coinage Act of 1864 which mandates that the inscription &quot;In God We Trust&quot; be placed on all coins minted as United States currency.

Dr. Rebecca Lee Crumpler becomes the first black woman to receive a medical degree.

==Education==
In the Morrill Act of 1862, the government granted land to Union states to sell for funding  educational institutions. This excluded the states which had seceded from the Union. The schools would teach military tactics, agriculture, and engineering. This answered the Republican campaign promise of 1860. These &quot;Land Grant Universities&quot; were proposed to spread small farm prosperity, as opposed to the large, inherited plantations, and to increase industrial innovations across a wider area.

In the 1860s, most schools were small, multiple grades were taught in one classroom at one time. Paper was expensive, and the more prosperous schools had students write their problems on individual student slates. Memorization was a common means of learning, and student knowledge was measured by oral recitation. Teachers often punished &quot;bad children&quot; with the dunce cap, a rap on a palm with a ruler, hitting or spanking, or even striking a child with a rod or a whip. Corporal punishment was seen as simply one way of enforcing obedience. Teacher and parent both generally agreed that obedience was the trait of good children.  

Farming was still a major form of employment in America. It had been so since the first ''semester'', the time when students were allowed to be in school because the crops had been sown. Students worked in the fields during harvest time, and most left school for good to work on a farm. Abraham Lincoln himself, as a youth on the frontier, had had little schooling. Yet despite these brief periods of education, the reading levels were actually quite high. By the fifth grade students were sometimes reading books that we would consider college level, and Latin was still a part of many curricula. 

Academies during this time provided education for children between the ages of thirteen and twenty. These academies offered an array of classes. Most of the academies kept the boys and girls separate. There were also ''seminaries'', or private schools, which might cater to boys or girls. Girl's schools varied widely. Emily Dickinson's school, Amherst Academy, taught  Mental Philosophy, Geology, Latin, and Botany.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.emilydickinsonmuseum.org/amherst_academy&lt;/ref&gt; Some schools left girls idle, with not even what we would call physical education. Others taught non-intellectual, &quot;feminine&quot; skills such as deportment, needle craft, and perhaps arts and crafts. The Home Economics movement, inaugurated by Catherine Beecher, advocated teaching homemaking skills in school. It also promoted female physical education. In contrast, feminists such as Susan B. Anthony and Emma Willard, and reformers such as Jane Addams and Mary McLeod Bethune, wanted to expand women's education into the plane of men. These women helped establish the higher education institutions where women were able to take classes not otherwise offered to them. The first co-educational college was Oberlin College, established in 1833. The first all-women's college was Vassar College in 1861.

==Questions For Review==

1. What are the four principal causes of the Civil War?

==References==
{{reflist}}


{{chapnav|Westward Expansion and Manifest Destiny|Reconstruction}}</text>
      <sha1>ek48fj7o4hn2829pzzd0q11bnyke2u2</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>US History/Reconstruction</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1403</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2687962</id>
      <parentid>2669046</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-02T18:54:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pittsburgh Poet</username>
        <id>1449338</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>changing Inventions to Technology ~~~~</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Congress passed the first Reconstruction Act on 2nd March, 1867. The South was now divided into five military districts, each under a major general. New elections were to be held in each state with freed male slaves being allowed to vote. The act also included an amendment that offered readmission to the Southern states after they had ratified the Fourteenth Amendment and guaranteed adult male suffrage. President Andrew Johnson immediately vetoed the bill but Congress re-passed the bill the same day. 

Andrew Johnson consulted General Ulysses S. Grant before selecting the generals to administer the military districts. Eventually he appointed John Schofield (Virginia), Daniel Sickles (the Carolinas), John Pope (Georgia, Alabama and Florida), Edward Ord (Arkansas and Mississippi) and Philip Sheridan (Louisiana and Texas). 

ing the American Civil War, in which the nation decided how to handle the return of the seceded states and the status of the Freedmen (the newly freed slaves). Most scholars have accepted 1865-1877 as the boundaries for Reconstruction. The era itself was controversial and pitted various segments of American society against one another. Differing conceptions on how to restore the former Confederate States into the Union collided with diverse opinions concerning the status of African-Americans. The meaning of freedom itself was at stake in this crucial time period. The nascent Republican Party was divided between the mainstream which wanted a modicum of protection for blacks, and the Radicals, who wanted a thorough reorganization of Southern society. Conservative elements of this time period (in particular the Democrats) believed that the old order that governed relations between the states and between blacks and whites should remain intact. The bulk of African-Americans desired equal civil and political rights, protection of their person, and in many cases a redistribution of land and the break-up of the plantation system. These diverse perspectives enabled the period from 1865 to 1877 to be, in many ways, a grand experiment in interracial democracy, but the period was also dominated by tense political relations and a preponderant violence across the South.

==Definition==
Reconstruction, in United States history, refers both to the period after the Civil War when 
the states of the breakaway Confederate States of America were reintegrated into the United States of America, and to the process by which this was accomplished.

For victory in the American Civil War to be achieved, Northern moderate Republicans and Radical Republicans concurred that the Confederacy and its system of slavery had to be destroyed, and the possibility of either being revived had to be eliminated. Controversy focused on how to achieve those goals, and who would decide when they were achieved. The Radical Republicans held that reaching those goals was essential to the destruction of the Slave Power, and necessary to guaranteeing perpetual unity of the states, as well as a solution to the many problems of Freedmen.

United States Senator Charles Sumner of Massachusetts, a Radical Republican, held that Congress should abolish slavery along with the Confederacy, extend civil and political rights to blacks, and educate black and white students together.

The &quot;moderates&quot; claimed early success in achieving the goals by assurances that the former Confederates had renounced secession and abolished slavery. Most moderates, like Abraham Lincoln and Andrew Johnson, wanted suffrage for black army veterans but not other African Americans. Southern political leaders renounced secession and gave up slavery, but were angered in 1867 when their state governments were ousted by federal military forces, and replaced by Radical Republican governments made up of Freedmen, Carpetbaggers and Scalawags.

Their primary instrument was the Black Codes (1865). These restricted the rights of Blacks and limited economic and educational opportunities. For example, there was very little, if any, employment available in the south. The Yankees may have won the war to end slavery, however the reconstruction did not benefit the African Americans who searched for employment.

== The Problem of Reconstruction ==

Reconstruction was the effort of rebuilding the South based on free labor instead of slave labor.  The issue to Northern politicians was how it would be done.  At the end of the Civil War, Congress proposed the Thirteenth Amendment, which sought to prohibit slavery. A state was not to gain re-admittance into the Union until it ratified the Amendment, but some states such as Mississippi were admitted despite failing to ratify. The Amendment became a part of the Constitution in December 6,1865.

During this time many Northerners moved to the South to start new lives. Sometimes carrying their belongings in briefcases made of carpet, they were known by Confederate Southerners as &quot;carpetbaggers.&quot; Confederate Southerners also had a derogatory name for southern whites who sided with the Republicans. They called them scalawags. The period just after the war also saw the rise of black codes, which restricted the basic human rights of freed slaves.Some of the more common codes seen were: race was dependent on blood, which meant if you had any amount of black blood in your body, you were considered black, freedmen could not get together unless accompanied by a white person, public restrooms and other facilities were segregated.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.u-s-history.com/pages/h411.html&lt;/ref&gt; 

This time in history was really volatile.  Many racially motivated riots broke out all over the country.  The hostilities the south held toward the north and the African Americans grew stronger and stronger.
===Ku Klux Klan===
[[Image:Mississippi_ku_klux.jpg|thumb|The Klan in Mississippi]]
Ku Klux Klan (KKK) is the name of several past and present organizations in the United States that have advocated white supremacy, anti-Semitism, anti-Catholicism, racism, homophobia, anti-Communism and nativism. These organizations have often used terrorism, violence, and acts of intimidation, such as cross burning and lynching, to oppress African Americans and other social or ethnic groups.

The first branch of the Ku Klux Klan was established in Pulaski, Tennessee, in May, 1866. A year later a general organization of local Klans was established in Nashville in April, 1867. Most of the leaders were former members of the Confederate Army and the first Grand Wizard was Nathan Forrest, an outstanding general during the American Civil War. During the next two years Klansmen wearing masks, white cardboard hats and draped in white sheets, tortured and killed black Americans and sympathetic whites. Immigrants, who they blamed for the election of Radical Republicans, were also targets of their hatred. Between 1868 and 1870 the Ku Klux Klan played an important role in restoring white rule in North Carolina, Tennessee and Georgia. 

The Klan's first incarnation was in 1866. Founded by veterans of the Confederate Army, its main purpose was to resist Reconstruction. It focused as much on intimidating &quot;carpetbaggers&quot; and &quot;scalawags&quot; as on putting down the freed slaves. The KKK quickly adopted violent methods. A rapid reaction set in. The Klan's leadership disowned violence as Southern elites saw the Klan as an excuse for federal troops to continue their activities in the South. The organization declined from 1868 to 1870 and was destroyed in the early 1870s by President Ulysses S. Grant's vigorous action under the Civil Rights Act of 1871 (also known as the Ku Klux Klan Act).

At the end of the American Civil War radical members of Congress attempted to destroy the white power structure of the Rebel states. The Freemans Bureau was established by Congress on 3rd March, 1865. The bureau was designed to protect the interests of former slaves. This included helping them to find new employment and to improve educational and health facilities. In the year that followed the bureau spent $17,000,000 establishing 4,000 schools, 100 hospitals and providing homes and food for former slaves.

Violence against African Americans started on the first days of Reconstruction and became more organized significant after 1867. Members of The Klan looked to frustrate Reconstruction. They also, tried to keep freedom in subjection. Terrorism dominated some counties and regions so, nighttime harassment, whippings, beatings, rapes, and murders became more common. The Klan's main purpose was political, even though, they tormented blacks who stood up for their rights. Active Republicans were the target of lawless nightriders. When freedmen that worked for a South Carolina scalawag started to vote, terrorists went to the plantation and, in the words of a victim, &quot;whipped every ... [black] man they could lay their hands on.&quot;

== Lincoln and Reconstruction ==
Lincoln firmly believed that the southern states had never actually seceded, because, constitutionally, they cannot. He hoped that the 11 states that seceded could be &quot;readmitted&quot; by meeting some tests of political loyalty. Lincoln began thinking about re-admittance early on. In his Proclamation of Amnesty and Reconstruction, which was issued in 1863, Lincoln established a simple process, hoping that Unionists would rise to political power rather than secessionalists. This plan would have granted presidential pardons to all southerners (save the political leaders at the time) who took an oath of future allegiance to the Union. Under Lincoln's plan, a state could be established as legitimate as soon as 10 percent of the voting population in the 1860 general election took this oath and a government was set up accepting the emancipation of the slaves.

While Lincoln proved to be instrumental in the emancipation of blacks, the Native Americans were not so lucky. Lincoln was responsible for the largest mass hanging in United States history. 38 Native Americans from the Santee Sioux tribe were hung On December 26, 1862. The US government failed to honor its treaties with the Indian Nations. They were suppose to supply the Indians with money and food for signing a treaty to turn over more than one million acres of land. Instead the agents kept the money and sold the food that was suppose to go the Indians to the white settlers. The food that was given to the Indians was spoiled and unfit for human consumption. Subsequntly, the Indians went off the reservation in hunting parties to try to find suitable food. One of the Indian hunting groups took some eggs from a white settlers land and that caused this extreme government action. Authorities in Minnesota asked President Lincoln to order the execution of all 303 Indian males. However, Lincoln was afraid of how Europe would react so he tried to compromise. They would only execute those who were in the group. Lincoln also agreed to kill or remove every Indian from the state and provide Minnesota with 2 million dollars in federal funds. Ironically, he only owed the Sioux 1.4 million for the land.    

Rejecting Lincoln's Presidential reconstruction plan, radical Republicans in congress arguing that it was too lenient, passed the Wade-Davis bill in 1864, which proposed far more demanding terms. It required 50 percent of the voters to take the loyalty oath and allowed only those who could swear that they had never supported the confederacy to run for office or hold federal employment. Lincoln rejected this plan and pocket-vetoed the bill. In March 1865, Congress created a new agency, the Freedman's Bureau. This agency provided food, shelter, medical aid, help to find employment, education, and other needs for blacks and poor whites.  The Freedman's Bureau was the largest scale federal aid relief plan at this time.  It was the first large scale governmental welfare program.

In 1864, his Vice Presidential running mate was the only Southern Senator to remain loyal to the Union - Andrew Johnson from Tennessee. After Lincoln was assassinated on April 14, 1865, and Johnson became President, the latter proved to be an obstacle to the Radical Republicans in Congress, who attempted to completely overhaul the Southern government and economy, which would have caused further tensions.

In May, 1865, Johnson made his own proclamation, one that was very similar to Lincoln's.  Offering amnesty to almost all Confederates who took an oath of allegiance to the Union, Johnson also reversed General Sherman's decision to set aside land for the express use of freed slaves. Not long after Johnson took office, all of the ex-Confederate states were able to be readmitted under President Johnson's plan.  In 1866, Johnson vetoed two important bills, one that bolstered the protection that the Freedmen's Bureau gave to blacks and a civil rights bill that gave full citizenship to blacks.

After realizing that if all of the Republicans, moderate and radical alike, united, they could overcome Johnson's vetoes, they soon passed the Civil Rights Act of 1866 and the Fourteenth Amendment.  This amendment declared citizenship for all persons born in the United States and required the states to respect the rights of all US citizens. The Civil Rights Act outlawed the black codes that had been prevalent throughout the South.

Over Johnson's vetoes, Congress passed three Reconstruction acts in 1867. They divided the southern states into five military districts under the control of the Union army.  The military commander in charge of each district was to ensure that the state fulfilled the requirements of Reconstruction by ratifying the Fourteenth Amendment and by providing voting rights without a race qualification. Tennessee was not included in the districts because it had ratified the Fourteenth Amendment in 1866 and was quickly readmitted to the Union.

In 1868, the House of Representatives impeached Andrew Johnson. Earlier, Congress had passed the Tenure of Office Act (over Johnson's veto), which required the President to dismiss officers only with the advice and consent of the Senate if he appointed them with the same advice and consent. Johnson believed that the Act was unconstitutional (and the Supreme Court, years after his Presidency, agreed in 1926), and intentionally violated it, to &quot;test the waters.&quot; Radical Republicans used this violation as an excuse to impeach Johnson, who was acquitted by one vote in the Senate.

In the election of 1868, Ulysses Grant was nominated for the Republican ticket and won on an incredibly small margin. Republicans noticed that if they did not act swiftly to protect the voting rights of blacks, they might soon lose a majority.  Thus, Congress passed the Fifteenth Amendment in 1869, which enforced that the suffrage of male citizens shall not be denied on account of race. This was a major blow to the women's movement, as it was the first time gender was deliberately placed into the Constitution. Republicans claimed that if the amendment had included both race and gender discrimination clauses, it would have never had a chance to pass in Congress.

=== African-Americans in Congress ===
A number of African-Americans were elected for the first time in American history during this period.  With the Reconstruction Acts sending federal troops in the southern states where African-Americans held majorities in South Carolina and Mississippi, and nearly equal numbers with whites in Louisiana, Florida, Georgia, and Alabama, Blacks were elected to Congress from these states.

John Willis Menard was elected in the 2nd District of Louisiana in 1868.  His challenger, 
Caleb Hunt, filed an objection with the election result and the House of Representatives, upon hearing arguments from both candidates, decided to seat neither of them.

Hiram Revels was elected by the Mississippi Senate by an 81-15 margin to finish the term of Mississippi Senator Albert G. Brown, who vacated the seat during the Civil War.  Revels served from February 23, 1870 to March 3, 1871.

Joseph Rainey was elected to the US House of Representatives from South Carolina's 1st District in the elections of 1870.  He was the longest serving African-American member of congress prior to William L. Dawson in the 1950's.

Blanche Bruce was elected to serve a full term in the US Senate by the Mississippi state senate in 1871.  Bruce was the only former slave to ever serve in the US Senate.  

== The Panic of 1873 ==

The Panic of 1873 was the first depression experienced by America and Europe following the Civil War.  The depression was a result of the fall for an international demand for silver.  Germany stopped using the silver standard after the Franco-Prussia war.  The United States enacted the Coinage Act of 1873 which shifted the backing of our monetary system with gold and silver to just gold.  The act immediately depreciated the value of silver and hurt western mining operations.  Another factor that influenced the Panic of 1873 was the risky over investment into railroad companies that would not bring quick returns.  The Jay Cook and Company was a United States bank that declared bankruptcy on September 18, 1873.  The bank went under as a result of over investment in the railroad business.  As a result, the New York Stock Exchange closed for ten days starting September 20, 1873.  89 of 364 railroad companies failed during the depression.  Real estate values, wages, and profits by corporations decreased over the course of the panic.  Thousands of businesses fell during the depression as well. The depression was a major highlight in President Grant's second term.

== The Great Railroad Strike of 1877 ==
The strike started on July 14, 1877 in Martinsburg, West Virginia.  The strike was caused by wage cuts from the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad Company.  The workers refused to let the railroad operate.  State militia was sent in to quell the strike but would not fire upon the strikers.  Governor Henry Mathews called upon federal troops to put down the strike and resume operations of the railroad.  The strike spread to Cumberland, Maryland.  Troops in Maryland fired upon the mob of strikers and killed ten rioters.  The strike occurred in Philadelphia, Baltimore, Pittsburgh, and even spread to St. Louis.  The strikes resulted in millions of dollars of property damage the casualties of many.  The great strike lasted 45 days, after finally being put down by federal troops from city to city.

== Republicans fall from power ==

Grant's presidency would bring about the decline of the Republican Party. He appointed a great number of corrupt officials to federal positions and to his cabinet. Many split with the party over that issue. Others grew tired of Reconstruction and proposed reconciliation with the South in a peaceful manner. These people called themselves Liberal Republicans, and nominated Horace Greeley to run against Grant in 1872. The Democrats also endorsed Greeley. Despite wide support, Grant won the election of 1872 decisively.

During the election season, Liberal Republicans were busy pushing the Amnesty Act through Congress, and in May 1872, it passed. The Amnesty Act pardoned most former Confederate citizens, and allowed them to run for office. The act restored the rights to the Democratic majorities in the South. Soon, Democrats had control of the Virginia and North Carolina governments. In states with black Republican majorities, the Ku Klux Klan (formed after the civil war as a white supremacist group) terrorized Republicans and forced them to vote Democratic or not at all. By 1876, Republicans controlled only three states in the South: Florida, Louisiana, and South Carolina-- all of which were still occupied by Union troops.

Republicans continued to decline during Grant's second term, after many high level political scandals came to light. Most shocking to the public was that a scandal involved the Vice President, and another involved the Secretary of War. The Northern population's confidence in the party was shaken even more when the nation slipped into a Depression that same year.

In the congressional elections of 1874, Republicans would suffer huge losses in both houses, and for the first time since before the start of the Civil War, Democrats were able to gain control of a part of Congress (the House). Congress no longer was able to be committed strongly to Reconstruction.

In the election of 1876, Democrats nominated New York governor S.J. Tilden to run, and the Republicans nominated Ohio governor Rutherford B. Hayes. On election day, it seemed that Tilden would win by more than 250,000 votes. But the seven, four, and eight electoral votes from South Carolina, Florida, and Louisiana, respectively, were disputed (Northern troops still occupied these states). Also, one of Oregon's three electoral votes was disputed. If Hayes won all 20 votes, he would win the election. Congress created a special commission of seven Democrats, seven Republicans, and one independent to review the election and decide a winner. But the independent resigned, and a Republican was appointed to take his place. The commission voted along party lines to award Hayes the election, but Democrats warned that they would fight the decision. 
[[Image:A certificate for the electoral vote for Rutherford B. Hayes and William A. Wheeler for the State of Louisiana dated 1876 part 6.jpg|thumb|right|150px|The certificate for the electoral vote for Rutherford B. Hayes and William A. Wheeler for the State of Louisiana]]
Republican and Democratic leaders secretly met up to draw up a compromise, and the result of the meeting was the Compromise of 1877. Proclaiming that Hayes would win the election, troops left the South and more aid was given to the South; it marked the end of Reconstruction. Ultimately, Reconstruction and the Compromise itself would be failures, as Democrats refused to hold up their end of the compromise, which was to protect the rights of African Americans in the South.

The period after Reconstruction saw the rise of the Democratic &quot;Redeemers&quot; in the South. The Redeemers vowed to take back the South from Republican rule, which had been ousted after the 1876 election. They passed Jim Crow laws, which segregated blacks and whites, and put voting restrictions on blacks that wouldn't be outlawed until the next century. Jim Crow laws were challenged in ''Plessy v. Ferguson'', when the Supreme Court voted to uphold the laws if and only if segregated facilities remained &quot;separate but equal.&quot;
==Sinmiyangyo==
The United States expedition to Korea in 1871 also known as Sinmiyangyo (Western Disturbance of the Year Sinmi year) was the first American military action in Korea. It took place predominantly on and around the Korean island of Ganghwa. The reason for the presence of the American military expeditionary force in Korea was to support an American diplomatic delegation sent to establish trade and diplomatic relations with Korea, to ascertain the fate of the General Sherman merchant ship, and to establish a treaty assuring aid for shipwrecked sailors. The isolationist nature of the Joseon Dynasty government and the assertiveness of the Americans led to a misunderstanding between the two parties that changed a diplomatic expedition into an armed conflict. The United States won a minor military victory, but as the Koreans refused to open up the country to them (and as the U.S. forces in Korea did not have the authority or strength to press the issue) the United States failed to secure their diplomatic objectives.

== Religion During the 18th Century ==
The first Jews settled in America in 1654. Later, between the years of 1820 and 1880, about 250,000 Jews came to the U.S. Some of the reason for the emigration to the U.S. was, because Jews in Germany did not have many rights. They could not own land, run for office, or vote. Many of them became merchants, tradesman, and moneylenders. During the 1800s, the German economy was changing from agriculture to industrial, so many non-Jewish farmers moved to the cities while others immigrated to America. This hurt the Jews who were selling goods and lending money to non-Jewish farmers. The opportunities that were available in American finally reached the Jews of Germany, so many fled there to gain some wealth. Not only did the economy cause the emigration, but also the fact that the revolution against Germany failed in 1848. Some rights that were not being given to both Germans and Jews were the right to a trial by jury and the freedom to hold meetings. The Jews were supporting the movement hoping it would result inthem to earn rights as well. The revolution ended unsuccessfully. Some decided to immigrate to the U.S. (Jewish Americans pg. 6-9).

In the later 1800s and early 1900s, many Jews began immigrating to America, even though their trips were extremely uncomfortable and unsanitary, There were about three hundred tightly packed men and women on each ship and they slept on bunk beds, some even three-tiered bunks. The bunk beds were about 6 feet long and 2 feet wide and only about 2.5 feet separated each bunk. Belongings could only be kept on the bunk beds with the family, which meant an individual could not pack much. One woman by the name of Sophia Kreitzberg was quoted saying and when you scratched you head you got lice on your hands (Stone 15). The ships smelled terrible from all the people and the boats were extremely dirty and filled with diseases and lice. The Jews were definitely not being respected while being on the ships going to the U.S. They were served nonkosher meat and soup, which many refused to eat. Instead, they had to eat whatever items they brought with them such as dried fruit, hardened break, or cheese (Stone 16). Stone, Amy. Jewish Americans. Milwaukee: World Almanac Library, 2007. Print.

The most dramatic increase in the U.S. Catholic population occurred during the latter half of the 19th century, due to a massive influx of European immigrants from Ireland, Italy, Germany, Austria-Hungary, and the Russian Empire (mostly Poles).  By 1850 Catholicism had become the United States' largest religious denomination, between 1860 and 1890 the Catholic population tripled in large part due to immigration.  This massive influx of Catholics to the United States would eventually lead a significant increase of power for the Catholic church, and will lead to a growing fear of the &quot;Catholic menace&quot; among the Protestant population of the United States.  Anti-Catholic groups such as the &quot;Know Nothings&quot;, the Orange Institution, the American Protective Association, and the Ku Klux Klan were openly &quot;suspicious&quot; of Catholics and regularly persecuted and discriminated against them [Catholics] with such acts as The Philadelphia Nativist Riot, &quot;Bloody Monday&quot;, and the Orange Riots of New York City in 1871 and 1872 (&lt;ref&gt;Michael Gordon, The Orange riots: Irish political violence in New York City, 1870 and 1871 (1993&lt;/ref&gt;).  Spawning out of this severe anti-catholic sentiment was a movement known as Nativism, which encouraged all native born American men (except the &quot;real&quot; Native Americans and African Americans) to rise up against foreigners.  The first Nativist publication was actually called &quot;The Protestant&quot;, with it's first edition being sold on January 2nd, 1830.  The editor of the &quot;Protestant&quot; was George Bourne, who used his publication to clearly convey his message that &quot;the goal of the paper is centered around the denunciation of the Catholic faith&quot; (The American Religious Experience, American Nativism, 1830-1845.  Baker, Sean).  Although anti-Catholic rhetoric was occasionally met with violence the nativists produced one of the greatest violent acts of the 1830's.  On August 10, 1834 a mob of 40 to 50 people gathered outside the Ursuline Convent school and burned it to the ground (&lt;ref&gt;The American Religious Experience, American Nativism, 1830-1845.  Baker, Sean&lt;/ref&gt;).  The Ursuline Convent burning marked an underlying acceptance of the anti-Catholic movement.  In 1834 F.B. Morse, a nativist leader who was a professor of sculpture and painting at New York University, wrote &quot;The Foreign Conspiracies Against the Liberties of the United States&quot;, in which his basic message is centered around protecting the American birth right of liberty.  The concern, and fear of the foreign and Catholic communities grew out of the Protestant fear of the monarchial tendencies of Catholicism, during this time urban areas were also starting to grow rapidly with the massive influx of immigrants who all congregated and lived in the same areas.  Nativists saw this as an act of &quot;clannishness&quot;, and an attempt to avoid or resist &quot;Americanization.&quot;  With the success of Morse, and his contemporary Lyman Beecher, the nativist movement reached a point where the public did not care whether the stories they heard were true or false, but began to accept works of fiction as truth as well.  In 1836 Maria Monk authored a worked called &quot;Awful Disclosures of the Hotel Dieu Nunnery of Montreal.&quot;  In her book she tells of her experiences with Catholicism, which involved forced sexual intercourse with priests and the murdering of nuns and children, the book concludes with her [Maria] escaping to save her unborn child.  Monk's mother denies her work, and said that Maria was never in a nunnery, and that a brain injury Maria received as a child may have been the cause of her stories.  In the Midwest and northern sections of the country Catholics were seen as incapable of free thought and were said to be &quot;anti-American Papists&quot; because it was thought that they took every direction from the Pope in Rome.  During the Mexican-American war Mexican Catholics were displayed in the media as silly or stupid due to their &quot;Papist superstition&quot;.  It was because of the general attitude in America about Catholics that about 100 American Catholics, mostly recently immigrated Irish, fought against the United States in the Mexican-American war.  These men fought for the Mexicans and were known as &quot;Saint Patrick's Battalion (&lt;ref&gt;Amy S. Greenberg: Manifest Manhood and the Antebellum American Empire (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1993&lt;/ref&gt;).  In 1850, Franklin Pierce presented several resolutions that would remove the restrictions on Catholics from holding public office in New Hampshire, these resolutions that were, at the time, considered &quot;pro-Catholic' were defeated (Battle of Religious Tolerance,&quot; The World Almanac, 1950, 53).  However as the 19th century passed, hostilities between Catholics and Protestants eased due to the fact that many Irish Catholics fought alongside Protestants during the Civil War, for both the North and the South.&lt;ref&gt;An American Religious Experience: American Nativism 1830-1845.  Sean Baker.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Education ==
Ex-slaves everywhere across the nation reached out for education. Blacks of all ages really wanted to know what was in the books that had been only permitted to whites. With freedom they started their own schools and the classes were packed days and nights. They sat on log seats or the dirt floors. They would study their letters in old almanacs and in discarded dictionaries. Because the desire to escape slavery's ignorance was so great, ignoring their poverty, many blacks would pay tuition, sometimes $1 or $1.50 a month.&lt;ref&gt;A People and A Nation, Eighth Edition&lt;/ref&gt;
Blacks and their white allies also saw a need for colleges and universities, in this case to train teachers, ministers, and professionals for leadership. There were seven colleges founded by the American Missionary Association, Fisk and Atlanta Universities, between 1866 and 1869. The Freedoms Bureau helped to establish Howard University in Washington D.C. As well as Northern religious groups, such as the Methodists, Baptists, and Congregationalists, supported dozens of seminaries and teachers colleges.&lt;ref&gt;A People and A Nation, Eighth Edition&lt;/ref&gt;
The earliest forms of education that blacks received was from the missionaries to convert them to Christianity. The education of blacks was very low during the civil war, until Lincoln issued the Emancipation Proclamation in 1863. The Department of Education was developed in 1867 to help start more effective schools systems. Howard University was developed in Washington D.C. for black youth in the liberal arts and sciences. The first public school day was in Boston in 1869.

== Technology ==

Just before the Civil War a vast source of petroleum was discovered in and around Titusville, Pennsylvania, and after the War this began to be exploited. At first oil was used for medicinal purposes alone. However, as the supply increased, it also began to be used for industrial purposes, and instead of whale oil. The dangerous and expensive whaling industry collapsed. While some cities used coal gas for night illumination, others began to use oil lamps, and major cities were lit at night. Petroleum, lamp oil (for the great engine lamp), and machine oil increased the usefulness of railways.  

Information could be transmitted across great distances via the telegraph. In the 1870s and 1880s inventors vied to transmit a human voice. The two major competitors were the Scots-born Alexander Graham Bell and Elisha Gray. In the year 1875, Alexander Graham Bell used an electromagnetic machine to transmit the sound of a steel reed. On February 14, 1876, a partner of Bell presented his patent to the patent office in Washington, D.C., on the same day as his rival Elisha Gray. Three weeks later, on March Seventh, Bells patent won out and was granted.

== Native Americans After The War ==
The Native Americans had to deal with many injustices during the Civil War.  This did not change at wars end.  While the African Americans were trying to gain social and economic power, the Native Americans were being forced further and further away.  Though these people were indigenous to the continent, the U.S. Government made it clear that they were not going to be citizens of this country.  The native Americans were forced to live out in the west on reservations.  Their travel was restricted and scrutinized by government agents who monitored them. Traveling off the reservations to hunt, fish or even visit the neighboring reservations was frowned upon by the Bureau of Indian Affairs (BIA). Subsequently, they instituted a pass system in order keep them under control. This system required the Natives to get a pass from the agents before they were allowed off the reservation.

White settlers also took issue with the Indians traveling on the trains.  However, the Central Pacific Railroad in Nevada granted the Native Americans permission to ride on top of the trains in exchange for their railroads being allowed to cross through the reservations. Many of the Indian agents were unhappy with all of the free traveling the Indians were getting away with.  As a result they began writing letters to the BIA to try to stop them. One of these Indian agents commented that &quot;The injurious effects of this freedom from restraint, and continual change of place, on the Indian, can not be over estimated&quot;.

With the 14th amendment the civil rights acts were contrived.  For the Indians however, their positioning was made clear. The Civil Rights Act of 1866 states, That all persons born in the United States, and not subject to any foreign power, excluding Indians not taxed, are hereby declared to be citizens of the United States&quot;. 

=== Battle at Little Bighorn ===

In 1876, after a few uneventful confrontations, Col. George A. Custer and his small cavalry came across the Sioux and some of their allies at the Little Bighorn River. To force the large Indian army back to the reservations, the Army dispatched three columns to attack.  One of these groups contained Lt. Custer and the Seventh Cavalry. They spotted the Sioux village about fifteen miles away just along the Rosebud River, Custer also found a nearby group of about forty men. He ignored orders to wait,and decided to attack before they could alert the main party. He was unaware of how much he was outnumbered.  The Sioux and their allies had three times as much force. Custer divided his forces in three, He sent troops under control of Captain Frederick Benteen to try to stop them from escaping through the upper valley of the Little Bighorn River. Major Marcus Reno job was to pursue the group, then cross the river, and attack the Indian village in a conjunction with the remaining troops under his command. He Intended to strike the Indian camp from the north and south, but he had no idea that he would have to cross a rough terrain in order to achieve this.  Once e came upon the mazes, bluffs nd ravines he realized his plan was ruined. As the Indians began to decend upon them Custer ordered his men to shoot their horses and stack the carcasses in front of them in order to form a wall, however this did not protect them against bullets. In less than an hour, Custer and all his men were killed in one of the worst American military disasters of all time. After one more day of fighting, Reno and Benteen's now unified forces fled when the Indians stopped fighting. They knew two more columns of soldiers were coming towards them, so they escaped toward them.
The massacre Custer would succumb to in his final battle completely eclipsed any success he had in the Civil War. Custer was defeated and killed at the Battle of the Little Bighorn on June 25, 1876,while fighting Native American tribes in a battle that has come to be known as &quot;Custer's Last Stand&quot;.


== Women's History of the Period ==
=== Victoria Woodhull ===
In 1872 Victoria Woodhull became the first woman to run for President of the United States. She was nominated by the Equal Rights Party on May 10. Though it is undisputed that she was the first female to run for president, the legality of her petition is questioned; her name didn't actually appear on the ballot and she was under the age of 35 which is the required age for a presidential candidate according to the constitution. Woodhull did not receive any electoral votes, but evidence supports that she received popular votes that were never counted.
=== Woman's Christian Temperance Union ===
The Woman's Christian Temperance Union was formed on December 22, 1873.  Fredonia, New York is credited as being the birthplace of the group.  The temperance movement was a social movement that pushed for the reduction of alcohol consumption.  The movement spread all over the country, and women would go to bars and drug stores to sing and pray.  The National Woman's Christian Temperance Union was established in 1874 in Cleveland, Ohio.  The women demonstrated use of non violent protestation of the consumption of alcohol by praying in saloons.  Often, they were denied entrance and yelled at by patrons.  The movement ultimately contributed to prohibition in America's future. 
==References==
{{reflist}}

 {{chapnav|Civil War|Age of Invention and Gilded Age}}</text>
      <sha1>mrlodwnzga5zqv4zwcpt4mi75c1clrh</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Latin/Lesson 11-Translation</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1404</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1864912</id>
      <parentid>1838855</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-06-28T21:26:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Adding {{WikiProject Languages}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{WikiProject Languages}} 

Isn't it a bit silly to use the Vulgate Bible as a translation exercise, considering the Vulgate itself was badly translated? :) -- [[User:Jimregan|Jimregan]] 23:46, 2 Oct 2003 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>mvd5fh2llmofc8gjobcisggjqd0djkr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Silver plating a fork (exam Q).png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1405</id>
    <revision>
      <id>636425</id>
      <parentid>153521</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-11-04T11:01:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Theresa knott</username>
        <id>93</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Drawn by theresa knott for a practise exam question.

{{GFDL}}
{{Cc-by-sa-2.5}}</text>
      <sha1>4uvxu2x2nnaojsn7nrsniqm5lxa5hek</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>GCSE Science/Electricity multiple choice practice question 6</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1406</id>
    <revision>
      <id>491283</id>
      <parentid>381520</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-06-18T07:40:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Silver_plating_a_fork_(exam_Q).png]]

A student decided to silver plate his/her mother's forks. S/he set up the apparatus above.  S/he set the power pack and variable resistor so that the ammeter read 0.1 A. S/he allowed the fork to remain in the electrolysis apparatus for 10 min.  Once s/he removed the fork s/he tested it by trying to scratch the silver off. S/he found that the layer of silver was too thin and decided that s/he would have to take steps to make the layer a lot thicker.

Which one of the following steps would '''not''' produce a thicker layer of silver ?

*[[GCSE Science/Electricity multiple choice practice question 6 answer 1|Increasing the voltage of the power pack]]
*[[GCSE Science/Electricity multiple choice practice question 6 answer 2|Increasing the resistance of the variable resistance]]
*[[GCSE Science/Electricity multiple choice practice question 6 answer 3|Increasing the time spent in the apparatus]]
*[[GCSE Science/Electricity multiple choice practice question 6 answer 4|Increasing the concentration of the silver nitrate solution]]

[[Category:GCSE Science]]</text>
      <sha1>6y61zgkvd09ovyw4cw9v928k7m594ku</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>GCSE Science/Electricity multiple choice practice question 6 answer 2</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1407</id>
    <revision>
      <id>491285</id>
      <parentid>381514</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-06-18T07:40:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">This is the correct answer. Well done!

Increasing the resistance would ''decrease'' the current and so decrease the thickness of the silver.

[[GCSE Science/Electricity multiple choice practice question 7|On to the next question&gt;&gt;]]

[[Category:GCSE Science]]</text>
      <sha1>cipyl5d2ayn09vwycr39uzsp14b7o8g</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>GCSE Science/Electricity multiple choice practice question 6 answer 1</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1408</id>
    <revision>
      <id>491284</id>
      <parentid>381512</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-06-18T07:40:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">I'm sorry but this is the wrong answer.

Increasing the voltage would increase the current making the layer of silver thicker. But the question asked which one of the four possible measures would ''not'' increase the thickness of the layer.

[[GCSE Science/Electricity multiple choice practice question 6|&lt;&lt;Back]]

[[Category:GCSE Science]]</text>
      <sha1>klx8rznphonaca5nlb98kifpm9ytyi7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>GCSE Science/Electricity multiple choice practice question 6 answer 3</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1409</id>
    <revision>
      <id>491286</id>
      <parentid>381516</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-06-18T07:40:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">I'm sorry but this is the wrong answer. Increasing the time gives the silver more time to build up. This means the layer ''will'' be thicker.

[[GCSE Science/Electricity multiple choice practice question 6 |&lt;&lt;Back]]

[[Category:GCSE Science]]</text>
      <sha1>ohgh5cw2uork6ifb9qdl1heo26tx5ed</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>GCSE Science/Electricity multiple choice practice question 6 answer 4</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1410</id>
    <revision>
      <id>491287</id>
      <parentid>381518</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-06-18T07:40:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">I'm sorry but this is the wrong answer. Increasing the concentration of silver nitrate will mean there are more ions to carry the current. The current will therefore be larger and so the silver layer will be ''thicker''. 

The question asked which method '''would not'' produce a thicker layer.

[[GCSE Science/Electricity multiple choice practice question 6|&lt;&lt;back]]

[[Category:GCSE Science]]</text>
      <sha1>4yozt3kt64rsz75ixw8no40ez8livce</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Lojban/Glossary</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1411</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518439</id>
      <parentid>461004</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-07-11T21:26:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">*Abstraction - See [[Lojban/Abstractions|Abstractions]]
*Acronym - See [[Lojban/Acronyms|Acronyms]]
*Anaphora - See [[Lojban/Anaphora]].
*Attitudinal - See [[Lojban/Attitudinals]]
*Brown, James Cooke - Began work creating Loglan around 1955. See [[Lojban/Introduction to Lojban]].
*Buffer vowel - Unwritten, spoken vowel in a consonant cluster to aid pronunciation. See [[Lojban/Sounds and alphabet|Sounds and alphabet]].
*cmene - See [[Lojban/Cmene]].
*Connective - See [[Lojban/Connectives|Connectives]].
*Discursive - See [[Lojban/Discursives|Discursives]].
*Elidable terminator - See [[Lojban/Elidable terminator]].
*fu'ivla - See [[Lojban/Fu'ivla]].
*Grammar - The study of the rules governing the use of a language. That set of rules is also called the grammar of the language, and each language has its own distinct grammar. Grammar is part of the general study of language called linguistics. See [[Lojban/Introduction to Lojban grammar]].
*Letteral - See [[Lojban/Letterals]]
*Logical Language Group
*Loglan - A constructed language designed for linguistic research, particularly investigation of the Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis. Dr. James Cooke Brown began work creating Loglan around 1955. See [[Lojban/Introduction to Lojban]].
*Lojban - Artificial language created by the Logical Language Group in 1987 based on the earlier Loglan, with the intent to make the language more complete, usable, and freely available. See [[Lojban/Introduction to Lojban]].
*lujvo - See [[Lojban/Lujvo]].
*mekso - See [[Lojban/Mekso]].
*Negation - See [[Lojban/Negation|Negation]]
*Pro-bridi - See [[Lojban/Pro-bridi]].
*Pro-sumti - See [[Lojban/Pro-sumti]].
*rafsi - See [[Lojban/Rafsi]].
*Sapir, Edward - (pronunciation: suh PEER), (1884-1939), American anthropologist-linguist; a leader in  American structural linguistics; author of Language : An Introduction to the Study of Speech (ISBN 0-15648-233-9); Born in Lauenberg, Germany. Pupil of Franz Boas, teacher of Benjamin Whorf.  See [[Lojban/Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis]].
*Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis - A linguistic hypothesis that states that there are certain thoughts of an individual in one language that cannot be understood by those who live in another language and that the way people think is strongly affected by their native languages. It is a controversial theory championed by linguist Edward Sapir and his student Benjamin Whorf. See [[Lojban/Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis]].
*selbri - See [[Lojban/Selbri]].
*sumti - See [[Lojban/Sumti]].
*sumtcita - See [[Lojban/Sumtcita]].
*tanru - See [[Lojban/Tanru]].
*tense - See [[Lojban/Tenses|Tenses]]
*Vocabulary - See [[Lojban/Vocabulary|Vocabulary]], [[Lojban/How to learn vocabulary]].
*Vocative - See [[Lojban/Vocatives]].
*Whorf, Benjamin Lee - (April 24, 1897 - July 26, 1941) was an American linguist. See [[Lojban/Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis]].

[[Category:Lojban]]</text>
      <sha1>qkngzuedeiw71xp1jzb8744ow8ohkhf</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Lojban/Recordings</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1412</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518444</id>
      <parentid>408271</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-07-11T21:27:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jguk</username>
        <id>18491</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">* [http://www.thestonecutters.net/xod/lojban/sound/xagjipemci.mp3 xagji pemci] - A poem by Michael Helsem, read by Jorge Llambias (mp3)
* [http://www.thestonecutters.net/xod/lojban/sound/selmohi.rm selmo'i] - A Chinese Poem translated &amp; read by Aulun (Real Audio)
* jbojufra - Five sentences
**[http://www.thestonecutters.net/xod/lojban/sound/sentences.mp3 Read by Jorge Llambias] - mp3
**[http://www.thestonecutters.net/xod/lojban/sound/jbojufra.rm Aulun] - Real Audio

[[Category:Lojban]]</text>
      <sha1>766474kgddff36a23efp8bojzoimgor</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Internet Technologies/The Internet</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1413</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2487155</id>
      <parentid>2487151</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-02-12T18:35:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Abramsky</username>
        <id>839293</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/41.220.27.134|41.220.27.134]] ([[User talk:41.220.27.134|talk]]) to last version by Jfmantis</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">The [[Wikipedia:Internet|Internet]] is a worldwide collection of computer networks that began as a single network that was originally created in 1969 by ARPA (Advanced Research Projects Agency), a U.S. government agency that was far more interested in creating projects that would survive a nuclear war than in creating anything useful for the civilian population.

In its original form, ARPANET, the U.S. government hoped to create a network of computers that would allow communication between government agencies and certain educational centers that would be able to survive a nuclear explosion.
It is doubtful that the original founders of ARPANET foresaw what we now know as &quot;the Internet.&quot; From its humble beginnings as a military project, the ARPANET grew slowly throughout the 70's and 80's as a community of academics accomplished the truly monumental task of hammering out the building blocks of this new, open, modular conglomeration of networks.

The various protocols, including IP, TCP, DNS, POP, and SMTP, took shape over the years, and by the time the World Wide Web ([[Wikipedia:HTML|HTML]] and HTTP) was created in the early 90's, this &quot;Internet&quot; had become a fully functional, fairly robust system of network communication, able to support this new pair of protocols which eventually turned the Internet into a household word.

While a large portion of users today confuse the Web with the Internet itself, it must be emphasized that the Web is only one type of Internet application, and one set of protocols among a great many which were in use for over a decade before the Web entered into the public awareness. 

The Web is a subset of the Net. Email is not a part of the Web, and neither are newsgroups, although Web designers have developed web sites through which users, the world over, commonly access both of these much older forms of Internet media.

While the Net is a largely abstract phenomenon, it cannot (at least, not yet) be accurately equated with the concept of &quot;cyberspace&quot; as depicted in science fiction. If &quot;judgement day&quot; were to occur as depicted in the latest &quot;Terminator&quot; film, much of the Internet would survive it, but most of the electrical and data infrastructure by which we access the net would not. The line which currently demarcates the &quot;digital divide&quot; would shift dramatically to a point where it would leave only a small segment of humanity in virtual touch. This limitation, however, will slowly be overcome as wireless technologies continue to proliferate and wired technologies become increasingly cheaper.

In March 1972 ARPA became known as DARPA, the Defense Advanced Research Project Agency, and then went back to ARPA in February 1993 and back to DARPA in March 1996 and has been ever since.  It was originally created as ARPA in 1958 in response to the launching of Sputnik.  The launch of Sputnik made America realize that the Soviet Union could exploit military technology.  DARPA has contributed to the creation of ARPANET as well as the Packet Radio Network, the Packet Satellite Network and the Internet.  As well as research into the Artificial Intelligence field commonly referred to as AI.  By the late 1970's the Department of Defense had adopted BSD UNIX as the primary operating system for DARPA.  It has also had its hands in Space projects which included the launching of the Apollo missions.  

==References==
* http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DARPA
* http://www.darpa.mil/DARPA50thevent/history.html

[[Category:Internet Technologies]]</text>
      <sha1>21sfdv8e8itcd99nib98b51nlh8z497</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Puzzles</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1414</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1949525</id>
      <parentid>1949522</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-10-16T00:22:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>status=50%; formatting; move tag to bottom</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Puzzles have been in existence for thousands of years, intended to amuse and bemuse.

Some may tax your mind more than others, but they should always be fun.

Enjoy this collection, avoid frustration, and fight boredom.

==Table of contents==
[[Image:Labyrinth 1 (from Nordisk familjebok).svg|right|200px]]
=== Games ===
* [[/Two-player games/]]
* [[/Bridge problems/]]
* [[/Chess problems/]]
* [[/Go problems/]]

=== Graphical puzzles ===
* [[/Bongard problems/]]
* [[/Subdivisions/]]

=== Language puzzles ===
* [[/Analogies/]]
* [[/Odd-one-out/]]
* [[/Riddles/]]

=== Mathematical puzzles ===
* [[/Action sequences/]]
* [[/Analytical puzzles/]]
* [[/Arithmetical puzzles/]]
* [[/Decision puzzles/]]
* [[/Geometric Puzzles|Geometric puzzles]]
* [[/Logic puzzles/]]
* [[/Number sequences/]]
* [[/Set theory puzzles/]]
* [[Puzzles/Statistical puzzles|Statistical &amp; combinatorics puzzles]]

=== Permutation puzzles ===
* [[Puzzles/Rubik's cubes|Rubik's cube (3x3x3)]]
* Rubiks Revenge (4x4x4)
* Rubik's Professor (5x5x5)
* Fifteen puzzle

=== Real life problems ===
* [[Puzzles/How do you ... ?|How do you ... ?]]
* [[Puzzles/Lateral puzzles|Lateral puzzles]]
* [[Puzzles/Non-scientific puzzles|Non-scientific puzzles]]
* [[Puzzles/Physics puzzles|Physics puzzles]]

=== About puzzles ===
* [[/Puzzles in science/]]
* [[/Solving puzzles/]]

== Puzzle resources ==
* [http://www.jimloy.com/puzz/puzz.htm Jim Loy's Puzzle Pages]
* [http://www.ocf.berkeley.edu/~wwu/riddles/intro.shtml Riddles]&amp;ndash;Wu:Riddles
* [http://www.ahapuzzles.com/ Aha! Puzzles - Original creative puzzles by Lloyd King]
* [http://cgi.math.princeton.edu/mathclub/index.php/Puzzles Puzzles] from the Princeton undergraduate mathematics student society.
* [http://rec-puzzles.org rec.puzzles Archive]
* [http://results.about.com/riddles/ ResultsAbout Riddles]: Collection of links to other riddle web sites.
* [http://www.mathpuzzle.com Mathpuzzle]: Puzzle blog of Ed Pegg Jr.
* [http://www.puzzlepicnic.com PuzzlePicnic]: Hundreds of deduction puzzles.
* [http://www.puzzles.com Puzzles.com]
{{cleanup|Needs more structure, needs to be expanded. Puzzles should be explained and discussed, not just listed.}}
{{subjects|games}}
{{Alphabetical|P}}
{{status|50%}}
__NOTOC__ __NOEDITSECTION__
[[fr:Puzzles]]</text>
      <sha1>tfmzzens7qxu2q1yhwarwwk1667afeu</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Puzzles</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1415</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2432029</id>
      <parentid>1894832</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-31T23:07:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ray Calvin Baker</username>
        <id>458918</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Wikiversity Contributor Needs Material on &quot;Puzzles&quot;! */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{rfd-survived}}

I think that the section &quot;statistical puzzles&quot; should rather read &quot;probability puzzles&quot; since this describes the nature of the contributed riddles more precisely (and there are really few statistical puzzles out there going beyond probability theory).
However, it seems a bit tedious to make the change because of the references already in place
-sboehringer
----

It's really nice to see so much interest! I'll try to put up some more cool puzzles (and of course I'd love to have some more puzzles put up by other people so that I can also try to solve a few :) [[User:ThomasStrohmann | Thomas]]

Suggestion: I think once we have more than 20 or so problems we should split them up into subcategories. [[User:ThomasStrohmann | Thomas]]

Suggestion: I think it will be easier to create for each puzzle an own solution page and put a link at the bottom of each puzzle. [[User:doopdoop|doopdoop]]

:I agree, maybe we should have (at least) two levels of hierarchy in our book: 1. subcategories which contain a list of puzzles for each type 2. a page for each puzzle + an 'official solution' page for this puzzle (the talk page of a puzzle could be used to discuss clarifications, alternate solutions, ...) [[User:ThomasStrohmann | Thomas]]
:Suggested structure (partially inspired by the rec.puzzles archive -&gt; '''''now implemented''''')

:What about the classical n-queens or traveling salesman problems?

--[[User:Eibwen|Eibwen]] 07:10, 1 Oct 2004 (UTC)

----

== Overview ==
* &lt;u&gt;[[Two 4's equals 64?]]:&lt;/u&gt; ''solved''
* &lt;u&gt;[[Puzzles/Logic puzzles/Knights, Knaves &amp; Spies|Knights, Knaves &amp; Spies]]:&lt;/u&gt; ''solved''
* &lt;u&gt;[[Puzzles/Logic puzzles/Knights, Knaves &amp; Spies II|Knights, Knaves &amp; Spies II]]:&lt;/u&gt;  ''solved''
* &lt;u&gt;[[Puzzles/Logic puzzles/Lying about your Age|Lying about your Age]]:&lt;/u&gt; ''solved''
* &lt;u&gt;[[puzzles:Decision puzzles:12 Coins|12 coins]]:&lt;/u&gt; ''solved''
* &lt;u&gt;[[Sharing Milk]]:&lt;/u&gt; ''solved''
* &lt;u&gt;[[The Burning Island]]:&lt;/u&gt; ''solved''
* &lt;u&gt;[[Crossing the River]]:&lt;/u&gt; ''solved''
* &lt;u&gt;[[Crossing the River II]]:&lt;/u&gt; ''solved'' 
* &lt;u&gt;[[Puzzles/Geometric Puzzles/Connecting Stars|Connecting Stars]]:&lt;/u&gt; ''solved''
* &lt;u&gt;[[Puzzles/Logic puzzles/Getting out of Prison|Getting out of Prison]]:&lt;/u&gt; ''solved''
* &lt;u&gt;[[Three Daughters]]:&lt;/u&gt; ''solved''
* &lt;u&gt;[[Puzzles:Decision puzzles:Weighings Once More|Weighings once more]]:&lt;/u&gt; ''solved''
* &lt;u&gt;[[Puzzles/Geometric Puzzles/Rubber Band|Rubber band]]:&lt;/u&gt; ''solved''
* &lt;u&gt;[[Puzzles:Arithmetical puzzles:Digits of the Square|Digits of the Square]]:&lt;/u&gt; ''solved''
* &lt;u&gt;[[Puzzles/Logic puzzles/Hats|Hats]]:&lt;/u&gt; ''solved''
* &lt;u&gt;[[Puzzles/Logic puzzles/Three Knights|Three Knights]]:&lt;/u&gt; ''solved''
* &lt;u&gt;[[Puzzles/Logic puzzles/Pizzas|Pizzas]]:&lt;/u&gt; ''solved''
* &lt;u&gt;[[Puzzles:Arithmetical puzzles:Luxury Cars|Luxury Cars]]:&lt;/u&gt; ''solved''
* &lt;u&gt;[[Puzzles/Geometric Puzzles/Connecting Utilities|Connecting Utilities]]:&lt;/u&gt; ''solved''
* &lt;u&gt;[[Yet another Weighing - Puzzle|Yet another Weighing]]:&lt;/u&gt; ''solved''
* &lt;u&gt;[[Puzzles/Escaping from Prison|Escaping from Prison]]:&lt;/u&gt; ''solved''
* &lt;u&gt;[[Puzzles/Logic puzzles/Scales and Weights|Scales and Weights]]:&lt;/u&gt; ''solved'', '''open for better solutions'''
* &lt;u&gt;[[Puzzles/Logic puzzles/Two Boys and a River|Two Boys and a River]]:&lt;/u&gt; '''open'''
* &lt;u&gt;[[Puzzles/Statistical puzzles/The Pentagon|The Pentagon]]:&lt;/u&gt; '''open'''
* &lt;u&gt;[[Puzzles:Non-scientific puzzles:Boy, Girl, and a Dog|Boy, Girl, and a Dog]]:&lt;/u&gt; '''open'''
* &lt;u&gt;[[Barrel of Ale]]:&lt;/u&gt; '''open'''

'''Note:''' even if a problem is solved, you should try and solve it without looking at the solution on the talk page. That way we increase the chance of getting alternative solutions!

----

I've implemented the structure suggested by [[User:doopdoop|doopdoop]]. Every problem now has it's own problem page and solution page. Also, I think we can use a problem's talk page to vote on the difficulty (say from 1-10, where 1=very easy to 10=(almost) impossible). [[User:ThomasStrohmann | Thomas]]

==Self-created puzzles==

I presume that we're allowed to put puzzles that we created ourselves onto the page, right? Or not? [[User:Eric119|Eric119]] 21:49, 11 Oct 2003 (UTC)

:Absolutely! I think that's at least as interesting as gathering the 'standard' puzzles that are out there.[[User:ThomasStrohmann | Thomas]]

:: Only ''as'' interesting?  Surely it's ''more'' interesting.  If we were only going to copy other sites/books, what would be the point? -- [[User:Smjg|Smjg]] 15:13, 13 July 2005 (UTC)

----

== Naming Conventions ==
I would like to suggest that we start adding a &quot;- Puzzle&quot; to the title of Puzzle pages. This would
avoid naimng conflicts with other Wikibooks and furthermore make it more easy to detect new and open
puzzles in the Recent changes. [[User:ThomasStrohmann | Thomas]]
: Hi, I am new here (in fact I just created my account), but I'd suggest to put &quot;Puzzle:&quot; to the front, like in the pages of [[Cookbook:Table of Contents|Cookbook]]. It should help to keep books together, and I wonder why this is not a standardized policy on Wikibooks yet... --[[User:Andreas Ipp|Andreas Ipp]] 14:59, 8 Jan 2005 (UTC)
::A little late for that? --[[User:Divinity|Divinity]] 17:27, 19 Jun 2005 (UTC)

::: Not at all.  Better late than never.  I hereby propose a hierarchy, so that the names'll look like this:
:::* [[Puzzles]] - contents page
:::* [[Puzzles/Logic puzzles|Puzzles:Logic puzzles]] - section page
:::* [[Puzzles/Logic puzzles/Knights, Knaves &amp; Spies|Puzzles:Logic puzzles:Knights, Knaves &amp; Spies]] - puzzle page
:::* [[Puzzles/Logic puzzles/Knights, Knaves &amp; Spies/Solution|Puzzles:Logic puzzles:Knights, Knaves &amp; Spies:Solution]] - solution page
::: And get the navigation header on every page while we're at it.  Moreover, there are even some pages that have pathologically meaningless titles - just look at [[Puzzles:Lateral puzzles]] for instance.  Let's get cleaning at once!  (I've already done puzzles 5 and 7 there, so you can see what I mean.  But still, shouldn't they all have more descriptive titles?) -- [[User:Smjg|Smjg]] 15:26, 13 July 2005 (UTC)
::::So to implement these ideas, you move the pages and redo all the links? [[User:Borbrav|Borbrav]] 18:01, July 14, 2005 (UTC)

::::: Yes.  I've started on it.  We can all work on it.  And while we're at it, we should make sure all pages have the navigation header, and that the navigation header has a line below it. -- [[User:Smjg|Smjg]] 10:32, 22 September 2005 (UTC)

Some pages are acquiring poorly laid out navigation headers, like this

: [[Puzzles]] | [[Puzzles/Logic puzzles|Puzzles:Logic puzzles]] | [[Puzzles/Logic puzzles/Knights, Knaves &amp; Spies|Puzzles:Logic puzzles:Knights, Knaves &amp; Spies]] | Solution

That's something else to fix in the process.  It should look like this:

: [[Puzzles]] | [[Puzzles/Logic puzzles|Logic puzzles]] | [[Puzzles/Logic puzzles/Knights, Knaves &amp; Spies|Knights, Knaves &amp; Spies]] | Solution
-- [[User:Smjg|Smjg]] 18:02, 22 September 2005 (UTC)

I've just created some navigation header templates, which we could use to make life easier.  So now we can do

:'''&lt;nowiki&gt;{{&lt;/nowiki&gt;[[Template:hc-navhead2|hc-navhead2]]&lt;nowiki&gt;|Puzzles|Logic puzzles}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;'''
:'''&lt;nowiki&gt;{{&lt;/nowiki&gt;[[Template:hc-navhead3|hc-navhead3]]&lt;nowiki&gt;|Puzzles|Logic puzzles|Knights, Knaves &amp; Spies}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;'''
:etc. up to {{tl|hc-navhead6}}.

A little less cumbersome than doing it manually, don't you think?

I've used it on [[Puzzles/Logic puzzles/Gold Coins]].  But I suppose we don't need to go through the ones we've already fixed changing them to use this template quite yet.  Note that they automatically include the horizontal line - hopefully this'll see the end of people omitting it. -- [[User:Smjg|Smjg]] 18:06, 12 January 2006 (UTC)

=== Bot spec ===

I've written the following specification, which should enable [[User:Tsca.bot]] to get to work.  I suggest that this stays here for a few days, giving people time to suggest changes to the spec, before the bot starts work. -- [[User:Smjg|Smjg]] 17:52, 3 February 2006 (UTC)

==== Pass 1: Fix the page titles ====

Starting from the main Puzzles page, follow the links.  Move each page to its correct title if it isn't already, using the displayed text of the link by which the page was reached.

For example, the page linked as '''Two-player games''' from the main '''Puzzles''' page shall become '''Puzzles:Two-player games'''.  The page linked as '''Picking Game''' under that page shall become '''Puzzles:Two-player games:Picking Game'''.

Special cases to observe:

# Ignore navigation header links (see below) during this stage of the process.
# If a colon appears in the text of a link, ignore all text preceding the colon when generating the new page name.
# If the link text begins with a lowercase letter, change the first letter to uppercase when generating the title.  For example, '''Puzzles:Arithmetical puzzles:Three Daughters:Solution''' not '''Puzzles:Arithmetical puzzles:Three Daughters:solution'''.
# If the text of a link contains the word '''solution''', then use '''Solution''' by itself as the name at that level rather than the whole text of the link.
# If two or more pages link to the same page (either directly or via redirects), then go by the link on the first page that was encountered.  For example, some puzzles have hint pages as well as the solution page, and have both hint and solution links from the main puzzle page.  The hint page may also have a solution link.  Invariably, you will reach the main puzzle page before the hint page.  Consequently, the solution page will be a child page of the main puzzle page, not of the hint page.
# Two pages, namely '''Number sequences''' and '''Riddles''', display several puzzles at once, each with its own solution page.  I'm not sure how the solution pages should be named at the moment.  Meanwhile, I suggest that we skip processing these pages, and then maybe we can deal with them later.

==== Pass 2: Tidying up the pages ====

Once the pages are at their correct titles, the bot can then work at tidying up the pages themselves.  On the main Puzzles page, I believe the only thing that needs doing is to update the links.  On the pages within the book, there is the following work to do:

# Make sure every page has a navigation header.  Use the {{tl|hc-navhead2}}, {{tl|hc-navhead3}}, etc. templates, replacing any manually typed header that may be present on the page.  It is sufficient to check whether the page begins with a link back to [[Puzzles]], and if so, delete the whole line.  Any horizontal line immediately below the nav header should also be removed, since the hc-navhead templates automatically include one.
# Apart from that which is in the navigation header, there should be no repetition of the puzzle title at the beginning of the page content as is present on some of the '''How do you ... ?''' pages.
# Adjust all links to point to the pages by their new, hierarchical names, and make the display text exactly match the final part of the title.
# Link text should be non-bold.

==== Changes ====

If you wish to propose or discuss any changes or additions, please do so here.

=== Recent attempts ===

[[User:Withinfocus|Withinfocus]], who added {{tl|cleanup-NC}}, obviously didn't practise what the notice preaches by looking at this talk page.  As it happens, at least two users - [[User:Think Fast|Think Fast]] and [[User:SB Johnny|SBJohnny]] - have undertaken to implement the slashes convention, while at the same time failing to agree on other common-sense conventions (&quot;Logic '''p'''uzzles&quot; vs. &quot;Analytical '''P'''uzzles&quot;).  There are also plenty of other cleanups that could be done to the page titles as well as making them use slashes. -- [[User:Smjg|Smjg]] 12:20, 26 November 2006 (UTC)
:Hah, I just saw this little dig even though I added that template many months ago. The addition of the template was perfectly valid. Should the naming convention need to be discussed it would be done here as it was in some form above. Flagging a poorly-organized book was my goal and that's what happened, therefore there was nothing I &quot;didn't practice&quot; and my actions are correct. My addition of the template does not require discussion, only the implementation of the naming change does. I'm writing this so that if others notice it they won't be afraid to mark books that need cleanup. This is an implementation of policy and all books should be well-formed here at Wikibooks. The naming suggestions above need improvement in many ways so that colon convention can be avoided, but that will be tackled when a user who knows categories and the slash convention well feels like taking the effort to reorganize here. I unfortunately do not have the time currently. -[[User:Withinfocus|&lt;font color=&quot;#000000&quot;&gt;'''within'''&lt;/font&gt;]][[User talk:Withinfocus|&lt;font color=&quot;#7A7A7A&quot;&gt;'''focus'''&lt;/font&gt;]] 17:00, 17 April 2007 (UTC)

Just to clarify, the system that has been mostly followed is that section titles (&quot;Logic puzzles&quot;, etc.) are in sentence case, but individual puzzle titles are in title case.  This makes a little sense, ISFA one might think of puzzle titles as like titles of a book, song, film, etc. whereas section titles are just descriptive phrases used to group the puzzles.  But is it ideal?

It gets even more tricky when you consider that puzzles within [[Puzzles/Chess problems|Puzzles:Chess problems]], and possibly a few others, have more or less descriptive titles rather than titles in the style of the others, and generally have puzzle titles in sentence case.

What are we going to do then?  Before we do any more page moving, we should all agree on a convention for capitalising titles.  We should also decide what to do with [[Puzzles:Number sequences]], which currently has the puzzles all on one page and each solution on a page of its own. -- [[User:Smjg|Smjg]] 18:06, 27 November 2006 (UTC)

== Non-scientific puzzles ==
There are some logical puzzles that are too simple to be called logical, or non-solveable, or too contradictory, but interesting nonetheless. I added a new section, [[Puzzles:Non-Scientific Puzzles|Non-Scientific Puzzles]]. --[[User:Divinity|Divinity]] 18:24, 19 Jun 2005 (UTC)


== New Link Under Puzzle Resources ==
I added this link to a lot of riddles however the answeres aren't necessarily given to you so for a lot of them you might need to figure them out or check the Wu Forum however these are a lot of great riddles.* [http://www.ocf.berkeley.edu/~wwu/riddles/intro.shtml Riddles]&amp;ndash;Wu:Riddles I also added this link which has a wide variety of puzzles *[http://www.jimloy.com/puzz/puzz.htm Jim Loy's Puzzle Pages]--[[User:71.234.101.173|71.234.101.173]] 19:39, 14 February 2007 (UTC)

== Some pages don't seem to belong ==

Is this supposed to be a book ''of'' puzzles, a book ''about'' puzzles or a book of ''links to'' puzzles?  I'd think the former.  In this case, some of the pages seem out of place:

* [[Puzzles/Bongard problems]] and [[Puzzles/Sudoku]] are web links to puzzles.  The former has a bit of information on what Bongard problems are, but that's an aside.  Of course, if somebody wants to create some puzzles of these kinds to publish in this book, that's fine.

* [[Puzzles:Rubik's cubes]] and the other bullet points under [[Puzzles#Permutation puzzles]] don't seem to make sense to have here.  Of course a web page can present an applet for the user to play Rubik's cube or any mechanical puzzle, but Wikibooks isn't really the place for this.  You could argue that the right thing to have here is puzzles on how to construct specific Rubik's Cube patterns or perform specific manoeuvres, but that's still probably not the right title for such a section.

-- [[User:Smjg|Smjg]] 18:16, 25 March 2007 (UTC)

== Wikiversity Contributor Needs Material on &quot;Puzzles&quot;! ==

I intend to read ALL of the previous discussion before I start serious editing.&lt;BR&gt;
I agree that there is a need to overhaul the available material, so I intend to join in the discussion here.&lt;BR&gt;
&lt;BR&gt;
New Wikibooks User: [[User:Ray Calvin Baker|Ray Calvin Baker]] ([[User talk:Ray Calvin Baker|discuss]]  [[Special:Contributions/Ray Calvin Baker|contribs]]) 23:07, 31 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>gwjqpeskmum7fz7ghnwc02f5x2twy76</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>US History/European History</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1416</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2693744</id>
      <parentid>2681181</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-22T23:08:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>67.171.66.101</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Greece and Rome */ adding (briefly) royal and republican Rome ~~~~</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">The peoples of Europe have had a tremendous effect on the development of the United States throughout the course of U.S. history. Europeans &quot;discovered&quot; and colonized the North American continent and, even after they lost political control over its territory, their influence has predominated due to a common language, social ideals, and culture.  Therefore, when endeavoring to understand the history of the United States, it is helpful to briefly describe their European origin. 

== Greece and Rome ==
:''See also: [[Ancient History/Greece]] and [[Ancient History/Rome]]''
[[Image:Romia Imperio.png|thumb|right|350px|The Roman Empire]]
The first significant civilizations of Europe formed in the second millennium BCE. By 800 BCE, various '''Greek''' city-states, sharing a language and a culture based on slavery, pioneered novel political cultures. In the Greek city of Athens, by about 500 BCE, the male citizens who owned land began to elect their leaders. These elections by the minority of a minority represent the first democracy in the world. Other states in Greece experimented with other forms of rule, as in the totalitarian state of Sparta. These polities existed side by side, sometimes warring with each other, at one time combining against an invading army from Persia. Ancient Athens is known for its literary achievements in drama, history, and personal narrative. The individual city-states did not usually see themselves as a single entity. (The conqueror ''Alexander the Great'', who called himself a Greek, actually was a native of the non-Greek state of Macedon.) The city-states of Greece became provinces of the Roman Empire in 27 BCE.

The city of '''Rome''' was founded (traditionally in the year 753 BCE). Slowly, Rome grew from a kingdom to a republic to a vast empire, which, at various points, included most of present-day Britain (a large part of Scotland never belonged to the empire), France (then known as Gaul), Spain, Portugal, Italy, Greece, Turkey, Iraq, Palestine (including the territory claimed today by the modern state of Israel), Northern Arabia, Egypt, the Balkans, and the entire north coast of Africa. This empire was maintained through free-born or adoptive citizenship, citizen education and indoctrination, a large and well-drilled army, and taxes directed by a large bureaucracy directed by the emperor. As each province produced more Roman citizens, the state became hard to maintain. Whole kingdoms in the north and east, and the invading peoples we know as the Germanic tribes (the Ostrogoths and Visigoths and the Franks) sat apart from the system.

After the death of one emperor in 180 CE, power struggles between the army and a succession of rulers of contested origins produced anarchy. Diocletian (243 - 316) reinstated the Empire by 284. Rome regained territory until 395, when the Empire was so large that it had to be divided into two parts, each with a separate ruler. The two halves sat uneasily together. The East, which considered itself the heir of Alexander the Great, spoke Greek or a dialect, while the West spoke Latin. The Eastern Empire survived until 1453, but the system to maintain the Western Empire broke apart. Plagues and crop failures troubled the world. In 476, Germanic tribes deposed the boy who was then the Emperor. Roman roads fell into disrepair, and travel became difficult. Some memories remained in the lands which had once known Roman rule. The supreme rulers of various tribes called themselves ''king,'' a distortion of the Roman word Caesar.

== The Roman Empire to the Holy Roman Empire ==
[[Image:Adhmar de Monteil  Antioche.jpeg|thumb|left|200px|A mitred Adhmar de Monteil carrying the Holy Lance in one of the battles of the First Crusade]]
After Rome's fall, monks from Ireland (which had never known Rome) spread Catholic Christianity and the culture and language of the Western Roman Empire across Europe. Catholicism eventually spread through England (where the Germanic tribes of the Angles and the Saxons now lived)and to the lands of the post-Roman Germanic tribes. Among those tribes, the Franks rose to prominence.

''Charlemagne'' (742 - 814), the King of the Franks, conquered great portions of Europe. He eventually took control of Rome. The senate and the political organs of Rome had disappeared, and Charlemagne did not pretend to become the head of the Church. Charlemagne's domain, a confederation of what had been Roman Gaul with Germanic states, was much smaller than  Diocletian had known. But prestige came with identity with the past, and so this trunk of lands became '''The Holy Roman Empire'''. Charlemagne's descendants, as well as local rulers, took their sanction from the Church, while the Church's pope influenced both religious and political matters. 

The result of political stability was technological advance. After the year 1000, Western Europe caught some of the East's discoveries, and invented others. In addition to vellum, Europeans now started making paper of rags or wood pulp. They also adopted the wind and water mill, the horse collar (for plows and for heavy weights), the moldboard plow, and other agricultural and technological advances. Towns came into being, and then walled cities. More people survived, and the knights and kings over them grew restive.

== Viking Exploration of North America ==
[[Image:Wikinger.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Danish seamen, painted mid-12th century.]]
In the eighth century, pushed from their homes in Scandinavia by war and population expansion, Norsemen, or '''Vikings''', began settling parts of the Faeroe, Shetland, and Orkney Islands in the North Atlantic. They went where ever treasure was, trading as far as Byzantium and Kiev in the East. In the West they raided from Ireland and England down to the Italian peninsula, sailing into a port, seizing its gold, and murdering or enslaving its people before fleeing. They began settling Iceland in approximately 874 CE. A Viking called ''Erik the Red'' was accused of murder and banished from his native Iceland in about 982. Eric explored and later founded a settlement in a snowy western island. Knowing that this bleak land would need many people to prosper, Eric returned to Iceland after his exile had passed and coined the word &quot;Greenland&quot; to appeal to the overpopulated and treeless settlement of Iceland. Eric returned to Greenland in 985 and established two colonies with a population of nearly 5000.

''Leif Erikson'', son of Erik the Red, and other members of his family began exploration of the North American coast in 986.  He landed in three places, in the third establishing a small settlement called Vinland. The location of Vinland is uncertain, but an archeological site on the northern tip of Newfoundland, Canada (L'anse aux Meadows) has been identified as the site of a modest Viking settlement and is the oldest confirmed presence of Europeans in North America. The site contains the remains of eight Norse buildings, as well as a modern reproduction of a Norse longhouse. But the settlement in Vinland was abandoned in struggles between the Vikings and the native inhabitants, whom the settlers called ''Skraelingar''. Bickering also broke out among the Norseman themselves. The settlement lasted less than two years. The Vikings would make brief excursions to North America for the next 200 years, though another attempt at colonization was soon thwarted.

By the thirteenth century, Iceland and Greenland had also entered a period of decline during the &quot;Little Ice Age.&quot; Knowledge of their exploration, in the days before the printing press, was ignored in most of Europe. Yet the Vikings are now considered the true European discoverers of North America. The influence of their people outlasted even the terrible raids, and their grandchildren became kings and queens. For example, a branch of Viking descendants living in France, the Normans, conquered England from the Anglo-Saxons in 1066.

== The Great Famine and Black Death ==
The Little Ice Age led to European famines in the years 1315-1317 and in 1321. In the year 1318 sheep and cattle began to die of a contagious disease. Farmers could not support the growing population. And then, in 1347, some Genoese trading ships inadvertently brought a new, invasive species of rat to Europe. These rats carried '''bubonic plague'''.

Plague was also called '''the Black Death''', from the darkened skin left after death and from its deadly reach. It had three strands: ''bubonic'', ''pneumonic'', and ''septicemic''.&lt;ref&gt;Massachusetts Medical Society, New England Surgical Society. Boston medical and surgical journal, Volume 149, Issue 2. 1903&lt;/ref&gt; In bubonic plague fleas carried by the rats would leave their hosts and bite people. The masses of bacteria would flow through the human system, killing cells and leaving their refuse in lymph nodes in the armpit, groin, and neck. These nodes would swell and turn black, creating bubos. Infection could also spread into the lungs, so that a person might cough or sneeze the germ into the air. This created pneumonic plague, spreading disease into spaces where people gathered and where rats dared not go. It also spread through contamination of food. The last form of disease, and its most deadly, was septicemic. This attacked the blood, leaving stretches of pale skin looking black, and killing the person within hours. 

Surviving laws of cities and guilds regulate public cleanliness and penalize adulteration of food. They cannot show how strictly these laws were applied. And they show no knowledge, of course, of germ theory and the need for sterilization. Older systems such as the few public baths which remained from the days of colonial Rome were seen as sinful and dangerous, invitations to the plague. The dwelling places of survivors of pre-Christian Rome, the Jews who were forced to live apart, were attacked by mobs who attributed the Black Death to their poisoning Christians' wells.  

The responses to plague can be seen in the records left by survivors -- one third of the population of Europe died in repeated waves of disease -- and in the subsequent changes in society. Airplanes and satellites show the foundations of plague-era towns which were emptied by the disease. In just one square mile of pre-plague Europe there are reports of there being 50,000 people.&lt;ref&gt;Gottfried, Robert S. The Black Death: Natural and Human Disaster in Medieval Europe. Simon and Schuster, 1985. 64.&lt;/ref&gt; In large cities, families would flee or lock themselves away, trying to keep themselves from death. Other families were locked in by city authorities. This is the beginning of the modern system of quarantine.&lt;ref&gt;Hunter, Susan S. Black death: AIDS in Africa. Palgrave Macmillan, 2003. 115.&lt;/ref&gt; Some branches of the family would not be among those so helped. The Black Death seemed erratic, sometimes taking people deemed good and pious, sometimes not. One priest or church prelate might die, and another survive. And a living priest might give no aid to other survivors. Some critiques of the Church which had become spread through most of Europe date from this era.  

Although some lands became waste through lack of tilling, those people who survived grasped the property of those who had not. Europe then had a land-based economic system. Rich people became richer. There began a labor shortage: the farmers who survived needed hands to take in their crops. The wages of farm hands began to rise. In the surviving towns they needed people to guard the gates: in the courts they began to look for rising young men. Cities became more powerful in the depleted lands, and authority grew more centralized.

== Education ==
During the Middle Ages Western society and education were heavily shaped by Christianity as expressed through the Roman Catholic Church. Towns, courts, and feudal manors had their priests, monasteries and nunneries had their ''scriptora'' or libraries, and after the 11th century CE, a few cities had Universities, schools to educate men to be high-ranking clerics, lawyers, or doctors. Where children had schools, their parents paid a fee so that they might learn Latin, the language St. Jerome had used for his translation of the Bible. Latin was the language of the Church. It was also learned, along with military tactics and the rules of chivalry, by men who trained to be knights. A smattering of Latin was necessary, along with Math, even for the elementary schools which sprang up in some cities. There both boys and girls were taught literacy and math, prerequisite for acceptance as an apprentice in many Guilds.  Latin across Europe created a European-wide culture: a doctor from Padua could talk to his fellow from Oxford in Latin. 

As in the Greek and Roman eras, only a minority of people went to school. There were not enough books, little travel, and no means of spreading standardized education. Schools were attended first by persons planning to enter religious life. Occasionally a cleric would reach out to educate a very bright peasant boy. This was one of the few ways peasants could rise in the world. But the vast majority of people were serfs who served as agricultural workers on the estates of feudal lords. They were, in effect, tied to the fate of the land. From the serf up to some high princes, the vast majority of people did not attend school, and were generally illiterate.

In the rise of the Universities in the 11th century, the Church translated several manuscripts of the ancient Greek writer Aristotle into Latin. From Aristotle's emphasis upon human reason, philosophy and science, and the Church's emphasis upon revelation and the teachings of Christ, medieval scholars developed ''Scholasticism''. This was an philosophical and educational movement  which attempted to integrate into an ordered system both the natural wisdom of Greece and Rome and the religious wisdom of Christianity. It was dominant in the medieval Christian schools and universities of Europe from about the middle of the 11th century to about the middle of the 15th century, though its influence continued in successive centuries. The idea of Man in the middle of ordered nature, and yet dominant over nature, bore fruit in the observation of natural phenomena, the beginnings of what the Western World knows as science. It also led to the exultation of system over observation, and the persistence of the Ptolemaic theories such as geocentrism among formally educated people. 

Noble girls were sometimes sent to live in nunneries in order to receive basic schooling. Nuns would teach them to read and write and the chores necessary to run their establishments, including spinning and weaving. (Cloth-making was a major national industry in the Middle Ages.) They taught them their manners and their prayers. Some of these girls later became nuns themselves.

== Christianity, Islam, Judaism ==

During the centuries after the fall of Rome, various flavors of Christian churches spread from Northern Africa and Armenia westward. This changed after ''Mohammed'' established Islam in 610 CE. Like Christianity, it spread through conversion and conflict. At its height it was also a faith of Europe, from Spain to Albania and Bosnia and their sister states. Both Prince and Caliph held that their state must have one faith, and no other belief was encouraged. When Jerusalem was reconquered by the Seljuq Turks, Christians were no longer able to go on religious pilgrimages to the Holy City.

At the end of the eleventh century, ''Pope Urban II'' inaugurated the Crusades, urging Western European kings and great nobles to begin what would be a century and a half of warfare. Christian armies fought first to reconquer and then to hold part of the Kingdom of Jerusalem. The Crusaders ultimately failed in the face of resurgent Muslim forces. Western Europeans within Church and State argued for and against the Crusades.

Despite the failure of the Crusades, militant Western Christianity persisted in Spain in an effort known as ''the Reconquista'' (the &quot;reconquest&quot;), which purged the land of the Muslims who had arrived there in 711.  By the fifteenth century, the Muslims were confined to the kingdom of Granada, which bordered the Mediterranean Sea in the southern side of the Iberian Peninsula.  Granada finally fell in 1492 to the Spanish Christians, ending the reconquista. 

Rome had destroyed Israel in 70 CE, but allowed a remnant of her people to survive. Fortified by rabbinic culture and centered on the Torah, they became a resilient group. They survived as the known world became Christian. They spread, as traders, through East and West. However, Christian relationships with Jews were punctuated by hatred. They were held to be guilty of Jesus' death, and they were supposed to be evil because they had not converted to Christianity. They were forced into the notorious ghettos, usually built on waste or undesirable land. They were forced to wear strange clothing which marked them off, and to pay heavy taxes.&lt;ref&gt;(Charing pg. 18-23). Charing, Douglas. Judaism. New York, NY: DK Pub., 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; Christians spread rumors that Jewish officials sometimes kidnapped and killed young boys for their sacrifices. Sometimes a mob might break into the ghetto, killing some people. Individuals were sometimes forced to convert. One of the effects of European nationalism was the expulsion of a country's Jewish population. England was the first, in the 13th century; later, a reviving France; later still, Spain and Portugal. Some men crewing the ships in the Age of Exploration were Jews, often practicing their faith in hiding.  

For a period in the late Twelfth century there two sets of Popes, a line in Rome and another in the French city of Avignon under the sway of that Court. In reaction against this, the Church centralized its powers in parallel to what nations were doing. There had been dissension before, in medieval England's Lollards and later with the Czech priest John Hus. However, it was only in an age after the printing press, when people began printing the Bible in their own languages, when ''Martin Luther'' founded the Protestant church. England's ''King Henry VIII'', who had won the title &quot;Protector of the Faith&quot; for a work defending the Pope, later left it to become the head of the Church of England. This division of Western Christianity created religious minorities, who were persecuted throughout Europe. Among these were the Pilgrims, who helped settle America.

== The Renaissance ==
:''See also: [[European History]]''
Another, more humble result of the plague was the accumulation of rags left over from clothing. These were quickly used to make paper. Books were very rare during the Middle Ages, and the monks who made them chained them to their shelves. It took one year for a man to make one book. In that climate Bibles took priority: we have only one copy of Democritus's most famous work surviving from this period. As rag paper replaced velum, books began to become more plentiful. The supply was augmented by Europe's adoption of ''Johannes Gutenberg'' 's fixed-type printing press in the 15th century.&lt;ref&gt;Elizabeth Eisenstein, The printing press as an agent of change: communications and cultural transformations in early modern Europe (2 vols. ed.). Cambridge UK: Cambridge University Press. 1979. ISBN 0-521-22044-0&lt;/ref&gt;

There had been earlier leaps in culture, including the wave of population and technological adaptation in the 12th century. This left its mark in increased population and the Roman Catholic Church's adoption of Aristotle. Yet the press made it possible for knowledge to have a foothold in society. Inventions in one place could be explained and adopted across a continent. The Greeks fleeing the fall of Byzantium brought their knowledge of ancient Greek culture to the West. The Bible, the basic book of Christendom, could be pored over by laypeople, and reading it could be learned by more people than ever before. Learning was no longer solely the province of the Church.

If the Bible was first off of the presses, pseudo-science and science followed soon after. The European witch trials were one result of the new medium. The questioning of scientific consensus was another. ''Andreas Vesalius'' published his observations about the circulatory system. Books discussing the theories of ''Nicolaus Copernicus'' and ''Galileo Galilei'' demolished the old geocentric theory of the cosmos. The arts were not neglected. Giorgio Vasari's biographical Lives introduced such new artists as ''Leonardo Da Vinci'' and ''Michelangelo Buonarroti'' to the larger world.

A later time called this growth of knowledge '''the Renaissance'''. They said it began in the Italian city-states, spreading throughout most of Europe. The Italian city of Florence was called the birthplace of this intellectual movement.

Books spread the Crusader's newly found experience and knowledge of the Mediterranean, a region whose technology was at that time superior to that of western Europe. Books written about traders, adventurers, and scholars spread knowledge of Chinese technology such as gunpowder and silk. They spread writings of the ancient world which had been lost to Europe, and nurtured a taste for new foods and flavors. They spread pictures of ancient Greek statues, Moorish carpets, and strange practices. 

In the fifteenth century, the Mediterranean was a vigorous trading area.  European ships brought in grains and salts for preserving fish, Chinese silks, Indian cotton, precious stones, and above all, spices. White cane sugar could be used to preserve fruit and to flavor medicine. Cinnamon was medicine against bad humors as well as preservative and flavoring, part of the mysterious ''poudre douce'', and now available even to some European common people.

== Toward Nation-States ==

The great age of exploration was undertaken by nation-states, cohesive entities with big treasuries who tended to use colonization as a national necessity. When such nations as Portugal, England, Spain, and France became stronger, they began building ships. 

=== The Rise of Portugal ===

The Italian peninsula dominated the world because of its position in the Mediterranean Sea. Universities in Padua, Rome, and elsewhere taught men from East and West. Above all, principalities such as the Republic of Venice and Florence controlled trade. Genoa and Venice in particular ballooned into massive trading cities. Yet there was at yet no nation of Italy, so each city's riches belonged only to that city. Individual cities used their monopoly to raise the price of goods, which would have been expensive in any case, because they were often brought overland from Asia to ports on the eastern Mediterranean. The mad prices, in turn, increased the desire of purchasers to find other suppliers, and of potential suppliers to find a better and cheaper route to Asia.

Portugal was just one of many potential suppliers, with a location which extended its influence into the Atlantic and down, south and east, to Africa.  Prince Henry, son of King John I, promoted the exploration of new routes to the East. He planned Portugal's 1415 capture of Ceuta in Muslim North Africa. He also sponsored voyages that pushed even farther down the West African coast. By the time of his death in 1460, these voyages had reached south to Sierra Leone.

Under King John II, who ruled from 1481 to 1495, Bartolomeu Dias finally sailed around the southernmost point of Africa to the Cape of Good Hope (1487-1488).  In 1497-1499 Vasco da Gama of Portugal sailed up the east coast of Africa to India.

The Portuguese colonized and settled such islands in the Atlantic as Madeira, Cape Verde, the Azores, and Sao Tome. These islands supplied them with sugar and gave them territorial control of the Atlantic. West Africa was more promising, not only unearthing a valuable trade route to India, but also providing the Portuguese with ivory, fur, oils, black pepper, gold dust, and a supply of dark skinned slaves who were used as domestic servants, artisans, and market or transportation workers in Lisbon. They were later used as laborers on sugar plantations on the Atlantic.

=== France, England, And The Hundred Years' War ===

King Harold of England faced William the Norman usurper after defeating the last Viking forces holding the North of England. And when William the Norman became William the Conqueror, he held England by consolidating the nation. His army was ruled from newly built castles, and had the best technology of the time. His sons and their sons fought the original inhabitants of their country in Scotland and Wales, pushing their boarders. They also claimed the right to their ancestral Normandy, in what is now France. (There had long been rivalry between England and France over the wool trade.) By a English king's marriage to an former queen of France, Eleanor of Aquitaine, the king subsequently claimed Aquitaine. During the years of 1337 to 1453, the kings of England claimed the whole of France and beyond, fighting '''The Hundred Years' War''' there and in the Low Countries. For some years the English threatened Paris, and there was a question whether the small area of France proper would be entirely conquered. The early stages of the war marked by English victory against a demoralized French people and their Prince. But around 1428, a young peasant girl from Lorriene, France named Joan of Arc approached a garrison of the French army. She told them that  Saint Michael, Saint Catherine, and Saint Margaret had told her to lead the army to victory. She said that God had come to her in a dream, and told her how to defeat the English. She claimed that God said Prince Charles of France needed to be crowned in order for France to claim victory over the English.&lt;ref&gt;Warner, Marina. Joan of Arc: The Image of Female Heroism.  University of California Press, 1999&lt;/ref&gt; After gaining the new French king, support of the populace, and several key victories, Joan was sold to the English for treason and as an appeasement. Yet France had been renewed. It pushed back against the invaders, and took back most of the land. In the next few centuries it was to remove England from Continental Europe.

The Hundred Years' War devastated both countries. But it ultimately turned both of them into stronger, colonial powers. The Hundred Years' War created opportunities for wealth and advancement for the knights of both countries. The Chivalric code showed great influence during this period. France absorbed Aquitaine, Castile, and Normandy itself, prosperous areas. The twin strokes of the plague and the Inquisition weakened opposition to the French king's rule. And English centralization continued as its own royalty sought service of serf and Baron. A group of new dialects, Middle English, came out of the tug between Norman lord and Anglo-Saxon peasant. If the nation could not get new land in Europe, it could use its ships to sail elsewhere.

== Review Questions ==
1. Explain how one of these late medieval devices affected prosperity: the wind mill; the horse collar; the printing press.

2. How did the plague infect individuals? How did mass death affect society?

3. What was the importance of these four men to the Renaissance? Galileo Galilei, Nicolaus Copernicus, Andreas Vesalius, Leonardo Da Vinci.

==References==
{{reflist}}
{{chapnav|Pre-Columbian|Exploration}}</text>
      <sha1>puweho2r9s2kw4p49c6j7am1ttumv8x</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>General Chemistry/Chemical equations</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1420</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2175071</id>
      <parentid>2142586</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-10-03T19:02:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>HethrirBot</username>
        <id>475400</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Robot: Cosmetic changes</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{GeneralChemTOC|next=Balancing Equations|prev=Stoichiometry}}

Chemical equations are a convenient, standardized system for describing [[../Chemical reactions|chemical reactions]]. They contain the following information.

*The type of '''reactants''' consumed and '''products''' formed
*The relative amounts of reactants and products
*The electrical charges on [[General Chemistry/Ionic bonds|ions]]
*The physical state of each species (e.g. solid, liquid)
*The reaction conditions (e.g. temperature, catalysts)

The final two points are optional and sometimes omitted.

== Anatomy of an Equation ==
&lt;center&gt;&lt;math&gt;\hbox{H}_{2 (g)} + \hbox{Cl}_{2 (g)} \to 2\hbox{HCl}_{(g)}&lt;/math&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

Hydrogen gas and chlorine gas will react vigorously to produce hydrogen chloride gas. The equation above illustrates this reaction. The reactants, hydrogen and chlorine, are written on the left and the products (hydrogen chloride) on the right. The large number 2 in front of HCl indicates that two molecules of HCl are produced for each 1 molecule of hydrogen and chlorine gas consumed. The 2 in subscript below H indicates that there are two hydrogen atoms in each molecule of hydrogen gas. Finally, the (g) symbols subscript to each species indicates that they are gases.

=== Reacting Species ===
'''Species''' in a chemical reaction is a general term used to mean atoms, molecules or ions. A species can contain more than one chemical element (HCl, for example, contains hydrogen and chlorine). Each species in a chemical equation is written:

&lt;center&gt;&lt;math&gt;\hbox{E}_{x(s)}^y&lt;/math&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

'''E''' is the chemical symbol for the element, '''x''' is the number of atoms of that element in the species, '''y''' is the charge (if it is an ion) and '''(s)''' is the physical state.

{{TextBox|1=
The symbols in parentheses (in subscript below each species) indicate the physical state of each reactant or product.

*'''(s)''' means solid
*'''(l)''' means liquid
*'''(g)''' means gas
*'''(aq)''' means aqueous solution (i.e. dissolved in water)
}}

For example, ethyl alcohol would be written &lt;math&gt;\hbox{C}_2\hbox{H}_6\hbox{O}_{(l)}&lt;/math&gt; because each molecule contains 2 carbon, 6 hydrogen and 1 oxygen atom. A magnesium ion would be written &lt;math&gt;\hbox{Mg}^{2+}&lt;/math&gt; because it has a double positive (&quot;two plus&quot;) charge. Finally, an ammonium ion would be written &lt;math&gt;\hbox{NH}_4^+&lt;/math&gt; because each molecule contains 1 nitrogen and 4 hydrogen atoms and has a charge of 1+.

=== Coefficients ===
The numbers in front of each species have a very important meaningthey indicate the relative amounts of the atoms that react. The number in front of each species is called a '''coefficient'''. In the above equation, for example, one H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; molecule reacts with one Cl&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; molecule to produce two molecules of HCl. This can also be interpreted as ''moles'' (i.e. 1 mol H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and 1 mol Cl&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; produces 2 mol HCl).

It is important that the ''Law of Conservation of Mass'' is not violated.  There must be the same number of each type of atoms on either side of the equation.  Coefficients are useful for keeping the same number of atoms on both sides:

&lt;center&gt;&lt;math&gt;2\hbox{H}_2 + \hbox{O}_2 \to 2\hbox{H}_2\hbox{O}&lt;/math&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

If you count the atoms, there are four hydrogens and two oxygens on each side.  The coefficients allow us to '''balance the equation'''; without them the equation would have the wrong number of atoms.  Balancing equations is the topic of the next chapter.

=== Other Information ===
Occasionally, other information about a chemical reaction will be supplied in an equation (such as temperature or other reaction conditions). This information is often written to the right of the equation or above the reaction arrow.  A simple example would be the melting of ice.

&lt;center&gt;&lt;math&gt;\hbox{H}_2\hbox{O}_{(s)} + heat \to \hbox{H}_2\hbox{O}_{(l)}&lt;/math&gt;, which could be written as &lt;math&gt;\hbox{H}_2\hbox{O}_{(s)} \xrightarrow{heat} \hbox{H}_2\hbox{O}_{(l)}&lt;/math&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

Reactions commonly involve '''catalysts''', which are substances that speed up a reaction without being consumed.  Catalysts are often written over the arrow.  A perfect example of a catalyzed reaction is photosynthesis.  Inside plant cells, a substance called ''chlorophyll'' converts sunlight into food.  The reaction is written:

&lt;center&gt;&lt;math&gt;6\hbox{CO}_2 + 6\hbox{H}_2\hbox{O} + sunlight \xrightarrow{chlorophyll} \hbox{C}_6\hbox{H}_{12}\hbox{O}_6  +  6\hbox{O}_2&lt;/math&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

== Examples ==
{| border=&quot;0&quot; cellpadding=&quot;15px&quot; cellspacing=&quot;15px&quot;
|&lt;math&gt;\hbox{CH}_{4(g)} + 2\hbox{O}_{2(g)} \to \hbox{CO}_{2(g)} + 2\hbox{H}_2\hbox{O}_{(l)}&lt;/math&gt;
| This is the equation for burning methane gas (CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;) in the presence of oxygen (O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) to form carbon dioxide and water: CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O respectively.  Notice the use of coefficients to obey the Law of Conservation of Matter.
|-
|&lt;math&gt;\hbox{Pb}_{(aq)}^{2+} + 2\hbox{I}_{(aq)}^- \to \hbox{PbI}_{2(s)}&lt;/math&gt;
| This is a ''precipitation'' reaction in which dissolved lead cations and iodide anions combine to form a solid yellow precipitate of lead iodide (an [[General Chemistry/Ionic bonds|ionic]] solid).
|-
|&lt;math&gt;2\hbox{SO}_{2(g)} + 2\hbox{V}_2\hbox{O}_{5(s)} \to 2\hbox{SO}_{3(g)} + 4\hbox{V}_2\hbox{O}_{(s)}&lt;/math&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;math&gt;4\hbox{V}_2\hbox{O}_{(s)} + \hbox{O}_{2(g)} \to 2\hbox{V}_2\hbox{O}_{5(s)}&lt;/math&gt;
|These two equations involve a catalyst.  They occur one after another, using divanadium pentoxide to convert sulfur dioxide into sulfur trioxide.  If you look closely, you can see that the vanadium catalyst is involved in the reaction, but it does not get consumed.  It is both a reactant and a product, but it is necessary for the reaction to occur, making it a catalyst.
|-
|&lt;math&gt;2\hbox{SO}_{2(g)} + \hbox{O}_{2(g)} \xrightarrow{V_2O_5} 2\hbox{SO}_{3(g)}&lt;/math&gt;
| If we add both equations together, we can cancel out terms that appear on both sides.  The resulting equation is much simpler and self-explanatory (although the original pair of equations is more accurate in describing how the reaction proceeds).
|}

{{Info|The last example demonstrates another important principle of chemical equations:  they can be added together.  Simply list ''all'' reactants from the equations you are adding, then list ''all'' products.  If the same term appears on both sides, it is either a catalyst, an ''intermediate product'', or it is not involved in the reaction.  Either way, it can be canceled out from both sides (if the coefficients are equal).  Try adding the first two vanadium equations together and see if you can cancel out terms to get the final equation.}}

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>cfp6skksk2uwjuo895gfa7v23u0kozf</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>French/Lessons/People and things</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1421</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2587633</id>
      <parentid>2586108</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-12-04T20:45:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JackBot</username>
        <id>396820</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;noinclude&gt;{{French/Lessons/Level one/Header||Les gens et les choses}}&lt;/noinclude&gt;
{{French/Lesson objective|
: ''Quest-ce que cest ? C'est une colombe.''
: ''Voici les deux garons !''
}}
== {{French/Section|Grammar|Gender of nouns|Genre des noms}} ==

In French, all nouns have a '''grammatical gender'''; that is, they are either masculine ('''m''') or feminine ('''f''').

Most nouns that express people or animals have both a masculine and a feminine form.  For example, the two words for ''the actor'' in French are {{French/Word|l'acteur|gender='''m'''}} and {{French/Word|l'actrice|gender='''f'''}}.

However, there are some nouns that talk about people or animals whose gender is fixed, regardless of the actual gender of the person or animal.  For example, {{French/Word|la personne|gender='''f'''|en=the person}} is always feminine, even when it's talking about your uncle; {{French/Word|le professeur|gender='''m'''|en=the professor}} is always masculine, even when it's talking about your female professor or teacher.

The nouns that express things without an obvious gender (e.g., objects and abstract concepts) have only one form. This form can be masculine or feminine. For example, {{French/Word|la voiture|en=the car}} can only be feminine; {{French/Word|le stylo|en=the pen}} can only be masculine.

=== {{French/Section|Grammar|Common endings|supplementary-id=french-common-endings}} ===
&lt;div id='french-common-endings'&gt;
{| {{French/Table|audio=French/Grammar/Common endings of masculine and feminine nouns.ogg|columns=4}}
! colspan=4 | Masculine nouns
|-
! -age
| le fromage || {{French/Section}} || {{French/Section|the cheese}}
|-
! -d
| le pied || {{French/Section}} || {{French/Section|the foot}}
|-
! -g
| le rang || {{French/Section}} || {{French/Section|the rank}}
|-
! -isme
| le matrialisme || {{French/Section}} || {{French/Section|materialism}}
|-
! -ment
| le mouvement || {{French/Section}} || {{French/Section|the movement}}
|-
! -n
| le ballon || {{French/Section}} || {{French/Section|the balloon}}
|-
! -r
| le professeur || {{French/Section}} || {{French/Section|the teacher}}
|-
! -t
| le chat || {{French/Section}} || {{French/Section|the cat}}
|-
! colspan=4 | Feminine nouns
|-
! -ce
| la grce || {{French/Section}} || {{French/Section|the grace}}
|-
! -che
| la touche || {{French/Section}} || {{French/Section|the touch}}
|-
! -e
| la dure || {{French/Section}} || {{French/Section|the duration}}
|-
! -ie
| la boulangerie || {{French/Section}} || {{French/Section|the bakery}}
|-
! -ion
| la nation || {{French/Section}} || {{French/Section|the nation}}
|-
! -ite/-it
| la stabilit || {{French/Section}} || {{French/Section|stability}}
|-
! -lle
| la fille || {{French/Section}} || {{French/Section|the girl}}
|-
! -nce
| la balance || {{French/Section}} || {{French/Section|the scales}}
|-
! -nne 
| la personne || {{French/Section}} || {{French/Section|the person}}
|-
! -ure
| la figure || {{French/Section}} || {{French/Section|the figure}}
|}&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- /french-common-endings --&gt;

=== Exceptions ===

There are many exceptions to gender rules in French which can only be learned. There are even words that are spelled the same, but have a different meaning when masculine or feminine; for example, {{French/Word|le livre|gender='''m'''}} means ''the book'', but {{French/Word|la livre|gender='''f'''}} means ''the pound''. Some words that appear to be masculine (such as ''la photo'', which should be masculine but is not because it is actually short for ''la photographie'') are in fact feminine, and vice versa. Then there are some that just don't make sense; ''la foi'' is feminine and means ''faith'' or ''belief'', whereas ''le foie'' is masculine and means ''liver''.

== {{French/Section|Vocabulary|Example nouns}} ==
{{French/Vocabulary gallery
| le cheval | /val/ | Fr-un cheval-fr.ogg | Oost-Fries Paard Lithografie 1898.png
| le chien | /j/ | Fr-chien.ogg | Flat Coated Retriever - black.jpg
| le livre | /liv/ | Fr-un livre-fr-ouest.ogg | Open book nae 02.svg
| la colombe | /klb/ | Fr-colombe.ogg | Rock dove - natures pics.jpg
| la chemise | /.miz/ | Fr-chemise.ogg | Shirt.jpg
| la maison | /m.z/ | Fr-une maison-fr-ouest.ogg | Go-home.svg
}}


{| {{French/Translations table|audio=French/Grammar/Example masculine and feminine nouns.ogg}}
! colspan=6 | Masculine nouns
|-
| le cheval || {{audio|Fr-un cheval-fr.ogg|/val/}} || the horse
|-
| le chien || {{audio|Fr-chien.ogg|/j/}} || the dog
|-
| le livre || {{audio|Fr-un livre-fr-ouest.ogg|/liv/}} || the book
|-
| le bruit || {{audio|Fr-bruit.ogg|/bi/}} || the noise
|-
! colspan=6 | Feminine nouns
|-
| la colombe || {{audio|Fr-colombe.ogg|/klb/}} || the dove
|-
| la chemise || {{audio|Fr-chemise.ogg|/.miz/}} || the shirt
|-
| la maison || {{audio|Fr-une maison-fr-ouest.ogg|/m.z/}} || the house
|-
| la libert || {{audio|Fr-libert.ogg|/li.b.te/}} || the liberty
|}

== {{French/Section|Grammar|Articles}} ==

=== {{French/Section||The definite article|L'article dfini}} ===

In English, the definite article is always ''the''.

In French, the definite article is changed depending on the noun's:
# gender
# plurality
# first letter
There are three definite articles and an abbreviation. ''Le'' is used for masculine nouns, ''La'' is used for feminine nouns, ''Les'' is used for plural nouns (both masculine or feminine), and ''L''' is used when the noun is singular and begins with a vowel or silent ''h'' (both masculine or feminine). It is similar to English, where ''a'' changes to ''an'' before a vowel.

{| {{French/Table|audio=French Grammar - The Definite Article.ogg|columns=7}}
| rowspan=2 | singular
| feminine
! la
| {{fr/IPA|/la/|approx=lah|audio=Fr-la.ogg}}
| la fille || {{fr/IPA||approx=lah fee-y&lt;sup&gt;uh&lt;/sup&gt;}} || the daughter
|-
| masculine 
! le
| {{fr/IPA|/l/|approx=luh|audio=Fr-le.ogg}}
| le fils || {{fr/IPA||approx=luh fees}} || the son
|-
| colspan=2 | singular, starting with a vowel sound
! l
| {{fr/IPA|/l/}}
| lenfant || {{fr/IPA||approx=lah&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;-fah&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;}} || the child
|-
| rowspan=3 colspan=&quot;2&quot; | plural
! rowspan=3 | les
| rowspan=3 | {{fr/IPA|/le/|approx=lay|audio=Fr-les.ogg}}
| les filles || {{fr/IPA||approx=lay fee-y&lt;sup&gt;uh&lt;/sup&gt;}} || the daughters
|-
| les fils || {{French/Section (''lay fees'')}} || the sons
|-
| les enfants || {{French/Section}} (''lay-zah&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;-fah&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;'')|| the children
|}

Unlike English, the definite article is used to talk about something in a general sense, a general statement or feeling about an idea or thing.

=== Elision ===
''Elision'' refers to the suppression of a final unstressed vowel immediately before another word beginning with a vowel. The definite articles ''le'' and ''la'' are shortened to ''l'' when they come before a noun that begins with a vowel or silent ''h''. When pronounced, the vowel sound is dropped.

{| {{French/Table|audio=French/Grammar/Elision.ogg|columns=5}}
| (le) ami || {{French/Section|}} || '''l''''ami || {{French/Section|{{fr/IPA|approx=lah-mee}}}} || the (male) friend
|-
| (la) amie || {{French/Section|}} || '''l''''amie || {{French/Section|{{fr/IPA|approx=lah-mee}}}} || the (female) friend
|-
| (le) lve || {{French/Section|}} || '''l''''lve || {{French/Section|{{fr/IPA|approx=lay-lehv}}}} || the pupil
|-
| (la) heure || {{French/Section|}} || '''l''''heure || {{French/Section|{{fr/IPA|approx=lewr}}}} || the hour, the time
|}

Elision does not occur on an aspired ''h'':
: (le) hros: {{French/Word|le hros|en=the hero}}

In addition to the definite article, elision will also occur with other words, such as ''que'', ''je'', ''le'', ''ce'', ''ne'', and ''de''.  The details on these words will be covered in later sections of the book.

=== {{French/Section||The indefinite article|L'article indfini}} ===

In English, the indefinite articles are ''a'' and ''an''. ''Some'' is used as a plural article in English.

Again, indefinite articles in French take different forms depending on gender and plurality. The articles ''un'' and ''une'' literally mean ''one'' in French.

{| {{French/Table|audio=French Grammar - The Indefinite Article.ogg|columns=6}}
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | singular
| feminine
! une
| {{fr/IPA|/yn/|approx=ewn}} || une fille{{ref|une}} || a daughter
|-
| masculine
! un
| {{fr/IPA|//|approx=uh&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;}} || un fils || a son
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; | plural
! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | des
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | {{fr/IPA|/d/|approx=deh}}
| des filles || some daughters
|-
| des fils{{ref|desfils}} || some sons
|}

{{note|une}} ''une'' is often (more often than not) pronounced (''ewnuh'') in poetry and lyric.&lt;br /&gt;
{{note|desfils}} ''Des fils'' does mean ''some sons'', but is a homograph: it can also mean ''some threads'' (when pronounced like {{audio|/fil/|approx=feel}}).

=== ''Some'' ===
Note that ''des'', like ''les'', is used in French before plural nouns when no article is used in English. For example, you are looking at photographs in an album. The English statement ''I am looking at photographs.'' cannot be translated to French as ''Je regarde photographies.'' because an article is required to tell which photographs are being looked at. If it is a set of ''specific'' pictures, the French statement should be {{French/Word|Je regarde '''les''' photographies.|en=I am looking at '''the''' photographs.}} On the other hand, if the person is just browsing the album, the French translation is {{French/Word|Je regarde '''des''' photographies.|en=I am looking at ''some'' photographs.}}

=== Plurality, pronunciation, and exceptions ===
The plural of most nouns is formed by adding an ''-s''. However, the ''-s'' ending is not pronounced. It is the article that tells the listener whether the noun is singular or plural. &lt;!-- add examples --&gt;

Most singular nouns do not end in ''-s''. The ''-s'' is added for the plural form of the noun. ''Fils'' is one exception. Whenever the singular form of a noun ends in ''-s'', there is no change in the plural form.

{| {{French/Table|columns=4}}
|le fils&lt;br /&gt;{{French/Section|the son}}||les fils&lt;br /&gt;{{French/Section|the sons}}||un fils&lt;br /&gt;{{French/Section|a son}}||des fils&lt;br /&gt;{{French/Section|(some) sons}}
|-
|le cours&lt;br /&gt;{{French/Section|the course}}||les cours&lt;br /&gt;{{French/Section|the courses}}||un cours&lt;br /&gt;{{French/Section|a course}}||des cours&lt;br /&gt;{{French/Section|(some) courses}}
|}

The final consonant is almost always not pronounced unless followed by an ''-e'' (or another vowel). {{French/Word|Fils|IPA=/fis/|audio=Fr-fils.ogg|approx=fees}} is also an exception to this rule.

=== Liaison ===
Remember that the last consonant of a word is typically not pronounced unless followed by a vowel. When a word ending in a consonant is followed by a word beginning with a vowel sound (or silent ''h''), the consonant often becomes pronounced. This is a process called ''liaison''.  When a vowel goes directly after ''un'', the normally unpronounced ''n'' sound becomes pronounced.

{| {{French/Table|audio=French/Grammar/Liaison with un.ogg|columns=4}}
| (un) ami
! un&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;ami
| {{French/Section|{{audio|Fr-ami.ogg|approx=uh&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;-nah-mee|/na.mi/}}}}
| {{French/Section|a (male) friend}}
|-
|(un) lve
! un&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;lve
| {{French/Section|{{audio|/ne.lv/|approx=uh&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;-nay-lehv}}}} || {{French/Section|a pupil}}
|}

Compare the pronunciation to words without liaison:
: {{French/Word|un garon|IPA=/ gas/|approx=uh&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt; gahr-soh&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;|audio=Fr-garon.ogg}}

''Une'' is unaffected by liaison.

Liaison also occurs with ''les'' and ''des''.

{| {{French/Table|audio=French/Grammar/Liaison with les and des.ogg|columns=4}}
| (les) amis
! les&lt;sub&gt;z&lt;/sub&gt;amis
| {{French/Section|{{audio|/leza.mi/|approx=lay-zhah-mee}}}} || {{French/Section|(some) (male) friends}}
|-
| (des) amis
! des&lt;sub&gt;z&lt;/sub&gt;amis
| {{French/Section|{{audio|/dza.mi/|approx=deh-zhah-mee}}}} || {{French/Section|(some) (male) friends}}
|-
| (des) amies
! des&lt;sub&gt;z&lt;/sub&gt;amies
| {{French/Section|{{audio|/dza.mi/|approx=deh-zhah-mee}}}} || {{French/Section|(some) (female) friends}}
|}

As with elision, an aspired ''h'' isn't liaised:
: ''(les) hangars'': {{French/Word|les hangars|IPA=le g}}

== {{French/Section|Vocabulary|People|Les personnes}} ==
{| {{French/Translations table|audio=French Vocabulary - People.ogg}}
| la personne || {{audio|Fr-personne.ogg|approx=lah pehr-sohn|/la p.sn/}} || person 
|-
! colspan=3 | Gender and age
|-
| l'homme {{French/Section|(m)}} || {{audio|Fr-homme.ogg|approx=lohm|/lm/}} || man
|-
| la femme || {{audio|Fr-femme.ogg|approx=lah fahm|/la fam/}} || woman
|-
| le garon || {{audio|Fr-garon.ogg|approx=luh gahr-soh&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;|/l ga.s/}} || boy
|-
| la fille || {{audio|Fr-fille.ogg|approx=lah fee-y&lt;sup&gt;uh&lt;/sup&gt;|/la fi.j/}} || girl
|-
| la fillette || {{audio|Fr-fillette.ogg|approx=lah fee-y&lt;sup&gt;uh&lt;/sup&gt;eht|/la fi.jt/}} || little girl
|-
! colspan=3 | Friends
|-
| l'ami {{French/Section|(m)}}&lt;br /&gt;le copain || {{audio|/la.mi/|approx=lah-mee}}&lt;br /&gt;{{audio|/l k.p/|approx=luh koh-pa&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;}} || male friend
|-
| l'amie {{French/Section|(f)}}&lt;br /&gt;la copine || {{audio|/la.mi/|approx=lah-mee}}&lt;br /&gt;{{audio|/la k.pin/|approx=lah koh-peen}} || female friend
|}

== {{French/Section|Vocabulary|Expressions}} ==

=== ''Quest-ce que cest ?'' ===
To say ''What is it?'' or ''What is that?'' in French, {{French/Word|Quest-ce que cest ?|IPA=/ks k s/|approx=kehs kuh seh}} is used. 

: {{French/Word|Qu'est-ce que?|en=What is it that ?}} is used often to say ''What?'' at the beginning  of sentences.

To respond to this question, you say ''Cest un(e) [''nom''].'', meaning ''It is a [''noun'']:
: {{French/Word|C'est un livre.|en=It's a book.}}

Remember that the indefinite article (''un'' or ''une'') must agree with the noun it modifies:
: {{French/Word|C'est un'''e''' chemise.|en=It's a shirt.}}

=== ''Il y a'' ===
{{French/Word|Il y a|IPA=/il.ja/|audio=Fr-il y a.ogg|approx=eel-y&lt;sup&gt;uh&lt;/sup&gt;ah when spoken or eel-ee-ah in lyric or poetry}} is used to say ''there is'' or ''there are''. ''Il y a'' expresses the existence of the noun it introduces.

: {{French/Word|Il y a une pomme.|en=There is an apple.}}

The phrase is used for both singular and plural nouns. Unlike in English (''is''  ''are''), ''il y a'' does not change form. 

: {{French/Word|Il y a des pommes.|en=There are (some) apples.}}

The ''-s'' at the end of the most pluralised nouns tells you that the phrase is ''there are'' instead of ''there is''. In spoken French, when both the singular and plural forms almost always sound the same, the article (and perhaps other adjectives modifying the noun) is used to distinguish between singular and plural versions. 

''A'' is the present third person singular form of the verb ''to have'', and ''y'' is a pronoun meaning ''there''. The phrase ''il y a'', then, literally translates to ''he has there''. This phrase is used in all French tenses. It is important to remember that verb stays as a form of ''have'' and not ''be''.

=== ''Voici'' and ''voil'' ===

Like in English, ''il y a'' is not often used to point out an object. To point out an object to the listener, use {{French/Word|voici|IPA=/vwa.si/|audio=Fr-voici.ogg|approx=vwah-see}}, meaning ''over here is/are'' or ''right here is/are'', and {{French/Word|voil|IPA=/vwa.la/|approx=vwah-lah}}, meaning ''over there is/are'', or ''there you have it''.

: {{French/Word|Voici les deux garons !|en=Here are the two boys!}}

=== Examples ===

{| {{French/Translations table|audio=French/Grammar/Examples of simple expressions.ogg}}
| C'est un chien. ||  || It's a dog.
|-
| Il y a un problme. ||  || There is a problem.
|-
| Il y a deux personnes ici. ||  || There are two people here.
|-
| Il y a deux tables dans le salon. ||  || There are two tables in the lounge.
|-
| Il ny a pas de chat. || || There is no cat.
|-
| il ny a pas que toi. || || You are not the only one.
|-
| Voici le fromage. ||  || Here's the cheese.
|}

== {{French/Section|Exercises}} ==

{{French/Exercise|Respond according to the pictures.|solution-audio=French/Exercise/Responses with c'est.ogg|
:: ''Quest-ce que cest?''
:: ''C'est .''
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Apple red delicius stalk.jpg|thumbnail|left|100px]]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:PearPhoto.jpg|thumbnail|left|70px]]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Satisfied cat.jpg|thumbnail|left|140px]]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Labrador jeune chienne assise.JPG|thumbnail|left|90px]] &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
|
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Apple red delicius stalk.jpg|thumbnail|left|100px|''C'est une pomme'']]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:PearPhoto.jpg|thumbnail|left|70px|''C'est une poire'']]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Satisfied cat.jpg|thumbnail|left|140px|''C'est un chat'']]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Labrador jeune chienne assise.JPG|thumbnail|left|90px|''C'est un chien'']] &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
}}
{{French/Exercise|Matching|
::Match each noun with its corresponding image.
: ''une colombe''
: ''des livres''
: ''une chemise''
: ''des chevaux''
: ''une maison''
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Shirt.jpg|110px]]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Go-home.svg|80px]]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Nuvola apps bookcase pastel.png|70px]]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Rock dove - natures pics.jpg|110px]] &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Nokota Horses cropped.jpg|110px]] &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
|
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[Image:Shirt.jpg|thumbnail|left|110px|''une chemise'']]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[Image:Go-home.svg|thumbnail|left|80px|''une maison'']]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[Image:Nuvola apps bookcase pastel.png|thumbnail|left|70px|''des livres'']]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[Image:Rock dove - natures pics.jpg|thumbnail|left|110px|''une colombe'']] &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[Image:Nokota Horses cropped.jpg|thumbnail|left|110px|''des chevaux'']] &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;}}

{{French/Exercise list
 | title = Translation
 | instructions = Translate each phrase from English to French
 | the boy | le garon
 | the female friend | l'amie, la copine
 | the man | l'homme
 | the little girl | la fillette
 | the woman | la femme
 | the person | la personne
 | the girl | la fille
 | the male friend | l'ami, le copain
}}

{{French/Exercise list
 | title = Translation
 | instructions = Translate each phrase from French to English
 | l'amie | the female friend
 | la fillette | the little girl
 | la personne | the person
 | la femme | the woman
 | l'ami | the male friend
 | la copine | the female friend
 | le garon | the boy
 | la fille | the girl
 | le copain | the male friend
 | l'homme | the man
}}

== {{French/Section|Exercises|supplementary-id=french-exercises}} ==
&lt;div id='french-exercises'&gt;
{{French/Exercise list
 | title = Gender
 | instructions = Classify each noun as masculine or feminine based on its ending.
 | rapidit | feminine
 | mutisme | masculine
 | rcration | feminine
 | bricolage | masculine
 | paille | feminine
 | dcoupage | masculine
 | grenouille | feminine
 | gallicisme | masculine
 | robinet | masculine
 | diffrence | feminine
 | rondelle | feminine
 | optimisme | masculine
 | question | feminine
 | modernisme | masculine
 | vaisselle | feminine
 | paysage | masculine
 | ambulance | feminine
 | originalit | feminine
 | famille | feminine
 | svrit | feminine
 | couronne | feminine
 | particularit | feminine
 | anarchisme | masculine
 | feuille | feminine
 | mobilit | feminine
 | tlvision | feminine
 | oreille | feminine
 | panne | feminine
 | frite | feminine
 | ordonnance | feminine
 | professionnalisme | masculine
 | sincrit | feminine
 | invitation | feminine
 | passage | masculine
 | abeille | feminine
 | rsolubilit | feminine
 | canne | feminine
 | attention | feminine
 | validit | feminine
 | bagage | masculine
 | coquillage | masculine
 | crativit | feminine
 | chance | feminine
 | monolinguisme | masculine
 | village | masculine
}}&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- /french-exercises --&gt;
&lt;noinclude&gt;{{French/Lessons/Level one||To be}}&lt;/noinclude&gt;</text>
      <sha1>o1mxjvccbk1lh791yvfssfgexpfv32v</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:Etothex</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>1425</id>
    <revision>
      <id>153541</id>
      <parentid>29973</parentid>
      <timestamp>2004-05-06T19:49:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Get-back-world-respect</username>
        <id>1073</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">To Etothex, Greetings.

In re the [[US History]] textbook: After Chapter 20 (&quot;Eisenhower, Civil Rights, and the Fifties,&quot;) I consider that further chapters need to be added. But the question is- where should the line be drawn? I think that we can have one Chapter on the Vietnam War and the Seventies, and another on Reagan, but that we should end there. Everything after that seems to be too recent to be included. What is your personal opinion, if I may ask? Thanking you, [[User:Lord Emsworth|Lord Emsworth]] 22:23, 4 Oct 2003 (UTC).

:Sure. I know lots of history books stop at Pres. Carter/Reagan because of several reasons, but maybe we could even get into the Clinton administration a bit. Definitely stop there, though. Current events haven't quite 'aged' enough yet. I just stopped at Eisenhower because I wasn't quite sure what to title them. I mean, I could say &quot;Chapter 21: The Vietnam War and the Sixties&quot;, but that suggests everything happened in the sixties and that's just not true. [[User:Etothex|Etothex]] 07:47, 5 Oct 2003 (UTC)

Hey :) Great start on [[Vectors]]! I'd just ask one thing, don't use &lt;math&gt;\cdot&lt;/math&gt; for multiplication, since that could conceivably be confused with the dot product later. Writing a product without the dot is still pretty clear :) Thanks [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 08:51, 9 Oct 2003 (UTC)

:Oh, sure. I'd written it when I was pretty sleepy and too lazy to look up the correct tex syntax for vectors, so I just wrote it out and didn't even think about dot product. :) I might add on trig later, if I feel like drawing some more diagrams. [[User:Etothex|Etothex]] 02:09, 11 Oct 2003 (UTC)

Just another point, you don't need to &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;math&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt; variables to get ''x''; you can just go &lt;nowiki&gt;''x''&lt;/nowiki&gt; - if you didn't know already :) [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 11:13, 14 Oct 2003 (UTC)
:Hmm, yeah. :) I did it because of the option in prefs for how to display tex syntax, as PNG or text. I've got a small monitor and even on 800x600(versus 1024x768) the text is small...So I kinda like it when I can turn on PNG when I need it. I don't know if anyone else uses this, but I find it convenient. I can switch back if it doesn't work, but otherwise, I'll just keep on doing it. [[User:Etothex|Etothex]] 23:36, 14 Oct 2003 (UTC)

:: Oh cool! I never really realized that you could do that; it's just easier when I type to just hit ' four times, I'm a lazy typist - I don't see any other real problem with it :) [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 03:21, 15 Oct 2003 (UTC)
==Vocabulary Project==
Hi Etothex, since you started the wikibook on German I thought you might be interested in a learnign project I am starting, especially for vocabulary. Please check my page and let me know what you think about it. [[User:Get-back-world-respect|Get-back-world-respect]] 19:49, 6 May 2004 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>lslnhlafvjjhw9mlhmf7ohdw9soupz0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>French/Lessons/Transportation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1426</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2587413</id>
      <parentid>2587410</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-12-04T16:38:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JackPotte</username>
        <id>99248</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* {{French/Section||To acquire|Acqurir}} */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;noinclude&gt;{{French/Lessons/Level two/Header||Le transport}}&lt;/noinclude&gt;
== {{French/Section|Dialogue|&lt;!-- title here --&gt;}} ==
{{sectstub}}

== {{French/Section|Culture|France's transportation system}} ==
{{sectstub}} &lt;!-- a one or two paragraph overview of transportation in France, with emphasis on material useful to foreigners --&gt;

== {{French/Section|Grammar|''-uire'' verbs}} ==
''-uire'' verbs are conjugated irregularly.

=== Formation ===
{| class=wikitable
!'''conduire {{fr/IPA|/k.di/ (''koh&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;-deweer'')|audio=Fr-conduire.ogg}} !! to drive'''
|-
|je conduis {{fr/IPA|/k.di/ (''koh&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;-dewee'')}} || I drive
|-
|tu conduis {{fr/IPA|/k.di/ (''koh&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;-dewee'')}} || you drive
|-
|il conduit {{fr/IPA|/k.di/ (''koh&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;-dewee'')}} || he drives
|-
|nous conduisons {{fr/IPA|/k.di.z/ (''koh&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;-dewee-zoh&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;'')}} || we drive
|-
|vous conduisez {{fr/IPA|/k.di.ze/ (''koh&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;-dewee-zay'')}} || you drive
|-
|ils conduisent {{fr/IPA|/k.diz/ (''koh&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;-deweez'')}} || they drive
|-
|conduit {{fr/IPA|/k.di/ (''koh&lt;sup&gt;(n)&lt;/sup&gt;-dewee'')}} || driven
|}

=== {{French/Section|Vocabulary|Other ''-uire'' verbs|supplementary-id=french--uire-verbs}} ===
&lt;div id='french--uire-verbs'&gt;
{| {{French/Translations table|audio=French/Grammar/-uire verbs.ogg}}
| produire || {{audio|Fr-produire.ogg|/p.di/}} || to produce ||  || &lt;!-- sample French sentence here --&gt; || &lt;!-- English sentence --&gt;
|-
| traduire || {{audio|Fr-traduire.ogg|/ta.di/}} || to translate ||  || &lt;!-- sample French sentence here --&gt; || &lt;!-- English sentence --&gt;
|-
| rduire || {{audio|Fr-rduire.ogg|/edi/}} || to reduce ||  || &lt;!-- sample French sentence here --&gt; || &lt;!-- English sentence --&gt;
|-
| rduire  ||  || to reduce {{French/Section|(someone)}} to ||  || Je l'ai rduit  l'obissance. || I reduced him to slavery.
|-
| rduire en ||  || to reduce {{French/Section|(something)}} to ||  || Il l'a rduit en cendres. || He reduced it to ashes.
|}&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- /french--uire-verbs --&gt;

=== Examples ===
{{sectstub}} &lt;!-- example sentences with conduire, produire, traduire, reduire, and other -uire verbs --&gt;

{| {{French/Translations table|audio=French/Grammar/Examples with -uire verbs}}
| Il conduit la voiture. ||  || He is driving the car.
|}

== {{French/Section|Vocabulary|Driving}} ==
{{sectstub}}

{| {{French/Translations table|audio=French/Vocabulary/Driving.ogg}}
| ouvrir ||  || to open ||  || &lt;!-- sample French sentence --&gt; || &lt;!-- English sentence --&gt;
|-
| fermer ||  || to close ||  || &lt;!-- sample French sentence --&gt; || &lt;!-- English sentence --&gt;
|}

== {{French/Section|Grammar|''Pass compos'' with ''tre''}} ==

Most verbs form the ''pass compos'' with ''avoir'', however there are a small number of verbs that are always conjugated with ''tre''.  In a general case, these verbs indicate a change in state or position.  

=== List of verbs ===

{| {{French/Translations table|audio=French/Grammar/Perfect oast with tre verbs.ogg}}
| aller ||  ||  ||  || Je suis all au cinma. || I went to the cinema.
|-
| venir ||  ||  ||  || Je suis venu en France. || I came to France.
|-
| arriver ||  ||  ||  || Le train est arriv. || The train has arrived.
|-
| partir ||  ||  ||  || Elle est partie travailler. || She left to go to work.
|-
| rester ||  ||  ||  || Je suis rest  la maison. || I stayed (at) home.
|-
| retourner ||  ||  ||  || Il est retourn au restaurant. || He returned to the restaurant.
|-
| tomber ||  ||  ||  || Je suis tomb dans la piscine. || I fell into the pool.
|-
| natre ||  ||  ||  || Je suis n en octobre. || I was born in October.
|-
| mourir ||  ||  ||  || Il est mort en 1917. || He died in 1917.
|-
| passer ||  ||  ||  || Il est pass devant la maison. || He went past in front of the house.
|-
| monter ||  ||  ||  || Je suis mont au sommet. || I climbed to the top.
|-
| descendre ||  ||  ||  || Il est descendu du train. || He got out of the train.
|-
| sortir ||  ||  ||  || Je suis sorti avec mes amies. || I went out with my friends.
|-
| entrer ||  ||  ||  || Je suis entr dans ma chambre. || I entered my room.
|-
| rentrer ||  ||  ||  || Il est rentr tt de l'cole. || He came back early from school.
|}

The verbs that take tre can be easily remembered by the acronym ''MRS. DR VANDERTRAMP'':

{| {{French/Table|columns=11}}
! M||R||S||  ||D||R|| || || || || 
|-
| mont||rest||sorti||  ||devenu||revenu|| || || || || 
|-
! V||A||N||D||E||R||T||R||A||M||P
|-
| venu||arriv||n||descendu||entr||rentr||tomb||retourn||all||mort||parti
|}

=== Direct objects ===

These verbs take their conjugated ''avoir'' when they are immediately followed by a direct object

For Example,
: ''Je '''suis''' descendu.''
with the direct object ''mes bagages'' becomes
: ''J''''ai''' descendu mes bagages.''

As another example,
: ''Je '''suis''' mont.''
with the direct object ''mes bagages'' becomes
: ''J''''ai''' mont mes bagages.''

As another example, but with ''ils'' instead of ''je'',
: ''Ils '''sont''' sortis.''
with direct object ''leur passeport'' becomes
: ''Ils '''ont''' sorti leur passeport.''

=== Subject-past participle agreement===
When conjugating with ''tre'', the past participles of the above verbs must agree with the subject of a sentence in gender and plurality. Note that there is no agreement if these verbs are conjugated with ''avoir''.

* If the subject is masculine singular, there is no change in the past participle.
* If the subject is feminine singular, an ''-e'' is added to the past participle.
* If the subject is masculine plural, an ''-s'' is added to the past participle.
* If the subject is feminine plural, an ''-es'' is added to the past participle.

{| {{French/Table|columns=2}}
| J suis all'''(e)'''. || Nous sommes all'''(e)s'''.
|-
| Tu es all'''(e)'''. || Vous tes all'''(e)(s)'''.
|-
| Il est all. || Ils sont all'''s'''.
|-
| Elle est all'''e'''. || Elles sont all'''es'''.
|}

== {{French/Section|Vocabulary|Trains and stations}} ==
{{sectstub}}

== {{French/Section|Grammar|The pronoun ''y''}} ==

=== Indirect object pronoun - ''to it, to them'' ===
The French pronoun ''y'' is used to replace an object of a prepositional phrase introduced by .
*Je rponds aux ( les) questions. - J'y rponds.
*I respond to the questions. - I respond to them.
Note that ''lui'' and ''leur'', and not ''y'', are used when the object refers to a person or persons.

=== Replacement of places - ''there'' ===
The French pronoun ''y'' replaces a prepositional phrase referring to a place that begins with any preposition except ''de'' (for which ''en'' is used).
*Les hommes vont en France. - Les hommes y vont.
*The men go to France - The men go there.
Note that ''en'', and not ''y'' is used when the preposition of the object is ''de''.

=== Idioms ===
* ''a y est!'' - ''There we go!'', ''There you have it.''
* ''J'y suis!'' - ''I get it!''

== {{French/Section|Vocabulary|Taking a taxi}} ==
{{sectstub}}

== {{French/Section|Grammar|''-rir'' verbs|supplementary-id=french--rir-verbs}} ==
&lt;div id='french--rir-verbs'&gt;
These verbs are conjugated irregularly, and normally follow the ''-er'' conjugation scheme. In past participle form, ''-ir'' is replaced with ''-ert'' for these verbs.

=== Formation ===
A common ''-rir'' verb is ''ouvrir'':

{| class=wikitable
!'''ouvrir {{fr/IPA|/u.vi/|audio=Fr-ouvrir.ogg}} !! to open'''
|-
|j'ouvre {{fr/IPA|/uv/}} || I open
|-
|tu ouvres {{fr/IPA|/uv/}} || you open
|-
|il ouvre {{fr/IPA|/uv/}} || he opens
|-
|nous ouvrons {{fr/IPA|/u.v/}} || we open
|-
|vous ouvrez {{fr/IPA|/u.ve/}} || you open
|-
|ils ouvrent {{fr/IPA|/uv/}} || they open
|-
|ouvert {{fr/IPA|/u.v/|audio=Fr-ouvert.ogg}} || opened
|}

The adjective {{French/Word|ouverture|en=opening|IPA=/u.v.ty/|audio=Fr-ouverture.ogg}} is derived from ''ouvrir'', and the adjective {{French/Word|ouvert|en=open|IPA=/u.v/|audio=Fr-ouvert.ogg}} is derived from its past participle.

=== Other standard ''-rir'' verbs===

{| {{French/Translations table|audio=French/Grammar/-rir verbs.ogg}}
| couvrir || {{audio|Fr-couvrir.ogg|/kuvi/}} || to cover, to cover up
|-
| dcouvrir || {{audio|Fr-dcouvrir.ogg|/de.ku.vi/}} || to discover 
|-
| offrir || {{audio|Fr-offrir.ogg|/.fi/}} || to offer
|-
| recouvrir || {{audio|Fr-recouvrir.ogg}} || to cover again
|-
| rouvrir || {{audio|Fr-rouvrir.ogg}} || to reopen, to open again
|-
| souffrir || {{audio|Fr-souffrir.ogg|/sufi/}} || to suffer, to endure
|}

=== ''-rir'' verb exceptions===

==== {{French/Section||To run|Courir}} ====

{| class=wikitable
!'''courir {{fr/IPA|/ku.i/|audio=Fr-courir.ogg}} !! to run'''
|-
|je cours {{fr/IPA|/ku/|audio=Fr-cours.ogg}} || I run
|-
|tu cours {{fr/IPA|/ku/|audio=Fr-cours.ogg}} || you run
|-
|il court {{fr/IPA|/ku/|audio=Fr-court.ogg}} || he runs
|-
|nous courons {{fr/IPA|/ku./|audio=Fr-courons.ogg}} || we run
|-
|vous courez {{fr/IPA|/ku.e/|audio=Fr-courez.ogg}} || you run
|-
|ils courent {{fr/IPA|/ku/|audio=Fr-courent.ogg}} || they run
|-
|couru {{fr/IPA|/ku.y/|audio=Fr-couru.ogg}} || run
|}

==== {{French/Section||To die|Mourir}} ====
{| class=wikitable
!'''mourir {{fr/IPA|/mu.i/|audio=Fr-mourir.ogg}} !! to die'''
|-
|je meurs {{fr/IPA|/ku/|audio=Fr-meurs.ogg}} || I die
|-
|tu meurs {{fr/IPA|/ku/|audio=Fr-meurs.ogg}} || you die
|-
|il meurt {{fr/IPA|/ku/|audio=Fr-meurt.ogg}} || he dies
|-
|nous mourons {{fr/IPA|/ku./|audio=Fr-mourons.ogg}} || we die
|-
|vous mourez {{fr/IPA|/ku.e/|audio=Fr-mourez.ogg}} || you die
|-
|ils meurent {{fr/IPA|/ku/|audio=Fr-meurent.ogg}} || they die
|-
|mort {{fr/IPA|/m/|audio=Fr-mort.ogg}} || died
|}

&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;''Mourir'' is the only ''-ir'' verb that takes ''tre'' as its helping verb in perfect tenses (and therefore agrees with the subject as a past participle in a perfect tense).

The word {{French/Word|mort|IPA=/m/|audio=Fr-mort.ogg}} is also used as a noun, meaning ''death'' or ''dead person'', or as an adjective, meaning ''dead'':
: ''Le roi est mort.'' - ''The king is dead.''

The derived word {{French/Word|mourant|IPA=/mu./}} means ''dying'' or ''person who is dying''.

==== {{French/Section||To acquire|Acqurir}} ====
{| class=wikitable
!'''acqurir {{fr/IPA|/a.ke.i/|audio=Fr-acqurir.ogg}} !! to acquire'''
|-
|j'acquiers {{fr/IPA|/a.kj/|audio=Fr-meurs.ogg}} || I acquire
|-
|tu acquiers {{fr/IPA|/a.kj/|audio=Fr-meurs.ogg}} || you acquire
|-
|il acquiert {{fr/IPA|/a.kj/|audio=Fr-meurt.ogg}} || he acquires
|-
|nous acqurons {{fr/IPA|/a.ke./|audio=Fr-mourons.ogg}} || we acquire
|-
|vous acqurez {{fr/IPA|/a.ke.e/|audio=Fr-mourez.ogg}} || you acquire
|-
|ils acquirent {{fr/IPA|/a.kj/|audio=Fr-meurent.ogg}} || they acquire
|-
|acquis {{fr/IPA|/a.ki/|audio=Fr-mort.ogg}} || acquired
|}

''Acquis'' is also a noun, meaning ''asset''.

=== Examples ===
{{sectstub}} &lt;!-- example sentences with any -rir verbs --&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- /french--rir-verbs --&gt;

== {{French/Section|Text|&lt;!-- title here --&gt;}} ==
{{sectstub}}

== {{French/Section|Exercises}} ==
{{sectstub}}
&lt;noinclude&gt;{{French/Lessons/Level two|Going out|Everyday life}}&lt;/noinclude&gt;</text>
      <sha1>0r5dn9aaurcy1byfu6vmejwayywynww</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>