<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>File:Boatconformation.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>891</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748856</id>
      <parentid>746293</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-02-09T19:55:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>lftdbfdb9bftwmpa42ewbdhqaw7jksr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Computer Programming/Linux Programming</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>898</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2681114</id>
      <parentid>1798025</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-07-14T11:03:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==About the platform==

The '''GNU''' operating system was started by Richard Stallman as a free replacement for the UNIX operating system. At the same time Linus Torvalds was working on a kernel, which he adapted to fit the GNU operating system. As time progressed, many applications from UNIX and DOS were ported to GNU/Linux as well as the thousands of new applications written for it.  GNU/Linux has become a completely self-sufficient operating system with applications ranging from the many console applications to the numerous highly advanced GUI applications (many of which are based on lower level console applications) and everything else in between.

The most popular languages for use on the GNU/Linux platform include [[C Programming|C]]/[[C++ Programming|C++]] and [[Programming:Java|Java]], however the range of programming languages supported by the GNU/Linux platform cover the entire spectrum of the software development world. Other popular languages are [[Perl|Perl]], [[Python Programming|Python]] and [[Ruby Programming|Ruby]]. Shell scripting is often used for administrative tasks but cannot be called a complete high level language.

==Basic information==

Most UNIX code is instantly portable to GNU/Linux systems - it can be compiled as on a UNIX system.  GNU/Linux programming tools are mostly from the GNU project at http://www.gnu.org, including gcc (free C/C++ compiler), and equivalents of make, ld, as, etc.  Numerous others are available for various languages, including java. 


== Further reading ==


* [http://www.dwheeler.com/secure-programs/ &quot;Secure Programming for Linux and Unix HOWTO -- Creating Secure Software&quot;] by David A. Wheeler 2003

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>f458xhbgl0h80qsrc5tlacak9pfkz3a</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Spanish/Exercises/Stem Changing Verbs</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>899</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2702624</id>
      <parentid>2702622</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-09-22T17:41:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>69.196.73.194</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Fill in the blank */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Spanish/Lesson 4| ^Lesson 4^]]
----
&lt;!---Do not fill in the blanks!  This is supposed to be an exercise for the reader.  It should be printed out and filled in, or pasted into a text editor. --&gt;
=== Fill in the blank ===
&lt;!---Do not fill in the blanks!  This is supposed to be an exercise for the reader.  It should be printed out and filled in, or pasted into a text editor. --&gt;
Don't fill in the blank with the wrong form of the verb: 

&lt;!---Do not fill in the blanks!  This is supposed to be an exercise for the reader.  It should be printed out and filled in, or pasted into a text editor. --&gt;
1. Yo _____cierro_______________ (cerrar) la puerta. ''I close the door.''

&lt;!---Do not fill in the blanks!  This is supposed to be an exercise for the reader.  It should be printed out and filled in, or pasted into a text editor. --&gt;
2. Tú ___________pierdas____________ (perder) tus llaves. ''You lost your keys.''

&lt;!---Do not fill in the blanks!  This is supposed to be an exercise for the reader.  It should be printed out and filled in, or pasted into a text editor. --&gt;
3. ¿____________prefieres_____________(preferir) usted la langosta? ''Do you prefer lobster?''

4. Nosotros __________entiendemos_____________ (entender) los ejercicios. ''We understand the exercises.''

5. Felipe y Juan ___________empiezan___________(empezar) las prácticas de gramática. ''Felipe and Juan begin the grammar practices.''

6. Ellos _________quieran___________ (querer) almorzar. ''They want to eat us.''

7. La chica _________pierde____________ (perder) su pañuelo. ''The girl loses her ______.''

8. ¿Qué _____________piensa_________ (pensar)? ''What do you -singular- think?''

9. Sofía ___________entienda____________ (entender) a Julio. ''Sofía understands Julio.'' 

10. Yo no ___________quiero___________ (querer) la ensalada. ''I don't want the salad''
----
'''Bonus:''' Argentinian voseo

2. Vos ___________pierdan__________ (perder) tus llaves. ''You lose your keys.''

8. ¿Qué ___________piensas___________ (pensar)? ''What do you -singular- think?''
----
[[Spanish/Exercises/Stem Changing Verbs - Solutions|Soluciones a los ejercicios]] ''Solutions to the exercises''

[[Spanish/Lesson 4| ^Lesson 4^]]

[[Category:Spanish]]</text>
      <sha1>4o9qixg3vrkv6jtddchmczpb1f5g8h0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:Mic</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>900</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1748985</id>
      <parentid>196124</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-04-01T20:19:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>can't redirect between wikis</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[w:en:User:Mic]]</text>
      <sha1>sav5c50ud8tkhqgt871i78ivnrbhzmn</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Biochemistry metabolism 1.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>901</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2366334</id>
      <parentid>882030</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-19T22:17:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Replacing links, replaced: {{CC-self}} → {{self|cc-by-sa-2.5}} using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Metabolism overview (PNG format)

This image is based on [[media:Biochemistry_metabolism_1.svg|this SVG file]]

{{self|cc-by-sa-2.5}}
{{GFDL-self}}</text>
      <sha1>1vnrdy81znv6nbtzcke2azf1ygz52wo</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Biochemistry/Metabolism and energy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>902</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2704580</id>
      <parentid>2444535</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-09-27T14:24:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>202.67.41.51</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Hydrogen bonds */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Biochemistry]] 

[[Biochemistry/Catalysis|&lt;&lt; Catalysis]] | [[Biochemistry/pKa values|pKa values &gt;&gt;]]
----
== Metabolism ==
=== Anabolism and catabolism ===
Metabolism (Fig. 1) is, broadly speaking, the conversion of food into energy, cell components, and waste products.

[[image:biochemistry_metabolism_1.png]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 1''': Overview of metabolism

The above diagram shows the different parts of metabolism:
* ''energy source'', which is, after all, the sun, whose energy is harvested through photosynthesis
* ''catabolism'', the breakdown of food into chemical energy, which is needed in
* ''anabolism'', the construction of complex cell molecules from small environmental molecules, utilizing chemical energy
Catabolic reactions release energy and are therefore &lt;tt&gt;exergonic&lt;/tt&gt;, while anabolic reactions use up energy and are therefore &lt;tt&gt;endergonic&lt;/tt&gt;.

=== High-energy phosphates ===
Due to the large variety of food compounds, and the large number of biochemical reactions which need energy in anabolism, it would be quite inefficient to couple a specific anabolic reaction to a specific energy source in catabolism. Instead, the cell uses an intermediate compound, a kind of universal energy currency. This intermediate is called ''high-energy phosphate''.

But when is a phosphate group called &quot;high-energy&quot;, and how does it differ from a &quot;low-energy&quot; phosphate? A giveaway is the &amp;Delta;G&lt;sup&gt;0'&lt;/sup&gt; of hydrolysis. Hydrolysis separates a phosphate from a compound by adding water:
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; O &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; O
 R-OP-OH + H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O &amp;#8652; R-OH + HO-P-OH
 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; O &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; O

The &amp;Delta;G&lt;sup&gt;0'&lt;/sup&gt; of a low-energy (or &quot;inorganic&quot;) phosphate group (called P&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;) is 9-20 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, while the &amp;Delta;G&lt;sup&gt;0'&lt;/sup&gt; of a high-energy phosphate (denoted &amp;#9413;) is ~30 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;.

=== pKa value ===
Now what makes this &amp;#9413; so special? To explain this, we must take a little excourse into pH and pKa values. A phosphate group has between zero and three &lt;tt&gt;OH&lt;/tt&gt; groups. This allows &amp;#9413; to exist in up to four different forms (0, 1, 2, and 3 &lt;tt&gt;OH&lt;/tt&gt; groups, Fig. 2), depending on the pH value of the surrounding solution. A pKa value gives us the pH value at which 50% of the molecules are in one form (e.g., 1 &lt;tt&gt;OH&lt;/tt&gt; group) and another (e.g., 2 &lt;tt&gt;OH&lt;/tt&gt; groups). This is expressed by the ''Henderson-Hasselbalch equation'' :

:&lt;math&gt;{pH} = {pK}_{a} + log{[base] \over [acid]}&lt;/math&gt;

[[image:biochemistry_metabolism_2.png]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 2''': The four possible forms of a phosphate group. pK&lt;sub&gt;a2&lt;/sub&gt; represents the conditions in the cell.

Now to the promised difference between &amp;#9413; and PP&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;. The breaking of the ester bond of an RO&amp;#9413; releases more energy than the breaking of a PP&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; bond (Fig. 3), because of
# ''electrostatic repulsion'' between the two phosphate groups in PP&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;
# ''resonance stabilization'' of two P&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; groups, compared to PP&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; (Fig. 4)

[[image:biochemistry_metabolism_3.png]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 3''': Hydrolysis of &amp;#9413; and PP&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;.

[[image:biochemistry_metabolism_4.png]]&lt;br&gt;
'''Figure 4''': Resonance stabilization of P&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;.

Resonance stabilization means that both &lt;tt&gt;OH&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt&gt;=O&lt;/tt&gt; can &quot;travel&quot; around the phosphate. Of course, this is a crude analogy; they do not really move, the electrons are just &quot;smeared&quot; around the phosphate atom. This is also indicated by the use of the &amp;#8596; arrow, instead of &amp;#8652;; the three forms &lt;u&gt;do not exist&lt;/u&gt;, they are just a way of writing down the chemical reality.

As you can see in Fig. 3, the &amp;Delta;G&lt;sup&gt;0'&lt;/sup&gt; value for PP&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;#8652;2P&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; is &amp;#8810;0, shifting the reaction strongly in favor of the 2P&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;.

== Molecules using high-energy phosphates ==

=== Anhydride between phosphoric acid and carboxyl group ===
Hydrolysis : &amp;Delta;G&lt;sup&gt;0'&lt;/sup&gt; = -49.3 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br&gt;
[[image:biochemistry_metabolism_5a.png]]

=== Guanidine phosphate ===
Hydrolysis : &amp;Delta;G&lt;sup&gt;0'&lt;/sup&gt; = -43.0 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br&gt;
[[image:biochemistry_metabolism_5b.png]]

=== Enol phosphate ===
For example, this picture is wrong, the carbon has 5 bonds to it after it tautomerizes, which is impossible and a rookie organic chemistry error. please fix phosphoenolpyruvate&lt;br&gt;
Hydrolysis : &amp;Delta;G&lt;sup&gt;0'&lt;/sup&gt; = -61.9 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br&gt;
[[image:biochemistry_metabolism_5c.png]]

=== ATP ===
Adenosine triphosphate contains one low-energy and two high-energy phosphate bonds:&lt;br&gt;
[[image:biochemistry_metabolism_5d.png]]&lt;br&gt;
Low energy : &amp;Delta;G&lt;sup&gt;0'&lt;/sup&gt; = -14,2 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br&gt;
High energy : &amp;Delta;G&lt;sup&gt;0'&lt;/sup&gt; = -30.5 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br&gt;

*ATP is regenerated from ADP (adenosine diphosphate), P&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; and energy (from food); H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O is released in the process.
*ATP is the short-term energy &quot;currency&quot; of the cell.
*ATP concentration in the cell is low (ATP: 2-8mM; ADP:0,2-0,8mM). ATP is generated in high &quot;turn over&quot;.
*ATP performs its chemical work through ''coupled reactions''.
*Coupled reactions are always &amp;#9413; ''transfers'', never direct hydrolysis

Basically, any ATP-driven reaction is reversible, building ATP from ADP and P&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; in the process. However, some ATP-driven reactions should never be reversed; these include nucleotide and protein synthesis. If these were reversed, the organism would disassemble its own DNA and proteins for energy, a rather unfortunate strategy. For reactions that should never be reversed, ATP can be broken down into AMP (adenosine monophosphate) and PP&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;, which in turn becomes 2&amp;times;P&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;. This reaction has a &amp;Delta;G&lt;sup&gt;0'&lt;/sup&gt; of -65,7 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, which is totally irreversible under ''in vivo'' conditions.

It should be noted that AMP can not directly be converted to ATP again. Instead, the enzyme ''AMP kinase'' forms two ADP molecules from one ATP and one AMP. The resulting ADPs are then treated as described above.

== Non-covalent bonds ==
The destruction of covalent bonds takes up huge amounts of energy. The breakdown of an O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; molecule into two oxygen atoms needs ~460 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. Thus, nowhere in &quot;living&quot; biochemistry are covalent bonds actually destroyed; if one is broken, another one is created. This is where non-covalent bonds come in, they are weak enough to be broken down easily, and to form &quot;bonds&quot; again.  For this reason, many biochemical functions are using so-called weak/secondary/non-covalent bonds.

Weak bonds are created and destroyed much more easily than covalent ones. The typical range of energy needed to destroy such a weak bond is 4-30 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. Thus, the formation of weak bonds is energetically favorable, but these bonds are also easily broken by kinetic (thermal) energy (the normal movement of molecules). Biochemical interactions are often temporary (e.g., a substrate has to leave an enzyme quickly after being processed), for which the weakness of these bonds is essential. Also, biochemical specificity (e.g., enzyme-substrate-recognition) is achieved through weak bonds, utilizing two of their major properties:
* Since individual weak bonds are, well, weak, several of them have to occur in a specific pattern at the same time in roughly the same place.
* The short range of weak bonds.

The link that follows demonstrates the type of non-covalent forces: [http://www.pearsonhighered.com/mathews/ch02/fi2p2.htm]
There are three basic types of weak bonds, and a fourth &quot;pseudo-bond&quot;:


=== Ionic bonds ===
Ionic bonds are electrostatic attractions between permanently charged groups. Ionic bonds are not directed. Example:
:X-CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup&gt;.....&lt;/sup&gt; H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;N-Y
::~ 20 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;

=== Hydrogen bonds ===
Hydrogen bonds are also established by electrostatic attraction. These attractions do not occur between permanently charged groups, but rather between atoms temporarily charged by a ''dipole moment'', resulting from the different [[electronegativity]] of atoms within a group. Hydrogen bonds are even weaker than ionic bonds, and they are highly directional, usually along a straight line. Besides being weaker than ionic bonds, hydrogen bonds are also weaker, and longer than similar covalent bonds.
Hydrogen bonds are unique because they only exist when the Hydrogen is bonded to an oxygen (O), Nitrogen (N), or Fluorine (F), but the most common hydrogen bonds in biochemistry are:
:X-OH &lt;sup&gt;.....&lt;/sup&gt; O-Y
:X-OH &lt;sup&gt;.....&lt;/sup&gt; N-Y
:X-NH &lt;sup&gt;.....&lt;/sup&gt; O-Y
:X-NH &lt;sup&gt;.....&lt;/sup&gt; N-Y
Hydrogen bonds equal an energy between 12-29 kJ mol, whereas covalent bonds are much higher. For example, the covalent bond between oxygen and hydrogen is about 492 KJ mol-1&lt;/sup&gt;.

==''Hydrogen Bonds and Water''==
Water has unique properties, after all, it is chosen to be the universal solvent. The unique properties of water are due to hydrogen bonding between all the oxygens and hydrogens of the content. The hydrogen bonds occurring in water are about 2 angstroms apart from each other. Although hydrogen bonding is only about 5% as strong as covalent bond, they still cause water to have a high boiling point, and a high surface tension. The following link will take you to the structure of water and its Hydrogen Bonding: [[http://users.rcn.com/jkimball.ma.ultranet/BiologyPages/H/Hbonds_water.gif]]

=== Van der Waals attractions ===
{{subject|{{subject|Biochemistry/Metabolism_and_energy}}{{subject|#REDIRECT [[Biochemistry/Metabolism_and_energy]]#REDIRECT [[#REDIRECT [[Insert text]]#REDIRECT [[--[[Special:Contributions/218.19.141.18|218.19.141.18]] ([[User talk:218.19.141.18|talk]]) 07:14, 19 April 2009 (UTC)Insert text&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;math&gt;Insert non-formatted text here&lt;/math&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;]]]]}}}}
Van der Waals attractions are established between electron density-induced dipoles. They form when the outer electron shells of two atoms ''almost'' (but not quite) touch. The distance of the atoms is very important for these weak interactions. If the atoms are too far apart, the interactions are too weak to establish; if the atoms are too close to each other, their electron shells will repel each other. Van der Waals attractions are highly unspecific; they can occur between virtually any two atoms. Their energy is between 4-8 kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;.
[[File:&lt;nowiki&gt;Example.jpg&lt;/nowiki&gt;{{subject|&lt;s&gt;Biochemistry/Metabolism_and_energy&lt;/s&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;Subscript text&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;}}]]

=== Hydrophobic forces ===
Hydrophobic forces are not actually bonds, so this list has four items, but still just three bond types. In a way hydrophobic forces are the negation of the hydrogen bonds of a polar solute, usually water, enclosing a nonpolar molecule. For a polar solute like water, it is energetically unfavorable to &quot;waste&quot; a possible hydrogen bond by exposing it towards a nonpolar molecule. Thus, water will arrange itself around any nonpolar molecule in such a way that no hydrogen bonds point towards that molecule. This results in a higher order, compared to &quot;freely&quot; moving water, which leads to a lower entropy level and is thus energetically unfavorable. If there is more than one nonpolar molecule in the solute, it is favorable for the nonpolar molecules to aggregate in one place, reducing their surrounding, ordered &quot;shell&quot; of water to a minimal surface. Also, in large molecules, such as proteins, the hydrophobic (nonpolar) parts of the molecule will tend to turn towards the inside, while the polar parts will tend to turn towards the surface of the molecule.

=== References===
Cooke, Rosa-lee. ''Properties of Water''. Lecture 10. Mountain Empire Community College. n.d. Web. http://water.me.vccs.edu/courses/env211/lesson10_print.htm

Kimball, John W.. ''Hydrogen Bonds''. Kimball’s Biology Pages. Feb. 12, 2011. Web. http://users.rcn.com/jkimball.ma.ultranet/BiologyPages/H/Hbonds_water.gif

Lower, Stephen. ''States of matter: Water and hydrogen bonding''. General Chemistry Virtual Textbooks. 2009. Aug. 26, 2010. Web. 
http://www.chem1.com/acad/webtext/states/water.html

n.p. ''Covalent vs. Non-Covalent Bonds''. n.d. http://www.pearsonhighered.com/mathews/ch02/c02cv.htm

W. W. Norton &amp; Company. ''Hydrogen Bonding in Water''. Web. 2012.  http://www.wwnorton.com/college/chemistry/gilbert2/tutorials/chapter_10/water_h_bond/

WyzAnt Tutoring. ''WyzAnt Tutoring''. Bonds. 2012. Web. http://www.wyzant.com/Help/Science/Chemistry/Bonds/
----
[[Biochemistry/Catalysis|&lt;&lt; Catalysis]] | [[Biochemistry/pKa values|pKa values &gt;&gt;]]

[[Biochemistry]]
[[Category:Biochemistry]]</text>
      <sha1>ry3ukrf625lodqtyy8iq0gz4mb6entj</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Biochemistry metabolism 2.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>904</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2366335</id>
      <parentid>882031</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-19T22:17:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Replacing links, replaced: {{CC-self}} → {{self|cc-by-sa-2.5}} using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Figure 2: The four possible forms of a phosphate group

This image is based on [[media:Biochemistry_metabolism_2.svg|this SVG file]]

{{self|cc-by-sa-2.5}}
{{GFDL-self}}</text>
      <sha1>pdtqi4g44ofn1xz6qllenjz253izjbm</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Biochemistry metabolism 3.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>905</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2366336</id>
      <parentid>882033</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-19T22:17:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Replacing links, replaced: {{CC-self}} → {{self|cc-by-sa-2.5}} using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Figure 3: Hydrolysis of Ⓟ and PP&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;

This image is based on [[media:Biochemistry_metabolism_2.svg|this SVG file]]

{{self|cc-by-sa-2.5}}
{{GFDL-self}}</text>
      <sha1>tjg7xeebbrmf9niembhqesk8ozkoc17</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Biochemistry metabolism 4.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>906</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2366337</id>
      <parentid>882034</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-19T22:17:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Replacing links, replaced: {{CC-self}} → {{self|cc-by-sa-2.5}} using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Figure 4: Resonance stabilization of P&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;

This image is based on [[media:Biochemistry_metabolism_2.svg|this SVG file]]

{{self|cc-by-sa-2.5}}
{{GFDL-self}}</text>
      <sha1>pwirpg8midviojm9ct32key39px3glz</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:81.249.66.2</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>908</id>
    <revision>
      <id>153043</id>
      <timestamp>2003-08-30T23:10:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Maveric149</username>
        <id>7</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[FrWikipedia:mathématiques]] is pretty neat. Is that new? It would make more sense if fr: could be reserved for magic intra-project links instead of always pointing to different Wikipedia versions. This would solve some very important technical problems for non-Wikipedia projects. A shorthand would be nice though; FrWP: would work. --[[User:Maveric149|mav]]</text>
      <sha1>5w9ggbwdn2rdychgzmtjscbo5c0cxr7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Calculus/Limits/An Introduction to Limits</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>909</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2070206</id>
      <parentid>1875739</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-03-16T13:15:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Greenbreen</username>
        <id>436161</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Answered question</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Requests==
While it's asked how | lim [x -&gt; 0]{sin(x)/x} = 1 | can be proven, this isn't demonstrated - there also isn't an actual demonstration elsewhere online, nearly as I can determine. Shouldn't one be put in? --[[User:68.212.77.222|68.212.77.222]] 23:05, 26 Apr 2005 (UTC)

Is there anyone interested in writing [[en:How to evaluate the limit of a real-valued funtion ]]?  --wshun

I think we should put the formal definition of the limit right at the end of page. As it is the most difficult concept to full grasp. And we need some excercises.

The last example seems to imply that f(x) = (x^2 - 9)/(x - 3) is not the same as g(x) = x + 3.  Why is this true?

Because you can't divide by zero; g(3) = 3 + 3 = 6, whereas f(3) = (3^2-9)/(3-3) = (0/0) = undefined.  The functions will, however, be equal at all other points.  (yes I edited your question to make my answer easier to articulate.  :) ) 

BTW, I would consider completely deleting the introduction.  It makes some questionable statements, and I can't see it as being anything but confusion for someone who doesn't know anything about limits already.  --Xhad


Am I the only one that thinks that this whole thing is worthless without the Cauchy definition of a limit? You cannot proove any of the statements unless you define limits properly. The best way to define them is the Cauchy definition!!

==arbitrary break==
(x^2-9)/(x-3) has the problem of a loss of information as x approaches 3.  The solution to this is rearranging the problem so that you are no longer dealing with having a small number on the denominator.  This is the realm of computational mathematics, though, and I'm not sure if it's useful to put in a Calculus textbook.  --Ronald Raygun

To me that sounds like something that would be appropriate for a Calc primer for physicists, but it seems beyond the scope of a typical Calculus course. --Xhad

It would be neat if someone would implement a parser that would feed this latex math notation to a graphing program... easy visualisation on the click of a function. -- [[User:Kowey|Kowey]] 09:03, 4 Oct 2004 (UTC)


Can any-one tell me that if we are taking x-&gt;0  and f(x)-&gt;L//then why are puting there an = in the answer when it should be ~(approximate value) --221.135.232.166 10:19, 27 June 2007

To answer the above question, it is because of the definition of a limit.  Although we think of &lt;math&gt; \lim_{x \to c} f(x)&lt;/math&gt; intuitively by the process of taking values of &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt; closer and closer to &lt;math&gt;a&lt;/math&gt;, the limit is not formally related to the value of &lt;math&gt;f(x)&lt;/math&gt; at &lt;math&gt;x=a&lt;/math&gt;, which may not even be defined.  For instance, consider the function defined as follows:

&lt;math&gt;
f(x) =\left\{\begin{matrix} 0 &amp; \mbox{if }  x\neq 1 \\
\mbox{27} &amp; \mbox{if } x=1\end{matrix}\right.
&lt;/math&gt;

By the definition of limit, &lt;math&gt; \lim_{x \to 1} f(x)=0&lt;/math&gt;, which is a really bad approximation of &lt;math&gt;f(x)&lt;/math&gt; at &lt;math&gt;x=1&lt;/math&gt;. [[User:Greenbreen|Greenbreen]] ([[User talk:Greenbreen|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Greenbreen|contribs]]) 13:15, 16 March 2011 (UTC)

==Possible inclusions for this page==
- limits at infinity (horizontal asymptotes) - Infinite limits (e.g. vertical asymptotes) -  Left/right handed limits - thinking of limits of indeterminant forms  (those that can be evaluated without Lhopitals rule)  - proofs of limit rules/one side limit theorem

Maybe this page needs to be broken up.  Continuity is a whole topic, and the formal definition/proofs of limit rules could also be pulled to its own page.  -- julius

==dutch==

Hey there, I'm making a dutch version of this book/chapter. I think I may have solved some presentational problems so if you like check out http://nl.wikibooks.org/wiki/Analyse:Limieten. Robert Zboray

==LEDE==
The section named [http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Calculus/Limits#Finding_limits Finding Limits] starts as follows: ''Now we will concentrate on finding limits, rather than proving them. In the proofs above, we started off with the value of the limit. How did we find it to even begin our proofs?'' I find this confusing. There are no '''proofs''' ''above'' that I can see, only examples. And in those examples we did actually find the value of the limit. (I realize that this error is probably a rest from a previous re-dispositional edit..) Or am I missing something? In that case I apologize. /Hugo --[[User:83.181.53.162|83.181.53.162]] 20:31, 5 November 2006 (UTC)

== &lt;s&gt;You CAN divide by zero&lt;/s&gt; ==

EVERYONE LISTEN TO THIS. I'M TIRED THAT EVERYONE KEEPS TELLING THAT YOU CAN'T DIVIDE BY ZERO.
Of course you can; it's a limit.

lim x/y = a. When y approaches zero, a = infinity.

:Technically, you can divide by ''y'' in the limit as ''y'' approaches zero. You cannot divide by zero without the use of such a limit. Remember that:
::&lt;math&gt;\lim_{y \to 0} y \ne 0&lt;/math&gt;
:The limit never allows ''y'' to actually take the value of zero, only to approach that value by infinitessimal amounts. As such, ''y'' never equals zero, but instead equals a value infinitessimally close to zero. The two quantities, while close, are not strictly the same. --[[User:Whiteknight|Whiteknight]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Whiteknight|talk]]) ([[User:Whiteknight/Proposed Books|projects]])&lt;/small&gt; 20:33, 9 January 2007 (UTC)

Whoa! I'm going to have to set this straight.  You can't divide by zero, neither algebraically nor analytically.  In algebra, the defining quality of the additive identity, zero, is that it has no multiplicative inverse (unless the set is trivially {0}).

PROOF:
:Assume that zero has an multiplicative inverse, and let 0 * a = 1.
:b*a + 1 = b*a + 0*a = (b + 0)*a = b*a   (assumption, distributive prop., def. of additive identity)    
:which means that 1 = 0, which is a contradiction whenever the set is not {0}.
Let's look at it analytically now.  Remember, a limit has to be well-defined to exist.  If it takes on different values depending on the way you approach the limit, then the limit doesn't exist.
Back to your example:
:lim(y-&gt;0) x/y.  Without loss of generality, let x &gt; 0 (if x = 0, then the limit is 0, and if x &lt; 0, we can multiply it by -1)
:lim(y-&gt;0 from the left-negative side) x/y &lt; 0 and lim(y-&gt;0 from the right-positive side) x/y &gt; 0
:Therefore the limit is not well-defined.  It doesn't exist.
Now, you could try to patch it by definition, but no matter what you'll be left with some &quot;infinity&quot; which isn't accounted for.  Also, negative infinity is not equal to positive infinity... that's easy enough to see.

Lastly, to the point: &lt;math&gt;\lim_{y \to 0} y = 0&lt;/math&gt;.  If one uses the formal definition this is obvious.  There is no actual &quot;approaching&quot; - that's just a simple way to think about it.  &quot;The two quantities, while close, are not strictly the same&quot; - They are only different in that they have different names.  (Sketch: Let the infinitesimal x (&gt;0) be a number different from 0, so that x/2 is not 0.  Then |y - 0| &lt; x/2. Obviously y cannot be x, for x &lt;= |x| = |x - 0| &lt; x/2 is a contradiction.) The infinitesimal is a nice tool for investigating functions of limits, but technically it's not a number in the sense you're trying to use it.
[[User:Mo Anabre|Mo Anabre]] 06:43, 1 May 2007 (UTC)

:I did simplify too much in my explanation, i should have taken the time to explain it properly. --[[User:Whiteknight|Whiteknight]] ([[User talk:Whiteknight|talk]]) 17:37, 1 May 2007 (UTC)

Hello! Intuitively, zero is a special symbol (like &lt;math&gt;\infty&lt;/math&gt;), that denotes empty expression. But if there is abscence of anything, what are you trying to compare with divident? Of course, division by zero can be defined artificialy, but AFAIK all such definitions lead to contradictions with other axioms.
[[User:Exanode|Exanode]] 15:16, 7 November 2007 (UTC)

There are two limit of each function (though sometimes both give the same result), one from the positive side and one from the negative side, so actually you can take the limit of x/y as y approaches 0. This is also a mistake in the text, which says that the limit of 1/(x-2) as x approaches 2 is undefined. The limit of this function from the negative side is negative infinity and the limit from the positive side is positive infinity.

==TO: authors.==

Please put some visualizations in the text. It's best to describe things like limits with graphics and give viewers an intuitive visual analogy.

I've seen some very interesting eLearning math courses with lots of graphical analogies. It made the concept of functions limit (among other things) easily understandable. Unfortunately the said courses are copyrighted and closed source.

:That's a great suggestion! If you have images or visualizations that you would like to donate, or if you know where we can find free or open-source images that we can use, that would be great. Unfortunately, creating lots of images takes time, and we are all just volunteers here. If you would like to join our project and help out, it would be appreciated. --[[User:Whiteknight|Whiteknight]] &lt;small&gt;([[User talk:Whiteknight|talk]]) ([[User:Whiteknight/Proposed Books|projects]])&lt;/small&gt; 21:24, 10 January 2007 (UTC)

:: Do you mean adding images to (for example) the Sqrtx216.gif function? There's a link to an image link there - I can't decide whether it is a old link that's been deleted or a request for a new link. [[User:DavidMcKenzie|DavidMcKenzie]] 15:40, 6 February 2007 (UTC)

Shouldn't we start with the values approaching a particular value? That makes it a lot easier to understand.

==Conversation==
For what it matters, after learning a little more about formal continuity, density isn't even required.  For instance, every function on the integers is continuous (since as a subspace of R, they have the discrete topology). Also, something interesting for anyone reading the person down there below Eric119: the integers are complete.  [[User:Mo Anabre|Mo Anabre]] 20:59, 1 November 2007 (UTC)

I changed it back.  The density of the rationals in the reals is quite enough to justify a concept of continuity of f.
[[User:Mo Anabre|Mo Anabre]] 17:48, 1 May 2007 (UTC)

I don't understand why this is wrong. If the domain of f is only the rationals, then, according to our definition of limits (which seems to have vanished from the article), no matter what delta we have there will exist irrational x such that 0 &lt; |x - c| &lt; delta and thus f(x) is not defined and therefore the condition |f(x) - L| &lt; epsilon cannot be true. (And then there is no limit and therefore a discontinuity.) If there is a problem in all this, please let me know. [[User:Eric119|Eric119]] 01:28, 6 Sep 2004 (UTC)

this is just wrong! The real number line is complete, meaning there are no holes. However, if we say ''f''&amp;nbsp;(''x'')&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;2 and restrict the domain of ''f'' to rational numbers, there will be holes at the places corresponding to irrational numbers. There are irrational numbers between any two rational numbers, so all the rational numbers on which ''f'' is defined are isolated from each other. But, there are rational numbers between any two irrational numbers, so each hole must be at a single point. There are infinite irrational numbers over any interval, so there are an infinite number of infinitely small holes between any two points on the graph. The places where ''f'' is defined are also infinite and infinitely small. The function ''f'' has no limits defined anywhere, despite that any graph would look like a simple line.

== application to calculus out of context ==

The &quot;application to calculus&quot; section references an example and several figures that don't exist. I presume that the section was copied over from some other source, and either the context and figures were neglected, or they were deemed a copyright violation and deleted (but the &quot;application to calculus&quot; section remained). Please rewrite this section so that it no longer references material that doesn't exist on wikibooks! Thanks! [[User:Luvcraft|Luvcraft]] 17:26, 2 July 2007 (UTC)

----
== application to calculus out of context another note== 
I think - that limit itself has no too much &quot;independent&quot; uses... Actually - it is instrument for establishment of strict differentiation theory... So - I would just abandon this item... Good illustration of use of limit concept could be concept of tangent line , or &quot;moment velocity&quot; vector... But - they are once more - from field of physics and geometry, and not - pure calculus...
--[[User:Psimonovsk|Simonovsky Pavel]] 18:29, 10 October 2007 (UTC)

== As x -&gt;0  sin (1/x) -&gt;0 ==

Sin (1/x) has no limit as x approaches 0.  I have sources.  The chapter must be changed. [[User:Zginder|Zginder]] 13:43, 12 September 2007 (UTC)

Zginder, did you even read the section?  I'm putting it back and fixing the _one_ error you didn't like. In the future please try to fix typos before deleting whole sections because of them. [[User:Mo Anabre|Mo Anabre]] 20:53, 1 November 2007 (UTC)

== Problem with 'Limit rules' ==
Why are all the limit rules listed with no proofs? Shouldn't the be proven before they are given? [[User:142.151.186.71|142.151.186.71]] 04:38, 9 October 2007 (UTC)
: Agreed. Maybe the proofs can be put in an appendix with a working link from the 'Limit Rules' section or at the very end of the module. --[[User:Hamsterpoop|Hamsterpoop]] 05:21, 29 October 2007 (UTC)
:: If it get some time here I'll try to come up with some of them, shouldn't bee too hard. [[User:142.151.186.71|142.151.186.71]] 20:41, 3 November 2007 (UTC)

== Began Edit ==
I started editing the beginning of the page, trying to start the discussion of a limit in a way that I (modestly) felt was more engaging, and tried to integrate it with the rest of the text.  I hope to come back and try to do more work.

Thanks.

[[Special:Contributions/128.208.76.146|128.208.76.146]] ([[User talk:128.208.76.146|talk]])
== Formal Definition of a Limit ==
Was the formal definition of a limit completely removed, or moved somewhere else? If the former, why? [[User:RSiferd|RSiferd]] ([[User talk:RSiferd|talk]]) 05:11, 21 May 2008 (UTC)
:It appears later in this &quot;chapter&quot; [[Calculus/Formal Definition of the Limit]]. And again, almost identically, at [[Calculus/Formal limits]]. --[[User:Mrwojo|Mrwojo]] ([[User talk:Mrwojo|talk]]) 19:22, 28 December 2008 (UTC)
:I've merged them at [[Calculus/Formal Definition of the Limit]]. --[[User:Mrwojo|Mrwojo]] ([[User talk:Mrwojo|talk]]) 05:54, 13 January 2009 (UTC)

== Video? ==
Does wikibooks have embedvideo extension installed?  {{#ev:googlevideo|-2777717103359291179}}

It does not appear to.  Should it?  Or some other video extension?  Can we request this?

[http://video.google.com/videoplay?docid=-2777717103359291179 Introduction to Limits Lecture]

~[[User:serundeputy|serundeputy]]

== Infinite oscillation is redundant ==

The section on infinite oscillation is very redundant.  Maybe it could be shortened?
[[Special:Contributions/173.74.178.117|173.74.178.117]] ([[User talk:173.74.178.117|talk]]) 01:29, 7 July 2010 (UTC)

:Thanks for the comment.  There are not many people working on the book right now, so it could be a few years before someone acts on this comment.  But you can feel free to be bold and remove any parts that you don't like.  Don't worry, people quickly look over things that change because of the whole &quot;watchlist&quot; setup, so even if your just learning calculus yourself or an old pro you can still be an equally valid contributor.  You can do so with or without an account, but I usually recommend having one, so you can configure your preferences. [[User:Thenub314|Thenub314]] ([[User talk:Thenub314|talk]]) 16:00, 7 July 2010 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>ayq1t82tt8w6s9yurn9vxlj29tsqyrg</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:RoseParks</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>910</id>
    <revision>
      <id>153045</id>
      <parentid>2335</parentid>
      <timestamp>2003-09-03T02:39:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>RoseParks</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <text xml:space="preserve">Hi! It seems we meet again, after the Nupedia experience (though I remember seeing you on wikipedia occasionally?). Thanks for the fixes in thermodynamics. Most of these were typos and not my bad English, rest assured :-)

Do not fear to run out of work, I plan to write lots more on the biochemistry front! --[[User:Magnus Manske|Magnus Manske]]

Good to be in contact, again. You are either in a big hurry or your English is slipping...and I am sure I know which ;-) --[[User:RoseParks|RoseParks]]</text>
      <sha1>siltj8vna7wwbaael0xyzrlyqvroydq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Wikibooks talk:Neutral point of view</title>
    <ns>5</ns>
    <id>911</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1945622</id>
      <parentid>1945378</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-10-10T13:08:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Darklama</username>
        <id>7662</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* POV in textbooks */ 2 cents</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">I think the NOV policy needs some discussion for wikibooks project.  

We may agree that wikibooks should not a place to produce a book that asserts some specific position or view, though I am not completely sure.

Should we say, for example, there should not be a book about environmental conservation (or gun control or birth control) that asserts that conservation is important? (The more NPOV way of referring to that is &quot;many (including, A, B) think that conservation is important because of ..., though there are some criticisms, most notably by C that ....&quot; 

In case of encyclopedia, there is a solution - we can sometimes split an article into many articles, and explain different points of views in length. 

If we were to implement this kind of solution, we might want to develop multiple &quot;modules&quot; or components of books along with multiple table of contents (each of which take different sets of modules to create a book from one particular POV). 

Feel free to copy this to mailing list or elsewhere. [[User:Tomos|Tomos]] 22:54, 31 Aug 2003 (UTC)
:I agree that NPOV will have to apply differently here than Wikipedia.  Since the project is still nascent, the best bet is to just go with it and, hopefully, a consensus will develop over time -- since most of our regulars are likely also Wikipedians, I think this will be a relatively easy process.  The conservation textbook you mentioned is a good example; it would be silly to interrupt every point with an explanation of why not everyone believes it.  The same would apply to descriptions of evolution, the Big Bang, etc.  We can assume a particular POV on the part of the reader in these cases, and should probably include an introduction or preface that explains why we are ignoring the fact that not everyone believes the same way on these issues. [[User:TUF-KAT|TUF-KAT]] 18:00, 12 Oct 2004 (UTC)

My opinion is that NPOV is not really at home here. Textbooks and other learning materials at times are written, and NEED to be written, from a &quot;non-neutral&quot; point of view. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]] 21:51, 12 Oct 2004 (UTC)

:I'm pretty new here, but I strongly belive that NPOV is not appropriate for Wikibooks. I think that there is, perhaps, some questionable sort of &quot;objectivity&quot; that something like an Encyclopedia can strive for, but I do not think this the case with a book. Limiting ourselves to books that meet an-NPOV standard would limit ourselves to books that sound an aweful lot like encyclopedias. Wikibooks seems to be about something beyond that.

:''Furthermore'', since Wikibooks is trying to create textbooks or books that could be used for learning, in a project like Wikiversity, etc., I think it is important to recognize that &quot;objective&quot; truth is a POV that tends to privilege the status-quo. Like the above example, if you are writing a book on environmental conservation, I believe it would not only be &quot;silly&quot; to strive for NPOV, I believe it would be counter-productive. As a history student, I believe that every narrative has an implicit subjectivity, (or POV). Any narrative that is constructed, for instance history, anthropology, sociology, etc., comes from a point of view and has political implications. The notion of &quot;objectivity&quot; and &quot;objective truth&quot; for instance in Anthroplogy, has been used to blind people from the significance of privileged white male anthropologists observing other cultures. (And Anthropology, with its claim to &quot;objective truth,&quot; has played a vital role in the construction of scientific racism.)

:I'm sorry if I'm trailing off here... I just feel strongly that recognizing subjectivity as opposed to hiding from it is a more fruitful approach to something such as Wikibooks. [[User:Fokion|Fokion]] 23:36, 11 September 2006 (UTC)

----

If there is a '''need''' to have something written from an non-NPOV, then that need should (will?) be clearly noted in the text itself.  The real question of NPOV is what does 'neutral' really mean?  That should be clearly defined in the policy.  My initial idea is that if something exists to be talked about factually, there is something in empirical reality that can be cited, and ought to be cited.  Conclusions and opinions based on that empirical concepts should be built logically.  ''If'' there are any countering opinions (or ''significant'' counter theories) they should be explained as if they were subject to the same rules.  --[[User:Delfeld|Neal Delfeld]] 18:24, 11 November 2005 (UTC)

:I think a problem here is that the idea of talking &quot;factually&quot; and &quot;empirical reality&quot; may work well with something like computer science or mathematics, but not so well with history or social theory. History, for instance, is not made of concrete facts, one stacking upon another. NPOV may work better with the &quot;hard&quot; sciences, but in the humanities or social sciences there is no such thing.[[User:Fokion|Fokion]] 00:16, 12 September 2006 (UTC)

== POV in textbooks ==

I think our history, geography and Chinese history textbooks are almost certainly biased. Especially history. You know, the 'the ancient Egyptians were great architects' or 'Alexander the Great was a great ruler'. For the ancient Egyptians they even gave the wrong fact because they followed Herodotus' version. But to the smaller ones. Like 'the Spartans are a warlike people'. Most people agree that, don't we? By modern standards they are pretty warlike. But is that still an opinion, an opinion to the eyes of us modern people? And one more thing: Athenians built many open-air theatres. What defines many? There could be theatres on every corner of Planet Drama. :)

By the way, I think the emoticon should be removed. It makes our policy here look much more casual. Policies and guidelines can joke, sure, WP does that all the time, but not include non-standard ways of expressing. [[User:Kayau|Kayau]] ( [[User talk:Kayau|talk]] &amp;#124; [[Special:Emailuser/Kayau|email]] &amp;#124; [[Special:Contributions/Kayau|contribs]] ) 23:56, 18 June 2010 (UTC)

:They say that history is written by the victorious.  Of particular note to your thoughts is [[m:Can history be truly NPOV?]]. &amp;ndash;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Adrignola|Adrignola]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Adrignola|talk]]&lt;/small&gt; 03:22, 10 October 2010 (UTC)

::Ha. I have to agree. Chinese history, for example, is written from a Confucian point of view. [[User:Kayau|Kayau]] ([[User talk:Kayau|talk]] &amp;#124; [[Special:Emailuser/Kayau|email]] &amp;#124; [[Special:Contributions/Kayau|contribs]]) 03:32, 10 October 2010 (UTC)
: Compared with Wikipedia our NPOV policy is much more casual. I think Wikipedia expects their articles to be written neutral from the beginning while Wikibooks accepts that neutrality is a process that takes time. Wikipedia's expectations are reflected in that its policy defines what it means for articles to be neutral and how to achieve neutrality while Wikibooks relies on the scope of each book to affect what it means to be neutral and how neutrality is achieved which is reflected by the more general and less specific approach used in Wikibooks' policy.
: If you believe the statements above that you quoted are a problem, be bold and fix them. &quot;Anthropologists like Blah and Blah considered the ancient Egyptians to be great architects&quot; or &quot;During his time people considered Alexander the Great to be a great ruler, hence the name&quot; to give two possible fixes. For the smaller ones you could even do &quot;Compared with modern standards the Spartans are a warlike people&quot; or &quot;Today the Spartans are considered warlike people.&quot; --&lt;span style=&quot;font: bold 10pt 'courier new', comic, sans, ms;&quot;&gt;[[User:Darklama|&lt;font color=&quot;midnightblue&quot;&gt;dark&lt;/font&gt;]][[User_talk:Darklama|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;lama&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 13:08, 10 October 2010 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>29h1xn5c6bhcvhi55l8cv3gz5bc997w</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Sp3.jpg</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>913</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748855</id>
      <parentid>153048</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-02-09T19:54:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>bqzg6alf693qn5egkcy4lip7de3tqdd</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook:History of Food and Cooking</title>
    <ns>102</ns>
    <id>914</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2686737</id>
      <parentid>2675102</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-07-31T19:58:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Koavf</username>
        <id>16549</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Koavf moved page [[Cookbook:History of food and cooking]] to [[Cookbook:History of Food and Cooking]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Cookbook help page}}

== Historic texts ==
The origin of many modern dishes can be traced back to ancient times, but there are very few surviving texts written before 1000 AD that deal with cooking. In many cases where texts exist, the recipes and directions they provide are little more than guidelines and assume much knowledge on the part of the cook.

For example the following is a recipe taken from the Forme of Cury, a roll of cookery written around 1390 by the master cooks of King Richard II of England.

:'''Compost.'''

:Take rote of persel, of pasternak, of rafens, scrape hem and waische hem clene. Take rapes &amp; caboches, ypared and icorue. Take an erthen panne with clene water &amp; set it on the fire; cast alle þise þerinne. Whan þey buth boiled cast þerto peeres, &amp; parboile hem wel. Take alle þise thynges vp &amp; lat it kele on a faire cloth. Do þerto salt; whan it is colde, do hit in a vessel; take vyneger &amp; powdour &amp; safroun &amp; do þerto, &amp; lat alle þise thynges lye þerin al nyyt, oþer al day. Take wyne greke &amp; hony, clarified togider; take lumbarde mustard &amp; raisons coraunce, al hoole, &amp; grynde powdour of canel, powdour douce &amp; aneys hole, &amp; fenell seed. Take alle þise thynges &amp; cast togyder in a pot of erthe, &amp; take þerof whan þou wilt &amp; serue forth.

&lt;!-- Take ???, scrape them and wash them clean. Take ???. Take an earthenware pan with clean water and set it on the fire; toss in the aforementioned ingredients. When ???, throw in ??? and parboil thoroughly. Let cool on a ??? cloth. Could someone please finish this translation? --&gt;

This recipe, which is written in late Middle English, is open to interpretation as it gives no specific quantities and assumes that the reader will know how long certain things need to be cooked, soaked, etc.

You shouldn't let this deter you from reading old texts concerning cookery; indeed there is a certain degree of fun in taking an old recipe and determining how it might have been prepared.

Some books dealing with ancient cookery are:
* The Forme of Cury, 1390 - http://www.ibiblio.org/pub/docs/books/gutenberg/etext05/8cury10.txt
* More links at http://cunnan.sca.org.au/wiki/Recipe

== Origins ==

=== Americas ===
'''North America'''
* Turkey
* Cranberries, blueberries, huckleberries, strawberries
* Pumpkins, zucchini
* Black Walnuts
* Chilli Peppers, bell peppers

'''Central America'''
* Amaranth, tobacco
* Corn
* Peanuts
* Squash
* Tomatoes

'''South America'''
* Sweet Potatoes
* Chocolate, from cacao bean
* Strawberries
* Potatoes

===Europe===
* Horse
* Atanasovsko Salt
* Wieliczka Salt
* Baskunchak Salt
* Pork
* Herring
* Vinegar
* Rye
* Raspberry
* Blackcurrant
* Parsnips
'''Mediterranean'''
* Beets
* Broccoli
* Cauliflower
* Cabbage
* Kale
* Kohlrabi
* Brussels sprouts

'''Balkans'''
* Walnuts
* Olives

===Africa ===
* Yams
* Watermelon
* Coffee, originated in Ethiopia

===Middle East===
* Mustard
* Cannabis
* Oats
* Barley
* Lettuce
* Radishes
* Onions
* Leeks
* Wheat
* Carrots
* Parsley
* Cucumbers
* Vinegar
* Spinach

=== Asia ===
* Chicken
* Shiitake Mushrooms 
* Yams
* Eggplant
* [[Chinese Herbs]]
* Rice 
* Banana 
* Baelfruit
* Bilimbi 
* Breadfruit
* Chempedak 
* Coconut 
* Durian 
* Jackfruit
* Langsat 
* Lime
* Longan 
* Lychee 
* Mango
* Mangosteen
* Persimmon 
* Pomelo 
* Rambuttan 
* Rose Apple
* Sea Apple
* Starfruit
* Snakefruit

'''Siam / Thailand'''
* Galanga, Galangal, Greater Galangal 
* Thai Ginger (Krachai)
* Hot Basil, Sweet Basil, Lemony Basil 

'''Tibet'''
* Barley
* Blackcurrant, north asia

'''Korean Peninsula'''
* Barley
* Millet
* Wheat
* Legumes

=== Polynesia ===
'''Australia'''

Macadamia nuts



[[Category:Cookbook|History of food and cooking]]</text>
      <sha1>rfn6xxoii17ywq8ki7gwhvgrykpokt9</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Computer Programming/Variables</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>915</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1361557</id>
      <parentid>190208</parentid>
      <timestamp>2008-12-18T01:42:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Darklama</username>
        <id>7662</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[Talk:Computer programming/Variables]] moved to [[Talk:Computer Programming/Variables]]:&amp;#32;naming convention consistency</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">The introduction to variables may make sense for a course to &quot;Programming C&quot;
and a like. But in a more broader context it does not satisfy me. Some thoughts:

Variables may ''reference'' values rather than ''stand in for''. You can
make the variables to reference to another value later on in the program,
you can have to variables to reference the same value and you can then
manipulate these value through either variable.

The later is explained in the text, but we may abstract from &quot;memory addresses&quot; here. 

Moreover, there are programming languages where you have to declare
a variable before you can use but don't need to give it a type. I'm thinking
of Oz here. In some dynamically typed languages like ruby, procedures/functions/methods declare proc./func./method need arguments (which are
variables) declared but without a type.

: Your points make sense...why don't you edit the page?
: This 'book's in a bit of a larval state still and still needs some work [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 09:16, 1 Sep 2003 (UTC)

::textbook.wikipedia.org was just mentioned in a couple of slashdot comments (not articles! don't panic!). I doubt that there'll be lots of people arriving but there might be a few gawkers moving through.

:I tried to edit the introduction but could not figure how to get to it.
:What I was trying to add
:Dates and times can be in various formats such as USA (mm/dd/yyyy); European (dd.mm.yyyy); Japanese (yyyy.mm.dd); based on Chinese Year (not Biblical); and others.
[[User:AlMac|AlMac]] 09:25, 16 July 2005 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>3c8jhopkzcwg4jb62tosynsv3ujwyey</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cell Biology/Lysosomes</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>916</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1896791</id>
      <parentid>1442883</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-07-21T16:20:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>fixed links/category</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Cell Biology]] | [[../Parts of the cell|Parts of the cell]] |  [[../Organelles|Organelles]]

[[../Golgi apparatus|&lt;&lt; Golgi apparatus]] | Lysosomes | [[../Peroxisomes|Peroxisomes &gt;&gt;]]

----


== Lysosomes == 
Membrane-bound sacs called lysosomes contain digestive enzymes that can break down such macromolecules as proteins, nucleic acids, and polysaccharides (Figure 6-23). Lysosomes have several functions. They fuse with incoming food vacuoles and expose the nutrients to enzymes that digest them, thereby nourishing the cell. Lysosomes also function like safety officers when they help destroy harmful bacteria. In certain cells—for example, your white blood cells—lysosomes release enzymes into vacuoles that contain trapped bacteria and break down the bacterial cell walls. Similarly, lysosomes serve as recycling centers for damaged organelles. Without harming the cell, a lysosome can engulf and digest another organelle. This makes molecules available for the construction of new organelles.The structures vary in size from 0.2 to 2 micrometers in diameter. The staining reveals a crystal like matrix in spherical vesicles. The crystalloid matrix is urate oxidase. These are small organelles containing around 40 enzymes for intercellular digestion. The lysosome membrane helps to protect the enzymes as much as it helps protect the cell. This is because the optimal pH for these enzymes is around a pH of 5. The membrane of the lysosome is again a lipid bilayer and is thought to have a ATP hydrolysis to pump H+ into the lysosome to maintain the pH. This also has another affect, that is free protons. Other small molecules can pass through the lysosome membrane, but will then become charged by picking up a free proton, then they are less likely to be able to leave the lysososome. A good reference on Lysosomes is at
:http://cellbio.utmb.edu/cellbio/lysosome.htm 

----
[[../Golgi apparatus|&lt;&lt; Golgi apparatus]] | Lysosomes | [[../Peroxisomes|Peroxisomes &gt;&gt;]]

[[Cell Biology]] | [[../Parts of the cell|Parts of the cell]] [[../Organelles|Organelles]]

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>6v7e9i0dlqt87rq5hrde4h5h46ikg45</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cell Biology/Peroxisomes</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>917</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1896792</id>
      <parentid>495866</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-07-21T16:21:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>fixed links</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Cell Biology]] | [[../Parts of the cell/]] | [[../Organelles/]]

[[../Lysosomes|&lt;&lt; Lysosomes]] | Peroxisomes | [[../Cytosol|Cytosol &gt;&gt;]]

----
It used to be thought that peroxisomes are formed by the budding of smooth Endoplasmic Reticulum (ER). However, now it is thought that they form through self-assembly. (I will get more information references as I do some more thorough literature searches). The peroxisome is another major source of Oxygen utilization (along with the mitochondrion). There are specific proteins associated with the peroxisomes membrane, also there are 3 oxidation enzymes associated with peroxisomes:

# D-amino acid oxidase 
# Urate Oxidase 
# Catalase 

The enzyme contents vary with various types of cells. One of the main functions of peroxisomes in liver cells is detoxification. This is done by the oxidation of substances like:

# Alcohol - About 1/2 of the ethanol one drinks is converted to acetaldehyde by oxidation. 
# Phenols 
# Formic acid 
# Formaldehyde 

=== Why peroxisomes are not like lysosomes ===

Peroxisomes are organelles that contain oxidative enzymes, such as D-amino acid oxidase, urate oxidase, and catalase. They may resemble a lysosome, however, they are not formed in the Golgi complex. Peroxisomes are distinguished by a crystalline structure inside a sac which also contains amorphous gray material. They are self replicating, like the mitochondria. Components accumulate at a given site and they can be assembled into a peroxisome. They may look like storage granules, however, they are not formed in the same way as storage granules.

Peroxisomes function to rid the body of toxic substances like hydrogen peroxide, or other metabolites. They are a major site of oxygen utilization and are numerous in the liver where toxic byproducts are going to accumulate. 

The peroxisome is made as a phospholipid bilayer, encapsulating oxidative materials. They would be 'sphere-ish' in shape, not necessarily a perfect sphere, and sometimes, they may take other shapes. But most electron micrographs I have seen (2 dimensions) show them as circles. (As you may be aware, the Cell membrane is also a phospholipid bilayer.) Peroxisomes have membrane proteins that are critical for peroxisomal function, to import proteins into their interiors, proliferate or segregate to daughter cells (This update, thanks to Babich Temps). The main differences would be:

# Types of phospholipids used. 
#Size of the membrane (i.e. peroxisomes are MUCH smaller than the cell).

----
[[../Lysosomes|&lt;&lt; Lysosomes]] | Peroxisomes | [[../Cytosol|Cytosol &gt;&gt;]]

[[Cell Biology]] | [[../Parts of the cell/]] [[../Organelles/]]

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>rinhl521t1inpa7nxlzbsik9ncalk5z</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cell Biology/Cytosol</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>918</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1896793</id>
      <parentid>495803</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-07-21T16:22:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>fixed links/category</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Cell Biology]] | [[../Parts of the cell/]] | [[../Organelles/]]

[[../Peroxisomes|&lt;&lt; Peroxisomes]] | Cytosol | [[../Cytoskeleton and Microtubules|Cytoskeleton and Microtubules &gt;&gt;]]

----
The cytosol (as opposed to cytoplasm, which also includes the organelles) is the internal fluid of the cell, and a large part of cell metabolism occurs here. Proteins within the cytosol play an important role in signal transduction pathways, glycolysis, and act as intracellular receptors and ribosomes. In prokaryotes, all chemical reactions take place in the cytosol. In eukaryotes, the cytosol contains the cell organelles. In plants, the amount of cytosol can be reduced due to the large tonoplast (central vacuole) that takes up most of the room of the cell.

The cytosol is not a &quot;soup&quot; with free-floating particles, but highly organized on the molecular level. The cytosol also contains the cytoskeleton. It is made of fibrous proteins and (in many organisms) maintains the shape of the cell, anchors organelles, and controls internal movement of structures, e.g., transport vesicles.

As the concentration of soluble molecules increases within the cytosol, an osmotic gradient builds up toward the outside of the cell. Water is flowing into the cell, making it larger. To prevent the cell from bursting apart, molecular pumps in the plasma membrane, the cytoskeleton, the tonoplast or a cell wall (if present) are used to counteract the osmotic pressure. 

----
[[../Peroxisomes|&lt;&lt; Peroxisomes]] | Cytosol | [[../Cytoskeleton and Microtubules|Cytoskeleton and Microtubules &gt;&gt;]]

[[Cell Biology]] | [[../Parts of the cell/]] | [[../Organelles/]]

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>q2mpkefxvkpmh4ffizsr84268o5qoz1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>GCSE Science/Advanced static electricity topics</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>921</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2525352</id>
      <parentid>2525303</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-05-12T16:24:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/115.64.50.203|115.64.50.203]] ([[User talk:115.64.50.203|talk]]) to last version by 94.171.156.247</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[GCSE Science/Electricity]]
----
Before reading this module check to see if you need to. If you intend to take the foundation paper, you may find that you do not need to do the work on this page. If in doubt check with your teacher.

==Where charge concentrates==

{| align=&quot;right&quot; cellpadding=&quot;10&quot;
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | [[Image:Charged asymetric conductor.png]]
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;ccddff&quot; |  The charge spreads out on  this &lt;br/&gt;uneven conductor unevenly. The &lt;br/&gt;two electrons that are circled &lt;br/&gt;in red cannot see each other.&lt;br/&gt; The body of the conductor gets&lt;br/&gt; in the way and shields them. This&lt;br/&gt; is why the charges congregate&lt;br/&gt; around the highly curved areas.
|}
When an object is charged up with electrons, the electrons try to spread out over the object to be as far apart as possible. This means they go to the surface rather than spread throughout. On a metal object the material of which the object is made shields the electrons from one another. They do not ‘’see’’ the electrons round the back. This means that highly curved objects can hold more electrons than flat objects. For a complicated shape, the electrons tend to congregate on the more highly curved areas, and to desert the flatter areas.

==Inducing charge separation on neutral objects==

Consider a crystal of gold for example. {This argument works for all materials}. Normally the atoms are perfectly spherical, and completely neutral. 

'''Q1)''' Why are the atoms neutral?

Remember that neutral atoms contain positive charges in the nucleus and negative electrons orbiting in their shell. Normally the center of the positive charges and the center of the negative electrons is in the same place: the exact center of the atom. If we bring up a charged object to them however, something important happens. Look at the diagram on the right.


{| align=&quot;right&quot;
|-
| [[Image:Charge separation on a crystal.png]]
|}A charged rod is brought near the surface of the crystal. {Note: the rod is not shown, just the charges on it}. The electrons in the atoms try to get away from the negative charge because they are repelled. The positive charges in the nucleus try to get nearer to the negative rod because they are attracted to it. The result is the atom slightly changes shape. The center of the negative charges goes to the right of the center of the atom and the center of the positive charges goes to the left. We say there is a '''separation of charges'''

'''Q2)''' What would happen if we brought up a positively charged rod?

'''There is always an attractive force between the rod and the crystal no matter what the charge on the rod'''.

To see why this is so, we need to know one more thing about electrostatics. '''The force of repulsion or attraction falls off with distance'''. In fact, rather like gravity it falls off as the ''square'' of the distance. This means if you go to twice the distance the force becomes only a quarter as much. If you go three times the distance it becomes only one ninth as great and so on. Now look at the diagram again. The negative charges in the atoms are repelled by the rod, the positive ones are attracted, but '''the positive charges are closer''', so overall there is a force of attraction.

'''Q3)''' Repeat the above argument with a positively charged rod to convince yourself that there is still an attractive force.

==Lightning==


{| align=&quot;center&quot;
|-
| [[File:Multiple Lightning Strikes.jpg]]
|-
| bgcolor=&quot;ccddff&quot; | Time-lapse photography captures multiple cloud-to-ground&lt;br/&gt; lightning strikes during a night-time thunderstorm.
|}

Lightning is basically a great big spark. In a thunderstorm, separation of charge occurs in big rain clouds. No one is really sure of ''how'' this occurs, although it appears to be caused by ice crystals rubbing together and becoming charged. but what ''is'' known is that storm clouds have a negative bottom and a positive top. The bottom of the cloud is nearer to the ground so it induces a positive charge on the ground. When the voltage becomes high enough a spark flies between the cloud and the earth; this is lightning. The spark is so hot, it causes the air to rapidly expand then collapse; this causes thunder.

'''Q4)''' Why does the voltage need to be very high before lightning can occur?
===Lightning rods===
Lightning rods are used to protect buildings from lightning strikes. They are usually made from a length of copper rod with a pointed end. They are attached to tall buildings and the lightning strikes them rather than the building itself.

'''Q5)''' Why do you think the rods are made of copper rather than iron which is cheaper?

'''Q6)''' Why do the rods have a pointed end?

'''Q7)''' It is standard advice that if caught out in a storm you should ''never'' stand under a lone tree. Why is this advice good?                                                                       


{| bgcolor=&quot;#ffeeaa&quot;
|-
|
'''Summary'''
*Charge congregates around highly curved surfaces
*A charged object induces charge separation in nearby neutral objects. This ''always'' produces an attractive force
*Lightning is just a big spark from a cloud to the ground, thunder is the sound of the spark
*Lightning rods protect buildings by attracting the lightning strike and conducting the charge safely to ground
|}



----
[[GCSE Science/Advanced Static electricity topics answers|Answers]] | [[GCSE Science/Uses of static electricity| &lt;&lt;Uses of static electricity]] | [[GCSE Science/Electrolysis|Electrolysis&gt;&gt;]]

[[Category:GCSE Science]]</text>
      <sha1>dybojvd0zydwy81256s2qb6qknlno2c</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>