<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>Botany/Introduction Botany</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>986</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2671282</id>
      <parentid>2671232</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-06-08T11:15:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Xania</username>
        <id>40302</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/124.6.181.212|124.6.181.212]] ([[User talk:124.6.181.212|talk]]) to last version by Vogone</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;small&gt;&lt;&lt; [[Botany#Detailed contents|Contents Page]] | &lt;/small&gt;Chapter 1&lt;small&gt; | [[Botany/Plant_cells|Chapter 2]] &gt;&gt;|&lt;/small&gt; 
----
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;big&gt;&lt;big&gt;Chapter 1. Introduction to Botany&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/big&gt;  
&lt;/center&gt;
----
&lt;p&gt;

== Botany as a Science ==

'''Botany''' is the branch of '''biology''' concerned with the scientific study of plants. Traditionally, botanists studied all organisms that were not generally regarded as animal. However, advances in our knowledge about the myriad forms of life, especially microbes (viruses and bacteria), have led to spinning off from Botany the specialized field called '''Microbiology'''. Still, the microbes are usually covered in introductory Botany courses, although their status as neither animal nor plant is firmly established.


Plants are living entities, and material presented within ''Biology'' will have relevance here, most particularly at the cellular and subcellular levels of organization (Chapter 2). Both plants and animals deal with the same problems of maintaining life on planet Earth &amp;mdash; their approaches seem quite different, but the end result is the same: continued existence in an organized state, as part of a universe whose tendency is towards greater disorganization.  Back on Earth, however, it is a fact that microbes, plants, and animals comprise a very interdependent system. We divide them apart, because our minds work best that way. We categorize and learn common features or properties of the categories. This approach is neither right nor wrong, but is clearly efficient for our minds.  Nonetheless, it is desirable to regularly step back and realize that the boundaries between categories are often just constructs, and exceptions to our categories usually abound.

It was alluded to in the opening definition that Botany is a '''science'''. Just what makes Botany, or anything else a science?  It is important to acquire a grasp of the fundamentals of science itself to fully appreciate both how botanical knowledge was gained as well as how it can be used. It is usually quickly disinteresting to acquire facts simply for the sake of knowing. Humans do not just appreciate mountains ''because they are there'', they climb them because they are there!

== Living Systems ==
Biology is defined as the study of life, and Botany is that discipline within Biology concerned with the study of living organisms called '''plants''' and with certain other living things that are not plants (but are not animals either).  

=== Defining 'Plant' ===
Like many words in common usage that apply to biological entities or concepts, the term '''''plant''''' is more difficult to define than might be at first obvious.  Although botanists describe a '''Kingdom Plantae''', the boundaries defining members of Plantae are more inclusive than our common concept of a &quot;plant&quot;.  We are tempted to regard ''plant'' as meaning a multicellular, eukaryotic organism that generally does not have sensory organs or voluntary motion and has, when complete, a root, stem, and leaves.  However, botanically only vascular plants have a root, stem, and leaves, and even some vascular plants, such as certain carnivorous plants and duckweed, fall afoul of that definition.  But to be fair, the vascular plants are the plants we tend to encounter every day and that most people would readily regard as &quot;plants&quot;.

A more significant point of departure between Plantae and plants occurs among the seaweeds. Technically, only a relatively minor group of seaweeds (the chlorophytes or green algae) are members of the Kingdom Plantae.  The majority of seaweeds, like the kelps (very large brown algae from the Order Laminariales), despite a superficial appearance of such, lack true stems, leaves, roots, and any kind of vascular systems as found in higher plants. Thus, the kelps are not Plantae; but are they plants? Certainly if we regard the green algae as plants, it is difficult to exclude the more prominent red and brown algae of our coastal waters.  

Another, much broader definition for ''plant'' is that it refers to any organism that is '''''photoautotrophic'''''&amp;mdash;produces its own food from raw inorganic materials and sunlight. This is not an unreasonable definition, and is one that focuses on the role plants typically play in an ecosystem. However, there are photoautotrophs among the '''Prokaryotes''', specifically photoautotrophic bacteria and cyanophytes. The latter are sometimes called (for good reasons) blue-green algae. Then there arises the problem that many people would consider that a mushroom is a plant; a mushroom is the fruiting body of a fungus (Kingdom Fungi) and not ''photoautotrophic'' at all, but ''saprophytic''. However, there are more than a few species of flowering plants, fungi, and bacteria that are not autotrophic, but ''parasitic''.

We cannot hope to offer a firm answer. The list of characteristics that separate the Plantae from the other biological kingdoms provides at least a technical definition, but realize it is only a technical definition. The problem this lack of precision or agreement in the definition of &quot;plant&quot; presents is one of understanding statements, often encountered in ''Wikipedia'' (and other) articles, of the sort: ''...xylem is one of the two transport tissues of plants''. In general it cannot be assumed this means all plants, algae through flowering plants. It very probably does not include fungi or bacteria. Indeed, it is usually safest to assume the discussion is about vascular plants (essentially the ferns, conifers, flowering plants, and a few others; see discussion below on &quot;General Terminology&quot;) unless stated differently (e.g., ''...in vascular and non-vascular plants this is ''such and such).

=== Plants as Organisms ===

The distinction between life and non-life is not as easily made as you might think. There exist intracellular &quot;parasites&quot; that are progressively less alive in terms of being metabolically active:

== Plants and their Uses ==

There can be no disputing the fundamental significance of plants to the ecology of our planet.  Photosynthetic plants utilize energy arriving from the sun to create complex organic molecules from inorganic substances, and by this process contribute oxygen to the atmosphere.  Advanced animal life is very much dependent upon this source of oxygen, as well as the organic molecules that form the basis of nearly every food web on the planet. However, humans utilize plants in many ways, especially as sources of pleasure, food, and material for shelter, clothing, and more. Consider here the role plants play in our everyday lives and in our economy.

== Introduction to Plant Classification ==
At the beginning of this chapter it was suggested that each of us categorizes information we encounter on a daily basis. Our minds seem to want to find relationships between facts and observations, to erect mental bins in which to place new items with previous &quot;facts&quot;.  This natural human process is the basis for prejudice, in as much as &quot;facts&quot; categorized together can become strongly associated. But these are personal constructs. In order for scientists of many races, speaking many languages, and coming from all manner of backgrounds and experiences to work productively together to solve common  problems, the objects with which they work must be classified within a universally accepted framework.    

The classification of living things is called '''systematics''', or '''taxonomy''', and ideally should reflect the evolutionary history (phylogeny) of the different organisms.  

Taxonomy arranges organisms in groups called '''taxa''', while systematics seeks clues to their relationships. The dominant system of ''Scientific Classification'' is called '''Linnaean taxonomy''', and includes classification ranks as well as an organism naming convention called '''binomial nomenclature'''.

Traditionally, all living things were divided into five kingdoms:

:[[Wikipedia:en:Monera|Monera]] &amp;mdash; [[Wikipedia:En:Protist|Protista]] &amp;mdash; [[Wikipedia:en:Fungi|Fungi]] &amp;mdash; [[Wikipedia:En:Plantae|Plantae]] &amp;mdash; [[Wikipedia:en:Animal|Animalia]]

However, this five-kingdom system has been replaced by Carl Woese's three-domain system,  which focuses on phylogenic roots and comparison of DNA structures.  The older approach  utilized visual observation as the basis of classification. The three domains reflect whether cells have nuclei ('''eukaryotic''') or not ('''prokaryotic'''), as well as differences in cell membranes and cell walls.

:[[Wikipedia:en:Archaea|Archaea]] &amp;mdash; [[Wikipedia:en:Eubacteria|Eubacteria]] &amp;mdash; [[Wikipedia:en:Eukaryota|Eukaryota]]

Recall (and review as necessary) how these groupings relate to the sequence of events in the evolutionary history of life as summarized in [[Wikipedia:en:Timeline of evolution|Timeline of Evolution]]. You will return to the subject of Scientific Classification to consider in much more detail the groups of organisms studied in Botany, beginning with Chapter 7. First, however, we shall turn our attention to the structure and function of cells and eventually to gain an understanding of plant structure (''plant anatomy'') and function (''plant physiology'').

=== General Terminology === 
In Section II of this text we will delve much deeper into &quot;plant&quot; systematics.  But you should be aware of some general terms related to classificatory schemes that are used regularly in discussing plants.  You have probably encountered these terms many times, although may not be aware of their exact definitions. For example, much of the material in Section I of this textbook is biased towards '''flowering plants'''.  That is, much of the descriptive material here as well as at Wikipedia refers specifically to these. Flowering plants are angiosperms; plants that have flowers and produce seeds, and comprise the majority of the plants we would normally encounter in say a nursery if not on the street, field, or empty lot. '''Seed-bearing plants''' include both the angiosperms and the gymnosperms, the latter now treated as a modern group called '''conifers'''.  The conifers are also common plants, especially in higher latitudes, but bear cones instead of flowers. Both conifers and flowering plants develop vascular tissues internally that conduct fluids (especially water) throughout the plant. Included in the '''vascular plants''' are ferns.  Ferns have vascular tissue, but reproduce by spores.  They do not produce seeds and do not bear flowers.

==See Also==
* ''[[Botany/Introduction discussion|Discussion]] of this chapter''
{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>ba3qenrx17lsdn1jxg82abfuw8ylib5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Botany/Plant cells</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>987</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2228691</id>
      <parentid>2228690</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-12-05T07:37:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Choess</username>
        <id>506784</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* Plant Cell Structure */ sp. (lupe-&gt;loupe)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;small&gt;&lt;&lt; [[Botany#Detailed_Contents|Contents Page]] | &lt;&lt; [[Botany/Introduction_Botany|Chapter 1]] | &lt;/small&gt;Chapter 2&lt;small&gt; | [[Botany/Plant_tissues|Chapter 3]] &gt;&gt;|&lt;/small&gt; 
----
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;big&gt;&lt;big&gt;Chapter 2. Plant Cells&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/big&gt;  
&lt;/center&gt;
----
== Introduction ==
[[image:lupe.jpg|thumb|200px|right|A loupe (left) and a hand-lens (right) - tools used by botanists in the field]]
A '''cell''' is a very basic structure of all living systems, consisting of '''protoplasm''' within a containing '''cell membrane'''.  Only entities such as viruses&amp;mdash;literally on the boundary between non-living chemicals and living systems&amp;mdash;lack cells or basic cell structure. All plants, including very simple plants called ''algae'', and all animals are made up of cells, and these are organized in various ways to create structure and function in an organism. Biologists recognize two basic types of cells: '''prokaryotic''' and '''eukaryotic'''. ''Prokaryotic cells'' are structurally more simple. They are found only in single-celled and some simple, multicellular organisms (all bacteria and some algae, which all belong to Bacteria and Archaea domains). ''Eukaryotic cells'' are found in most algae, all higher plants, fungi, and animals (Eukarya domain). Thus, differences between these two cell types are critical to how an organism is classified, and an important consideration in the evolutionary sequence of life on the planet Earth.

== Plant Cell Structure ==

Nearly all cells are too small to be seen with the unaided eye. As always there are some exceptions, but generally magnification is required to detect a cellular structure. In plants, a good hand-lens or loupe (see photo at right) will sometimes suffice, but in working with cells or observing how cells are organized to form tissues and structures, a high power '''[[Wikipedia:en:Microscope|microscope]]''' is used.

* Read about [[Wikipedia:en:Cell (biology)|Cells]] ~ &lt;small&gt;You may wish to follow some or all links to &quot;Main articles&quot; as these provide detail that may interest you; or you might return to explore further should questions arise later in the course.&lt;/small&gt;  
* Read [[Wikipedia:en:Plant_cell|Plant cells]] &lt;small&gt;and, at minimum, articles at the following links (but ignore, for now, the topic of &lt;u&gt;Plant Cell Types&lt;/u&gt;):&lt;/small&gt;
**[[Wikipedia:en:Cell_wall|Cell Wall]]
**[[Wikipedia:en:Protoplasm|Protoplasm and cytoplasm]]
**[[Wikipedia:en:Vacuole|Vacuole]]
**[[Wikipedia:en:Ergastic substances|Ergastic substances]]
**[[Wikipedia:en:Plastid|Plastids]]
**[[Wikipedia:en:Chloroplast|Chloroplasts]]

:Also note that the textbook, ''[[Cell Biology]]'', is available at ''WikiBooks'' and can be used as a more detailed reference. You should read the [[Cell Biology/Introduction|Introductory Chapter]] (all subsections) at this time.  

&lt;tt&gt;Questions&lt;/tt&gt;:
#''Can you think of reasons why ''macroscopic'' organisms are multicellular?'' &lt;small&gt;(Macroscopic means large, in the sense of &quot;not microscopic&quot;)&lt;/small&gt;

== Basic Cell Function ==

You should, by now, have a general appreciation for the complexity of cellular structure. Improvements in microscopy, especially development of the [[Wikipedia:en:Electron_microscope|Electron microscope]], have revealed that cells are not merely membranous sacks containing fluid of gel-like consistency. The degree of organization of the '''cytoplasm''' into  '''organelles''' and their '''membranes''' should have you convinced that much (perhaps most) of what is really going on around you on this planet is occurring at a scale that is simply inaccessible to your eyes. And while you cannot be expected to directly observe chemical reactions at a molecular scale, contemplate that you cannot, even with powerful optics, directly observe most of the structure where these reactions are somehow controlled to produce outcomes favorable to life&amp;mdash;indeed, are life. Hopefully, as you acquire knowledge and become a biologist&amp;mdash;a botanist&amp;mdash;you will learn to recognize the relevant phenomena by their macroscopic expressions (that which you can readily observe with the unaided eye).    

To appreciate basic cell function, it is necessary to first list the processes or outcomes that cells must accomplish to further existence. More specialized functions will be discussed under plant cell structure, as our interest must eventually focus on plants. For now, recall that in your reading you have already encountered these several basic abilities of cells: 

*'''Metabolism''' involves taking in of raw material to use in building cell components and  breaking down of other molecules to provide energy for various growth processes; byproducts may be released. 
*'''Protein biosynthesis''' by transcription of DNA to RNA and then translation to protein, used in growth or released for use elsewhere by the organism.          
*'''Reproduction''' by cell division. 

Now explore each in turn. Think initially of a single-celled organism with no special abilities, only a &quot;will&quot; to stay alive and perpetuate itself. Remember, the environment will not be kind. The cell must grow and reproduce to counter the tendency of outside forces to breakdown molecular structure and destroy life. Then consider the situation where a cell is part of a multicellular organism, and may be performing more limited and specialized functions. 

*Read [[Wikipedia:en:Cell_metabolism|Cell metabolism]] (&lt;small&gt;Follow links and read at least these articles&lt;/small&gt;):
** [[Wikipedia:en:Metabolic pathway|Metabolic pathway]] (&lt;small&gt;Links need not be followed&lt;/small&gt;)
** [[Wikipedia:en:Cellular respiration|Cell respiration]] (&lt;small&gt;Follows all links&lt;/small&gt;)

*Read [[Wikipedia:en:Protein_biosynthesis|Protein biosynthesis]] (&lt;small&gt;Follow links as necessary to understand process and terminology; Also included is:&lt;/small&gt;)
** [[Wikipedia:en:Gene_expression|Gene expression]]
*Read [[Wikipedia:en:Cell_division|Cell reproduction]] (&lt;small&gt;The following links are included:&lt;/small&gt;)
** [[Wikipedia:en:Mitosis|Mitosis]]
** [[Wikipedia:en:Cell_cycle|Cell cycle]]

&lt;tt&gt;Questions&lt;/tt&gt;:
#''Have you been able to discern a relationship between genes and basic cell function? If so, is this also a basic cell function, and where do we list it?''   

== Plant Cell Specializations ==

We will learn about the cells of algae and other organisms (e.g., bacteria and fungi) traditionally covered within Botany in later chapters on those organisms (Chapters 5 - 7).  Here, we concentrate on the cells of plants. 

The simplest type of plant cell is called a '''parenchyma cell''' and most of the basic metabolic and reproductive processes of the plant occur in these cells.  A term for ''parenchyma'' cells with chloroplasts, is '''chlorenchyma cells'''.  Other plant cell types that we shall be considering are:

*'''Collenchyma''' ~ living cells with thickened walls for increased support
*'''Sclerenchyma''' ~ lignified dead cells forming fibers for increased support
*'''Epidermal''' ~ surface covering
*'''Cork'''
*'''Xylem tracheid''' ~ single long (up to 1 mm) thin cells for transporting water and support
*'''Xylem vessel''' ~ cells form individual elements in an even longer (up to 1 meter in extreme cases) tube for transporting water 
*'''Meristematic cells''' ~ growth

*Read [[Wikipedia:en:Parenchyma|Parenchyma cell]]

----

[[Botany/Microscopy_laboratory|Laboratory Exercises]] for Chapter 2 &gt;&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;big&gt;[[Botany/Plant_cells_discussion|Discussion of questions]] for Chapter 2&lt;/big&gt; &gt;&gt;&gt;

----
&lt;center&gt;
{{BotanyTOC}} 
&lt;/center&gt;

[[Category:Botany]]</text>
      <sha1>i32eis5ysg9347gt28cmx36n58k5nud</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Botany/Plant structure</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>989</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2677588</id>
      <parentid>2316495</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-06-30T13:56:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>106.69.197.113</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* The Leaf */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;small&gt;&lt;&lt; [[Botany#Contents|Contents Page]] | &lt;&lt; [[Botany/Plant_tissues|Chapter 3]] | &lt;/small&gt;Chapter 4&lt;small&gt; | [[Botany/Plant_reproduction|Chapter 5]] &gt;&gt;|&lt;/small&gt; 
----
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;big&gt;&lt;big&gt;Chapter 4. Plant Vegetative Organs&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/big&gt;  
&lt;/center&gt;
----
&lt;div style=&quot;float:right;margin:0 0 1em 1em;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;[[image:Parrotfeather_reduced.jpg|Myriophyllum aquaticum]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;''The parrot's feather, an aquatic plant (Myriophyllum aquaticum)&lt;br&gt;Click to [[Media:Parrotfeather.jpg| enlarge]] picture''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

== Introduction ==

As was noted in the previous [[Botany/Plant_tissues|chapter]], most plant cells are specialized to a greater or lesser degree, and arranged together in '''tissues'''.  A tissue can be ''simple'' or ''complex'' depending upon whether it is composed of one or more than one type of cell.  Tissues are further arranged or combined into '''organs''' that carry out life functions of the organism.  Plant organs include the '''leaf''', '''stem''', '''root''', and '''reproductive structures'''.  The first three are sometimes called the ''vegetative organs'' and are the subject of exploration in this chapter. Reproductive organs will be covered in [[Botany/Plant_reproduction|Chapter 5]].

The relationships of the organs within a plant body to each other remains an unsettled subject within plant morphology. The fundamental question is whether these are truly different structures, or just modifications of one basic structure (Eames, 1936; Esau, 1965). The plant body is an integrated, functional unit, so the division of a plant into organs is largely conceptual, providing a convenient way of approaching plant form and function. A boundary between stem and leaf is particularly difficult to make, so botanists sometimes use the word '''shoot''' to refer to the stem and its appendages (Esau, 1965).

== The Leaf ==
The plant leaf is an organ whose shape promotes efficient gathering of light for photosynthesis. The form of the leaf must also be balanced against the fact that most of the loss of water a plant might suffer is going to occur at its leaves (transpiration). Leaves are extremely variable in terms of their size, shape, and adornments (such as small hairs on the face of the leaf).

Although the leaves of most plants carry out the same basic functions, there is nonetheless an amazing variety of leaf sizes, shapes, margin types, forms of attachment, ornamentation (hairs), and color. Examine the [[Botany/Leaves (forms)|Leaves (forms)]] page to learn the extensive terminology used to describe this variation. Consider that there are functional reasons for the modifications from a &quot;basic&quot; type.

== The Stem ==
The stem arises during development of the embryo as part of the ''hypocotyl-root axis'', at the upper end of which are one or more cotyledons and the shoot primordium.  

* Read: [[Wikipedia:en:Plant_stem|Stem]]

== The Root ==
The root is the (typically) underground part of the plant axis specialized for both anchoring the plant and absorbing water and minerals. 
* Read: [[Wikipedia:en:Root|Root]] (&lt;small&gt;Follow any links for terms you do not understand and to gain a complete picture of root structural variation&lt;/small&gt;)

::Be sure to read about and understand the meaning of each (at a minimum) of the following terms: '''adventitious roots''', '''endodermis''', '''epidermis''', '''gravitropism''', '''root cap''', '''root hair''', '''stele''', '''taproot'''.

Most of the material you have read discusses the root organ as found in the angiosperms (flowering plants). However, among the vascular plants, only Psilotales lack such an organ, having instead rhizomes that bear hair-like absorbing structures called '''rhizoids''' (Eames, 1936 in Esau, 1965).


'''Questions''':

 4-1. At this point the conceptual differences between cell types, tissues, organs,
      and organisms may be somewhat confusing. Using the leaf as an example, describe
      this structure in a way that considers the cell types, tissues, and organs for
      that part of the leaf where photosynthesis is concentrated.

----
:&lt;Big&gt;[[Botany/Plant_structure_laboratory|Laboratory Exercises]] for Chapter 4 &gt;&gt;&lt;/big&gt;
:&lt;big&gt;[[Botany/Plant_structure_discussion|Discussion of questions]] for Chapter 4 &gt;&gt;&gt;&lt;/big&gt;
----
&lt;center&gt;
{{BotanyTOC}}
&lt;/center&gt;

[[Category:Botany]]</text>
      <sha1>4i4fybg4v9y8lvhs8ndx1l8xxskzyip</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Electrolysis copper sulphate.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>992</id>
    <revision>
      <id>636432</id>
      <parentid>153125</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-11-04T11:03:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Theresa knott</username>
        <id>93</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">drawn by theresa knott

{{GFDL}}
{{Cc-by-sa-2.5}}</text>
      <sha1>ilh8urrgwk7ley762k1hc7q29nke2eq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>GCSE Science/Circuits</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>997</id>
    <revision>
      <id>616045</id>
      <parentid>491239</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-10-18T04:13:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Guanabot</username>
        <id>5478</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>User-controlled Bot: table syntax updated</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[GCSE Science/Electricity]]

You've probably done quite a lot of work in basic electrical circuits in lower school, but we will revise them here so don't worry if you've forgotten them.

Before we start you need to know a whole host of circuit symbols. 

'''Q1)'''See how many of the following you can name:

{| align=&quot;center&quot;
|-
| [[image:Circuit symbols 1.png]]
| &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;  
| [[Image:Circuit symbols 2.png]]
|}

You should already know about half of them. For the others see [[GCSE Science/Circuits answers|here]]. You need to learn all these symbols by heart, but don't worry about that just yet. It's much easier to learn the symbols if you know what the components actually do, and we will be looking at that later on.

==What is a circuit?==

{| align=&quot;right&quot;
|-
| [[Image:Simple bulb and switch circuit.png]]
|}

A circuit is a loop in which electricity can flow.  Consider a simple circuit with a  cell, a switch and a bulb. The current flows from the cell, via the closed switch to the bulb. The bulb lights because the electricity carries energy. '''But''' even after the bulb there current still needs to go around the rest of the loop back to the cell. If there is a break ''anywhere'' in the loop, the bulb will not light. This is a concept that is not all that difficult, yet most people do not understand it. 

Ask a selection of adults you know and many will say:&lt;br&gt;
''&quot;Electricity flows from the cell to the bulb, where it gets used up&quot;''

'''Q2)''' What is wrong with the above statement?

'''Q3)''' Look at the selection of circuits below. What is wrong with each of them?


{| align=&quot;center&quot;
|-
| [[Image:Three wrong circuits.png]]
|}

What we have been looking at so far has been largely revision. You should already be familiar with what a circuit is and how it works. Let's now go on to some more advanced work.


[[GCSE Science/Electrolysis|&lt;&lt; Electrolysis]] | [[GCSE Science/Current, voltage resistance and Ohm's law|Current, voltage resistance and Ohm's law]]

[[Category:GCSE Science]]</text>
      <sha1>48c0k01mxgi5mv1ctl9gkrkvn8rtfsz</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Circuit symbols 1.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>998</id>
    <revision>
      <id>636321</id>
      <parentid>153130</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-11-04T10:54:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Theresa knott</username>
        <id>93</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Some circuit symbols. Drawn by theresa knott

{{GFDL}}
{{Cc-by-sa-2.5}}</text>
      <sha1>6o4ujroaxsc5sc4aa5qvl828v35jyrw</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Circuit symbols 2.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>999</id>
    <revision>
      <id>636322</id>
      <parentid>153131</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-11-04T10:54:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Theresa knott</username>
        <id>93</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">the second lot of circuit symbols for gcse electricity by theresa knott

{{GFDL}}
{{Cc-by-sa-2.5}}</text>
      <sha1>jtj6n0xtvaehu8asmphac1vtmaj7eez</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Botany/Contributors</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1000</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2063479</id>
      <parentid>489723</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-03-04T17:58:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Avicennasis</username>
        <id>314063</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WP:AWB/T|Typo fixing]], typos fixed: persued → pursued (2), contributers → contributors using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;center&gt;
== Contributors ==
&lt;/center&gt;

While Wikibooks offers somewhat clearer opportunities for &quot;authorship&quot; than Wikipedia, there remains the fact that anything put here is really just a contribution, and everyone who furthers the effort is a contributor. In this respect there are no &quot;authors&quot;. If you are interested in developing a particular subject within the field of botany as part of this textbook, please start the module and link it here. We will work out the chapter arrangement after you get started. Of course, you can also just expand on an existing chapter.

*[[w:user:Marshman|Eric Guinther]] is a biologist and environmental consultant living in Kane'ohe, Hawai'i. He envisioned this particular textbook &quot;project&quot; and developed the approach of creating a textbook around articles found in [http://www.Wikipedia.org/ Wikipedia]. By then working specifically on those articles referred to, the quality and quantity of the ''Study Guide to the Science of Botany'' was gradually enhanced.  These efforts were done with the steady help of numerous talented contributors at Wikipedia who, collectively, would have no interest in working on a textbook project per se.  Ultimately, the user of the guide benefits from the textbook's approach: 1) by having more control over the depth into any subtopic pursued and 2) being limited in that pursuit only by that considerable information available at Wikipedia and other linked websites. 

*Others (add your name and thoughts here if you are a serious contributor)

*Other anonymous Wikibook contributors (see individual page histories).

*Numerous other [http://en.wikipedia.org/ Wikipedia] contributors.

&lt;&lt;[[Botany|Return to Contents Page]]

[[Category:Botany]]</text>
      <sha1>mu1dxn48ti8viwr1x0a4u8boqfee1dw</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User:CyberMaus</title>
    <ns>2</ns>
    <id>1002</id>
    <revision>
      <id>153134</id>
      <timestamp>2003-09-08T19:09:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>CyberMaus</username>
        <id>108</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">I started over at en: where my [[en:User:CyberMaus|intro]] is. A short while later, I became intrigued by simple english. Now I've found another area that grabbed me by the scruff of the neck - the Cookbook project.</text>
      <sha1>56bcw55widvy2xnwel5a18q3xx3nzwg</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cookbook talk:Eating for Health</title>
    <ns>103</ns>
    <id>1003</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1553641</id>
      <parentid>1553640</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-06-30T19:30:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Iwatchaltonbrown</username>
        <id>243605</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">IMO there are no &quot;food enemies&quot; as such. Those listed are essential to health. Even LDL, the &quot;bad&quot; cholesterol, is essential to certain metabolic functions. It causes problems when the level is too high or the ratio of LDL to HDL is too high even when the overall cholesterol level is &quot;acceptable&quot;. Perhaps it should be emphasized that any nutrient taken in excess is bad. Even vitamins are toxic or have unpleasant side effects when taken in large amounts. [[User:CyberMaus|CyberMaus]] 20:55, 8 Sep 2003 (UTC)
:I agree. A book on healthy eating should concentrate on good and bad diet, not good and bad foods [[User:Theresa knott|Theresa knott]]

== Charred meat? ==

Can the carcinogenic (free radicals?) effect of eating charred/browned meat be countered by ingesting antioxidants (such as tea) ?

Charred/browned meat is yummy and it would be a shame to avoid it unnecessarilly [[User:Irrevenant|Irrevenant]] 21:48, 7 November 2005 (UTC)

:It seems so... but ingesting the antioxidants and skipping the charred meat would be even better. [[User:AlbertCahalan|AlbertCahalan]] 20:14, 22 April 2006 (UTC)

::I agree, I would hate to have to give up seared or browned meats. I don't think the carcinogens produced during normal cooking are significant enough to warrant total removal from one's diet. [[User:64.238.163.200|64.238.163.200]] 21:33, 22 July 2006 (UTC)

== e coli == 
I am skeptical of the statements made here about organic foods, e-coli and irradiation. I have read reports that ecoli on '''un'''certified organic farms are higher than on commercial farms, but that on certified farms this level is only somewhat higher than commercial farms (characterized by the staff conducting the study as &quot;not significant&quot;). Even so, this does not directly lead to the conclusion that it is &quot;important&quot; for these organic foods to be irradiated. Irradiation has also been accused of negative side effects (though it does have the approval of the FDA). Futhermore, the danger from ecoli is '''much''' higher from meat products, but the current wording singles out organic produce. I do think a general-purpose e-coli warning is probably appropriate... but this is not it. [[User:Kellen|Kellen]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:Kellen|T]]&lt;/sup&gt; 23:33, 12 December 2005 (UTC)

:I got rid of it, even though I mostly agree with it. It didn't fit well. The 600 degree claim was misleading, because there is no single temperature at which bacteria suddenly all die. As far as food dangers go, bacteria are severely underestimated by most people, but ''e coli'' isn't anywhere near being the main danger. (my father is a food microbiologist with his doctorate, so you can be sure I've had far more education about the matter than would be normal) The danger from meat products would be much higher if people treated meat and vegetables the same. Few people eat raw meat though, so vegetables are quite dangerous in actual use. The main danger with meat is that some idiots will handle cooked meat with the same dishes that were used to handle it when raw. Many people are also careless about faucet handles. People don't even think about vegetable contamination. They eat raw vegetables, sometimes without even a rinse. [[User:AlbertCahalan|AlbertCahalan]] 21:41, 22 April 2006 (UTC)

:Food irradiation is an excellent process. It is always used on spices. On other foods it is not used, because bomb-driven hysteria resulted in a mandatory label that looks rather scary. Spices are exempt from the labeling requirement. The dangerous chemical changes caused by food irradiation are the same as those caused by cooking; one can not eliminate all risk. We cook food. Sometimes cooking is far worse than irradiation. Failure to irradiate and/or cook food can hurt you too, via mold toxins for example, so you have to pick your poison. [[User:AlbertCahalan|AlbertCahalan]] 21:41, 22 April 2006 (UTC)

== The article states lettuce as being nutritionally worthless ==

Researching this I discovered that according to www.nutritiondata.com iceberg lettuce actually receives a score of 4.9/5 nutritional rating, therefore, being one of the more nutritional foods available.

== MSG Instead of Salt? ==

Whilst adding salt to food is definitely not very healthy, using MSG as a substitute doesn't seem like a very good idea, considering its bad reputation for destroying neurons in the brain.

:Of course salt is healthy just as long as you don't eat too much, it, like every edible substance has some stuff that the body needs, and table saly has what I think is called iodine. Stating otherwise is blatant and enthusiastic asshattery, douchebaggery, and POVism. This is the kind of thing a former MSG enthusiast would say.

== Healthful? ==

Is there some specific reason not to use &quot;healthy&quot;?
: Ditto. --[[User:Swift|Swift]] ([[User talk:Swift|talk]]) 00:24, 6 December 2008 (UTC)

== Deep Fried Mars Bars ==

This cookbook links to the recipe for Deep Fried Mars Bars 4 times. I have been dieting for some time and I remember when I first started reading about junk food and then getting a very horrble feeling in my entire being untill I ate what I had read about. Therefore this is a horrible cookbook that needs to be altered. --[[User:203.118.177.19|203.118.177.19]] 07:07, 3 November 2007 (UTC)

== Most of this information is worthless ==

Whoever said that MSG destroys neurons is a crazy freak. People complain about Chinese food 'cause it has MSG, but there's more MSG in an Italian meal than a fast-food Chinese, and people don't complain about Italian food syndrome. Plus, whoever wrote this says we should boil meat? What kind of lunatic boils a steak? This article is worthless.

== carrots ==

if you eat too many carrots your skin will turn orange. just look at a former WWII RAF pilot and you'll see. lol i was kidding no i wasn't.</text>
      <sha1>ptvsazziloruu5kt61zd5aq4l67chv4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>GCSE Science/Circuits answers</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1025</id>
    <revision>
      <id>616046</id>
      <parentid>491241</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-10-18T04:13:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Guanabot</username>
        <id>5478</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>User-controlled Bot: table syntax updated</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">
{| align=&quot;center&quot; cellspacing=&quot;5&quot;
|-
| [[image:Circuit symbols 1.png]] ||  Switch (open)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Switch (closed)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Cell&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Battery&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Diode&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Resistor&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Variable resistor
| [[Image:Circuit symbols 2.png]] ||  Bulb&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Fuse&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Thermistor&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Light dependent resistor&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Ammeter&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Voltmeter&lt;br&gt;
|}

Did you get many right? You should already know, cell, battery, bulb, switch and resistor. You will have to learn the others as well before the exam.

[[GCSE Science/Circuits|&lt;&lt;Back]]

[[Category:GCSE Science]]</text>
      <sha1>a0uqa0wjgusq9tc7pzayf53w650oshi</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Botany/Plant reproduction</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1026</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2688535</id>
      <parentid>2688038</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-08-04T08:30:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/131.228.29.15|131.228.29.15]] ([[User talk:131.228.29.15|talk]]) to last version by QuiteUnusual</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">&lt;small&gt;&lt;&lt; [[Botany#Contents|Contents Page]] | [[Botany/Plant structure|Chapter 4]] | &lt;/small&gt;Chapter 5&lt;small&gt; | [[Botany/Plant_morphology|Chapter 6]] &gt;&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 
----
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;big&gt;&lt;big&gt;Chapter 5. Plant Reproduction&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/big&gt;  
&lt;/center&gt;
----
[[Image:P Morc D1252.JPG|right|thumb|360px|Noni (''Morinda citrifolia'') flowers and fruit. Note stages of progressive maturation shown from a cluster of flowers to an accessory fruit.]]

== Vegetative Reproduction ==

Vegetative reproduction is a type of '''asexual reproduction'''&amp;mdash;other terms that apply are ''vegetative propagation,'' ''clonal growth'', or ''vegetative multiplication''. Vegetative '''growth''' is enlargement of the individual plant; vegetative reproduction is any process that results in new plant &quot;individuals&quot; without production of seeds (see ''The Seed'' below) or spores.  It is both a natural process in many, many species as well as one utilized or encouraged by horticulturists and farmers to obtain quantities of economically valuable plants. In this respect, it is a form of cloning that has been carried out by humankind for thousands of years and by &quot;plants&quot; for hundreds of millions of years.

*Read [[Wikipedia:en:Vegetative_reproduction|Vegetative Reproduction]] (&lt;small&gt;Follow all links&lt;/small&gt;)

== Sexual Reproduction ==
=== The Flower ===

The '''flower''' is the reproductive organ of plants classified as ''angiosperms''&amp;mdash;that is, the flowering plants comprising the '''Division Magnoliophyta'''. All plants have the means and corresponding structures for reproducing sexually, and these other cases will be explored in later chapters. However, because '''flowering plants''' are the most conspicuous plants in almost all terrestrial environments, we justifiably devote this chapter to the flowering plants alone.  You will learn how other plant groups (and non-plant groups, such as fungi) reproduce sexually in Section II of the ''The Guide''.  

The basic function of a flower is to produce '''seeds''' through '''sexual reproduction'''. Seeds are the next generation, and serve as the primary method in most plants by which individuals of the species are dispersed across the landscape.  Actual dispersal is, in most species, a function of the '''fruit''': structural parts that typically surround the seed.  But the seed contains the germ of life of the next generation. 

* Read [[Wikipedia:en:Plant sexuality|Plant sexuality]] (&lt;small&gt;Follow links you find interesting, concentrating on acquiring a grasp of the terminology&lt;/small&gt;)
* Read [[Wikipedia:en:Flower|The Flower]] (&lt;small&gt;Follow links you find interesting, but at minimum read each of the following articles&lt;/small&gt;)
** Read [[Wikipedia:en:Sepal|calyx]] - the sepals
** Read [[Wikipedia:en:Petal|corolla]] - the petals
** Read [[Wikipedia:en:Stamen|androecium]] - the stamens
** Read [[Wikipedia:en:Carpel|gynoecium]] - the pistil(s)
::Be sure to read about and understand the meaning of each of the following terms: '''androecium''', '''anthesis''', '''calyx''', '''carpel''', '''corolla''', '''gynoecium''', '''inferior ovary''', '''nectary''', '''perigynous''', '''petal''', '''pistil''', '''pollen''', '''sepal''', '''stamen''', '''superior ovary''', '''syncarpous'''. 
* Read [[Wikipedia:en:Inflorescence|Inflorescence]]
::Be sure to read about and understand the meaning of each of the following terms: '''bract''', '''inflorescence''', '''panicle''', '''raceme''', '''spadix''', '''spikelet'''.

'''Questions''':

 5-1. Do you think the flower structure is in any way responsible for the considerable
      success of flowering plants in populating the earth? 

=== The Seed and Germination===

the primary purpose of the seed is one of preserving the continuity of life&amp;mdash;starting a new generation in a new physical location. For large plants (shrubs and trees), this can be especially important because successful germination and growth close to the parent may be difficult or impossible; the established plant monopolizes light and water resources in its immediate vicinity. Seeds can also serve the function of overwintering or surviving harsh conditions. The entire generation&amp;mdash;every individual&amp;mdash;may die in the Fall or the dry season. In many annual species, only the seed exists during unfavorable dry or cold conditions.  

* [[Wikipedia:en:Seed|The Seed]] (&lt;small&gt;Follow all links on anatomy and function&lt;/small&gt;)
** Read [[Wikipedia:en:Germination|Germination]]

'''needed here an explanation of clonal reproduction of plants... through genets, rhizomes or whatever.  I am not a botanist, please, if you are, explain this.'''

=== The Fruit ===

The fruit is the actual agent of dispersal in most flowering plants.
 
* [[Wikipedia:en:Fruit|The Fruit]]

----
:&lt;big&gt;[[Botany/Plant_reproduction_laboratory_flower|Laboratory Exercises (flowers)]] for Chapter 5 &gt;&gt;&lt;/big&gt;
:&lt;big&gt;[[Botany/Plant_reproduction_laboratory_seed|Laboratory Exercises (seeds)]] for Chapter 5 &gt;&gt;&lt;/big&gt;
:&lt;big&gt;[[Botany/Plant_reproduction_discussion|Discussion of questions]] for Chapter 5 &gt;&gt;&lt;/big&gt;
----
&lt;center&gt;
{{BotanyTOC}}
&lt;/center&gt;

[[Category:Botany]]</text>
      <sha1>m5u1e0dx6evgok3fmi0w0pxwgnh8gjf</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Simple bulb and switch circuit.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1027</id>
    <revision>
      <id>636424</id>
      <parentid>153157</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-11-04T11:00:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Theresa knott</username>
        <id>93</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Drawn by theresa knott

{{GFDL}}
{{Cc-by-sa-2.5}}</text>
      <sha1>7kj2cvz1nvybrdzm9crscjcbmq609rm</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Three wrong circuits.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1028</id>
    <revision>
      <id>636441</id>
      <parentid>153158</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-11-04T11:06:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Theresa knott</username>
        <id>93</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Diagram of broken circuits, drawn by theresa knott

{{GFDL}}
{{Cc-by-sa-2.5}}</text>
      <sha1>6w235sxetvmb0e9xbs3pilr8kyv7nku</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Peas in a bowl.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1029</id>
    <revision>
      <id>636317</id>
      <parentid>153159</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-11-04T10:52:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Theresa knott</username>
        <id>93</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">diagram that demonstrates how current flows in a circuit. Drawn by theresa knott

{{GFDL}}
{{Cc-by-sa-2.5}}</text>
      <sha1>7tk8bvvd6ycx2lstdsm0sb0d6zrpbz8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>GCSE Science/Current, voltage resistance and Ohm's law</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1030</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2263079</id>
      <parentid>2263074</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-02-08T16:07:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jomegat</username>
        <id>12605</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rejected the last 2 text changes (by [[Special:Contributions/88.104.59.45|88.104.59.45]]) and restored revision 2199106 by Recent Runes</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[Electronics]]
[[GCSE Science/Electricity]]
----

==What is electricity anyway?==
So far in this module we have been using words like electricity, current, voltage, and resistance without actually explaining in depth what these words mean. On this page you will learn what these words mean, and how they relate to one another.

===What is electricity on a microscopic level===
Let's think about a wire, made of copper.
You should already know that it is made of particles called copper atoms, which have a positive nucleus surrounded by negative electrons.
We need not concern ourself with the nucleus, because it does not move.
They are stuck in a rigid crystal structure.
Instead we need to look at the electrons. Copper, like all metals, has some loose electrons.
These electrons are not held rigidly by the atoms but are free to roam about anywhere as long as they stay somewhere in the metal.
We call them ''conduction electrons'' because they are the ones that conduct electricity.
To see how electric current flows imagine a small petri dish, with an even smaller one glued inside.
The channel between the two dishes  is then filled with peas.
The channel represents the wires in a circuit, the peas the electrons.


{| align=&quot;right&quot;
|-
| [[Image:Peas in a bowl.png]]
|}

'''Charge''' is the quantity of free charged particles (in this case electrons). The SI unit of charge is the coulomb.

You ''could'' count the electrons, but there are an awful lot of electrons! Each electron carries a ''tiny'' charge, of &amp;minus;1.602×10&lt;sup&gt;-19&lt;/sup&gt; coulomb. We can turn this figure on its head and say that if we grouped together 6.2415&amp;times;10&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt; electrons we would have &amp;minus;1 coulomb of charge.

==Electric field:-==

An electric field is a region where an object experiences a force due to its charge.

The strength of the electric field (electric field strength  E ) is described by considering how much force is experienced by a unit charge (a charge of 1 coulomb) when it's placed in the field. 

The electric field at any point is therefore expressed in newtons per coulomb.

Some fields (such as the field between two parallel charged plates) have the same field strength throughout the field - uniform fields. Others (particularly radial fields due to isolated point charges) do not have constant field strength.


In a battery there is a negative and positive terminal. The conventional current flows from positive to negative (the large line to the small line). Because opposites attract, these charges in the battery will be attracting each other, but they can not move directly to each other through the battery because of the chemical processes. If there is a complete external circuit, this attraction from the battery will give the free electrons in the metal (i.e. the wire) a force which will make them move. If you think about it these electrons are being forced to the other side of the battery because of this attraction. We call this driving force the Electro-motive Force (e.m.f). Emfs are measured in volts, and are sometimes referred to simply as voltage. The larger the emf (the voltage) the more quickly electrons flow round the circuit. What is the rate of flow of the electrons?....the current. so, a larger voltage means a larger current.

== Current ==

Now imagine that you were to put your finger on one pea and push it in a clockwise direction. All the peas would move because they are all touching one another. This is just what happens when an electric current flows.


'''Current''' is the flow of charged particles (the particles are usually electrons).
The SI '''unit''' of current is the ampere (symbol A).

To understand how current is defined think of standing at a given point in the wire. Electrons are flowing past you.



One Ampere is a flow of one coulomb going past every second.

::1 A = 1 C·s&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;  (1 A = 1 C/s)

====Definition of the ampere====


BUT this flow of charge idea is NOT the definition of the ampere. The ampere is defined in terms of the force produced between two wires each carrying identical currents:-


''The ampere is that constant current which, if maintained in two straight parallel conductors of infinite length, of negligible circular cross-section, and placed 1 meter apart in vacuum, would produce between these conductors a force equal to 2 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-7&lt;/sup&gt; newton per meter of length.''

==Voltage==
Having looked at charge and current, we now need to look at what voltage means.

As you know, electrons repel each other. If you hold one electron near another electron, you have to push against it to hold it in place. If you try to bring it even closer, you have to do work (force times distance) to get it to that new position.

The voltage between one point and another is simply how much work per coulomb is required to move any small test charge from point A to point B.

In most electronic components, it doesn't matter much which path the test charge takes in-between point A and point B.

Voltage is related to the ''energy'' of the charges. Let's go back to the peas in the petri dish. They can be pushed slowly or they can be pushed quickly. The faster they go, the more energy they have.  It's a similar situation for the electrons, except the push isn't provided by a finger! It's provided by the battery.

The battery gives the charges energy. This energy is given up to the various components in the circuit, e.g. bulbs, resistors etc. The energy per unit charge is called the voltage (or the potential difference).

====Definition of the volt====

One volt means one joule of energy per coulomb of charge.

More accurately it has 2 definitions:

Electromotive Force is the amount of energy converted from non-electrical to electrical form when driving 1 coulomb of charge around a completed and closed circuit.

Potential Difference is the amount of energy converted from electrical to non-electrical form when driving 1 coulomb of charge around a completed and closed circuit.

The potential difference between 2 points in a conductor is defined as 1 volt, if 1 Joule of energy is converted from electrical form to non-electrical form, when 1 coulomb of charge per second (1 amp) flows through it. Note: This will only occur between 2 points in a conductor, that has a resistance, defined as 1 ohm. See resistance below.

:1 V = 1 J·C&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;  (1 V = 1 J/C)

==Resistance and Ohm's law==

Resistance is easy to understand. It's just how difficult it is for the charges to flow through an electrical component or from one point to another in an electrical circuit. Imagine a group of walkers travelling down a road. They approach a fork in the road. To the left is a flat straight road leading to a nearby town. To the right is a huge mountain, over which a steep and winding road traverses. This road also leads to the nearby town.

Naturally all the walkers chose the left route. Let's now suppose that there are millions of walkers. They are jam packed on the road, and they are all in a hurry to get to the town as quickly as possible. Now when they come to the fork in the road which way should they go? Most will still go to the left, but a few might chose to go to the right, the road is more difficult but there is no traffic jam, so they might get there quicker.

It's a similar thing with moving charges. Like charges repel, so they would rather not pack in very closely together. Some routes, like wires have very low resistance, while other routes like bulbs have much higher resistance. More charges will go down a low resistance route than a high resistance one. The unit of resistance is the ohm, represented by the Greek letter Omega (&amp;Omega;).

===Ohm's Law===
This law relates resistance, current, and voltage. It's very easy to remember because it's obvious when you think about it. 

Let's think of a wire carrying current from a battery, to a bulb then back to the battery. The voltage of the battery provides the energy of the flowing electrons. Let's assume we want to increase the rate of flow of charge. Remember that current is the rate of flow of charge so we want to increase the current.

*'''Increase the voltage''' If we increase the voltage, we increase the energy of the charges. Each charge will then flow faster, so the current will increase. (A fast moving river carries more water per hour than a slow one of the same size). So current must be proportional to voltage.

*'''Increase the number of charges flowing''' The more charges that flow, the bigger the current will be. (A wide river carries more water per hour than an equally fast flowing but narrower one.) The way to increase the number of charges is to ''decrease'' the resistance. So the current must be proportional to 1&amp;divide;Resistance. We say that it is inversely proportional to the resistance.

*'''So''', the current is proportional to the voltage, and is inversely proportional to the resistance.

So &lt;math&gt;Current = Voltage \times \frac{1}{Resistance}&lt;/math&gt;

:::&lt;math&gt;Current = \frac{Voltage}{Resistance}&lt;/math&gt;

Rearranging gives :
:::&lt;math&gt;Voltage = Current \times Resistance&lt;/math&gt;

In symbols:
:::&lt;math&gt;V=IR&lt;/math&gt;

This is Ohm's law. Learn it by heart.

'''Q2)''' A wire has a resistance of two &amp;Omega; and a voltage of 3 V is applied. What is the current?

'''Q3)'''A wire has a 5 V potential difference applied. the current is 10 A, what is the resistance?

'''Q4)''' A current of 2 A is flowing through a wire with a voltage of 20 V. What is the resistance of the wire?

(Remember to give the units for all your answers).



{| bgcolor=&quot;ffeeaa&quot;
|-
| '''Summary'''
|-
|
* The unit of current is the ampere (A), and means one coulomb per second.
* The unit of potential difference is the volt (V), and means one joule per coulomb.
* The unit of resistance is the ohm (&amp;Omega;), and is equal to voltage over current.
* Ohm's law, &lt;math&gt;V=IR&lt;/math&gt;, determines the relationship between these three units.
|}

----
[[GCSE Science/Current, voltage resistance and Ohm's law answers|Answers]] | 
[[GCSE Science/Circuits|&lt;&lt;Circuits]] | [[GCSE Science/Circuits Part2|Circuits Part 2&gt;&gt;]]

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>k5p3pegfac5fuut1qxmjqc8q4jmw3vs</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:Kpjas</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>1031</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1954021</id>
      <parentid>1289417</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-10-21T16:13:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Slovio has been nominated for deletion</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Hey Kpjas, thanks for the work on Othello. Was it hard ? Can we expect more Shakespeare plays to follow ? Did you have to write the script yourself ? --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]
----
If a blessing is all you need and mine is good enough, then go for it ! It took me quite some time to do just one scene of Othello by hand. A little bit of noise due to unexpected variations are no big problem for me; each modern version of Shakespeare's plays has variations due to editorial insight anyways. Any slight errors can be worked out over time, right ? Thanks for your help on this, I am very excited about the opportunities we will have to bring people together for learning. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

:So what did you decide ? Are you going to go for it ? --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

Cool, with Macbeth I see you have not yet given up. Who do we have to talk to tho to enable the annotation feature ? --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

==Importing texts==
Is it possible to use scripts to import other texts, such as the physics book that we started to import over to the site by hand ? It would certainly save a lot of tedious work. --[[User:Karl Wick|Karl Wick]]

==Protecting Shakespeare texts==
Hello Kpjas,

I am feeling very tired with deleting the vandalism on Romeo and Juliet. I cannot revert to your version, because I do not know how

This has been done on 2 acts (Act 3, Scenes 1 and 3) by at least 6 separate IPs, during the past 2 days (8-9 June 2004).

Since you are the one who designed these pages (and will almost certainly have to retype Scene 3 of Act 3), would you consider protecting them?

Thank you very much,

[[User:EuropracBHIT|EuropracBHIT]] 04:17, 9 Jun 2004 (UTC)

== wikification of slovio ==

Great work! I'll continue writing the next lesson tomorrow :) --[[User:Dcabrilo|Dcabrilo]] 06:35, 19 July 2005 (UTC)

== Re:Health science bookshelf ==

[[User:Mike.lifeguard]] has done a little bit of work over on the health sciences bookshelf. Specifically, the [[First Aid]] book was his masterpiece. I guess I don't really understand what kinds of problems you are talking about with copyright. What kinds of unforeseeable legal problems are you anticipating? We're pretty flexible, as long as you aren't straight copying content that doesn't belong to you. --'''Whiteknight'''&amp;nbsp;([[User:Whiteknight|Page]])&amp;nbsp;([[User talk:Whiteknight|Talk]]) 23:05, 25 September 2008 (UTC)

:Okay, I see what you are saying. That page you mentioned does look a little suspect, however going back [http://en.wikibooks.org/w/index.php?title=Pharmacology/Antibiotics&amp;oldid=950848 a few revisions] shows us a page that seems less likely to be problematic. If there is something you suspect is a copy+paste violation, do a best effort google search to double check. If things do go bad, we can try, in order of most disruptivity: (1) reverting to a clean revision on the page, (2) deleting the entire page but not the surrounding book, and finally (3) deleting the book. Things would have to be pretty bad, and obviously so, if we were going to resort to option #3.
:If a page doesn't appear to be a copyvio, or if it appears so but you can't confirm it, or if nobody raises an allegation about it, don't worry about it. --'''Whiteknight'''&amp;nbsp;([[User:Whiteknight|Page]])&amp;nbsp;([[User talk:Whiteknight|Talk]]) 22:46, 26 September 2008 (UTC)

==[[:Slovio]]==
{{tmbox|type=delete|text=
'''[[:Slovio|Slovio]] has been nominated for deletion. Please [[Wikibooks:Requests for deletion#Slovio|share your thoughts]].'''&lt;br/&gt;You are being notified because you have contributed to this work. If you haven't read it already, please see our [[WB:DP|deletion policy]]. &amp;ndash;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Adrignola|Adrignola]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Adrignola|talk]]&lt;/small&gt; 16:13, 21 October 2010 (UTC)}}</text>
      <sha1>dh0ttffe78od4u9otxwbdfly627dg9k</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:237trimethyloctane.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1032</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748847</id>
      <parentid>746309</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-02-09T19:52:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>lftdbfdb9bftwmpa42ewbdhqaw7jksr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:267trimethyloctane.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1033</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748846</id>
      <parentid>746310</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-02-09T19:52:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>lftdbfdb9bftwmpa42ewbdhqaw7jksr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:237trimethyloctanelines.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1034</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748845</id>
      <parentid>746308</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-02-09T19:52:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Whiteknight</username>
        <id>10714</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Licensing==
{{GFDL}}</text>
      <sha1>lftdbfdb9bftwmpa42ewbdhqaw7jksr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>