<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.9.xsd" version="0.9" xml:lang="en">
  <page>
    <title>Organic Chemistry/Haloalkanes</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1118</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2683948</id>
      <parentid>2683936</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-07-23T14:19:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rejected the last text change (by [[Special:Contributions/36.253.65.42|36.253.65.42]]) and restored revision 2649955 by 78.26</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">'''Haloalkanes''' are alkanes that contain one or more members of the halogen family. The halogens found in organic molecules are chlorine, bromine, fluorine, and iodine. Some texts refer to this class of compounds as '''halogenoalkanes''' or '''alkyl halides'''. This text will frequently use both '''haloalkane''' and '''alkyl halide''', so it's important to remember that they are the same thing.

''Note:'' The X in R-X represents a generic halogen atom.

=Preparation=

Methods for preparation are found elsewhere in this text:

*Preparation from [[Organic_Chemistry/Alcohols#Conversion_of_alcohols_to_haloalkanes|Alcohols]] (nucleophilic substitution)

*Preparation from [[Alkanes]] (radical substitution)

*Preparation from [[Organic_Chemistry/Alkenes#Electrophilic_addition|Alkenes]] (electrophilic addition)
*Preparation by halogen exchange.*It is generally used for preparing iodoalkanes.
*Preparation from silver salts of acids*

=Properties=

==Naming Haloalkanes==

Haloalkanes are named by adding a prefix to the name of the alkane from which they are derived. The prefix denotes the particular halogen used.

'''F''' = ''Fluoro-''&lt;br&gt;
'''Cl''' = ''Chloro-''&lt;br&gt;
'''Br''' = ''Bromo-''&lt;br&gt;
'''I''' = ''Iodo-''&lt;br&gt;

If other substituents need to be named, all prefixes are still put in alphabetical order. When necessary, numbers identify substituent locations.

===Example names of haloalkanes===

{| CELLPADDING=&quot;3&quot;
|-
|
 || '''IUPAC name''' || '''Common name'''
|-
| CH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;—F || Fluoromethane || Methyl fluoride
|-
| CH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;—Cl || Chloromethane || Methyl chloride
|-
| CH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;—Br || Bromomethane || Methyl bromide
|-
| CH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;—I || Iodomethane || Methyliodide
|-
| F—CH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;—F || Difluoromethane
| Methylene fluoride
|-
| Cl—CH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;—Cl || Dichloromethane
| Methylene chloride
|-
| F—CH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;—Cl || Chlorofluoromethane
|
|-
| CHBrClF || Bromochlorofluoromethane ||
|-
| HCCl&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; || Trichloromethane
| Chloroform
|-
| CHX&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; || Haloforms (X=halogen) || 
|-
| CCl&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; || Tetrachloromethane
| Carbon tetrachloride
|-
| CH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;CHCl&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; || 1,1-Dichloroethane
|
|-
| [[Image:Dibromomethylcyclohexane.png]]
| (Dibromomethyl)cyclohexane ||
|-
| [[Image:Dibromomethylcyclohexane2.png]]
| Equatorial (Dibromomethyl)cyclohexane
|
|-
| [[Image:1,6-Dichloro-2,3,5-trimethy.png]]
| 1,6-Dichloro-2,5-dimethylhexane ||
|-
| [[Image:1,1-Dichloro-3-methylcyclo.png|50 px]]
| 1,1-Dichloro-3-methylcyclobutane ||
|}

==Physical properties==

'''R-X bond polarity:''' C—F &gt; C—Cl &gt; C—Br &gt; C—I

&lt;center&gt;
{|
|'''atom''' &lt;nowiki&gt;| &lt;/nowiki&gt;
|''' electronegativity''' &lt;nowiki&gt;| &lt;/nowiki&gt;
|''' difference from C''' (= 2.5) &lt;nowiki&gt;| &lt;/nowiki&gt;
|-
|F
|4.0
|1.5
|-
|Cl
|3.0
|0.5
|-
|Br
|2.8
|0.3
|-
|I
|2.5
|0.0
|}
&lt;/center&gt;

The difference in electronegativity of the carbon-halogen bonds range from 1.5 in C-F to almost 0 in C-I. This means that the C-F bond is extremely polar, though not ionic, and the C-I bond is almost nonpolar.

'''Physical appearance:''' Haloalkanes are colourless when pure. However bromo and iodo alkanes develop colour when exposed to light. Many volatile halogen compounds have sweet smell.

'''Boiling point:''' Haloalkanes are generally liquids at room temperature. Haloalkanes generally have a boiling point that is higher than the alkane they are derived from. This is due to the increased molecular weight due to the large halogen atoms and the increased intermolecular forces due to the polar bonds, and the increasing polarizabilty of the halogen.

For the same alkyl group, the boiling point of haloalkanes decreases in the order RI &gt; RBr &gt; RCl &gt; RF.This is due to the increase in [[w:van der Waals forces|van der Waals forces]] when the size and mass of the halogen atom increases.

For isomeric haloalkanes, the boiling point decrease with increase in branching. But boiling points of dihalobenzenes are nearly same; however the para-isomers have higher melting points as it fits into the crystal lattice better when compared to ortho- and meta-isomers.

'''Density:''' Haloalkanes are generally more dense than the alkane they are derived from and usually more dense than water. Density increases with the number of carbon and halogen atom. It also increases with the increase in mass of halogen atom.

'''Solubility:''' The haloalkanes are only very slightly soluble in water, but dissolves in organic solvents. This is because for dissolving haloalkanes in water the strong hydrogen bonds present in the latter has to be broken. When dissolved in organic (non polar) solvents, the intermolecular attractions are almost same as that being broken.

'''Bond Length:''' C—F &lt; C—Cl &lt; C—Br &lt; C—I

&lt;center&gt;
{|
|'''bond'''
|'''length''' (pm)
|-
|C-F
|138
|-
|C-Cl
|177
|-
|C-Br
|193
|-
|C-I
|214
|}
&lt;/center&gt;

Larger atoms means larger bond lengths, as the orbitals on the halogen is larger the heavier the halogen is. In F, the orbitals used to make the bonds is 2s and 2p, in Cl, it's 3s and 3p, in Br, 4s and 4p, and in I, 5s and 5p. The larger the principal quantum number, the bigger the orbital. This is somewhat offset by the larger effective nuclear charge, but not enough to reverse the order.

==Chemical properties==

'''Bond strength:''' C—F &gt; C—Cl &gt; C—Br &gt; C—I

&lt;center&gt;
{|
|'''bond'''
|'''strength''' (kJ mol&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;)
|-
|C-F
|484
|-
|C-Cl
|338
|-
|C-Br
|276
|-
|C-I
|238
|}
&lt;/center&gt;

The orbitals C uses to make bonds are 2s and 2p. The overlap integral is larger the closer the principal quantum number of the orbitals is, so the overlap is larger in the bonds to lighter halogens, making the bond formation energetically favorable.

'''Bond reactivity:''' C—F &lt; C—Cl &lt; C—Br &lt; C—I

Stronger bonds are more difficult to break, making them less reactive. In addition, the reactivity can also be determined by the stability of the corresponding anion formed in solution. One of the many trends on the periodic table states that the largest atoms are located on the bottom right corner, implying that iodine is the largest and fluorine being the smallest. When fluorine leaves as fluoride (if it does) in the reaction, it is not so stable compared to iodide. Because there are no resonance forms and inductive stabilizing effects on these individual atoms, the atoms must utilize their own inherent abilities to stabilize themselves. Iodide has the greatest surface area out of these four elements, which gives it the ability to better distribute its negative charge that it has obtained. Fluorine, having the least surface area, is much more difficult to stabilize. This is the reason why iodine is the best leaving group out of the four halogens discussed.

=Reactions=

'''Determination of Haloalkanes:''' A famous test used to determine if a compound is a haloalkane is the Beilstein test, in which the compound tested is burned in a loop of copper wire.  The compound will burn green if it is a haloalkane. The numbers of fluorine, chlorine, bromine and iodine atoms present in each molecule can be determined using the sodium fusion reaction, in which the compound is subjected to the action of liquid sodium, an exceptionally strong reducing agent, which causes the formation of sodium halide salts. Qualitative analysis can be used to discover which halogens were present in the original compound; quantitative analysis is used to find the quantities.

==Substitution reactions of haloalkanes==

R-X bonds are very commonly used throughout organic chemistry because their polar bonds make them reasonably reactive. In a '''substitution reaction''', the halogen (X) is replaced by another substituent (Y). The alkyl group (R) is not changed.


{| WIDTH=&quot;75%&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;background-color: #FFF7F7; border: solid 1px #FFBDBD; padding: 1em;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; |
The &quot;''':'''&quot; in a chemical equation represents a pair of unbound electrons.
|}


{| WIDTH=&quot;75%&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;background-color: #F3F3FF; border: solid 1px #D6D6FF; padding: 1em;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; |
'''A general substitution reaction'''

Y: + R—X &amp;rarr; R—Y + X:
|}

Substitutions involving haloalkanes involve a type of substition called '''Nucleophilic substitution''', in which the substituent Y is a '''nucleophile'''. A nucleophile is an electron pair donor. The nucleophile replaces the halogen, an ''electrophile'', which becomes a '''leaving group'''. The leaving group is an electron pair acceptor. Nuclephilic substition reactions are abbreviated as S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt; reactions.


{| WIDTH=&quot;75%&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;background-color: #FFF7F7; border: solid 1px #FFBDBD; padding: 1em;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; |
&quot;Nu&quot; represents a generic nucleophile.
|}


{| WIDTH=&quot;75%&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;background-color: #F3F3FF; border: solid 1px #D6D6FF; padding: 1em;&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; |

&lt;H2&gt;General nucleophilic substitution reactions&lt;/H2&gt;

Nu:&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; + R—X &amp;rarr; R—Nu + X:&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Nu: + R—X &amp;rarr; R—Nu&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; + X:&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;
|}

&lt;center&gt;
'''Common Nucleophiles'''

{| CELLPADDING=&quot;3&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
| '''Reagent''' || '''Nucleophile''' || '''Name''' || Product || Product name
|-
| NaOH/KOH || :O&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;H || Hydroxide || R—OH || Alcohol
|-
| NaOR' || :O&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;R' || Alkoxide || R—O—R' || Ether
|-
| ||:S&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;H || Hydrosulfide || R—SH || Thiol
|-
| NH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; || :NH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; || Ammonia || R—NH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; || Alkylammonium ion
|-
| KCN || :C&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;N || Cyanide || R—CN || Nitrile
|-
| AgCN || Ag-CN: || Silver cyanide || R-NC || isonitrile
|-
| || :C&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;equiv;C—H || Acetylide
| R-C&amp;equiv;C—H || Alkyne
|-
| NaI || :I&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; || Iodide || R—I || Alkyl Iodide
|-
|R'&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt;M&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; || :R'&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; || Carbanion || R-R' || Alkane
|-
| KNO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; ||O=N&amp;mdash;O || Nitrite || R&amp;ndash;O&amp;mdash;N=O || Alkyl nitrite
|-
| AgNO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; ||Ag&amp;mdash;&amp;Ouml;&amp;mdash;N=O || Silver nitrite ||  R&amp;mdash;NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; || Nitroalkane
|-
| LiAlH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; || H || Hydrogen ||  RH || alkane
|-
| R'COOAg || R'COO&lt;sup&gt;-&lt;/sup&gt; || Alkanoate || R'COOR || Ester
|}
&lt;/center&gt;


'''Example:''' Suggest a reaction to produce the following molecule.

[[Image:1-ethoxy-3-methylbutane.gif]]
 

'''Answer:'''

[[Image:1-bromo-3-methylbutane.gif]]&lt;font size=5&gt;+&lt;/font&gt;[[File:Ethanolat-Ion.svg|150px|Ethanolate]]

&lt;font size=5&gt;OR&lt;/font&gt;

[[Image:3-methylbutan-1-olate.gif]]&lt;font size=5&gt;+&lt;/font&gt;[[File:Bromoethane.png|120px|Bromoethane]]

''Any halogen could be used instead of Br''

===Reaction mechanisms===

Nucleophilic substitution can occur in two different ways. S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;2 involves a '''backside attack'''. S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;1 involves a '''carbocation intermediate'''.

'''S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;2 mechanism'''
[[File:backsideattack.gif|frame|center|Illustration of the Sn2 mechanism. First, the electrons in the nucleophile attack the central carbon atom from the side opposite the leaving group (in this case, a halogen). The electrons forming the bond between the central carbon atom and the halogen move to the halogen, causing the halogen to leave the molecule.]]

'''S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;1 mechanism'''
[[File:sn1mechanism.gif|frame|center|Illustration of the Sn1 mechanism. First, in the presence of a polar solvent, the C-X bond breaks, forming the carbocation. This carbocation intermediate is highly reactive. In this case, it reacts with water. Note that the water may attack from either side.]]

===Comparison of S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;1 and S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;2 mechanism===

'''Stereochemistry:''' &lt;br&gt;
S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;2 - Configuration is inverted (i.e. R to S and vice-versa). &lt;br&gt;
S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;1 - Product is a mixture of inversion and retention of orientation because the carbocation can be attacked from either side. In theory the products formed are usually racemic due to the 50% change of attack from the planar conformation. Interestingly, the amount of the inverted product is often up to 20% greater than the amount of product with the original orientation. Saul Winstein has proposed that this discrepancy occurs through the leaving group forming an ion pair with the substrate, which temporarily shields the carbocation from attack on the side with the leaving group. &lt;br&gt;

'''Rate of reaction:'''&lt;br&gt;
S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;2 - Rate depends on concentrations of both the haloalkane and the nucleophile. S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;2 reactions are fast.&lt;br&gt;
S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;1 - Rate depends only on the concentration of the haloalkane. The carbocation forms much slower than it reacts with other molecules. This makes S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;1 reactions slow.&lt;br&gt;

'''Role of solvent:'''&lt;br&gt;
S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;2 - Polar aprotic solvents favored. Examples: Acetone, THF (an ether), dimethyl sulfoxide, n,n-dimethylformamide, hexamethylphosphoramide (HMPA).&lt;br&gt;
Nonpolar solvents will also work, such as carbon tetrachloride (CCl&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;br&gt;
Protic solvents are the worst type for S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;2 reactions because they &quot;cage,&quot; or solvate, the nucleophile, making it much less reactive.&lt;br&gt;
S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;1 - Polar protic solvents favored. Examples: H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O, Formic acid, methanol.&lt;br&gt;
Aprotic solvents will work also, but protic solvents are better because they will stabilize the leaving group, which is usually negatively charged, by solvating it. Nonpolar solvents are the worst solvent for S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;1 reactions because they do nothing to stabilize the carbocation intermediate.&lt;br&gt;

'''Role of nucleophile:'''&lt;br&gt;
S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;2 - Good nucleophiles favored&lt;br&gt;
S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;1 - Any nucleophile will work (since it has no effect on reaction rate)&lt;br&gt;

'''Carbocation stability:'''&lt;br&gt;
3&lt;sup&gt;&amp;deg;&lt;/sup&gt; carbon - most stable = S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;1 favored&lt;br&gt;
2&lt;sup&gt;&amp;deg;&lt;/sup&gt; carbon - less stable = either could be favored&lt;br&gt;
1&lt;sup&gt;&amp;deg;&lt;/sup&gt; carbon - seldom forms = S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;2 favored&lt;br&gt;
CH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; - never forms = S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;2 favored&lt;br&gt;
The reason why the tertiary carbocation is most favored is due to the inductive effect. In the carbocation intermediate, there is a resulting formal charge of +1 on the carbon that possessed the haloalkane. The positive charge will attract the electrons available. Because this is tertiary, meaning that adjacent carbon atoms and substituents are available, it will provide the most electron-density to stabilize this charge.

===Example===

Predict whether the following reactions will undergo S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;2 or S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;1 and tell why.

1:
[[File:haloalkanemechanismsproblem1.gif|border|center]]

2:
[[File:haloalkanemechanismsproblem2.gif|border|center]]

3:
[[File:haloalkanemechanismsproblem3.gif|border|center]]

'''Answers:'''&lt;br&gt;
1) S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;2. Good nucleophile, polar solvent.&lt;br&gt;
2) S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;1. Tertiary carbon, polar solvent. Very slow reaction rate.&lt;br&gt;
3) S&lt;sub&gt;N&lt;/sub&gt;2. Primary carbon, good nucleophile, nonpolar solvent.&lt;br&gt;

==Grignard reagents==

Grignard reagents are created by reacting magnesium metal with a haloalkane. The magnesium atom gets between the alkyl group and the halogen atom with the general reaction:

R-Br + Mg &amp;rarr; R-Mg-Br

Gringard reagents are very reactive and thus provide a means of organic synthesis from haloalkanes. For example, adding water gives the alcohol R-OH.
Basic:
R-X + Mg → R-Mg-X
For example
(X=Cl and R=CH3):
CH3-Cl + Mg → CH3MgCl
(methylmagnesiumchloride)

==Elimination reactions==

With alcoholic potassium hydroxide, haloalkanes lose H-X and form the corresponding alkene. Very strong bases such as KNH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;/NH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; convert vic-dihalides (haloalkanes with two halogen atoms on adjacent carbons) into alkynes.

&lt;noinclude&gt;
----

[[Organic Chemistry/Stereochemistry|&lt;&lt; Stereochemistry]] | Haloalkanes | [[Organic Chemistry/Alcohols|Alcohols &gt;&gt;]]
&lt;/noinclude&gt;

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>jmcp33gh6uz3wqegpsfht2emekduy06</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>US History/Early Colonial Period</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1119</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2246979</id>
      <parentid>2246973</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-01-05T20:49:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>QuiteUnusual</username>
        <id>134830</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/68.99.115.15|68.99.115.15]] ([[User talk:68.99.115.15|talk]]) to last version by QuiteUnusual</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">== The Arrival of Columbus ==

Christopher Columbus and three ships - the ''Ni&amp;ntilde;a'', the ''Pinta'', and the ''Santa Maria'' - set sail on August 3, 1492. On October 12, a lookout cried out that he had sighted land. The crew set foot on an island that day, naming it San Salvador. It is unknown which exact island was discovered by Columbus. (Note that the island presently called San Salvador is so-called in honor of Columbus' discovery; it is not necessarily the one on which Columbus set foot.)

The Native Americans inhabiting the islands were described as &quot;Indians&quot; by Columbus, who had believed that he had discovered the East Indies (modern Indonesia). In reality, he had found an island in the Caribbean. He continued to explore the area, returning to Spain. Columbus' misconception that he found Asia was corrected years later by the Italian explorer Amerigo Vespucci, after whom ''America'' may be named.

== The Protestant Reformation ==

In Europe, the power of the Pope and the influence of Catholicism was undoubted. The Catholic religion affected every aspect of politics on the continent. However, in the sixteenth century, the conditions were ripe for reform. Gutenberg's printing press made the spread of ideas much easier. The influence of nationalism grew, and rulers began to resent the power possessed by the Pope. 

The Protestant movement may have commenced earlier, but the publication of ''Ninety-Five Theses'' by Martin Luther in 1517 spurred on the revolution within the Church. Luther attacked the Church's theology, which, he believed, misrepresented The Bible and placed too much authority in the hands of the clergy, and wished to reform the Church. After being excommunicated, Luther published many books on Reform. Luther's works were most
influential in Germany and Scandinavia.

Persons other than Luther championed the cause of Reform. In Switzerland, Huldreich Zwingli advanced Protestant ideas, which mostly affected his home country. Similarly, Frenchman John Calvin helped the spread of Protestantism in France and the Netherlands.

English Protestantism resulted from the direct influence of the British monarch.  Henry VIII (1509-1547) sought to divorce his wife, Catherine of Aragon, because she had failed to produce a viable male heir to the throne.  When his divorce led to excommunication by the Pope, Henry simply declared the entire country free of Catholic domination and a bastion of Protestantism.  Henry reasoned that England could survive under its own religious regulation (Anglican) and he named himself head of the church.

== Elizabethan England ==

'''Elizabethan Succession'''&lt;br&gt;

After Henry VIII died, he was succeeded by his son Edward VI (1547-1553) who reigned briefly before dying.  Edward's death led to the ascension of Henry's daughter by Catherine, Mary I (1553-1558).  A staunch Catholic, Mary sought to return England back to the Catholic church.  Her religious zeal and persecution of Protestants earned her the nickname, &quot;Bloody Mary.&quot;  After a short reign, she was succeeded by her half-sister, Elizabeth.  Elizabeth I (1558-1603) was the daughter of Henry's second wife, Anne Boleyn.  Her ascendency to the throne resulted when neither of her half siblings, Edward and Mary, produced an heir to the throne.  

'''Religious Reform'''&lt;br&gt;

Under her siblings' reign, the nation constantly battled religious fervor as it sought to identify itself as either Protestant or Catholic.  Henry VIII had severed ties with the Roman Catholic Church upon his excommunication after divorcing Catherine of Aragon.  He established the Church of England (the precursor to the Anglican Church) as the official state religion and named himself, not the Pope, as its head.  Under Mary, the country returned to Catholic rule.  The Elizabethan Age brought stability to English government. Elizabeth sought a compromise (the Elizabethan Settlement) which returned England to a nation governed by Protestant theology with a Catholic ritual.  Elizabeth called Parliament in 1559 to consider the Reformation Bill that re-established an independent Church of England and redefined the sacrament of communion.  Parliament also approved the Act of Supremacy, establishing ecclesiastical authority with the monarch.

'''Economic Reform'''&lt;br&gt;

Elizabeth's far more important response was to stabilize the English economy following the 1551 collapse of the wool market.  To respond to this economic crisis, Elizabeth used her power as monarch to shift the supply-demand curve.  She expelled all non-English wool merchants from the empire.  Her government placed quotas on the amount of wool that could be produced while also encouraging manors to return to agricultural production.  She also started trading directly with the Spanish colonies in direct violation of their tariff regulations.  This maritime violation would later result in an attack on England by the Spanish Armada in 1588.

Queen Elizabeth was a very popular monarch.  Her people followed her in war and peace.  She remained unmarried until her death, probably through a reluctance to share any power and preferring a series of suitors.  This gave her the name,  ''the Virgin Queen,'' and in honor of her, a colony was named ''Virginia'' a few years after her death.

In the aftermath of the Armada's overwhelming defeat and building on the development of a strong fleet started by Henry VIII, England began to gain recognition as a great naval power. Nationalism in England increased tremendously. Thoughts of becoming a colonial power were inspired. These thoughts were aided by the fact that the defeated Spanish lost both money and morale, and would be easy to oppose in the New World.

== Early Colonial Ventures ==

'''Richard Hakluyt'''

In 1584, Richard Hakluyt proposed a strong argument for expansion of English settlement into the new world.  With his ''Discourse Concerning Western Planting,'' Hakluyt argued that creating new world colonies would greatly benefit England.  The colonies could easily produce raw materials that were unavailable in England.  By establishing colonies, England would assure itself of a steady supply of materials that it currently purchased from other world powers.  Second, inhabited colonies would provide a stable market for English manufactured goods.  Finally, as the economic incentives were not enough, the colonies could provide a home for disavowed Englishmen.

'''Roanoke'''

The English had already begun the exploration of the New World prior to the Armada's defeat. In 1584, Queen Elizabeth granted Sir Walter Raleigh a charter authorizing him to explore the island of Roanoke, which is part of what is now North Carolina. 

Between 1584 and 1586, Raleigh financed expeditions to explore the island of Roanoke and determine if the conditions were proper for settlement. In 1586, about a hundred men were left on the island. They struggled to survive, being reduced to eating dogs. They were, however, rescued- except for fifteen men whose fate remained a mystery.

After another expedition in 1587, another group of men, women, and children- a total of more than one-hundred people- remained on the island. Governor John White of the Roanoke colony discovered from a local Native American tribe that the fifteen men who were not rescued were killed by a rival tribe. While attempting to gain revenge, White's men killed members of a friendly tribe and not the members of the tribe that allegedly killed the fifteen men.

Having thus strained relations with the Natives, the settlers could not survive easily. John White decided to return to England in 1587 and return with more supplies. When he returned, England faced war against Spain. Thus delayed, White could not return to Roanoke until 1590. When he did return, White discovered that Roanoke was abandoned. All that gave clue to the fate of the colony was the word ''Croatan,'' the name of a nearby Native American tribe, carved out on to a tree. No attempt was made to discover the actual cause of the disappearance until several years later.

There are only theories as to the cause of the loss of Roanoke. There are two major possibilities. Firstly, the settlers may have been killed by the Natives. Second, the settlers may have assimilated themselves into the Native tribes. But there is no evidence that settles the matter beyond doubt.

==Review Questions==
Use the content in this chapter and/or from external sources to answer the following questions. Remember to properly cite any sources used.

#Identify or explain the significance of the following people:&lt;br&gt;(a) Christopher Columbus&lt;br&gt;(b) Martin Luther&lt;br&gt;(c) King Henry VIII&lt;br&gt;(d) Richard Hakluyt&lt;br&gt;(e) Elizabeth I&lt;br&gt;(f) Sir Walter Raleigh&lt;br&gt;
#What primary factor(s) led to the shift from Catholicism to Protestant belief in England?
#Why did King Henry VIII establish the Church of England?  How did this influence the English Reformation?
#Differentiate between Elizabeth I's policies and Henry VIII's. What attitudes did the English have toward Elizabeth and her rule?
#What did the defeat of the Spanish Armada symbolize to all of Europe?
#What difficulties did the colonists of Raleigh face between 1584 and 1587? What was the fate of the colony?

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>p221n1gshdxcw73t5ea6xlpioftmh8w</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>US History/English Colonies</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1121</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2718069</id>
      <parentid>2716649</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-25T17:26:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pittsburgh Poet</username>
        <id>1449338</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 2716649 by [[Special:Contributions/Takeitupmyass|Takeitupmyass]] ([[User talk:Takeitupmyass|discuss]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">== Patterns of Colonization ==

The islands of Great Britain went through centuries of turmoil in the Renaissance, resulting in the political and religious foundation of the Church of England, the British Civil War, and total transformation of economic, political, and legal systems. Yet through this time, despite pressure from other nations and America's own Natives, English colonies were planted and thrived. These colonies were founded, organized, and maintained as a set of diverse states with integral ties. 

American colonization was funded in three different ways. In one plan, '''corporate colonies''' were established by joint stock companies. A joint stock company was a project in which people would invest shares of stock into building a new colony. Depending on the success of the colony, each investor would receive profit based on the shares he bought. This method of investing proved to be less risky than starting a colony from scratch, and in the process each investor could have some influence on how the colony was run. These investors often elected their own public officials. (An example of a joint stock company on another continent was the British East India Company.) Virginia was settled in this way.

'''Proprietary colonies''' were owned by a person or family, who could make laws and appoint officials as he or they pleased. The colony's development was often a direct result of this ownership. Charles II granted William Penn the territory now known as Pennsylvania. Penn gave refuge to Quakers, a group of millenialist Protestants who opposed the Church of England, in his new colony. (Quakers did not have ministers and did not hold to civil or religious inequality, making them a dangerous element in hierarchical societies.) Penn was an outspoken Quaker and had written many pamphlets defending the Quaker faith. He also invited settlers from other countries and other Protestant minorities, and even some Catholics. 

Finally, '''royal colonies''' were under the direct control of the King, who usually appointed a Royal Governor. The resulting settlement was not necessarily identical to England. For example, England broke with Catholicism during the reign of Henry the Eighth, and the Old Faith was seen not only as religious heresy but the prelude to domination by other countries. Yet Maryland's grant of toleration of Catholics was granted as a boon from the British Crown. In 1634, Lord Baltimore appointed George Calvert of England to settle a narrow strip of land north of Virginia and south of Pennsylvania as a Catholic colony via a royal charter. Fifteen years later, in 1649, he signed the Act of Toleration, which proclaimed religious freedom for its colonists. Despite the original charter, Protestants later became the majority faith. After Lord Baltimore's death several years later, Margaret Brent, the wife of an esteemed landowner in Maryland, executed his will as governor of the colony. She defied gender roles in the colonies by being the first woman of non-royal heritage to govern an English colony.

== Massachusetts Bay Colony ==
The Massachusetts Bay Colony, another corporate colony, was founded as a place far from England where its religious dissenters could live. The Puritans, a group of radical Protestants who wanted what they called a return to the faith of the Bible, suffered torture and execution because they disagreed with the official Church of England. In 1620, forty-one Puritans (who called themselves Pilgrims) sailed for the new world. Their own contemporary accounts show that the Pilgrims originally intended to settle the Hudson River region near present day Long Island, New York. Once Cape Cod was sighted, they turned south to head for the Hudson River, but encountered treacherous seas and nearly shipwrecked. They then decided to return to Cape Cod rather than risk another attempt to head south. After weeks of scouting for a suitable settlement area, the Mayflower's passengers finally landed at Plymouth in present-day Massachusetts on December 26, 1620.

[[File:The Mayflower Compact 1620 cph.3g07155.jpg|thumb|Passengers of the Mayflower signing the &quot;Mayflower Compact&quot;]]

William Bradford, who was selected as a governor after the death of John Carver, wrote a journal that helps us to better understand the hardships colonists endured, encounters with the Native Americans, and ultimately, the success of the colony. The Pilgrims agreed to govern themselves in the manner set forth in the Mayflower Compact, which signed on the Pilgrims' ship, The Mayflower. After two years they abandoned the communal form of partnership begun under the Compact and in 1623 assigned individual plots of land to each family to work.  

Ten years later, the joint-stock Massachusetts Bay Company acquired a charter from King Charles of England. The colony of Plymouth was eventually absorbed by Massachusetts Bay, but it remained separate until 1691. 

A large group of Pilgrims later migrated to the new colony of Massachusetts Bay. In keeping with its mother Church of England, the colony did not provide religious freedom. It only allowed (male) Puritans the right to vote, established Puritanism as the official religion of the colony in The Act of Toleration, and punished people who did not go to their Church.

== New York ==
Other countries used the joint-stock company to fund exploration. In 1609, the Dutch East India company discovered a territory on the eastern coast of North America, from latitude 38 to 45 degrees north. This was an expedition in the yacht Halve Maen (&quot;Half Moon&quot;) commanded by Henry Hudson. Adriaen Block and Hendrick Christiaensz explored the territory from 1611 until 1614. In March of 1614 the States General, the governing body of the Netherlands, proclaimed exclusive patent for trade in the New World. The States General issued patents for development of New Netherland as a private commercial venture. Ft. Nassau was swiftly built in the area of present day Albany to defend river traffic and to trade with Native Americans. New Netherland became a province of the Dutch Republic in 1624. The northern border was then reduced to 42 degrees north, as the English had encroached north of Cape Cod. 

According to the Law of Nations, a claim on a territory required not only discovery and charting but settlement. In May 1624 the Dutch completed their claim by landing thirty Dutch families on Noten Eylant, modern Governors Island. 

In the next few decades incompetent directors-general ran New Netherland. The settlers were attacked by Native Americans, and British and Dutch conflicts seemed destined to destroy the colony. All that changed when Peter Stuyvesant was appointed Director-General in 1647. As he arrived he said, &quot;I shall govern you as a father his children&quot;. He expanded the colony's borders. He oversaw conquest of the one settlement of northernmost Europe, New Sweden, in 1655. He resolved the border dispute with New England in 1650. He improved defenses against Native American raids, and the population of the colony went from 500 in 1640 to 9,000 by 1664. But in August of 1664, four English warships arrived in New York Harbor demanding the surrender of the colony. At first, Stuyvesant vowed to fight, but there was little ammunition and gunpowder. He received weak support from the overwhelmed colonists, and was forced to surrender. 

In an attempt to gain supremacy over trade, and in following mercantilist ideas, the English waged war against the Dutch in 1664. The English took control over the Dutch harbor of New Amsterdam on the Atlantic coast of America. James, the brother of King Charles II, received the charter for New Amsterdam and the surrounding Dutch territory. 

In 1673 the Dutch, lead by Michiel de Ruyter, briefly reoccupied New Netherland again, this time naming it New Orange. After peace was made, ending the Third Anglo-Dutch War, they agreed to return it to the English.

== Patterns of Colonization in the Other Early Colonies ==

The territory of Carolina was granted as a proprietary colony to eight different nobles. The proprietors divided Carolina into two separate colonies -- North and South Carolina.

Four colonies were formed by division from already extant larger territories. When New Holland was taken to become New York, King James granted a portion of the territory, present-day New Jersey, to Lord Berkeley and Sir George Cartaret, while retaining present-day New York for himself as a proprietary colony. Another portion of the territory became the crown colony Connecticut. A corner of Pennsylvania which was not peopled by Quakers separated in 1704 to become the colony of Delaware. 

Rhode Island was a unique experiment in religious and political freedom. Massachusetts banished Roger Williams after he began asserting that Jesus Christ meant for the Church to be separate from the governing authority. This dissenter from the Church of England, and then from the Puritans, became the first American Baptist. After many adventures in other colonies, he bought land from the Narragansett Indians for a new settlement. Providence was meant to be a colony free from religious entanglements and a refuge for people of conscience. He was later followed by Anne Hutchinson. She had outraged Boston divines because she was a woman who preached, and because she believed that one's works were not always tied to grace, unlike the Puritans. She also bought land from the Indians. On this was the settlement subsequently named Portsmouth, and afterward a dissident sister town, Newport.  

Georgia was another proprietary colony, with a charter granted to James Oglethorpe and others in 1732. It was intended as a &quot;buffer&quot; colony to protect the others from attacks from the Florida Spanish and the Louisiana French. Because of this, Georgia was the only colony to receive funds from the Crown from its founding. The laws in Great Britain put people in prison for debt. Many of these people were shipped from overcrowded jails to freedom in the wilds of Georgia colony. America was already seen as a land of prosperity, and Oglethorpe hoped that the ex-prisoners would soon become honest and rich. However, few of the prisoners of London jails knew how to survive in the new wilderness.

==Portrait of the British Colonies==

The Colonies are often considered as three groups: '''New England''' (New Hampshire, Massachusetts, Rhode Island, Connecticut), '''the Southern Colonies''' (Maryland, Virginia, the Carolinas, and Georgia), and '''the Middle Colonies''' (New York, New Jersey, Pennsylvania and Delaware).  Sometimes the Carolinas and Georgia are counted as separate from the Chesapeake Colonies.

Each group had geographic and economic characteristics. New England's rocky soil only encouraged small farms, and its agricultural opportunities were limited. Thus it focused on fishing, forestry, shipping, and small industry to make money.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last = Morison |first = Samuel Eliot |coauthors = |title = The Oxford History of the American People |publisher = Mentor |year = 1972 |location = New York City |pages =199–200 |url = |doi = |id = |isbn = 0451-62600-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  

Richer land in the Southern colonies was taken over by individual farmers who grasped acreage. This created large plantation farms that grew tobacco, and later cotton. Farms in the Carolinas also farmed sugar, rice, and indigo. In the 17th century, these were farmed by indentured servants, people who would work for a period of years in return for passage to America and land. Many of these servants died before their indentures ended. A group of indentured servants rose up in Bacon's Rebellion in 1676. After Bacon's Rebellion, plantations began using African slaves instead. Even after release from indenture, many of these white people remained in the economic lower classes, though not subject to the slave codes, which became more harsh as time passed, denying almost all liberty to slaves in the southern colonies. By the American Revolution, one in five colonists was an African slave. And the products produced by slavery in the South were consumed and traded by towns in the Middle Colonies and New England. Few people questioned the slave economy.  

The Middle Colonies had medium-sized farms. These colonies also had people from many different cultures with many different beliefs. Individuals in these states used indentured servants, and later slaves, but there was not the concentration of masses of slave labor found in the Southern colonies.  

Another distinction lies in religious practices. New England was mostly Congregationalist, with some admixture of Presbyterian congregations and the religious non-conformists who called themselves Baptists. These were all descendants of dissenters before and during the British Civil War. The South was mostly Anglican, cherishing religious and secular traditions and holidays. The Middle Colonies held small groups of people from Holland, German lands, and even Bohemia, and they brought a welter of Catholic and Protestant faiths. 

Among the whites sent to the colonies by English authorities were many Scots-Irish people from Ulster. These had been Calvinist Protestants in the middle of a Irish Catholic majority, at odds both with them and with England. This minority settled in the frontier region of the Appalachian Mountains and eventually beyond in the Ohio and Mississippi country. In America their desire for land and freedom pushed the colonial boundary westward at little cost to the government, and provided an armed buffer between the eastern settlements and Native American tribes which had been driven away from the seaboard. Colonial frontiersmen endured a very harsh life, building their towns and farms by hand in a dense wilderness amid economic deprivation and native attack.

Each colony developed its own areas of edification and amusement, depending upon the local faith and the local capacities. The culture of the South recorded early interest in musical theater, with Charleston, South Carolina and Williamsburg, Virginia as hubs of musical activity. A performance of Richard III, the first professional production of Shakespeare in America, took place in New York City in 1750. And preachers, lecturers, and singers entertained the colonists.

Their commonalities were stronger than their differences. All three regions shared a population mostly derived from the British Isles. All had terrible roads, and all had connections to the Atlantic Ocean as a means of transportation. And all were tied to the Atlantic economy. Atlantic merchants used ships to trade slaves, tobacco, rum, sugar, gold, silver, spices, fish, lumber, and manufactured goods between America, the West Indies, Europe and Africa.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Cod: A Biography of the Fish That Changed the World|last=Kurlansky|first=Mark|publisher=New York: Walker|isbn=0-8027-1326-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;  New York, Philadelphia, Boston, and Charleston were the largest cities and main ports at that time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url= http://www.census.gov/population/www/documentation/twps0027/tab02.txt| title= Earliest Population Figures for American Cities | author= U.S. Census Bureau|accessdate=2010-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Early Technology ==

The first wave of colonists used hand labor to cultivate their farms, and established such land-based crafts such as pottery and tanning. As later ships brought cattle and horses, draft animals became part of the economy. Indentured servants, and then slaves kidnapped from Africa, were imported. This was when larger plantations began to be founded. In the latter part of the eighteenth century small-scale machine-based manufacturing began to appear. Individuals started to dig for coal and iron ore. New England used the latter to begin making building tools and horseshoes. A new textile industry arose, dependent in part upon Southern cotton. Powered by coal and fed by the need for strong metal, household forges pioneered new techniques of iron-making. The blacksmith and the tinsmith became part of large settlements. Colonies started making mechanized clocks, guns, and lead type for printing.

== Mercantilism, Salutary Neglect and British Interference ==
The American colonies, entirely new societies separated by an ocean from Great Britain, believed they had the right to govern themselves. This belief was encouraged by the Glorious Revolution and 1689 Bill of Rights, which gave Parliament the ultimate authority in government. A policy of relatively lax controls or '''Salutary Neglect''' ended in increased British regulation resulting from the policy of mercantilism, and seen through the Lords of Trade and the later Navigation Acts.

=== Mercantilism ===
Parliament placed controls on colonial trade in obedience to the economic policy of '''mercantilism'''. This was the idea that a nation's economic power depended on the value of its exports. A country could use its colonies to create finished goods, rather than raw materials. These could be traded to other countries, thus increasing the strength of the colonizing nation. This policy had been put forth by a Frenchman named Jean-Baptiste Colbert. It seemed tailor-made for Great Britain. Spain had American gold as its economic base, and France had American furs. England had neither of these. But it had American cotton, molasses, and tobacco, as well as its state-of-the-art ships.  Prior to the mid-1700s, the colonies had enjoyed a long period of &quot;salutary neglect&quot;, where the British largely let the colonies govern themselves. This now ended.

=== The Lords of Trade ===
In an attempt to enforce mercantilist policies, King Charles II created '''the Lords of Trade''' as a new committee on the Privy Council. The Lords of Trade attempted to affect the government of the colonies in a manner beneficial to the English, rather than to the colonists. 

The Lords of Trade attempted to convert all American colonies to royal ones so that the Crown could gain more power. Under King James II, the successor to Charles II, New York, New Jersey, and the Puritan colonies were combined into the Dominion of New England in 1687. 

However, the Dominion only lasted a brief time. King James II, a Catholic, was seen as a threat by British Protestants. James was overthrown (he was technically held abdicated by Parliament) in the bloodless Glorious Revolution of 1688. In 1689, James' daughter Mary II and her husband William III took the throne as joint rulers. However, the British Parliament actually held the power. The Dominion of New England was dissolved, the various separate colonies were reestablished, and the Lords of Trade were abandoned (replaced by a Board of Trade, a purely advisory body).

===Navigation Acts===
Beginning in 1660, the Parliament of England passed '''the Navigation Acts''' to increase its benefit from its colonies. The Acts required that any colonial imports or exports travel only on ships registered in England. They forbid the colonies to export tobacco and sugar to any nation other than England. And the colonies could not import anything manufactured outside England unless the goods were first taken to England, where taxes were paid, and then to the colonies.  

In the 1730s, The Sugar Act established a tax of six pence per gallon of sugar or molasses imported into the colonies. By 1750, Parliament had begun to ban, restrict, or tax several more products.  It tried to curtail all manufacture in the the colonies.  This provoked much anger among the colonists, despite the fact that their tax burdens were quite low, when compared to most subjects of European monarchies of the same period.

Colonists hated the navigation acts because they believed they would be more prosperous and rich if they had a free-enterprise and no boundaries. They also believed that some vital resources would not be found in Britain. Navigation acts was tree branch of mercantilism.

== Indians in the 1700s ==

Indians of the Great Plains:

Today, the area where the Indians of all the Great Plains lived is located from the Rocky mountains to the Mississippi River. During the 1700s, there were about 30 tribes that lived on the Great Plains. These tribes tended to rely on buffalo as their food source as well as other daily needs, such as clothing. Not only did Indians, specifically women, make their clothing out of buffalo, but also out of deer. Women would soak the deer or buffalo and scrape off the hair of the dead animal.&lt;ref name=&quot;englar&quot;&gt;Englar, Mary. The Great Plains Indians: Daily Life in the 1700s. Mankato, MN: Capstone, 2006. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

Also, Indian tribes traded with one another. The amount of horses an individual owned was a sign of wealth; Indians would trade their horses for food, tools, weapons(such as guns), and hides. Since the tribes spoke many different languages from one another, they had to use sign language to be able to trade with each other.&lt;ref name=&quot;englar&quot; /&gt;

== Philadelphia Election Riot ==
A riot broke out on election day in Philadelphia in 1742 as a result of the Anglican population disagreeing with the Quaker majority.  The riot stemmed over a power struggle between the Anglican and Quaker population.  The Quakers had a history of political dominance over Philadelphia.  The German population backed the Quaker vote because of the Quaker Pacifism which would protect from higher taxes and ultimately the draft.  On election day, the Anglicans and sailors fought with the Quakers and Germans.  The Quakers were able to seek shelter in the courthouse and complete the election.  The Anglican party lost the election and 54 sailors were jailed following the riot.

== Education ==
As the people in the colonies through the 1700s were made up of people with different interests, they provided different sorts of education for their children. Although there were commonalities -- a rich family in any of the three regions might send a son to Europe for his education -- people in different colonies tended to educate in differing ways. 

New England's motives for education were both civil and religious. The good citizen had to know his or her Bible. This was the Pilgrim ethos, set up in opposition to what they saw as the ignorance imposed by tyrants. Both boys and girls were often taught to read the Bible by their parents, perhaps with the aid of a horn book, an alphabet and syllabary covered by horn. A law was passed in 1647 in Massachusetts that stated that if more than 50 families lived in a community, a schoolteacher must be hired. (This was the beginning of the American grammar school, which initially taught Latin, but later included practical subjects such as navigation, engineering, bookkeeping, and foreign languages.)&lt;ref&gt;A People and a Nation, Eighth Edition&lt;/ref&gt; Education became mandatory in the Massachusetts Bay Colony in 1642. Most of the schools opened in the colonial era were private. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.excite.com/education/education/history-of-american-education&lt;/ref&gt; The second motive was that a Christian ought to be able to govern in his society. (Government was the province of godly, property-holding men, rather than women.) To obtain this youths had to gain a classical education -- that is, one based thoroughly on Latin. The first public-supported school in the United States was the Boston Latin School in 1635. It had a rigorous education, and as a result, few students. Harvard was the first university in America, founded in 1636 and originally intended to teach Protestant clergy. Because of the small number of people graduating from the classical curriculum, attendance was low. Some people jumped directly from the classical curriculum to the University, sometimes entering Harvard as young as 14 or 15 years old. Cotton Mather graduated Harvard at 15, an exception only because of his extreme precocity. In private schools, boys and girls learned penmanship, basic Math, and reading and writing English. These fed the various trades, where older children were apprenticed. Girls who did not become servants were often trained for domestic life, learning needlework, cooking, and the several days-long task of cleaning clothes.  

Like New England, the Middle Colonies had private schools which educated children in reading and writing. However, the basics were rarer. The further west one lived, the less likely one was to be able to go to school, or to read and write at all. Ethnic and religious sub-groups would have their own private schools, which taught their own children their own folk-ways. In none of the colonies was higher education certain. Secondary schools were very rare outside of such major towns as Boston, New York, Philadelphia, and Charleston.&lt;ref&gt;A People and a Nation Eighth Edition&lt;/ref&gt;

The Chesapeake experience was different again. Children could only could only read and write if their parents could.&lt;ref&gt;A People and a Nation Eighth Edition&lt;/ref&gt; And the South had few schools, of any kind, until the Revolutionary era. Children in wealthy families would study with private tutors. Though wealthy girls might learn 'the womanly arts,' they would not have the same curriculum as their brothers. Martha Washington's granddaughter Eliza Custis was laughed at by her stepfather when &quot;[I] thought it hard they would not teach me Greek and Latin because I was a girl -- they laughed and said women ought not to know those things, and mending, writing, Arithmetic, and Music was all I could be permitted to acquire.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Edmund S. Morgan. Virginians At Home: Family Life in the Eighteenth Century. Charlottesville, VA: Dominion Books, 1962(1952). P. 17&lt;/ref&gt; Middle class children might learn to read from their parents, and many poor children, as well as all black children, went unschooled. The literacy rates were lower in the South than the North until about the 19th century.&lt;ref&gt;A People and a Nation, Eighth Edition&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1693 the College of William &amp; Mary was founded, Virginia's first University. As the 18th century wore on, it specialized not in theology for clergymen but in law.&lt;ref&gt;Morgan, p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1701, the Collegiate College was founded. In 1718 it received funds from a Welsh governor of the British East India Company, Elihu Yale, and was renamed Yale College. These were later joined by several other universities, including Princeton in 1747. In the 18th century, astronomy, physics, modern history and politics took a bigger place in the college curriculum. Some colleges experimented with admitting Native American students in the 18th century, though not African-Americans.&lt;ref&gt;A People and a Nation, Eighth Edition&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1640, ''The whole Booke of Psalms Faithfully Translated into English Metre'', commonly known as the Bay Psalm Book, was printed in Cambridge, Massachusetts. It was the first book written in the new world. The Bay Psalm Book was the first metrical English translation of the Biblical psalms.&lt;ref&gt;Farris, Jean Americans Musical Landscape, Volume 5&lt;/ref&gt; This famous and influential songbook was succeeded by a whole New England publishing industry. Sometime after 1687 the first ''New England Primer'' was published as an aid to childhood reading and spelling.  

An alternative to the classical curriculum emerged in Benjamin Franklin's American Academy, founded in Philadelphia in 1751. This body represented something closer to the modern American high school, offering vocational education. This sort of school later outnumbered the classical secondary school. However, Franklin's Academy was private as well, making such learning open only to those who could afford it.

During this period colonists attempted to convert Native Americans to Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1G2-2536600517.html&lt;/ref&gt;

== Review Questions ==
1. Choose one of the following colonies: New York, Virginia, Massachusetts, Georgia. In which of the three areas is it located? Why and how was it initially colonized? How did its immigrants and the religions they adhered to affect it?

2. Why did the British interfere with the colonies?

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{chapnav|Exploration|Road to Revolution}}</text>
      <sha1>g8o38bpnijpf7bqedyc0yo186qnzhqc</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>US History/Road to Revolution</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1122</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2703438</id>
      <parentid>2703437</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-09-24T21:50:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Savh</username>
        <id>385809</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WB:REVERT|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/173.17.73.210|173.17.73.210]] ([[User talk:173.17.73.210|talk]]) to last version by Pittsburgh Poet</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">== The French and Indian War ==

''(The following text is from Wikipedia)''

The '''French and Indian War''' (1754&amp;ndash;1763) was the North American chapter of the Seven Years' War. The name refers to the two main enemies of the British, the royal French forces and the various American Indian forces allied with them. This conflict, the fourth such colonial war between the kingdoms of France and Great Britain, resulted in the British conquest of all of New France east of the Mississippi River, as well as Spanish Florida. France ceded control of French Louisiana west of the Mississippi to its Spanish ally, to compensate it for its loss of Florida. By the end of this war France kept only the tiny islands of Saint Pierre and Miquelon north of the Caribbean. These colonies today still allow France access to the Grand Banks. 

In Great Britain and France, the North American theatre of the Seven Years' War war usually has no special name, and so the entire worldwide conflict is known as the ''Seven Years' War'' (or the ''Guerre de sept ans''). The &quot;Seven Years&quot; refers to events in Europe, from the official declaration of war in 1756 to the signing of the peace treaty in 1763. These dates do not correspond with the actual fighting in North America, where the fighting between the two colonial powers was largely concluded in six years, from the Jumonville Glen skirmish in 1754 to the capture of Montreal in 1760.&lt;ref&gt;Anderson, Fred. ''Crucible of War: The Seven Years' War and the Fate of Empire in British North America, 1754-1766.'' New York: Knopf, 2000. p. 747&lt;/ref&gt; 

Elsewhere the conflict is known by several names. In British North America, wars were often named after the sitting British monarch, such as King William's War or Queen Anne's War. Because there had already been a King George's War in the 1740s, British colonists named the second war in King George's reign after their opponents, and thus it became known as the ''French and Indian War''.&lt;ref&gt;Anderson, ''Crucible of War.'' p. 747.&lt;/ref&gt; This traditional name remains standard in the United States, although it obscures the fact that American Indians fought on both sides of the conflict.&lt;ref&gt;Jennings, Francis. ''Empire of Fortune: Crowns, Colonies, and Tribes in the Seven Years War in America.'' New York: Norton, 1988. p. xv.&lt;/ref&gt; American historians generally use the traditional name or the European title (the Seven Years' War), and have also invented other, less frequently used names for the war, including the ''Fourth Intercolonial War'' and the ''Great War for the Empire''.&lt;ref&gt;Anderson, ''Crucible of War.'' P. 747&lt;/ref&gt; Canadian francophones and English speakers both refer to it as the Seven Years' War (''Guerre de Sept Ans'') or the War of the Conquest (''Guerre de la Conquête''), as the war in which New France was conquered by the British and became part of the British Empire. This war was also known as the ''Forgotten War''.

==Reasons for war==
The French and Indian War began less than a decade after France and Great Britain had fought on opposing sides in the European War of the Austrian Succession (1740&amp;ndash;1748). One cause for the conflict was '''territorial expansion'''. Newfoundland's Grand Banks were fertile fishing grounds and coveted by both sides. Both sides also wanted to expand their territories for trapping furs to trade, and for other pursuits that aided their economic interests. Both the British and the French used trading posts and forts to claim the Ohio Country, the vast territory between the Appalachian Mountains and the Mississippi River, from the Great Lakes to the Gulf of Mexico. English claims resulted from royal grants with no definite western boundaries. La Salle had claimed the Mississippi River for France: its drainage area includes the Ohio River Valley. Both Great Britain and France took advantage of Native American factions to secure these claims, to protect their territories, and to keep the other from growing too strong.  

A second cause was '''political &amp; religious ideology'''. The English Protestant colonists  feared papal influence in North America. New France was administered by French governors and Roman Catholic hierarchy. French missionaries included Armand de La Richardie. English history was told as a story of freedom from Catholic (i.e., foreign) influence. French control over North America represented a threat to Great Britain. In their turn, the French feared English  anti-Catholicism, in a time when Catholics were still being persecuted under English law.

== Declaration and Action Anticipating the War ==
===Céloron's expedition===
In June 1747 the Governor-General of New France, the Marquis de la Jonquière, ordered Pierre-Joseph Céloron to lead an expedition to the Ohio Country to remove British influence from the area. Céloron was also to confirm allegiance of the Native Americans in the Ohio territory to the French crown.

Céloron's expedition consisted of 213 soldiers of the Troupes de la marine (French Marines) transported by twenty-three canoes. The expedition left Lachine on June 15, 1749, and two days later reached Fort Frontenac. It then continued along the shoreline of present-day Lake Erie. At Chautauqua Portage (Barcelona, New York), it moved inland to the Allegheny River.

The troop headed south to the Ohio River at present-day Pittsburgh, where Céloron buried lead plates engraved with the French claim to the Ohio Country. Whenever British merchants or fur-traders were encountered by the French, they were informed of the illegality of being on French territory and told to leave the Ohio Country. When the expedition arrived at Logstown, the Native Americans there informed Céloron that they owned the Ohio Country, and they would trade with the British, despite anything the French said.&lt;ref&gt;Fowler, W. M. ''Empires at War: The French and Indian War and the Struggle for North America, 1754-1763.'' New York: Walker, 2005. P. 14&lt;/ref&gt;

Céloron continued the expedition. At its farthest point south, it reached the junction between the Ohio River and the Miami River, just south of the village of Pickawillany. Here lived the old Chief of the Miami tribe, whom Céloron called &quot;Old Britain.&quot; When Céloron arrived at Pickawillany, he informed the elderly Chief of &quot;dire consequences&quot; of continuing to trade with the British. &quot;Old Britain&quot; ignored the warning. After this meeting, Céloron and his expedition began the trip home, reaching Montreal only on November 10, 1749. In his report, Céloron wrote: &quot;All I can say is that the Natives of these localities are very badly disposed towards the French, and are entirely devoted to the English. I don't know in what way they could be brought back.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Fowler, W. M. ''Empires at War.'' P. 14&lt;/ref&gt;

===Langlade's expedition===
On March 17, 1752, Governor-General de la Jonquière died. His temporary replacement was Charles le Moyne de Longueuil. It was not until July 1, 1752 that Ange Duquense de Menneville arrived in New France to take over the post. 

In the spring of 1752, Longueuil dispatched an expedition to the Ohio River area. The expedition was led by Charles Michel de Langlade, an officer in the Troupes de la marine. Langlade was given 300 men, some French-Canadians, and others members of the Ottawa tribe. His objective was to punish the Miami of Pickawillany for continuing to trade with the British. At dawn on June 21, 1752, the war party attacked the British trading center at Pickawillany, killing fourteen people of the Miami nation, including &quot;Old Britain.&quot; The expedition then returned home.

===Marin's expedition===
In the spring of 1754, Paul Marin de la Malgue was given command of a 2,000 man force of Troupes de la Marine and Aboriginals. His orders were to protect the Ohio from the British. Marin followed the route that Céloron had mapped out four years before. However, where Céloron had buried lead plates, Marin was constructing and garrisoning forts. The first fort that was constructed by Paul Marin was at Presque Isle (Erie, Pennsylvania) on Lake Erie's south shore.  He then had a road built to the headwaters of Rivière aux Boeuf (now known as Waterford, Pennsylvania). Marin then constructed a second fort at Le Boeuf, designed to guard the headwaters of the Rivière aux Boeuf.

===Tanaghrisson's proclamation===
On September 3, 1753, Tanaghrisson (d. 1754), Chief of the Mingo, arrived at Fort Le Boeuf. One tradition states that Tanaghrisson hated the French because they had killed and eaten his father.  Tanaghrisson told Marin, &quot;I shall strike . . .&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Fowler, ''Empires at War.'' P. 31&lt;/ref&gt; threatening the French. The show of force by the French had alarmed the Iroquois in the area. They sent Mohawk runners to William Johnson's manor in Upper New York. Johnson, known to the Iroquois as &quot;Warraghiggey&quot;, meaning &quot;He who does big business&quot;, had become a respected member of the Iroquois Confederacy in the area. In 1746, Johnson was made a colonel of the Iroquois, and later a colonel of the Western New York Militia.

At Albany, New York, there was a meeting between Governor Clinton of New York and Chief Hendrick, as well as other officials from a handful of American colonies. Chief Hendrick insisted that the British abide by their obligations and block French expansion. When an unsatisfactory response was offered by Clinton, Chief Hendrick proclaimed that the &quot;Covenant Chain&quot;, a long-standing friendly relationship between the Iroquois Confederacy and the British Crown, was broken.

===Dinwiddie's reaction===
[[Image:Washington 1772.jpg|right|200px|thumb|The earliest authenticated portrait of George Washington shows him wearing his colonel's uniform of the Virginia Regiment from the French and Indian War. However, this portrait was painted years after the war in 1772.]]
Governor Robert Dinwiddie of Virginia found himself in a predicament. Many merchants had invested heavily in fur trading in Ohio. If the French made good on their claim to the Ohio Country and drove out the British, then the Virginian merchants would lose a lot of money. 
Dinwiddie could not possibly allow the loss of the Ohio Country to France. In October 1753 he wrote a letter to the commander of the French forces in the Ohio Country, Jacques Legardeur de Saint-Pierre, demanding an immediate French withdrawal. To deliver it he delegated Major ''George Washington'' of the Virginia militia. Major Washington left for Fort Le Boeuf on the 31st of October, along with his interpreter Jacob Van Braam and several other men. 

A few days later, Washington and his party arrived at Wills Creek (Cumberland, Maryland). Here Washington enlisted the help of Christopher Gist, a surveyor who was familiar with the area. They arrived at Logstown on November 24, 1753. At Logstown, Washington met with Tanaghrisson, who was angry over the French military encroachment upon his land. Washington convinced Tanaghrisson to accompany his small group to Fort Le Boeuf.

On December 12, 1753, Washington and his men reached Fort Le Boeuf. Commander Saint-Pierre invited Washington to dine with him that evening. Over dinner, Washington presented Saint-Pierre with the letter from Dinwiddie. Saint-Pierre was civil in his response, saying, &quot;As to the Summons you send me to retire, I do not think myself obliged to obey it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Fowler, ''Empires at War''. P. 35.&lt;/ref&gt; The French explained to Washington that France's claim to the region was superior to that of the British, as René-Robert Cavelier, Sieur de a Salle (1643&amp;ndash;1687) had explored the Ohio Country nearly a century earlier.&lt;ref&gt;Ellis, Joseph J. ''His Excellency George Washington.'' New York: Vintage Books, A Division of Random House, Inc., 2004. P. 5&lt;/ref&gt;

Washington's party left Fort Le Boeuf early on December 16, 1753. By January 16, 1754, they had arrived in Williamsburg, Virginia.  In his report, Washington stated, &quot;The French had swept south.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Fowler, ''Empires at War'', p. 36&lt;/ref&gt;  They had constructed and garrisoned forts at Presque Isle, Le Boeuf and Venango.

==War==
The French and Indian War was the last of four major colonial wars between the British, the French, and their Native American allies. Unlike the previous three wars, the French and Indian War began on North American soil and then spread to Europe, where Britain and France continued fighting. Britain officially declared war on France on May 15, 1756, marking the beginnings of the Seven Years' War in Europe. Native Americans fought for both sides, but primarily alongside the French (with one exception being the Iroquois Confederacy, which sided with the American colonies and Britain). The first major event of the war was in 1754. Lieutenant Colonel George Washington, then twenty-one years of age, was sent to negotiate boundaries with the French, who did not give up their forts. Washington led a group of Virginian (colonial) troops to confront the French at Fort Duquesne (present day Pittsburgh). Washington discovered the French troops at '''the Battle of Jumonville Glen''' (about six miles or ten kilometers North-West of soon-to-be-established Fort Necessity). In the ensuing skirmish, a French Officer, Joseph Coulon de Jumonville, was killed. Washington pulled back a few miles and established Fort Necessity. The French forced Washington and his men to retreat. Meanwhile, the Albany Congress was taking place as means to discuss further action. 

Edward Braddock led a campaign against the French at Fort Duquesne in 1755. Washington was again among the British and colonial troops. Braddock employed European tactics -- bold, linear marches and firing formations -- and employed heavy cannon. This led to disaster at the '''Monongahela'''. The French and natives were heavily outmanned and outgunned. But they used superior tactics, taking cover behind trees and bushes to gun down and rout the British. Braddock was killed. Despite four close calls, Washington escaped unharmed and led the survivors in retreat. This stunning British defeat heralded a string of major French victories over the next few years, at '''Fort Oswego''', '''Fort William Henry''', '''Fort Duquesne''', and '''Carillon''', where veteran Montcalm famously defeated five times his number. The sole British successes in the early years of the war came in 1755, at '''the Battle of Lake George''', which secured the Hudson Valley; and in the taking of '''Fort Beauséjour''' (which protected the Nova Scotia frontier) by Lieutenant Colonel Robert Monckton. A consequence of this last battle was the subsequent forced deportation of the Acadian population of Nova Scotia and the Beaubassin region of Acadia. 

In 1756 William Pitt became Secretary of State of Great Britain. His leadership, and France's continued neglect of the North-American theater, eventually turned the tide in favor of the British. The French were driven from many frontier posts such as Fort Niagara, and the key Fortress Louisbourg fell to the British in 1758. In 1759, '''the Battle of the Plains of Abraham''' gave Quebec City to the British, who had to withstand a siege there after the '''Battle of Sainte-Foy''' a year later. In September of 1760, Pierre François de Rigaud, Marquis de Vaudreuil-Cavagnal, the King's Governor of New France, negotiated a surrender with British General Jeffrey Amherst. General Amherst granted Vaudreuil's request that any French residents who chose to remain in the colony would be given freedom to continue worshiping in their Roman Catholic tradition, continued ownership of their property, and the right to remain undisturbed in their homes. The British provided medical treatment for the sick and wounded French soldiers, and French regular troops were returned to France aboard British ships with an agreement that they were not to serve again in the present war.

'''Summary of the war in America'''
In 1752 the French and their Native allies raided a trading outpost sited at modern day Cleveland rid the area of Pennsylvanians. In 1754 General George Washington attacked French soldiers and then became trapped in his poorly built, Fort Necessity in Great Meadows Pennsylvania and more than one-third of Washingtons's men shortly became casualties. Twenty-two year old Washington and his men surrendered and were allowed to leave back to Virginia. In July 1755, a few miles south of Fort Duquensne in Pennsylvania, the combined forces of French and Natives attacked British colonial troops that were preparing a to assault the fort. The aftermath that ensued would result in a British defeat and General Edward Braddock would be killed. Once London heard of this Britain declared war upon France and formally began the seven years war. After this the British feared that France would attempt to retake Nova Scotia and that the 12,000 French Nova Scotians would break their neutrality, so the British military forced around seven thousand French Nova Scotians from their homeland. This was history's first large-scale modern deportation, the French would be sent from Louisiana to the Caribbean and families would become torn apart. In July of 1758 The British had recaptured the fort at Loiusberg winning control of the St. Lawerence River. This would cut the major French supply route and open up more supply lines for the British. In the fall of 1758 the Shawnee and Delaware Natives accepted peace offerings from the British and the French abandoned Fort Duquesne. A decisive attack would happen in the fall of 1759 when General James Wolfe's forces defeated the French on the Plains of Abraham and thus taking Quebec. A year after this event the British would capture Montreal and the North American stage of the war would be over.

===Outcome===
[[File:Vue de la descente a Terre Neuve par le chevalier de Ternay en 1762.jpg|330px|thumb|right|The descent of the French on St. John's, Newfoundland, 1762.]]
Though most of the North American fighting ended on September 8, 1760, when the Marquis de Vaudreuil surrendered Montreal &amp;mdash; and effectively all of Canada &amp;mdash; to Britain (one notable late battle allowed the capture of Spanish Havana by British and colonial forces in 1762), the war officially ended with the signing of the Treaty of Paris on February 10, 1763. The treaty sealed France's loss of all its North American possessions east of the Mississippi except for Saint Pierre and Miquelon islands off Newfoundland. All of Canada was ceded to Britain. France regained the Caribbean islands of Guadeloupe and Martinique, which had been occupied by the British. The economic value of these islands to France was greater than that of Canada at the time, because of their rich sugar crops; and the islands were easier to defend. However, the British were happy to take New France: defense was not an issue, and they had many sources of sugar. Spain gained Louisiana, including New Orleans, in compensation for its loss of Florida to the British.

French Canada contained approximately 65,000 French-speaking Roman Catholic residents. Early in the war, in 1755, the British had expelled French settlers from Acadia. (Some of these eventually fled to Louisiana, creating the Cajun population.) Now at peace, and eager to secure control of its hard-won colony, Great Britain made concessions to its newly conquered subjects with the Quebec Act of 1774. The history of the Seven Years' War, particularly the siege of Québec and the death of British Brigadier General James Wolfe, generated a vast number of ballads, broadsides, images, maps and other printed materials, which testify to how this event continued to capture the imagination of the British public long after Wolfe's death in 1759.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.collectionscanada.ca/virtual-vault/ Virtual Vault], an online exhibition of Canadian historical art at Library and Archives Canada&lt;/ref&gt;
  
The European theatre of the war was settled by the Treaty of Hubertusburg on February 15, 1763. The war changed economic, political, and social relations between Britain and its colonies. It plunged Britain into debt, which the Crown chose to pay off with tax money from its colonies. These taxes contributed to the beginning the American Revolutionary War.

===Battles and expeditions===
;United States

**Battle of Jumonville Glen (May 28, 1754)
**Battle of Fort Necessity, aka the Battle of Great Meadows (July 3, 1754)
**Braddock Expedition (Battle of the Monongahela aka Battle of the Wilderness) (July 9, 1755)
**Kittanning Expedition (climax September 8, 1756)
**Battle of Fort Duquesne (September 14, 1758)
**Battle of Fort Ligonier (October 12, 1758)
**Forbes Expedition (climax November 25, 1758)

*Province of New York
**Battle of Lake George (1755)
**Battle of Fort Oswego (August, 1756)
**Battle on Snowshoes (January 21, 1757)
**Battle of Fort Bull (March 27, 1756)
**Battle of Sabbath Day Point (July 26, 1757)
**Battle of Fort William Henry (August 9, 1757)
**Attack on German Flatts (1757) (November 12, 1757)
**Battle of Carillon (July 8, 1758) 
**Battle of Ticonderoga (1759)
**Battle of La Belle-Famille (July 24, 1759)
**Battle of Fort Niagara (1759)
**Battle of the Thousand Islands, 16-25 August, 1760

*West Virginia
**Battle of Great Cacapon (April 18, 1756)

;Canada
*New Brunswick
**Battle of Fort Beauséjour (June 16, 1755)

*Nova Scotia
**Battle of Louisburg (July 27, 1758)

*Ontario
**Battle of Fort Frontenac (August 25, 1758)
**Battle of the Thousand Islands, 16-25 August, 1760

*Quebec
**Battle of Beauport (July 31, 1759)
**Battle of the Plains of Abraham (September 13, 1759)
**Battle of Sainte-Foy (April 28, 1760)
**Battle of Restigouche, July 3-8, (1760) 

*Newfoundland
**Battle of Signal Hill  September 15, 1762

== Proclamation of 1763 ==
''(The following text is taken from the Wikipedia article)''

[[Image:map of territorial growth 1775.jpg|thumb|A portion of eastern North America; the 1763 &quot;Proclamation line&quot; is the border between the red and the pink areas.]]

The '''Royal Proclamation of 1763''' was issued October 7, 1763 by George III following Great Britain's acquisition of French territory in North America after the end of the Seven Years' War. The purpose of the proclamation was to make sure Britain could control its new territory for its  The Proclamation in essence forbade Americans from settling or buying land west of the Appalachians. Colonists were angry because many already had land in that area. Additionally, the Proclamation gave the Crown a monopoly in land bought from Native Americans.

===Native land===
In the fall of 1763, a royal decree was issued that prohibited the North American colonists from establishing or maintaining settlements west of an imaginary line running down the crest of the Appalachian Mountains. The proclamation acknowledged that Native Americans owned the lands on which they were then residing and white settlers in the area were to be removed. 

However, provision was made to allow specially licensed individuals and entities to operate fur trading ventures in the proscribed area. There were two motivations for this policy: 

To avoid warfare with the Indians. This aim had little to do with affection for the tribes, but simply reflected the facts that Indian conflicts were very expensive and that the British had not yet deployed sufficient soldiers in the west to keep the peace. Some Indians welcomed this policy, believing that the separation of the races would allow them to resume their traditional lifeways; others realized that the proclamation, at best, would only provide some breathing room before the next onslaught of settlers. 

To concentrate colonial settlements on the seaboard where they could be active parts of the British mercantile system. The first priority of British trade officials was to populate the recently secured areas of Canada and Florida (see Treaty of Paris), where colonists could reasonably be expected to trade with the mother country; settlers living west of the Appalachians would be highly self-sufficient and have little opportunity to trade with English merchants. 
The reaction of colonial land speculators and frontiersmen was immediate and understandably negative. From their perspective, risking their lives in the recent war had been rewarded by the creation of a vast restricted native reserve in the lands they coveted. Most concluded that the proclamation was only a temporary measure and a number ignored it entirely and moved into the prohibited area.
Almost from its inception, the proclamation was modified to suit the needs of influential people with interests in the American West. This included many high British officials as well as colonial leaders. 

Beginning in 1764, portions of the Proclamation Line were adjusted westward to accommodate speculative interests. Later, in 1768, the first Treaty of Fort Stanwix formally recognized the surrender of transmontane lands claimed by the Iroquois.

The Proclamation of 1763 was a well-intentioned measure. Pontiac’s Rebellion had inflicted a terrible toll on the frontier settlements in North America and the British government acted prudently by attempting to avoid such conflict in the foreseeable future. 

The colonists, however, were not appreciative and regarded the new policy as an infringement of their basic rights. The fact that western expansion was halted at roughly the same time that other restrictive measures were being implemented, made the colonists increasingly suspicious


Almost immediately, many British colonists and land speculators objected to the proclamation boundary, since there were already many settlements beyond the line (some of which had been temporarily evacuated during Pontiac's War), as well as many existing land claims yet to be settled. Indeed, the proclamation itself called for lands to be granted to British soldiers who had served in the Seven Years' War. Prominent American colonists joined with land speculators in Britain to lobby the government to move the line further west. As a result, the boundary line was adjusted in a series of treaties with Native Americans. The Treaty of Fort Stanwix and the Treaty of Hard Labor (both 1768) and the Treaty of Lochaber (1770) opened much of what is now West Virginia and Kentucky to British settlement.

===Organization of new colonies===
Besides regulating colonial expansion, the proclamation dealt with the management of newly ceded French colonies. It established government for four areas: Quebec, West Florida, East Florida, and Grenada. All of these were granted the ability to elect general assemblies under a royally appointed governor or a high council, which could then create laws and ordinances specific to the area in agreement with British and colonial laws. In the meantime, the new colonies enjoyed the same rights as native-born Englishmen, something that British colonists had been fighting over for years. An even bigger affront to the British colonies was the establishment of both civil and criminal courts complete with the right to appeal--but those charged with violating the Stamp or Sugar Act were to be tried in admiralty court, where the defendant was considered guilty until he or she could prove his or her innocence.

===Legacy===
The influence of the Royal Proclamation of 1763 on the coming of the American Revolutionary War (1775–1783) has been variously interpreted. Many historians argue that the proclamation ceased to be a major source of tension after 1768, since the aforementioned treaties opened up extensive lands for settlement. Others have argued that colonial resentment of the proclamation contributed to the growing divide between the colonies and the Mother Country.

In the United States, the Royal Proclamation of 1763 ended with the American Revolutionary War, because Great Britain ceded the land in question to the United States in the Treaty of Paris (1783). Afterwards, the U.S. government also faced difficulties in preventing frontier violence, and eventually adopted policies similar to those of the Royal Proclamation. The first in a series of Indian Intercourse Acts was passed in 1790, prohibiting unregulated trade and travel in Native American lands. Additionally, the U.S. Supreme Court case Johnson v. M'Intosh (1823) established that only the U.S. government, and not private individuals, could purchase land from Native Americans.

The Royal Proclamation continued to govern the cession of aboriginal land in British North America, especially Upper Canada and Rupert's Land. The proclamation forms the basis of land claims of aboriginal peoples in Canada – First Nations, Inuit, and Metis. The Royal Proclamation of 1763 is thus mentioned in Section Twenty-five of the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms.

== The Stamp Act and other Laws ==

In 1764, George Grenville became the British Chancellor of the Exchequer (minister of finance). He allowed customs officers to obtain general writs of assistance, which allowed officers to search random houses for smuggled goods. Grenville thought that if profits from smuggled goods could be directed towards Britain, the money could help pay off debts. Colonists were horrified that they could be searched without warrant at any given moment. Also in 1764, with persuasion from Grenville, Parliament began to impose several taxes on the colonists. '''The Sugar Act''' of 1764 reduced the taxes imposed by the Molasses Act, but at the same time strengthened the collection of the taxes. It also provided that British judges, and not juries, would try cases involving that Act.

The next year, Parliament passed the '''Quartering Act''', which required the colonies to provide room and board for British soldiers stationed in North America; the soldiers would serve various purposes, chiefly to enforce the previously passed acts of Parliament.

Following the Quartering Act, Parliament passed one of the most infamous pieces of legislation: the '''Stamp Act'''. Previously, Parliament imposed only external taxes on imports. But the Stamp Act provided the first internal tax on the colonists, requiring that a tax stamp be applied to books, newspapers, pamphlets, legal documents, playing cards, and dice. The legislature of Massachusetts requested a conference on the Stamp Act; the Stamp Act Congress met in October that year, petitioning the King and Parliament to repeal the act before it went into effect at the end of the month, crying &quot;taxation without representation.&quot;

The act faced vehement opposition throughout the colonies. Merchants threatened to boycott British products. Thousands of New Yorkers rioted near the location where the stamps were stored. In Boston, the Sons of Liberty, a violent group led by radical statesman Samuel Adams, destroyed the home of Lieutenant Governor Thomas Hutchinson. Parliament did indeed repeal the Stamp Act, but additionally passed the Declaratory Act, which stated that Great Britain retained the power to tax the colonists, even without substantive representation.

Believing that the colonists only objected to internal taxes, Chancellor of the Exchequer Charles Townshend proposed bills that would later become the '''Townshend Acts'''. The Acts, passed in 1767, taxed imports of tea, glass, paint, lead, and even paper. The colonial merchants again threatened to boycott the taxed products, reducing the profits of British merchants, who in turn petitioned Parliament to repeal the Townshend Acts. Parliament eventually agreed to repeal much of the Townshend legislation. But Parliament refused to remove the tax on tea, implying that the British retained the authority to tax the colonies despite a lack of representation.

In 1773, Parliament passed the '''Tea Act''', which exempted the British East India Company from the Townshend taxes. Thus, the East India Company gained a great advantage over other companies when selling tea in the colonies. The colonists who resented the advantages given to British companies dumped British tea overboard in the Boston Tea Party in December of 1773. 

&lt;center&gt;[[Image: Boston Tea Party.jpg]]&lt;br&gt;''The Boston Tea Party''&lt;/center&gt;

In retaliation for the Boston Tea Party, Parliament passed the '''Coercive Acts''', which were in the colonies known as the Intolerable Acts.Parliament reduced the power of the Massachusetts legislature and closed the port of Boston. Also, the Quartering Act was extended to require private individuals to lodge soldiers. Furthermore, Parliament allowed royal officials accused of crimes to be tried by a British, rather than a colonial, jury.

== First Continental Congress ==

In order to debate a response to the Intolerable Acts, all American colonies except for Georgia sent delegates to '''the First Continental Congress''' at Philadelphia. The Congress met in September 1774 and issued a Declaration of Rights and Grievances. When the Congress adjourned, it stipulated another Congress would meet if King George III did not meet the demands of the Declaration. When the Second Congress did meet, the military hostilities of the Revolutionary War had already begun, and the issue of Independence, rather than a redress of grievances, dominated the debates.

==Education==

Literacy grew for both men and women during the 18th century. In New England and the Middle States, more middle-class girls were sent to school. However, as Science and the requirements for citizenship became more a part of education, girls were excluded from learning these topics. 

Higher education continued to develop, with the 1746 opening of The College of New Jersey (later known as Princeton), and King's College (now Columbia) in 1754. All of these universities were meant exclusively for White men, though some of the colleges experimented by admitting Native Americans. In the public schools, vocational education expanded.&lt;ref&gt;A people and a nation eight edition&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wikipedia.org\ education_in_the_Age_of_Enlightenment.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;American Education the colonial experience by Cremin A. Lawrence&lt;/ref&gt;

Though what was lost by failing to educate the underclasses was incalculable, we can gauge the possibilities through such individuals as Benjamin Banneker and Phillis Wheatley. Mr. Banneker, a self-educated free African-American, observed the stars, wrote his own almanac, and was one of the surveyors of what would later become the District of Columbia. Miss Wheatley, an African-born slave educated and freed by her mistress, wrote a remarkable volume of poems published in the year 1773. Most of these had been published in ''The Newport Mercury'', edited by Benjamin Franklin's brother James.  

==Questions For Review==
1. What were the reasons for the French and Indian War?

2. What was the strategy of General Braddock against the French at Fort Duquesne? What was the strategy of the defending French and Indian forces?

3. Examine the succession of acts imposed upon the American Colonists in the wake of the war, beginning with the Sugar Act. What was the intended purpose of each act? What was its actual effect?

==Footnotes==
{{reflist}}

===Further reading===
*Eckert, Allan W. ''Wilderness Empire''. Bantam Books, 1994, originally published 1969. ISBN 0-553-26488-5. Second volume in a series of historical narratives, with emphasis on Sir William Johnson. Academic historians often regard Eckert's books, which are written in the style of novels, to be fiction.
*Parkman, Francis. ''Montcalm and Wolfe: The French and Indian War''. Originally published 1884. New York: Da Capo, 1984. ISBN 0-306-81077-8.
*Taylor, Alan. ''American Colonies: The Settling of North America''. Penguin Books, 2001. Edited by Eric Foner. ISBN 0-670-87282-2.


{{chapnav|English Colonies|American Revolution}}</text>
      <sha1>05wfhp1ml8t3ll8wk73t1y4pnvs46u9</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>US History/American Revolution</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1123</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2718167</id>
      <parentid>2682523</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-10-25T23:17:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pittsburgh Poet</username>
        <id>1449338</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>/* The Early Government of the New United States */ added a link to the original Articles of Confederation ~~~~</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">The British forces might at first glance seem to have every advantage. At the outset of the War they had stocks of cannon and ammunition. The Colonists had single-shot rifles from local forges, guns which took time to load and could easily misfire or explode. When Washington took command of the army in 1775, he learned that there was only enough gunpowder to provide nine rounds of ammunition per man.&lt;ref&gt;McCullough, David. ''1776.'' New York: Simon and Schuster, 2005. p. 28&lt;/ref&gt; The British had a large professional army drilled to a pitch like that of Ancient Rome, well-supplied with food, uniforms, and arms. But the American lack of training meant that they did not mass in the European style. Instead they relied on snipers, individuals hidden behind the trees who shot their bullet and then loaded again while their neighbors fired. They had learned this during the French and Indian War. Snipers helped strengthen the American odds. 

==The Beginning of the War (1775 - 1778)==

===Catholics in the Revolution===

The complex situation of Catholicism in Great Britain had results in their Colonies. At the time of the American revolution, Catholics formed approximately 1.6% of the total American population of the original 13 colonies. If Catholics were seen as potential enemies of the British state, Irish Catholics, subject to British rule, were doubly-damned. In Ireland they had been subject to British domination. In America Catholics were still forbidden from settling in some of the colonies. Although the head of their faith dwelt in Rome, they were under the official representation of the Catholic Bishop of the London diocese, one James Talbot. When War began, Bishop Talbot declared his faithfulness to the British Crown. (If he had done otherwise, Catholics in England would have been in trouble. Anti-Catholic sentiment still ran high.) He forbade any Colonial priest to serve Communion. This made practice of the faith impossible. This created sympathy for the Colonial rebels. The Continental Army's alliance with the French increased sympathy for the faith. When the French fleet arrived in Newport, Rhode Island, the colony repealed the Act of 1664 and allowed citizenship to Catholics. (This anticipated the provision of the Constitutional Bill of Rights which would strike anti-Catholic laws from the books.) After the war, the Pope created an American Bishop, John Carroll -- a descendant of the same Carrolls who had helped found Maryland -- and an American Diocese communicating directly with Rome.

===Lexington and Concord===
[[Image:Battle_of_Lexington.jpeg|thumb|300px|right|The skirmish at Lexington.]]
The British government commanded General Thomas Gage to enforce the Intolerable Acts and shut down the Massachusetts legislature. Gage decided to confiscate a stockpile of colonial arms located in Concord. On April 19, 1775, Gage's troops marched to Concord. On the way, at the town of Lexington, Americans who had been warned in advance by Paul Revere and others of the British movements made an attempt to stop the troops. No one knows which side fired the first shot, but it sparked battle on Lexington Green between the British and the Minutemen. Faced against an overwhelmingly superior number of British regular troops in an open field, the Minutemen were quickly routed. Nevertheless, alarms sounded through the countryside. The colonial militias poured in and were able to launch guerrilla attacks on the British while they marched on to Concord. The colonials amassed of troops at Concord. They engaged the British in force there, and they were able to repulse them. They then claimed the contents of the armory. The British retreated to Boston under a constant and withering fire from all sides. Only a reinforcing column with artillery support on the outskirts of Boston prevented the British withdrawal from becoming a total rout. The following day the British woke up to find Boston surrounded by 20,000 armed colonists, occupying the neck of land extending to the peninsula the city stood on.

=== The Battle of Bunker Hill ===
[[Image:Bunker_hill.jpg|thumb|right|250px|The Battle of Bunker Hill.]]
The action changed from a ''battle'' to a ''siege'', where one army bottles up another in a town or a city. (Though in traditional terms, the British were not besieged, since the Royal Navy controlled the harbor and supplies came in by ship.) General Artemas Ward, the head of the Massachusetts militia, had the initial oversight of the siege. He set up headquarters at Cambridge, Massachusetts and positioned his forces at Charlestown Neck, Roxbury, and Dorchester Heights. The 6,000 to 8,000 rebels faced some 4,000 British regulars under General Thomas Gage. Boston and little else was controlled by British troops. General Gage countered the siege on June 17 by attacking the colonists on Breed's Hill and Bunker Hill. Although the British suffered tremendous casualties compared to the colonial losses, the British were eventually able to dislodge the American forces from their entrenched positions. The colonists were forced to retreat when many colonial soldiers ran out of ammunition. Soon after, the area surrounding Boston fell to the British. However, because of the losses they suffered, they were unable to break the siege of the city. Despite the early defeat for the colonists, the battle proved that they had the potential to counter British forces, which were at that time considered the best in the world.  

=== The Last Chance For Peace ===

The Second Continental Congress adopted '''the Olive Branch Petition''', a petition for peace,  on July 5, 1775. The Congress affirmed its allegiance to the Crown. It was received in London at the same time as it heard of the Battle For Bunker Hill. The King refused to read the petition or to meet with its ambassadors. Parliament reacted by passing the Prohibitory Act, which banned trade with the colonies.

===Battle For Boston===

Despite the British access to the ships, the town and the army were on short rations. Salt pork was the order of the day, and prices escalated rapidly. While the American forces had some information about what was happening in the city, General Gage had no effective intelligence of rebel activities.

On May 25, 1775, 4,500 reinforcements and three new generals arrived in Boston Harbor. The fresh leaders were Major General William Howe and Brigadiers John Burgoyne and Henry Clinton. Gage began planing to break out of the city.

On July 3, 1775, George Washington arrived to take charge of the new Continental Army. Forces and supplies came in from as far away as Maryland. Trenches were built at Dorchester Neck,  extending toward Boston. Washington reoccupied Bunker Hill and Breeds Hill without opposition. However, these activities had little effect on the British occupation.

[[Image:Henry_Knox.PNG|thumb|right|150px|Henry Knox helped bring the Continental Army the artillery used to defeat the British.]]In the winter of 1775&amp;ndash; 1776, Henry Knox and his engineers under order from George Washington used sledges to retrieve sixty tons of heavy artillery that had been captured at Fort Ticonderoga. Knox, who had come up with the idea to use sledges, believed that he would have the artillery there in eighteen days. It took six weeks to bring them across the frozen Connecticut River, and they arrived back at Cambridge on January 24, 1776. Weeks later, in an amazing feat of deception and mobility, Washington moved artillery and several thousand men overnight to take Dorchester Heights overlooking Boston. General John Thomas fortified the area. The British fleet had become a liability, anchored in a shallow harbor with limited maneuverability, and under the American guns on Dorchester Heights. 

When General Howe saw the cannons, he knew he could not hold the city. He asked that George Washington let them evacuate the city in peace. In return, they would not burn the city to the ground. Washington agreed: he had no choice. He had artillery guns, but did not have the gunpowder. The whole plan had been a masterful bluff. The siege ended when the British set sail for Halifax, Nova Scotia on March 17, 1776. The militia went home, and in April Washington took most of the Continental Army forces to fortify New York City.

===Ethan Allen and Fort Ticonderoga===

[[Image:Fort_Ticonderoga_1775.jpg|thumb|left|300px|Ethan Allen capturing Fort Tinconderoga.]]
The British had considered Fort Ticonderoga a relatively unimportant outpost in a conflict which had up to then been mostly based in Massachusetts. However, a veteran of the French and Indian War, Ethan Allen, had his eye on the fort. Allen had built up a Vermont territorial militia, the Green Mountain Boys, until it was an effective fighting force. Vermont was claimed by the New York colony, but Allen wanted more independence. In April of 1775, Allen was surprised by a visit by Commander Benedict Arnold of the Connecticut Militia. Arnold announced that '''he''' had been commissioned to seize the cannons of Fort Ticonderoga. A heated discussion between the two concluded with the agreement that the two militias would combine to attack the fort. This was for the best, for both forces together were small, well short of brigade strength. On May tenth, the combined American forces captured the fort. They seized the arms, including the cannons, which were then hauled by oxen all the way to Boston.

== Strengthening The Cause ==

Through the media available in that day, the Revolution promoted the idea of honorable men in revolt against tyranny. Newspapers in North and South published incendiary stories and inspiring engravings. The theater contributed dramatic outcries, including those of Mary Otis Warren. Songs were played and sung to rally flagging spirits.

===Thomas Paine's 1776===

In January of 1776, the Englishman Thomas Paine published the pamphlet ''Common Sense''. This anti-monarchical publication encouraged American independence, using examples from the Bible and republican virtues to argue that kings were never good for any free state. In late 1776 he began printing his series of pamphlets, ''The American Crisis'', calling soldiers to mass to the cause of the Revolution. The first of these pamphlets begins with the stirring words, &quot;These are the times that try men's souls.&quot;

===The Declaration of Independence===

[[Image:Flag at Independence Hall.jpg|thumb|right|Raising the first flag at Independence Hall. Copy of a painting by Clyde O. Deland.]]

As military hostilities built up, the Second Continental Congress appointed George Washington as General of the Continental Army. Washington gave up his salary for the position all through the war. (As he was among the richest men in the colonies, he could afford this choice.) In June of 1776, the Second Continental Congress felt it needed a spur for separation from Great Britain. It appointed a Committee of Five to draft '''a declaration of independence''': John Adams, Benjamin Franklin, Robert Livingston, Roger Sherman and Thomas Jefferson. Jefferson became the principal author of this document. 

Although the British king was no longer principally responsible for his dominion's policy, the Declaration of Independence called him a tyrant. It justified the rights of the rebellion with words the European Enlightenment would have hailed: &quot;We hold these truths to be self-evident, that all men are created equal[.]&quot; The Continental Congress signed the document on July 4, 1776. However, the signatures at this point showed that they wished independence: they could not alone achieve it.

===Army Bands===

One of the attributes of a well-drilled company of soldiers was its military band. The British and Hessian troops drilled to the beat of drums, which carried the rhythm of the march above the noise of musket fire, and provided a way to communicate on the battlefield. &quot;By 1778 soldiers marched at seventy-five 24″ steps per minute in common time and nearly double that (120 steps per minute) when marching in quick time.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Anon. &quot;Middle-brook Order, June 4, 1777: What It Really Says about the Quality of Revolutionary War Field Music.&quot; Paper read at School of the Musician, Brigade of the American Revolution, April 4, 1989. Revised February 12, 2011. Copyright 1989, 2011 HistoryOfTheAncientsDotOrg. http://historyoftheancients.wordpress.com/2012/09/06/1195/&lt;/ref&gt; The music of the fife (a shrill flute) and drum helped build soldier morale. 

If the Rebellion could not have good supplies, it would at least have high morale. With the ''Middle-brook Order'', George Washington directed that every officer must provide military music for his troops. This was despite the limited number of instruments.&lt;ref&gt;Anon, &quot;Middle-brook Order.&lt;/ref&gt; The bands were used to announce the beginning and end of the day, direct troops in battle, and uplift spirits.

===Popular Music in the Revolution===

One of the two major songs of the Revolution was the hymn ''Chester'', first published in 1770 in &quot;The New England Psalm Singer&quot; and revised in 1778. Its author and composer, William Billings, created a combination of the biblical (''Let tyrants shake their iron rod'') and the topical (''Howe and Burgoyne and Clinton too,/ With Prescot and Cornwallis join'd'').

Another was the song ''Yankee Doodle'', adapted from a tune of the Seven Years War. This was originally used by the British to laugh at the provincial manners of the Colonists, but was turned into a theme of the American upstarts.

==Canada==

In September of 1775, the Colonists, led by General Richard Montgomery, invaded Canada. At first the invasion proved successful, with Montgomery capturing Fort St. Jean and the city of Montreal. On December 30 he made the decision to launch an attack onto the British held city of Quebec. It proved disastrous, and Montgomery was killed in battle. This was the last major action in Canada, although Benidict Arnold and a number of other generals did attack the coasts or Canada, or launch raids across the border.

== The Turning Point of the War ==
Despite the numerous defeats they faced in the early years of the war, the colonists were able to turn the tide around with several major victories.

=== New York and New Jersey ===
In July, 1776, General William Howe and thirty-thousand British troops arrived at Staten Island in New York. The large army attacked and defeated General George Washington's American forces in the Battle of Long Island. After nearly having his entire army captured, Washington led a skilled withdrawal out of New York. Eventually the Continental Army was forced to set up camp in Pennsylvania.

Howe could have ended the war by pursuing Washington's forces. But Howe was very cautious and took almost no risks. He feared losing too many men so far from home. Britain hired German mercenaries (Hessians) to guard the British fort at Trenton. Howe took advantage of these replacements and decided to wait until spring to attack the Continental Army again.

Washington also took advantage of the situation, though from a different perspective. He figured that the Hessians would be weakest on Christmas night, after heavy feasting and drinking. On the night of December 25, 1776, Washington led his troops 9 miles, and across the Delaware River to ambush the Hessians. Crossing the river was difficult. A hail and sleet storm had broken out early in the crossing, winds were strong and the river was full of ice floes. The crossing took 3 hours longer than expected, but Washington decided to continue the attack anyway. As Washington predicted, the mercenaries were completely caught off guard and had little time to respond. Within just a over an hour, on the morning of December 26, the Continental Army had won the Battle of Trenton. The Americans had just 4 wounded and 0 killed against 25 Hessians Killed, 90 wounded and 920 captured. The victory increased the troops' morale and eventually led to re-enlistments. Some historians even speculate Trenton saved the revolution. 

On January 2, the British came to re-take Trenton, and did so with heavy casualties. Washington once again led a clever withdrawal, and advanced on Princeton. At the Battle of Princeton, the Continental Army attacked the rear-guard of the British Army, and forced them to retreat from New Jersey.

=== The Battle of Saratoga ===
[[Image:Surrender_of_General_Burgoyne.jpg|thumb|left|250px|Burgoyne surrendering the Continental Army.]]
In the summer of 1777, British General John Burgoyne and General Howe agreed to attack the colonial Army from two sides and defeat it. Howe marched north, winning the Battles of Brandywine and Germantown and eventually capturing Philadelphia. But Burgoyne was not so fortunate. Delayed by natural traps set up by the Continental Army, his troops slowly marched from Canada to Albany. By September of the year, his forces reached Saratoga, where an enormous American Army attacked the troops. In October, General Burgoyne surrendered all his forces to the Americans. General Howe resigned his post, thwarted despite his victories in Pennsylvania.

The Battle of Saratoga proved to be the major turning point in the war. It persuaded France that America had to overthrow Great Britain, and French aid now was introduced to the colonists. The battle was also the last time the British would advance North. By the summer of 1778, following the Battle of Monmouth in New Jersey, all fighting would take place in the South.

=== Defeat of the Iroquois ===
The Iroquois Confederacy in its zenith had been the equal of the European Powers. But since the French and Indian war it had been in decline. The Tribes of the Confederacy disagreed on who to support in the Revolution. The Onedia and Tuscaroras supported the Americans, while the Mohawk, Onondaga, Cayuga, and the Seneca supported the British. The Confederacy managed to stay together until 1777, when following the Battle of Saratoga, the 4 Tribes supporting the British began to attack American settlements across New York and Pennslyvenia. 

A back and forth battle followed. The Iroquois would attack American Forts and Towns, then the Americans would burn Iroquois villages. In 1779 George Washington sent General Sullivan to destroy the Iroquois Nation. After defeating the Iroquois at the Battle of Newtown, Sullivan's army then carried out a scorched earth campaign, methodically destroying at least forty Iroquois villages. The devastation created great hardships for the thousands of Iroquois refugees outside Fort Niagara that winter, and many starved or froze to death. The survivors fled to British regions in Canada and the Niagara Falls and Buffalo areas. Thus ended the 700-year history of the Iroquois Confederacy.

== Conclusion of the War (1778 - 1781) ==

After the loss at Saratoga, the French, traditional rivals of the British, offered their aid in the Revolution. The United States allied itself with France in 1778. Spain and the Dutch Republic also joined the American side, both lending money to the United States and going to war with Britain.
===On the Seas===
War broke out on the seas as well. Americans granted commissions to &quot;privateers&quot; to attack and destroy all British ships, whether they were military or not. One of the most famous privateers, John Paul Jones, scored several victories at sea for the Americans, even attacking the shores of Britain itself.
[[Image:Yorktown80.JPG|thumb|250px|Benjamin Lincoln accepting the British surrender at Yorktown, with Washington in the background.]]

===The War Heads South===

An attempted treachery was defeated when its architect, British Major John Andre, was captured in September of 1780. Benedict Arnold, one of the heroes of Fort Ticonderoga, had been placed in charge of Fort Clinton, New York (now called West Point). In response to a bribe, Arnold neglected maintenance of the fortification, and was then preparing to turn the fort over to the British. After he had learned of Andre's arrest he fled to join the British army.

Britain turned its attention from the North to the South, where more loyalists lived. They were at first very successful, defeating the Americans at Waxhaws, Charleston, and Camden. Lord Cornwallis, commander of the British forces in the south, was faced with the challenge of chasing down the Americans. Nathanael Greene had split his army into two, leaving one under the control of Daniel Morgan. Morgan drew Banastre Tarleton, who was commanding one half of the British Army, to Cowpens where they were they decisively defeated the British. The other half of the British Army, still under control of Cornwallis, defeated the Americans at the Battle of Guilford Court House. However, it was a bloody victory for Cornwallis and he was forced to withdraw to Yorktown Virginia to regroup.

After hearing that the British were in Yorktown, and there was a French Fleet arriving, Washington took the Continental Army, along with French Troops, to Yorktown and surrounded the British. By mid September the town was under siege. Cornwallis was assured by British Commander-in-Chief, Henry Clinton, who was in New York, that he would be relieved shortly. However, the British relief force was defeated by the French fleet. The British continued to hold off for a few more days, but the allied army moved in closer and closer to Yorktown, and their cannons destroyed many of the British defenses. On October 19, 1781, Cornwallis surrendered his entire army, over 7,000 men. 

Scattered fighting continued, but back in Britain, the British were crushed by this defeat. Parliament voted to cease all offensive operations in &quot;the colonies.&quot; Washington took his army to Newburgh, New York, where he stopped a mutiny in the Army.

At the conclusion of the war in 1783 large numbers of loyalists and their families relocated to the home country of England and in large part to Canada as well as to other British Colonies. They submitted claims for lost property and lands in America. Many of the claims were not accepted by the English government for lack of evidence of the losses or significantly reduced. The property and lands were acquired by the American communities and then resold to the highest bidders. 

Due to the climatic effects of a 1782 eruption of an Icelandic volcano, the loyalists also experienced one of the coldest Canadian winters on record which contributed to poor crops in 1783-1784. Starvation, disease and hardship were rampant and many resolved to return to the United States despite the threats of retribution rather than subsist on their meager produce.

== Treaty of Paris (1783) ==

The British lost hope of crushing the rebellion after Yorktown. They decided to negotiate peace with The United States, France, and Spain. '''The Treaty of Paris''' was signed on September 3rd, 1783. In it, the United States was recognized as an independent nation, with boundaries stretching from the Canadian border in the North, to the Mississippi River to the West, and the northern border of Florida in the South. Britain was forced to return Florida to Spain, but could still hold Canada. Congress was told to advise the states to restore property lost or stolen from the Loyalists. (However, many Loyalists had fled during the Revolution, and many of them did not return to claim their property.)

{{chapnav|Road to Revolution|Constitution Early Years}}

==The Early Government of the New United States==

[Copied from Wikipedia]

The '''Articles of Confederation''', formally the '''Articles of Confederation and Perpetual Union''', was an agreement among the 13 founding states that established the United States of America as a confederation of sovereign states and served as its first constitution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last = Jensen| first = Merrill| title = The Articles of Confederation: An Interpretation of the Social-Constitutional History of the American Revolution, 1774–1781| year = 1959| publisher = University of Wisconsin Press| isbn = 978-0-299-00204-6| pages = xi, 184 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Its drafting by the Continental Congress began in mid-1776, and an approved version was sent to the states for ratification in late 1777. The formal ratification by all 13 states was completed in early 1781. Even when not yet ratified, the Articles provided domestic and international legitimacy for the Continental Congress to direct the American Revolutionary War, conduct diplomacy with Europe and deal with territorial issues and Native American relations. Nevertheless, the weakness of the government created by the Articles became a matter of concern for key nationalists. [Whom?]

{{wikisource|The Articles of Confederation}}

==Footnotes==
{{reflist}}

==Questions for Review==

1. Who were these authors/composers, and what were they known for? (Mary Otis Warren, Thomas Jefferson, Thomas Paine, William Billings.)

2. How does the battle of Lexington and Concord show the early strengths and weaknesses of the American fighters?

3. Examine a copy of the Declaration of Independence in relation to this and the previous chapters. How does its rhetoric (choice of words) address the concerns of the American rebellion? How does it deviate from actual events to make a point?

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>brafjhrmrpe6b9wo72bqrs12m0pav0x</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>US History/Truman and Cold War</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1125</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2528885</id>
      <parentid>2528884</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-05-25T16:23:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Wim b</username>
        <id>83416</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 2528884 by [[Special:Contributions/86.14.71.28|86.14.71.28]] ([[User talk:86.14.71.28|discuss]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">From 1942-1945, the [[w:Red Army|Red Army]] had advanced upon the capital city of Hitler's so called &quot;Thousand Year Reich,&quot; crushing everything in its path.  The Soviets had fought their way through 1500 miles from Stalingrad to Berlin as their allies, the British and Americans, advanced from the beaches of Normandy. On April 27, 1945, advanced units of the US and Soviet armies met in the town of Torgau. There they had spent much time enjoying the company of being allies, brothers-in-arms, but never suspected what would happen after they would dethrone the man who had failed on his conquest of world domination.&lt;ref&gt;Isaacs, Jeremy, Taylor Downing, Markus Schurr, Heike Schlatterer, and Norbert Juraschitz. DerKalte Krieg: Ein Illustrierte Geschichte, 1945-1991. Mu%u0308nchen [etc.: Diana Verlag, 1999. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Bitter Aftermath of Victory==
===Soviet Union===
At the end of World War II, the [[w:Soviet Union|Soviet Union]] controlled the largest army the world had ever known.  Though the &quot;Mother Country&quot; lay ravaged; nearly one third of its former wealth had been destroyed.  32,000 factories were in ruin, 65,000 kilometers of railway track were now useless, and the number of citizens lost during the war are unknown but in a high margin. Of the townships lost, 17,100 were destroyed; of its villages and hamlets, 70,000 were burned to the ground; of its collective farms, 100,000 were completely demolished due to military occupation. Citizens who did survive were now starving and resorting to barbaric ways of surviving under these disastrous conditions.

The Soviet Union was basking in the glory of victory, since everywhere there was immense respect for the Red Army. From years of titanic struggle with the Wehrmacht, meaning &quot;defensive might&quot; in German, the Soviets were widely regarded as having borne the brunt of destroying Nazism, and &quot;Uncle Joe&quot; Stalin had become a popular figure in Europe and in the United States. All across Europe sizable elements of the population were seriously considering the virtues of Communism because very few wanted a return to the failed capitalism of the pre-war era. Many Europeans thought that having won the war, Stalin could now win the peace
&lt;ref&gt;Isaacs, Jeremy, Taylor Downing, Markus Schurr, Heike Schlatterer, and Norbert Juraschitz. DerKalte Krieg: Ein Illustrierte Geschichte, 1945-1991. Mu%u0308nchen, etc.: Diana Verlag, 1999. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
After the war, America's economy was ready to expand into markets on every continent.  During the war, much of the world had built up a debt to the United States, and many ex-allies turned towards America for financial relief.  Britain negotiated a loan of $3.75 billion. Even the Soviet Union discussed with Washington about the possibility of a $6 billion loan for desperately needed reconstruction.&lt;ref&gt;Isaacs, Jeremy, Taylor Downing, Markus Schurr, Heike Schlatterer, and Norbert Juraschitz. DerKalte Krieg: Ein Illustrierte Geschichte, 1945-1991. Mu%u0308nchen, etc.: Diana Verlag, 1999. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the Bretton Woods Conference on the postwar global economy in 1944, the dollar was established as the worlds principal trading currency, while the pound was relegated to second place. Because the dollar was the only currency freely convertible throughout the world,many nations hoped for loans and assistance from the United States. And since the United States was the only power possessing the atom bomb, America seemed to have the advantage in both military and economy when it came to determining the future shape of the world.&lt;ref&gt;Isaacs, Jeremy, Taylor Downing, Markus Schurr, Heike Schlatterer, and Norbert Juraschitz. DerKalte Krieg: Ein Illustrierte Geschichte, 1945-1991. Mu%u0308nchen, etc.: Diana Verlag, 1999. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the Cold War the United States opened up many different job opportunities to help out other countries who agreed not to favor communism. This began to become very beneficial to the United States because many countries came to the United States aid to help fight against communism.

==Yalta Conference==
In early February 1945, United States President Franklin D. Roosevelt, British Prime Minister Winston Churchill, and Soviet leader Josef Stalin, the three leaders of the anti-Nazi alliance, met at Yalta in the U.S.S.R.&lt;ref&gt;Sibley, Katherine A. S. The Cold War. Westport, CT: Greenwood, 1998. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;
These leaders of the Allied powers were known as &quot;The Big Three”.  The Big Three had met before in November 1943 at the Tehran Conference.  The reason the meeting was in Yalta is because Stalin could not travel too far.  His doctors advised him to travel some place close, so Stalin recommended Yalta, which is by the Black Sea.&lt;ref&gt;http://militaryhistory.about.com/od/worldwarii/p/yalta.htm&lt;/ref&gt; They each had goals to shape the postwar world. The Soviet Union, with 21 million people dead, wanted Germany to pay reparations to fund massive rebuilding efforts. They hoped to expand their influence throughout eastern Europe and guarantee national security. Two German invasions in a quarter century was more than enough and Germany had to be permanently weakened. 

The topics of the Conference included Soviet Russia's entry into the war against Japan, composition of the post-war government of Germany,voting arrangements in the new United Nations organizations, and the future of the liberated governments of Eastern Europe.&lt;ref&gt;Sibley, Katherine A. S. The Cold War. Westport, CT: Greenwood, 1998. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

While all were important topics, the Yalta Declaration on Liberated Europe, which called for free elections and constitutional liberties in Eastern Europe, was the most controversial topic of the Yalta Conference.&lt;ref&gt;Sibley, Katherine A. S. The Cold War. Westport, CT: Greenwood, 1998. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Truman Doctrine ==

World War II changed the balance of power in the international community by reducing the influence of France and the United Kingdom, while at the same time elevating the influence of the United States and the Soviet Union, which assumed the role of the world's only two superpowers. Initially, the sentiments of the US government towards the avowedly socialist Soviet Union were friendly, but in the aftermath of the war, relations between the two powers quickly deteriorated. At the end of World War II, a number of entities were established by Allied nations to help maintain international order; the most notable of these was the [[w:United Nations|United Nations]]. Within the framework of the UN, the United States and Britain advocated for the creation of a regulatory entity for the world's monetary system which would help avoid another worldwide depression similar to that seen during the Great Depression before the war.  Talks among Allied delegates were held in 1944 which resulted in the creation of the [[w:International Monetary Fund|International Monetary Fund]] and what would eventually become the [[w:World Bank|World Bank]], both of which were established to make currency exchange easier and to regulate international debt. The Soviet government was highly suspicious of these entities--it viewed them as a tool for the western world to force capitalism on socialist member-states--and it refused to support them.

This refusal of the USSR to support the IMF and the World Bank set off a diplomatic chain reaction that would eventually grow into what became known as the Cold War.

The Soviet Union believed that its control of Eastern Europe was vital to its security, and said that it was rightful for it to do so, for &quot;we suffered at Stalingrad&quot;. As agreed at the Yalta Conference, the World War II Allies divided Germany into four zones, giving one zone each to the United Kingdom, France, the United States, and the Soviet Union. The Soviet Union's zone, known as East Germany, was later transformed into a Communist state, after an agreement on a unified Germany could not be reached. The other three zones, West Germany, were joined - at first economically through a currency reform - during the implementation of the Marshall Plan in 1948. The city of Berlin, which was surrounded by East Germany, was divided in two parts between East and West Germany. Critics correctly pointed out that the Soviet Union was little involved in the Greek Civil War, that the communists in Greece were more pro-Tito than pro-Stalin, and that the resistance movement had non-communists as well as communist members. Nor was The Soviet Union threatening turkey at the time. Others suggested that such aid should be channeled through the United Nations.

In 1947, Greece became the focus of the Cold War. The Greek monarchy had been supported by Great Britain since 1945. Greek Communists threatened to overthrow this regime, which was corrupt and not representative of the people. In order to &quot;shock&quot; the American public into accepting American involvement in order to help other peoples resist the &quot;communist threat&quot; and secure the strategically and economically important Middle East for US influence, President Harry Truman issued the ''Truman Doctrine''. The Doctrine suggested that the US would aid nations threatened by revolutionary forces. Congress agreed and appropriated $400 million in aid for Greece and Turkey. By 1949, the Communists in Greece were defeated. In 1952, Greece and Turkey entered the NATO.

== The Marshall Plan ==

The Marshall Plan was the first attempt to achieve the goals that America set in western Europe. The European nations were still unstable, both in politics and in economics, and so they did not have the money to purchase the good that they required from the U.S. The people and government of America were all extremely worried that if Europe's funds continued to be so unstable, this would trigger another great depression. With the memories of all the hardships and economic ruin of the Great Depression in the 1930s fresh in the American people's minds, the government decided they needed to do something. In order to make sure that there was not another worldwide depression, in 1948 the American government decided to launch a massive European recovery program called the Marshall Plan which sent 12.4 billion dollars to western Europe. A condition of this program was that Europe would spend this foreign-aid money on American products. This program ended in 1951. The Marshall Plan was a mixture of failure and success. In Europe, it assisted to further divide eastern and western Europe and it caused inflation which did nothing to solve the balance-of-payment problem. However, this program did succeed in spurring western European industrialization and investment. &lt;ref&gt;A People and A Nation Eighth Edition&lt;/ref&gt;

== Reconstruction of the New World ==

The leadership in the United States by contrast, came out of war extremely confident about the immediate security of the country’s borders. Separated from the other world powers by two vast oceans, the American home base had been virtually immune from attack during the fighting—only the occasional shell from a submarine or a hostile balloon reached the shores of the continental United States American casualties were fewer than those of any other major combatants—hugely so in comparison with the Soviet Union. With its fixed capital intact, its resources more plentiful than ever, and in lone possession of the atomic bomb, the United States was the strongest power in the world at war’s ends. 

Yet this was no time for complacency, Washington officials reminded one another. Some other power — almost certainly the USSR — could take advantage of the political and economic instability in war-torn Europe and Asia, and eventually seize control of these areas, with dire implications for America’s physical and economic security. To prevent this eventuality, officials in Washington sought forward bases overseas, in order to keep a airborne enemy at bay. To further enhance U.S. security, American planners, in direct contrast to their Soviet counterparts, sought the quick reconstruction of nations—including the former enemies Germany and Japan—and a world economy based on free trade. Such a system, they reasoned, was essential to preserve America’s economic well being.

The Soviets, on the other hand refused to join the new World Bank and International Monetary Fund, created at the July 1944 Bretton Woods Conference by forty-four nations to stabilize trade and finances. They held that the United States dominated both institutions and used them to promote private investment and open international commerce, which Moscow saw as capitalist tools of exploitation.  With the United States as its largest donor, the World Bank opened its doors in 1945 and began to make loans to help members finance reconstruction projects; the IMF, also heavily backed by the united states, helped members meet their balance-of-payment problems through currency loans.

== Reconstruction of Japan ==

The atomic bomb allowed the United States to win World War II against Japan before a Soviet invasion. After Japan's surrender in 1945, the United States military was called in to reconstruct Japan. American General Douglas MacArthur headed the Reconstruction effort.
After dropping the two atomic bombs on Japan, a large area of its land has become uninhabitable due to high amounts of radio activity in its surrounding areas. This high amount of radio activity has caused many sicknesses and people ending up dieing from cancer and other diseases.

In 1947, a new Constitution for Japan was created. The Constitution entirely changed the role of the Emperor from an active leader to a passive symbol of the nations. The Diet, or legislature, was modeled on the British Parliament. The Constitution granted an enormous number of rights to Japanese citizens. Finally, the Constitution formally denounced all military conflict and prohibited Japan from keeping any armed forces.

The Reconstruction of Japan made other sweeping changes. For example, the Reconstruction introduced labor unions and reduced the influence of monopolistic businesses. 

During the Cold War, America was determined to make an ally out of the Empire of Japan. The Reconstruction made an about-face, reversing its policy of reducing the power of large businesses. More regulations regarding the economy were made. In 1951, the US agreed to grant Japan full independence and autonomy. The treaty, however, did permit the US to maintain parts of its military in Japan. The treaty became effective in 1952.

== The Rise of Communism in China ==
After the fall of the Qing Dynasty, China was in a state of confusion and unrest. The nation saw the worst nightmares as the people were without an authority to rule over. She soon became rudderless giant. Many land lords took advantage of the situation and gradually the situation became worse. The period of warlordism  in China lasted from 1916 to 1927 when warlords fought against each other regardless of common ideas or purpose. This was a dark period in China’s history.

Meanwhile the principles of communism began to spread in the country and those ideals attracted a majority of the people. The people who belonged to the lower strata were for these principles especially for the law of equality.

The rise of Communism in China is mainly due to a man named Mao Zedong. He was poorly educated as a child but highly intelligent. Zedong left home and had become a member of the Nationalist Army as the Revolution began around 1911. He was soon introduced to and became powerfully influenced by the philosophies of Marxism.

After decades of civil war and invasion by Japan, the communists under Mao prevailed. The opposition nationalists fell and barely managed to retreat offshore to Taiwan. Communism came to power in 1949 under the power of Mao. Communism began as a movement that paved the way for the liberation of the proletariat.  Proletariat is that class of society which lives entirely from the sale of its labor and does not draw profit from any kind of capital; whose weal and woe, whose life and death, whose sole existence depends on the demand for labor – hence, on the changing state of business, on the vagaries of unbridled competition. The proletariat, or the class of proletarians, is, in a word, the working class of the 19th century.

Anarchy was to some extend controlled by Mao but he faced failure many times. Mao’s initiatives did cause a kind of equality to emerge in China, but it was not one in which all the inhabitants of China benefited. Contrarily, many of them suffered extreme poverty and greatness was lost in the realms of academia, science, and technology which hindered China’s ability to become a modern nation capable of interacting on the global scale.

Chinese policy changed after Deng Xiaoping took control in 1977 after Mao’s death. Deng Xiaoping succeeded him although he possessed different views than those of Mao’s – especially in regards to economic matters. Deng Xiaoping believed that it was necessary for China to embrace a more free market system so that it could recover economically.


Though he failed in developing the steel industry of the country he could implement his improvement policies in most of the other fields. China’s economy began to flourish and Deng began promoting modern industrialization as well. He allowed people to once again own land and businesses which resulted in many of the government’s collective farm and industry programs to be stopped. Deng also allowed for loans to be given to some state supported businesses. He also encouraged citizens to invest in these companies and to work hard by allowing a system of incentives to be developed for hard work.
 

As a result of embracing slightly capitalistic principles, China was able to begin the reconstruction of its economy. Despite many governmental controls that were still in place on industry and trade, China’s economy began to flourish and Deng began promoting modern industrialization as well. China has continued to stay true to being a socialist state because it still regulates lending, especially to private companies which still often find it difficult to obtain credit or a loan for their ventures.

== The Red Scare and McCarthyism ==


While Communism was expanding across the World, the United States entered an era of paranoia known as the ''Red Scare''. Suspicion of Communist influence in government was pandemic.

In Congress, the House of Representatives established a Committee on Un-American Activities. The Committee performed actions such as investigating entertainment companies. The entertainment industry, fearful of an investigation, often refused to hire Communist artists or anyone at all ever connected with Communism.

In the Senate, meanwhile, Wisconsin Senator Joseph McCarthy accused certain government officials of being disloyal Communists. While a communist conspiracy involving State Department employees was eventually uncovered, the word ''McCarthyism'' would forever refer to a vindictive persecution of the innocent.

The Red Scare proved costly in American foreign policy. When China fell to Communism, many experts on China and the regions around it were fired. This was a problem when the Korean War (see below) rolled around. It was also a pain in the Vietnam War, as the Vietnam terrain experts had all been accused of being Communist.

Congress passed the McCarran Internal Security Act in 1950, overriding President Truman's veto. The Act created a public body known as the ''Subversive Activities Control Board''; the Board was charged with monitoring and investigating Communist Activities. 

At the local level, some communities banned literature that they feared would encourage Communism. Public servants lost their jobs due to unfounded accusations of disloyalty. Lives were destroyed by the Red Scare. Ironically, the career of Joseph McCarthy was also derailed during the Red Scare; in 1954, the Senate decided to formally censure him for abusing his powers and using unfair tactics in targeting innocent government officials.

Even at the height of the McCarthyist furor in the early 1950s, the anti-Communist crusade was relatively mild. Many prosecutions faltered on appeal and only a few foreign-born radicals were actually deported. Only Julius and Ethel Rosenberg were put to death; and of the roughly 150 people who went to prison, most were released within a year or two.

The Hollywood blacklist—as the broader entertainment industry blacklist is generally known—was the mid-twentieth-century list of screenwriters, actors, directors, musicians, and other U.S. entertainment professionals who were denied employment in the field because of their political beliefs or associations, real or suspected. This group became known as the Hollywood Ten.

== The Korean War ==

After World War II, the US attempted to curb Soviet influence on the Korean Peninsula by occupying southern part of that area. The area occupied by the US became South Korea, while the other part became North Korea. North Korea soon passed into the control of the Communist Party.

In May, 1949, fighting between North and South Korean troops broke out near the border between the two nations. In an attempt to add South Korea to the Communist World, North Korea invaded South Korea in 1950. The People's Republic of China and the Soviet Union lent their support to North Korea, while the United States did the same to South Korea.
On June 25, 1950 a large military force moved across the 38th parallel in the Republic of Korea. Since 1910, Korea had been divided into two by the powers of Japans victory in 1945. The Korean war was seen as an internal struggle, with the north heavily armed and backed by China and the Soviet Union invading the lightly armed south. The two parts moved along the temporary border while the anti-government fighting began to flare into the south.

On June 27, 1950 the United Nations security Council first adopted a ceasefire resolution. When the United Nations Security Council voted to aid South Korea in stopping North Korean aggression, the United States agreed to send troops to the Korean Peninsula. General Douglas MacArthur was given the command of UN troops in Korea. The United States agreed to send troops over on June 30 along with increasing aid to the French fight against Communists rebels in Indochina. MacArthur was placed in command on July 8. At the beginning the U.S. troops were lacking training and were out of shape. In the first few weeks of fighting the U.S. troops were pushed back to a defensive perimeter at Pusan.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Don't Know Much About History&quot; by Kenneth C. Davis&lt;/ref&gt; 

By the autumn of 1950, North Korean troops were forced out of South Korea. In October, General MacArthur ordered troops to cross into North Korea. In the third week of that month, the US took the capital of North Korea, Pyongyang. 

However, just six days after the United Nations forces took Pyongyang, the People's Republic of China sent a quarter million men on a series of counterattacks. In December, Chinese &quot;volunteers&quot; took over Pyongyang and by January 1951 they had taken the South Korean capital, Seoul.

The US intended to do whatever it took to win the Korean War. It even planned on using the atomic bomb. However, President Truman did not trust General MacArthur to follow orders when using the atomic bomb. Therefore, he asked for MacArthur's resignation; MacArthur complied.

In 1953, Dwight D. Eisenhower became President of the US. Having promised during the election campaign to end the Korean War, he fulfilled this promise by continuing negotiations with the North and South Koreans, Chinese, and the Soviet Union and using &quot;brinkmanship&quot; to reach an agreement acceptable to all countries involved except for South Korea, which tried to induce the US to help unite Korea.

==Weapons of the Cold War==
The nuclear arms race was central to the Cold War. Many feared where the Cold War was going with the belief that the more nuclear weapons you had, the more powerful you were. Both America and The Soviet Union massively built up their stockpiles of nuclear weapons.

The world greatly changed when USA exploded the H-bomb in 1952. This one bomb was smaller in size than the Hiroshima atomic bomb but 2500 times more powerful. The Soviets produced an H-bomb in 1953 and the world became a much more dangerous place.

However, it is possible that the sheer power of these weapons and the fear that they evoked, may have stopped a nuclear war.

USA produced a bomber - the B52 - that could fly 6,000 miles and deliver a nuclear pay-load. Such a development required massive financial backing from the government - something which America could afford to do and which The Soviet Union could not. The Soviet Union concentrated on producing bigger bombs - a far more cost effective procedure.

In October 1957, the world was introduced to the fear of a missile attack when the Soviet Satellite Sputnik was launched. This was to lead to ICBM’s :  Inter-continental ballistic missiles. As a result, America built the [[w:Distant Early Warning Line|DEW line]] around the Arctic - Distant Early Warning system.

At the end of the 1950’s, American Intelligence estimated that in a Soviet missile attack, 20 million Americans would die and 22 million would be injured.

During the 1960’s, the Soviet's put their money into producing larger missiles, Eventually creating Tsar Bomba, the biggest Nuclear Weapon ever created. America built fewer but technologically superior missiles - the Atlas could go 5,000 miles at a speed of 16,000 mph. By 1961, there were enough bombs to destroy the world.

Despite this, great emphasis was put on new weapon systems - mobile missile launchers were built, missiles were housed underground in silos and in 1960 the first Polaris submarine was launched carrying 16 nuclear missiles. Each missile carried four warheads which could targeted on different cities; hence one submarine effectively carried 64 nuclear warheads.

During the 1960’s the theory of MAD developed - Mutually Assured Destruction. This meant that if The Soviet Union attacked the west, the west would make sure that they would suitably retaliate  i.e. there would be no winners.

By 1981, USA had 8,000 ICBMs and USSR 7,000 ICBMs

By 1981, USA had 4,000 planes capable of delivering a nuclear bomb. the USSR had 5000.

USA defense spending for 1981 = 178 billion dollars. By 1986, it was 367 billion dollars.

By 1986, it is estimated that throughout the world there were 40,000 nuclear warheads - the equivalent of one million Hiroshima bombs.

British Intelligence estimated that just one medium sized H-bomb on London would essentially destroy anything living up to 30 miles away.

Confronted by such awesome statistics, world leaders had to move to a position where they trusted each other more. Throughout the 1960's and 1970's &quot;detente&quot; had been used to ease bad relations between the superpowers. This was to culminate in the Reykjavik meeting between presidents Reagan and Gorbachev that started real progress in the cut in nuclear weaponry in future meetings (if little was actually gained at the meeting in Reykjavik).

== President Harry S. Truman ==
President Truman was born on May 8th; 1884.  During World War 1, Truman was part of the Democratic party.  He was elected a county official in Kansas, and later elected a senator.  Moving his way up Truman eventually became Roosevelt's vice president.  Truman faced many challenges in his life as president.  These include wars, civil rights, and women's rights. Harry Truman was the 33rd President of the United States. Truman had been vice president for only 82 days when President Roosevelt died, April 12, 1945. He told reporters, &quot;I felt like the moon, the stars, and all the planets had fallen on me.&quot; He had had very little communication with Roosevelt about world affairs or domestic politics and was uninformed about major initiatives relating to the war and the top secret Manhattan Project, which was about to test the world's first atomic bomb. Truman was much more difficult for the Secret Service to protect than the wheel chair–bound Roosevelt had been. Truman was an avid walker, regularly taking walks around Washington. Truman was President from April 12, 1945 to January 20, 1953. Deciding not to run again, he retired to Independence; at age 88, he died December 26, 1972, after a stubborn fight for life.

Eisenhower
==Eisenhower==
In addition to his desire to halt the advance of “creeping socialism” in U.S. domestic policy, Eisenhower also wanted to “roll back” the advances of Communism abroad. After taking office in 1953, he devised a new foreign policy tactic to contain the Soviet Union and even win back territory that had already been lost. Devised primarily by Secretary of State John Foster Dulles, this so-called New Look at foreign policy proposed the use of nuclear weapons and new technology rather than ground troops and conventional bombs, all in an effort to threaten “massive retaliation” against the USSR for Communist advances abroad.

In addition to intimidating the Soviet Union, this emphasis on new and cheaper weapons would also drastically reduce military spending, which had escalated rapidly during the Truman years. As a result, Eisenhower managed to stabilize defense spending, keeping it at roughly half the congressional budget during most of his eight years in office.

The doctrine of massive retaliation proved to be dangerously flawed, however, because it effectively left Eisenhower without any options other than nuclear war to combat Soviet aggression. This dilemma surfaced in 1956, for instance, when the Soviet Union brutally crushed a popular democratic uprising in Hungary. Despite Hungary’s request for American recognition and military assistance, Eisenhower’s hands were tied because he knew that the USSR would stop at nothing to maintain control of Eastern Europe. He could not risk turning the Cold War into a nuclear war over the interests of a small nation such as Hungary.

As an alternative, Eisenhower employed the CIA to tackle the specter of Communism in developing countries outside the Soviet Union’s immediate sphere of influence. Newly appointed CIA director Allen Dulles (the secretary of state’s brother) took enormous liberties in conducting a variety of covert operations. Thousands of CIA operatives were assigned to Africa, Asia, Latin America, and the Middle East and attempted to launch coups, assassinate heads of state, arm anti-Communist revolutionaries, spread propaganda, and support despotic pro-American regimes. Eisenhower began to favor using the CIA instead of the military because covert operations didn’t attract as much attention and cost much less money.

A CIA-sponsored coup in Iran in 1953, however, did attract attention and heavy criticism from liberals both at home and in the international community. Eisenhower and the Dulles brothers authorized the coup in Iran when the Iranian government seized control of the British-owned Anglo-Iranian Oil Company. Afraid that the popular, nationalist, Soviet-friendly prime minister of Iran, Mohammed Mossadegh, would then cut off oil exports to the United States, CIA operatives convinced military leaders to overthrow Mossadegh and restore Mohammed Reza Shah Pahlavi as head of state in 1953. Pahlavi returned control of Anglo-Iranian Oil to the British and then signed agreements to supply the United States with almost half of all the oil drilled in Iran.

The following year, a similar coup in Guatemala over agricultural land rights also drew international criticism and severely damaged U.S.–Latin American relations.

==References==

{{reflist}}
{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>gqvp6zhxaujdw9546ddlgq7jyuea3wq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>US History/Friction Between States</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1126</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2019646</id>
      <parentid>2019374</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-01-19T19:57:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Recent Runes</username>
        <id>66908</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/76.232.69.23|76.232.69.23]] ([[User talk:76.232.69.23|discuss]]) to last revision by [[User:Adrignola|Adrignola]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">== Ideas and Questions of the Time ==

The overriding question throughout the decade preceding the Civil War was, “Should slavery be allowed in the new territories of the United States?” Before 1848, the question had been hypothetical; however, with the new lands acquired during the Mexican War, it was time for America to make a firm decision regarding the expansion of slavery. 

The central ideas dominating the debate were:

=== The Wilmot Proviso ===

On August 8, 1846, Representative David Wilmot, a Pennsylvania Democrat, presented a proposal expressing that “slavery nor involuntary servitude shall ever exist in any part of any territory obtained from Mexico.” The Wilmot Proviso was never accepted as law, but it at long last put the issue forth on the political table.

=== The Calhoun Resolutions ===

John C. Calhoun, the South Carolina statesman, responded with the Calhoun Resolutions, which said that Congress had no right to stop any citizen with slaves in their possession from taking those slaves into one of the territories. If they did so, the Fifth Amendment, which states that no person can be “deprived of life, liberty, or property, without due process of law,” would be violated. While this was not made formal legislation either, this belief became the standard in most of the south. 

=== Popular Sovereignty ===

A third option, which appealed to many moderates, most prominently Stephen A. Douglas of Illinois, was the idea of popular sovereignty. This was the idea of letting the settlers of a territory themselves decide whether slavery was to be allowed in it, by voting on state constitutions and other such measures. The primary merit of this initiative was that it took the debate out of Congress, which quickly grew tired of the issue, and put it into the hands of people it truly affected. There was also an unspoken understanding that most of the territories would end up being free, as most settlers that were already in those areas did not bring their slaves with them.

== Compromise of 1850 ==

America looked to the Senate for an answer to the question of slavery within the territories. Henry Clay, nicknamed the &quot;Great Compromiser,&quot; constructed a compromise: California was admitted as a free state, but all other territories in the Mexican Cession were allowed to choose between becoming a free territory or a slave territory. Also, as part of the Compromise, the slave trade was banned in the District of Columbia, and a Fugitive Slave Act was passed to allow the capture of fugitive slaves.

The Fugitive Slave Act was a very controversial measure. Previously, many in the North felt that slavery merely occurred in the South and that they had nothing to do with it. But under the Fugitive Slave Act, Northerners were required to help return runaway slaves. Thus, the Northerners felt that they were being dragged into aiding the institution of slavery. Several Northern states passed laws prohibiting their officials from aiding the enforcement of the Act.

While the admission of California as a free state gave the free states the majority in Congress, the pro-slavery measures in the Fugitive Slave Act made the Compromise seem more favorable to the South.

== Uncle Tom’s Cabin ==

Harriet Beecher Stowe’s &lt;i&gt;Uncle Tom’s Cabin&lt;/i&gt;, published in 1852, is often called “the book that started the Civil War.” The melodramatic story of the evil overseer Simon Legree and his slaves Eliza and Uncle Tom painted an accurate picture of the horrors of slavery, and gave rise to much abolitionist feeling in the North. However, the effects were not easily visible from the start: because the country was growing tired of the sectional bickering over slavery, it took a while for the story to becoming embedded in the American imagination.

==Nat Turner==
Nat, commonly called Nat Turner, (October 2, 1800 – November 11, 1831) was an American slave whose slave rebellion in Southampton County, Virginia, was the most remarkable instance of black resistance to enslavement in the antebellum southern United States. His methodical slaughter of white civilians during the uprising makes his legacy controversial, but he is still considered by many to be a heroic figure of black resistance to oppression. At birth he was not given a surname, but was recorded solely by his given name, Nat. In accordance with a common practice, he was often called by the surname of his owner, Samuel Turner.

== Election of 1852 ==

In one of the less spectacular elections in American history, Senator Franklin Pierce of the Democratic party defeated General Winfield Scott of the Whig party. The Whigs tried to rely on Scott’s heroics as a general during the Mexican war to get him elected, a strategy that proved unsuccessful. Pierce, of New Hampshire, ended up being largely an ineffective president, trying and failing to please both the North and the South.

== The Kansas-Nebraska Act and its Effects ==

Throughout this time, plans were underway for a transcontinental railroad. A question arose as to what Eastern city should be the main terminus. Senator Stephen Douglas of Illinois hoped to advance his own state’s interests by making Chicago the railroad hub. To do this, he suggested a piece of legislation known as the “Kansas-Nebraska Act,” requiring recognition of two new territories, Kansas and Nebraska, west of Missouri and Iowa, respectively. These territories would both help his railroad and solve the overdue issue of the territories in the remainder of the Louisiana Purchase. 

But to get the Kansas-Nebraska Act passed, he would have to get the support of Southerners, who wanted a railroad along a more southern route. For this reason, Douglas included in the Act the provision of popular sovereignty in the territories. 

This blatantly violated the Missouri Compromise of 1821, which stated that slavery would be prohibited above the 36º30’ line. Douglas therefore opened himself up to the verbal barrage of protests from the North, who denounced the cancellation of the Missouri Compromise as unfair. Yet the Act passed, to the indignation of many Northerners, with the support of President Pierce.

=== The North ===

Many in the North figured that if the Missouri Compromise was not an unbreakable law, neither was the Fugitive Slave Act, leading to many demonstrations against it. Boston witnessed the most remarkable of these, leading to many New Englanders turning against Pierce for his support of the Kansas-Nebraska Act.

=== Political Parties ===

The Whig party essentially buckled under the pressure of the Kansas-Nebraska Act, with the North condemning it and the South supporting it. Whigs from the North joined some Democrats and Free Soilers that united under the general principle of the Wilmot Proviso, eventually calling themselves the Republican Party and offering its first presidential candidate, John C. Fremont in 1856.

== &quot;Bleeding Kansas&quot; ==

There was never much doubt that the settlers of Nebraska would, in the face of popular sovereignty, choose to bar slavery. Kansas, however, was another matter. Abolitionist and pro-slavery groups tried to rush settlers to Kansas in hopes of swinging the vote in the group's own direction. Eventually, both a free-state and a slave-state government were functioning in Kansas - both illegal. 

Violence was abundant. In May 1856, a pro-slavery mob ransacked the chiefly abolitionist town of Lawrence, demolishing private property of the anti-slavery governor, burning printing presses, and destroying a hotel. Two days later, in retaliation, Abolitionist John Brown and his sons went to the pro-slavery town of Pottawatomie Creek and hacked five men to death in front of their families. This set off a guerilla war in Kansas that lasted through most of 1856. 

Violence over the issue of Kansas was even seen in the Senate. Massachusetts Senator Charles Sumner accused South Carolinian Andrew Butler of having &quot;chosen a mistress to whom he has made his vows - Slavery.&quot; Upon hearing these words, Butler's nephew, Representative Preston Brooks, walked onto the Senate floor and proceeded to cane Sumner in the head. Sumner suffered so much damage from the attack that he could not return to the Senate for over three years. Brooks was expelled by the House. Cheered on by southern supporters (many of whom sent Brooks new canes, to show approval of his actions), came back after a resounding reelection.

After much controversy and extra legislation, Kansas found itself firmly abolitionist by 1858.

==Rachel v. Walker==
Rachel v. Walker was a lawsuit involving a slave who, in 1834, sued for her freedom from John Walker in the Supreme Court of Missouri, and won. This result was cited in 1856 in the famous Dred Scott v. Sandford case before the Supreme Court of the United States.[1]
== Dred Scott ==

The question of the constitutionality of Congressional Compromises was decided by the Supreme Court in 1856. In &quot;Scott v. Sanford&quot;, the Court ruled against a slave, Dred Scott, who had sued to become free. The Court ruled 7-2 that Scott remained a slave, and there were nine written opinions. The Chief Justice of the United States, Roger Taney, decided that blacks were so inferior that they could not be citizens of the United States, and that, consequently, they could not sue for his freedom (a state issue)in diversity in federal court, and therefore the court lacked jurisdiction. Nevetheless (the biggest &quot;nevertheless&quot; in American history) in a supererogatory effort to settle the question of slavery once and for all, the Marylander Taney ruled that the Missouri Compromise (which had banned the expansion of slavery into the territories north of Missouri) among other laws, was unconstitutional because it restricted the Constitutional right to own property. Many felt that Taney had committed a legal error in his decision. First, Taney had ruled that Scott had no right to sue. The case should have ended there. Taney had ruled on the constitutionality of the Missouri Compromise, which had, under Taney's own ruling that Scott had no right to sue, no bearing upon the case. Thus, the outrage against the Dred Scott decision was increased even more.

[[File:Slave and Free States before the American Civil War 2.svg|center|thumb|700px|Free and Slave States in 1869]]

== John Brown’s Raid ==

John Brown, an extreme abolitionist last seen engineering the Pottawatomie Massacre in Kansas, came to the federal arsenal at Harper’s Ferry, Virginia for his last fight. He planned to take over the arsenal, give weapons to the slaves that would support him, and make a center of black power in the Appalachian Mountains that would support slave uprisings in the south. 

The raid did not go quite as planned. Brown did take over the arsenal and took a couple of hostages, but ended up being assaulted by  Virginia militia and U.S. Marines under the command of Col. Robert E. Lee of the US 2nd Cavalry. He was tried, convicted, and hanged for treason to the State of Virginia. 

However, his Raid left a profound impact. John Brown became a martyr for the abolitionist cause during the Civil War. In the South, his actions gave cause to rumors of Northern conspiracy supporting slave insurrections, engendering further suspicion of outsiders in the South. A later Northern marching song sang “John Brown’s body lies a-mouldering in the grave, but his soul is marching on.”

== Lincoln ==
&lt;div style=&quot;width: 340px; float:left; margin:0 1 0em 2em; text-align: center;&quot;&gt; [[Image:Lincoln_Campaign_Poster.jpg]]&lt;br&gt; '' Lincoln campaign poster''&lt;/div&gt;
In 1860, four major candidates ran for President. The Whigs, adopting the name &quot;Constitutional Union&quot;, nominated Tennessean Senator John Bell. The Northern Democrats nominated Senator Stephen Douglas of Illinois and the Southern Democrats nominated the Vice President John Breckenridge of Kentucky. The more united Republican party nominated Abraham Lincoln, who spoke out against expansion of slavery. Though he assumed that, under the constitution, Congress could not outlaw slavery in the South, he assured all that he would work to admit only free states to the US. Due to divisions between the parties, Lincoln won the election by carrying every  Northern State. Douglas won Missouri, Bell the Upper South, and Breckenridge the Deep South. The South was outraged. The North had a far larger population than the South, and thus had more electoral votes. The South had been out voted. 



{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>f6hfjkzugutfjs79l98zded7la5yokz</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>US History/Preface</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1129</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2616181</id>
      <parentid>1928587</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-03-12T16:59:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pittsburgh Poet</username>
        <id>1449338</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>I'm attempting to edit for clarity: I will neither add nor take away facts. ~~~~</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">This textbook is based on the College Entrance Examination Board test in Advanced Placement United States History. The test is a standard on the subject, covering what most students in the United States study in high school and college, so we treat it as the best reference. 

The text was reorganized and edited in November 2008 to be closer to the content and organization the college board requires.  The content was carefully chosen for significance and interest.  We welcome reader feedback and suggestions for improvement.

Enjoy!
The AP Course Description can be found [http://www.collegeboard.com/student/testing/ap/history_us/topics_1_9.html?ushist here].


{{chapnav||Introduction}}</text>
      <sha1>gks4owcp7w5hzsoxlxvpzv0dpcgwgop</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>GCSE Science/Circuits Part2</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1130</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2066301</id>
      <parentid>1245110</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-03-06T04:54:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Avicennasis</username>
        <id>314063</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WP:AWB/T|Typo fixing]], typos fixed: the the → the using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[GCSE Science/Electricity]]
----
Now we have learned Ohm's Law we can start applying it to some circuits.

The test circuits below can be used to investigate how the voltage across a component varies with the current flowing through the component. Either circuit can be used. The one on the left is easiest to set up, the one on the right is easiest to use once it is set up, but does require you to use the rheostat as a potential divider.

Note that the voltmeter is in parallel with the component and the ammeter is in series with it.This is necessary so that the ammeter and voltmeter do not interfere with the circuit in anyway. An ideal meter does not change either the current or the voltage. 

The wire should be ''resistance wire'', such as nichrome. Ordinary copper wire would short circuit the power pack and blow the pack's fuse.


{| align=&quot;center&quot;
|-
| [[Image:Voltage current characterstic test circuit.png]]
| [[Image:Voltage current test circuit with P.D..png]]
|-
| A test circuit || A better test circuit
|}

Set up either circuit and then by turning the voltage setting on the power pack and the slider on the rheostat, adjust the current to read 0.1 A. Take a reading of the voltage. Repeat for 0.2 A, 0.3 A up to 1.0 A. Repeat the readings but this time go from 1.0 A to 0.9 A and so on down to 0.1 A.

Set your results out in a table like this.


{| border=&quot;1&quot;  bgcolor=&quot;ffffdd&quot;
|-
! Current&lt;br&gt;(A)
! Voltage going up&lt;br&gt;(V)
! Voltage going down&lt;br&gt;(V)
! Average voltage&lt;br&gt;(V)
|-
| 0.1 || &lt;br&gt; || &lt;br&gt; || &lt;br&gt;
|-
| 0.2 || &lt;br&gt; || &lt;br&gt; || &lt;br&gt;
|-
| 0.3 || &lt;br&gt; || &lt;br&gt; || &lt;br&gt;
|-
| 0.4 || &lt;br&gt; || &lt;br&gt; || &lt;br&gt;
|-
| 0.5 || &lt;br&gt; || &lt;br&gt; || &lt;br&gt;
|-
| 0.6 || &lt;br&gt; || &lt;br&gt; || &lt;br&gt;
|-
| 0.7 || &lt;br&gt; || &lt;br&gt; || &lt;br&gt;
|-
| 0.8 || &lt;br&gt; || &lt;br&gt; || &lt;br&gt;
|-
| 0.9 || &lt;br&gt; || &lt;br&gt; || &lt;br&gt;
|-
| 1.0 || &lt;br&gt; || &lt;br&gt; || &lt;br&gt;
|}

Now plot the average voltage against the current on graph paper. You should find the points all fall approximately on a straight line. The slope of the line =Voltage/Current. This is the resistance.

Below is a typical voltage/current graph for a wire. Note that all the points fall approximately on a straight line. 


[[Image:VC_wire.png]] 

The slope of the line is 1.1 V/A.

Therefore the resistance  of this wire is 1.1 &amp;Omega;

All ''Ohmic'' components have a constant resistance like this. However, ''non-Ohmic'' components (that is, components that do not obey Ohm's law) do not have such a resistance. A bulb, for example, has a resistance that increases as the current flowing through it goes up, because the filament is heating up. A current-voltage graph for a bulb would be a curve.

'''Q1)''' Plot a current/voltage graph for the following set of data for a 12V filament bulb.


{| bgcolor=&quot;ffeeaa&quot;
|-
| '''Summary'''
|-
|
* Resistance is the gradient of a current-voltage graph.
* Ohmic conductors, such as a wire, will have a constant resistance (straight line on the graph).
* Non-Ohmic conducts, such as a bulb, will have a changing resistance due to temperature (curved line on the graph).
|}

----

[[GCSE Science/Answers Circuits Part2|Answers]] | [[GCSE Science/Current, voltage resistance and Ohm's law|&lt;&lt;Current, Voltage, Resistance]] | [[GCSE Science/Parallel and series circuits|Parallel and series circuits&gt;&gt;]]

[[Category:GCSE Science]]</text>
      <sha1>j385rjkotqzfg5fhyc86o1bg68p28b0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Algebra/Complex Numbers</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1132</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2516511</id>
      <parentid>2365534</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-04-25T21:24:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>64.141.108.82</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Introduction */ Fix equation formatting</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">:''See also: [[High School Mathematics Extensions]], [[High School Mathematics Extensions/Supplementary/Complex Numbers|Complex numbers]], [[Wikipedia:Complex number|Complex numbers at Wikipedia]]''
{{Algebra Page}}
&lt;noinclude&gt;{{navigation|Book=Algebra
|current=Complex Numbers
|previous=Binomial Theorem
|next=Parabola
|cat=Algebra (book)}}&lt;/noinclude&gt;
----
'''Complex numbers''' are the extension of the real numbers, i.e., the number line, into a number plane. They allow us to turn the rules of plane geometry into arithmetic. Complex numbers have fundamental importance in describing the laws of the universe at the subatomic level, including the propagation of light and quantum mechanics. They also have practical uses in many fields, including signal processing and electrical engineering.

== Introduction ==
Currently, we are able to solve many different kinds of equations for &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt;, such as &lt;math&gt;x + 7 = 12&lt;/math&gt;, or &lt;math&gt;3x = 4&lt;/math&gt;, or &lt;math&gt;x +10 = 0&lt;/math&gt;. In each of these cases the solution for &lt;math&gt;x&lt;/math&gt; is a real number: respectively 5, 4/3, and -10.

However, there is no real number ''x'' that satisfies the equation &lt;math&gt;x^2 = -1\,&lt;/math&gt;, since the square of any real number is nonnegative.

Conceptually it would be nice to have some kind of number to be the solution of &lt;math&gt;x^2 = -1\,&lt;/math&gt;. This &quot;number&quot; would not be a real number, however, and we refer to such a number as an ''imaginary'' number.

We then extend the real number system to accommodate this special number. It turns out that there will be two imaginary solutions of the equation &lt;math&gt;x^2 = -1&lt;/math&gt;. One of them will be called &lt;math&gt;i\,&lt;/math&gt; and, following the normal rules for arithmetic, the other solution is &lt;math&gt;-i\,&lt;/math&gt;. We may be inclined to say that &lt;math&gt;\sqrt{-1}=i\,&lt;/math&gt;.  That would, however, be incorrect solely because in words this says that &quot;'''the''' square root of -1 is &lt;math&gt;i&lt;/math&gt;&quot;, but there is no basis for preferring &lt;math&gt;i&lt;/math&gt; over &lt;math&gt;-i&lt;/math&gt; (or vice versa) as the square root of -1.  Rather, the two square roots have equal standing. 

We say that all numbers of the form a +b&lt;math&gt;i\,&lt;/math&gt;, where &lt;math&gt;a&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;b&lt;/math&gt; are any real numbers, is the set of ''complex'' numbers, and we denote this set '''C'''. 
The real numbers '''R''' may be considered to be the subset of complex numbers '''C''' = {a +b&lt;math&gt;i\,&lt;/math&gt;} for which b = 0. Complex numbers can be added, subtracted, multiplied, and divided (except by 0). We will explore some of the properties of these numbers later.

There are in fact two commonly used definitions of complex numbers, but they are immediately seen to be logically equivalent.

For a negative root like &lt;math&gt;\sqrt{-4}\,&lt;/math&gt;, we split the number into two parts such that one part is &lt;math&gt;\sqrt{-1}\,&lt;/math&gt; like &lt;math&gt;\sqrt{-4}\, = \sqrt{4*-1}\, = \sqrt{4}\,* \sqrt{-1}\, &lt;/math&gt; which leads to &lt;math&gt;2i&lt;/math&gt;

== Definition 1==
A '''complex number''' is an expression of the form ''x + iy'', in which ''x'' and ''y'' are real numbers and ''i'' is a new number, called the '''imaginary unit''', for which expressions the normal rules of calculation apply together with the extra rule: ''i&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;=-1''.

== Definition 2==
A '''complex number''' is a pair of real numbers ''(x,y)'', satisfying the properties:

:&lt;math&gt;(a,b)+(c,d)=(a+c,b+d)\,&lt;/math&gt;
:&lt;math&gt;(a,b) \cdot (c,d)=(ac-bd,ad+bc)&lt;/math&gt;

In both cases a complex number consists of two real numbers ''x'' and ''y''. The real number ''x'' is called the '''real part''' and the real number ''y'' the '''imaginary part''' of the complex number.

From the properties we deduce that complex numbers of the form (x,0) behave just like the real numbers, so we identify (1,0) with 1 and hence (x,0) with x. Furthermore we see that:

:&lt;math&gt;(0,1) \cdot (0,1)=(-1,0)=-1&lt;/math&gt;.

It is common use to write ''i'' instead of (0,1), so:
:&lt;math&gt;\, i=(0,1)&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;\, i^2=-1&lt;/math&gt;.

Any complex number ''(x,y)'' may now be written as ''x + iy''.



=== Some examples ===
A ''complex number'' is a number that is in the form z = ''a'' + ''b''i, where ''a'' and ''b'' are real numbers. We say that ''a'' is the ''real'' part of z and write Re(z), and that ''b'' is the ''imaginary'' part of z, and write Im(z)

A number of the form ''b''i is sometimes called a ''pure imaginary'' number, as it has no real part. The pure imaginary numbers are also complex numbers, because ''b''i = 0 + ''b''i. In the same way, all real numbers are also complex numbers, because ''a'' = ''a'' + 0i. So the set of complex numbers includes real numbers, pure imaginary numbers, and the sums of reals and pure imaginaries.

Here are some examples
* 1 + 4i: a complex number, real part 1, imaginary part 4
* 2 - 2i: a complex number, real part 2, imaginary part -2.
* -4i: a complex number, real part 0, imaginary part -4
* 2: a complex number (also a real number), real part 2, imaginary part 0.

Notice that the number 2 is a complex number '''and''' a real number. This fact is clearer if we write 2 = 2 + 0i.

Any complex number may be written in three main forms, which we will explore later. The form ''x'' + ''y''i is known as the ''Cartesian'' form.

=== Complex numbers and matrices ===
Complex numbers can be identified with a certain set of ''matrices''. If we think of the 2x2 identity matrix as the number 1, and we think of &lt;math&gt;i&lt;/math&gt; which we introduced above as the matrix
:&lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix}
0 &amp; -1 \\
1 &amp; 0 \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;,

then the complex number &lt;math&gt;a+bi&lt;/math&gt; then has the form
:&lt;math&gt;\begin{pmatrix}
a &amp; -b \\
b &amp; a \end{pmatrix}&lt;/math&gt;.

== Properties ==
Complex numbers obey most of the properties of real numbers. Take two complex numbers, &lt;math&gt;z_1=a+bi\,&lt;/math&gt; and &lt;math&gt;z_2=c+di\,&lt;/math&gt;. 

=== Addition ===
How can we add these two complex numbers? 

We don't even have to think about &lt;math&gt;i&lt;/math&gt; as being &quot;special&quot; in any way, just treat it as any other symbol and proceed by the standard rules of algebra, grouping along the way.

We obtain: 
:&lt;math&gt;z_1+z_2=(a+bi)+(c+di)=(a+c)+(b+d)i\,&lt;/math&gt;

If one uses the matrix analogy above, regular matrix addition works to add complex numbers in the same way. Verify for yourself that this is true.

=== Subtraction ===
Subtraction proceeds just as before. 
:&lt;math&gt;z_1-z_2=(a+bi)-(c+di)=(a-c)+(b-d)i\,&lt;/math&gt;


=== Multiplication ===
By the normal rules, taking into account that &lt;math&gt;i^2=-1\,&lt;/math&gt;, we find:
:&lt;math&gt;z_1z_2=(a+bi)(c+di)=ac+adi+bci+bdi^2=(ac-bd)+(bc+ad)i\,&lt;/math&gt;


If one uses the matrix analogy above, regular matrix multiplication works to multiply complex numbers in the same way. Verify for yourself that this is true.

=== Conjugates ===
The ''conjugate'' of a complex number &lt;math&gt;z&lt;/math&gt;, written &lt;math&gt;\bar{z}&lt;/math&gt;, is the same number with the sign of the imaginary part changed: the conjugate of ''a'' + ''b''i = ''a'' - ''b''i (and vice versa).

Let us examine what happens when we have a complex number ''z'' = ''a'' + ''b''i, what is the product of ''z'' and its conjugate?

:(''a''+''b''i)(''a''-''b''i) = ''a''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; + ''ab''i - ''ab''i - ''b''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;i&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = ''a''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; ''' + ''' ''b''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;

Notice the imaginary parts cancel out, so the product is a ''real number''. This will aid us greatly in the division of a complex number, as we will see.

Notice also that this is the ''sum'' of two squares, analogous to the difference of two squares.

Matrix transposition behaves as conjugation if one uses the matrix analogy.

=== Division ===
How do we compute the quotient
:&lt;math&gt;\frac{a+bi}{c+di}&lt;/math&gt;
of two complex numbers? It is not difficult. Let the quotient be:

:&lt;math&gt;\frac{a+bi}{c+di}=r+si&lt;/math&gt;,
then cross multiplication gives:
:&lt;math&gt;\,a+bi=(r+si)(c+di)=rc-sd+i(rd+sc)&lt;/math&gt;,
hence
:&lt;math&gt;\,a=rc-sd&lt;/math&gt;,
and
:&lt;math&gt;\,b=rd+sc&lt;/math&gt;.

So we have to solve two linear equations. Solution:

:&lt;math&gt;r=\frac{ac+bd}{c^2+d^2}&lt;/math&gt;,
and
:&lt;math&gt;s=\frac{bc-ad}{c^2+d^2}&lt;/math&gt;.

Note that this is complete nonsense unless &lt;math&gt;c^2+d^2 \ne 0&lt;/math&gt;.  In fact, it is easy to see that the pair of linear equations have a solution exactly when this is true, i.e., when c and d are not both zero. Or in other words, when &lt;math&gt;c+di \ne 0&lt;/math&gt; as a complex number. Thus we can divide by a complex number ''only'' when it is non-zero.

Luckily there is a little trick to speed up this computation. We multiply the denominator with a well chosen number as to make it real. We ''realize the denominator'' by multiplying with the conjugate of the denominator; a complex number times its conjugate is a real number:

:&lt;math&gt;\,(c+di)(c-di)=c^2-(di)^2=c^2+d^2&lt;/math&gt;.

hence:
:&lt;math&gt;\frac{a+bi}{c+di} = \frac{a+bi}{c+di}\cdot \frac{c-di}{c-di} = \frac{ac-adi+bci+bd}{c^2+d^2} = \frac{(ac+bd)+(bc-ad)i}{c^2+d^2}=\frac{ac+bd}{c^2+d^2} + \frac{bc-ad}{c^2+d^2}i&lt;/math&gt;.

Note that in the multiplication and division of complex numbers, we usually work out the whole problem instead of just memorizing the equation of the answer.  The reader will note that we use here the familiar trick from algebra of multiplying by the number 1 in a particularly convenient form: &lt;math&gt;\frac{c-di}{c-di}&lt;/math&gt;.  (We leave it to the reader to verify that any non-zero complex number divided by itself is in fact equal to 1.)

=== Problem set=== 
Given the above rules, answer the following questions. 

====Exercises====
# (7 + 2i) + (11 - 6i) =
# (8 - 3i) - (6i) =
# (9 + 4i)(3 - 16i) =
# 3i &lt;math&gt;\times&lt;/math&gt; 9i = &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
# &lt;math&gt;\frac{i}{2+i}=&lt;/math&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
# &lt;math&gt;\frac{11 + 3i}{\sqrt{3} - 4i}=&lt;/math&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
# &lt;math&gt;{(x + yi)}^{-1}=&lt;/math&gt;&lt;br&gt;

===== Answers =====
# 18 - 4i
# 8 - 3i - 6i = 8 - 9i
# 27 - 144i + 12i - 64i&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 91 - 132i
# -27. (&lt;math&gt;i \times i = i^2 = -1&lt;/math&gt;)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
# &lt;math&gt;\frac{i}{2+i} \times \frac{2-i}{2-i} = \frac{1+2i}{5} = \frac{1}{5} + \frac{2}{5}i&lt;/math&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
# &lt;math&gt; \frac{11 + 3i} {\sqrt{3} - 4i} \times \frac{\sqrt{3} + 4i} {\sqrt{3} + 4i} = &lt;/math&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;math&gt;\frac{11 \sqrt{3} + 44i + 3i \sqrt{3}+12i^2}{3+16} = &lt;/math&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;                        &lt;math&gt;\frac{(11 \sqrt{3} - 12) + (44i + 3i \sqrt{3})} {19} = &lt;/math&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;                          &lt;math&gt;\frac{11 \sqrt{3} - 12}{19} + \frac{44 + 3 \sqrt{3}} {19} i &lt;/math&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
# Recall that &lt;math&gt;x^{-1}=\frac{1}{x}&lt;/math&gt; can be seen as the division of two complex numbers: &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;math&gt;{(x + yi)}^{-1}= \frac{1}{x + yi} \times \frac{x - yi}{x - yi}=&lt;/math&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;         &lt;math&gt;\frac{x - yi}{x^2 - y^2 i^2} = \frac{x}{x^2 + y^2} - \frac{y}{x^2 + y^2} i &lt;/math&gt;

== The Argand Plane ==
We can represent complex numbers ''geometrically'' as well. 
Every complex number can be represented in the form z=x+iy (so x=Re(z) and y=Im(z)).
Then we can represent z in the xy-plane by the point (x,y).
Notice that this is a one-to-one relationship: for each complex number, we have one corresponding point in
the plane, and for each point in the plane there corresponds one complex number.
When we use the xy-plane in this way to represent complex numbers, we call the plane
the &quot;Argand plane&quot;.
We will refer to the &quot;y&quot; axis as the imaginary axis, and the &quot;x&quot; axis as the real axis.

Notice that a purely imaginary number is represented in the Argand plane by a point on the
imaginary axis.  A purely real number is represented by a point on the real axis.

Here is an example of the Argand plane.
:[[Image:Argand2.png]]

There are two complex numbers drawn in the plane; viz., 1 + i, -2 - i. Their sum is plotted on the graph, -1. The red and blue lines demonstrate how geometrically, a parallelogram can be constructed, and their apex forms their sum.

=== Modulus and argument ===
:[[Image:Modulus and argument.png]]
On this diagram we can see the number 3 + 4i. The red line is the distance away from the origin (the number 0 + 0i). The gray line represents the distances away from the respective axes. We can see that the red line makes an angle &amp;theta; from the real axis.

It is clear that almost all complex numbers have this distance away from the origin and that almost all complex numbers make an angle away from the real axis. We give these two qualities special names; the distance away from the origin is known as the ''modulus'' of the complex number, and the angle &amp;theta; is known as the ''argument'' of the complex number.

We write the modulus of a complex number z by |z|, and the argument of the complex number as arg z.

We can calculate the modulus and argument by basic trigonometry. 

==== Calculating the modulus ====
In the above example, we have the number 3 + 4i. We can form a triangle in the Argand plane with base 3 and height 4. By Pythagoras we can find the length of the hypotenuse by &lt;math&gt;\sqrt{3^2+4^2} = \sqrt{9+16} = \sqrt{25} = 5&lt;/math&gt;.

And thus, the length of the hypotenuse is thus the modulus of the complex number, and it is 5 for 3+4i.

===== Generalization =====
If ''z'' = ''x'' + ''y''i, |''z''| is clearly &lt;math&gt;\sqrt{x^2+y^2}&lt;/math&gt;.

Equivalently, &lt;math&gt;|z|=\sqrt{\mathrm{Re}(z)^2+\mathrm{Im}(z)^2}&lt;/math&gt;.

==== Calculating the argument ====
We have the same triangle as we had in calculating the modulus. Remember from trigonometry that tan &amp;theta; is the ratio of the height over the base. So, for 3 + 4i, we have tan &amp;theta; = 4/3, and thus &amp;theta; = arctan 4/3 = 0.9...

With complex numbers, we always take two things:
* the argument must be in radians
* the argument lies in the interval [-&amp;pi;,&amp;pi;], and we always adjust the angle so it does.

Note that arg 0 is undefined.

==== Generalization ====
If ''z'' = ''x'' + ''y''i, arg ''z'' is clearly arctan (y/x), or, equivalently, arg ''z'' = arctan (Im(''z'')/Re(''z'')).

=== The polar form ===
We are now able to calculate the modulus and argument of a complex number, where these two numbers are able to uniquely describe every number in the Argand plane. 

Using these two characteristics of complex numbers, we are now able to formulate a new way of writing these numbers. 

Note that in the above diagram, we obtain a triangle that describes the complex number 3 + 4i. Clearly, we can do this for all complex numbers in the Argand plane (except for 0). 

To simplify our work, let us look at numbers in the circle of unit length equidistant from 0. From trigonometry, we can parameterize all the points on a circle in the Cartesian plane by (cos &amp;theta;, sin &amp;theta;). In complex number notation we can say that all numbers on this unit circle are in the form cos &amp;theta;+i sin &amp;theta;. 

This works well on the unit circle, but how does this generalize to describing ''all'' numbers on the plane? We simply make the circle larger or smaller to encompass the number; this is done by multiplying by the modulus.

So then, we obtain the polar form ''r''(cos &amp;theta; + i sin &amp;theta;) = ''z'', where ''r'' is the modulus.

== Euler's formula ==
A very significant result in the area of complex numbers is Euler's formula. It basically asserts that
: ''r''e&lt;sup&gt;i&amp;theta;&lt;/sup&gt; = r (cos &amp;theta; + i sin &amp;theta;)

This statement can be verified through a rearrangement of the [[Wikipedia:Taylor series|Taylor Series]] of the cosine and sine functions.

Note that conjugate complex numbers have an opposing argument. 2e&lt;sup&gt;2i&lt;/sup&gt; and 2e&lt;sup&gt;-2i&lt;/sup&gt; are conjugate pairs.

=== Proofs ===
====Using Taylor series====
Here is a proof of Euler's formula using [[Wikipedia:Taylor series|Taylor Series]] expansions
as well as basic facts about the powers of ''i'':

: &lt;math&gt;
  i^0 = 1, \ i^1 = i, \ i^2 = -1, \ i^3 = -i, \ i^4 = 1, \ i^5 = i, \ i^6 = -1, \ i^7 = -i, \ i^8 = 1, \dots
&lt;/math&gt;

The functions ''e''&lt;sup&gt;''x''&lt;/sup&gt;, cos(''x'') and sin(''x'') (assuming ''x'' is real) can be written as:

: &lt;math&gt; e^x = 1 + x + \frac{x^2}{2!} + \frac{x^3}{3!} + \cdots &lt;/math&gt;

: &lt;math&gt; \cos x = 1 - \frac{x^2}{2!} + \frac{x^4}{4!} - \frac{x^6}{6!} + \cdots
&lt;/math&gt;

: &lt;math&gt; \sin x = x - \frac{x^3}{3!} + \frac{x^5}{5!} - \frac{x^7}{7!} + \cdots
&lt;/math&gt;

and for complex ''z'' we ''define'' each of these function by the above series, replacing ''x'' with ''iz''. This is possible because the radius of convergence of each series is infinite. We then find that

: &lt;math&gt;e^{iz} = 1 + iz + \frac{(iz)^2}{2!} + \frac{(iz)^3}{3!} + \frac{(iz)^4}{4!} + \frac{(iz)^5}{5!} + \frac{(iz)^6}{6!} + \frac{(iz)^7}{7!} + \frac{(iz)^8}{8!} + \cdots&lt;/math&gt;

: &lt;math&gt;= 1 + iz - \frac{z^2}{2!} - \frac{iz^3}{3!} + \frac{z^4}{4!} + \frac{iz^5}{5!} - \frac{z^6}{6!} - \frac{iz^7}{7!} + \frac{z^8}{8!} + \cdots&lt;/math&gt;

: &lt;math&gt;= \left( 1 - \frac{z^2}{2!} + \frac{z^4}{4!} - \frac{z^6}{6!} + \frac{z^8}{8!} + \cdots \right) + i\left( z - \frac{z^3}{3!} + \frac{z^5}{5!} - \frac{z^7}{7!} + \cdots \right) &lt;/math&gt;

: &lt;math&gt;= \cos (z) + i\sin (z) \,&lt;/math&gt;

The rearrangement of terms is justified because each series is absolutely convergent. Taking ''z'' = ''x'' to be a real number, gives the original identity as Euler discovered it.&lt;math&gt;\square&lt;/math&gt;

====Using calculus====
Define the complex number ''z'' such that
:&lt;math&gt;z=\cos x + i\sin x \,&lt;/math&gt;
Differentiating ''z'' with respect to ''x'':
:&lt;math&gt;\frac{dz}{dx}=-\sin x + i\cos x&lt;/math&gt;
Using the fact that ''i''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = -1:
:&lt;math&gt;\frac{dz}{dx}=i^2\sin x + i\cos x=i(\cos x + i\sin x)=zi&lt;/math&gt;
Separating variables and integrating both sides:
:&lt;math&gt;\int\frac{1}{z}\,dz=\int i\,dx&lt;/math&gt;
:&lt;math&gt;\ln z=xi + C\,&lt;/math&gt;
where C is the constant of integration. To finish the proof we have to argue that it is zero. This is easily done by substituting x = 0.
:&lt;math&gt;\ln z = C\,&lt;/math&gt;
But z is just equal to:
:&lt;math&gt;\ z = \cos x + i\sin x = \cos 0 + i \sin 0 = 1\,&lt;/math&gt;
thus
:&lt;math&gt;\ln 1 = C\,&lt;/math&gt;

:&lt;math&gt;\ C = 0\,&lt;/math&gt;

So now we just exponentiate
:&lt;math&gt;\ \ln z = xi\,&lt;/math&gt;

:&lt;math&gt;\ e^{\ln z} = e^{xi}\,&lt;/math&gt;

:&lt;math&gt;\ z = e^{xi}\,&lt;/math&gt;

:&lt;math&gt;\ e^{xi} = \cos x + i\sin x\,\square&lt;/math&gt;

=== Corollaries ===
A number of significant results follow as corollaries to Euler's result.


=== de Moivre's theorem ===
De Moivre's theorem is useful in calculating powers of complex numbers. It states that
:  (''r'' (cos &amp;theta; + i sin &amp;theta;))&lt;sup&gt;n&lt;/sup&gt; = ''r''&lt;sup&gt;n&lt;/sup&gt; ( cos ''n''&amp;theta; + i sin ''n''&amp;theta;)

This follows clearly (from the laws of exponents) if we rewrite the theorem in the form
: (''r''e&lt;sup&gt;i&amp;theta;&lt;/sup&gt;)&lt;sup&gt;n&lt;/sup&gt;=''r''&lt;sup&gt;n&lt;/sup&gt;e&lt;sup&gt;i''n''&amp;theta;&lt;/sup&gt;

=== Equivalent trigonometric forms ===
From the cosine/sine form of the complex number, we can rewrite the cosine and sine function in terms of exponentials.
: cos &amp;theta; = 1/2 (e&lt;sup&gt;i&amp;theta;&lt;/sup&gt; + e&lt;sup&gt;-i&amp;theta;&lt;/sup&gt;)
: sin &amp;theta; = 1/(2i) (e&lt;sup&gt;i&amp;theta;&lt;/sup&gt; - e&lt;sup&gt;-i&amp;theta;&lt;/sup&gt;)

=== Relation of e, &lt;math&gt;\pi&lt;/math&gt;, i, 1, and 0 ===
By substituting &amp;pi; into the formula, we obtain the following result:

&lt;math&gt;e^{\pi i}+1=0&lt;/math&gt;

The actual mathematical relevance of this equation is actually very little.  It is known more for its relation of the many branches of mathematics:  e comes from calculus, &amp;pi; from geometry, i comes from algebra, 1 is the multiplicative identity, and 0 is the additive identity.  It is also known for its simple mathematical aesthetic.

== Forming trigonometric identities ==
The aforementioned equivalent trigonometric forms, combined with the Binomial theorem, allow us to create some trigonometric identities that would be difficult to form in any other way. These identities can be used to simplify integral problems.

=== Cosine/sine powers ===
How can we simplify, say, (cos ''x'')&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;?

Let us look at a simple example for motivation.
First, rewrite as
:(cos ''x'')&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; = (1/2 (e&lt;sup&gt;ix&lt;/sup&gt;+e&lt;sup&gt;-ix&lt;/sup&gt;))&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; =
1/2&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; (e&lt;sup&gt;ix&lt;/sup&gt;+e&lt;sup&gt;-ix&lt;/sup&gt;)&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;

By the Binomial theorem, 
:(''a''+''b'')&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;=''a''&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; + 5''a''&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;''b'' + 10''a''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;''b''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; + 10''a''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;''b''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; +  5''ab''&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; + ''b''&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;.

Replacing a with e&lt;sup&gt;i''x''&lt;/sup&gt;/2 and b with e&lt;sup&gt;-i''x''&lt;/sup&gt;/2, we obtain 
:10e&lt;sup&gt;-i''x''&lt;/sup&gt;/32+10e&lt;sup&gt;i''x''&lt;/sup&gt;/32+5e&lt;sup&gt;3i''x''&lt;/sup&gt;/32+5e&lt;sup&gt;-3i''x''&lt;/sup&gt;/32+e&lt;sup&gt;5i''x''&lt;/sup&gt;/32+e&lt;sup&gt;-5i''x''&lt;/sup&gt;/32=
:(5/16)(e&lt;sup&gt;-i''x''&lt;/sup&gt;+e&lt;sup&gt;i''x''&lt;/sup&gt;)+(5/32)(e&lt;sup&gt;3i''x''&lt;/sup&gt;+e&lt;sup&gt;-3i''x''&lt;/sup&gt;)+(1/32)(e&lt;sup&gt;5i''x''&lt;/sup&gt;+e&lt;sup&gt;-5i''x''&lt;/sup&gt;)=
:(5/16)(2 cos ''x'')+(5/32)(2 cos 3''x'')+(1/32)(2 cos 5''x'')=
:'''(5/8) cos ''x''+(5/16) cos 3''x''+(1/16) cos 5''x''=(cos ''x'')&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;'''

==== Procedure====
We can summarize from the above example the general procedure:
To simplify an expression in the form:
* cos(''x'')&lt;sup&gt;k&lt;/sup&gt;
* sin(''x'')&lt;sup&gt;k&lt;/sup&gt;

the procedure is:
* write cos(''x'') or sin(''x'') in the exponential form, all to the power of ''k''
* expand using the Binomial theorem
* collect conjugate pairs
* write back from the exponential form into the trigonometric form

=== Cosine/sine multiples ===
We can also form identities in the form:
* cos(''kx'')
* sin(''kx'').

Let's look at another example to see how it's done.

==== Example ====
Let's expand sin(3''x''). 

Recall de Moivre's theorem stating
: (cos(''x'')+i sin(''x''))&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; = cos(3''x'')+i sin (3''x'')

We will use this fact to expand out the left side. For ease of manipulation, it may be easier to let ''c'' = cos(''x''), and ''s''=sin(''x''). Then use the Binomial theorem again to expand out:
: (''c''+i''s'')&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;=''c''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; + 3i ''c''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;''s'' - 3''cs''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; - i ''s''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;
Collect real and imaginary parts
: (''c''+i''s'')&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;=''c''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;  - 3''cs''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; + i(3''c''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;''s'' - ''s''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;)

Now, this is of course equal to cos(3''x'')+i sin (3''x''). So, substituting back cos(''x'') for ''c'' and similarly for sin(''x''), we can equate real and imaginary parts, and we get
: sin(3''x'')=3 cos(''x'')&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;sin(''x'') - sin(''x'')&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;
and we get
: cos(3''x'')=cos(''x'')&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;  - 3 cos(''x'')sin(''x'')&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
for free.

NB: In the cosine expansion, one could write sin(''x'')&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; as 1-cos(''x'')&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; to obtain a formula consisting completely of cosines. (analogously one could write the sine expansion using only sines)

&lt;!--

==== Problem set ==== 
Given the above rules, answer the following (answers follow to even-numbered questions).
# Prove that ''r''e&lt;sup&gt;i&amp;theta;&lt;/sup&gt; and ''r''e&lt;sup&gt;-i&amp;theta;&lt;/sup&gt; are conjugate pairs.
# Write ''z''=1+1i in the form ''r'' (cos &amp;theta; + i sin &amp;theta;)
## Thus calculate ''z''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; by de Moivre's theorem.
# Write &lt;math&gt;\sqrt{2}i&lt;/math&gt; in the exponential form.
## Thus calculate ''z''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; by de Moivre's theorem.
--&gt;

== External links ==

*[http://wims.unice.fr/wims/wims.cgi?module=home&amp;search_category=X&amp;search_keywords=complex Online interactive exercises] on complex numbers.

'''This is incomplete and a draft, additional information is to be added.'''

[[de:Komplexe_Zahlen]]
[[zh:複數]]</text>
      <sha1>q90fkion1ala3rv752nmqiatk6upqif</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Voltage current characterstic test circuit.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1133</id>
    <revision>
      <id>636377</id>
      <parentid>153260</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-11-04T10:56:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Theresa knott</username>
        <id>93</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">A test circuit. Drawn by Theresa Knott

{{GFDL}}
{{Cc-by-sa-2.5}}</text>
      <sha1>7d5cyulbk294jo8srxsktjg07l64mqv</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:Voltage current test circuit with P.D..png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1134</id>
    <revision>
      <id>636415</id>
      <parentid>153261</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-11-04T10:58:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Theresa knott</username>
        <id>93</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve">A potential divided test circuit


{{GFDL}}
{{Cc-by-sa-2.5}}</text>
      <sha1>26kzt5sg3ccoy299mo47ubkbu0ichzq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>File:VC wire.png</title>
    <ns>6</ns>
    <id>1135</id>
    <revision>
      <id>636309</id>
      <parentid>153262</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-11-04T10:49:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Theresa knott</username>
        <id>93</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>tag</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Voltage current graph for a wire. Drawn by Theresa Knott


{{GFDL}}
{{Cc-by-sa-2.5}}</text>
      <sha1>i7lgs3v0nqkeo6256nr3uchbbcyht9m</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>User talk:Zhuo Jia Dai</title>
    <ns>3</ns>
    <id>1151</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2220682</id>
      <parentid>2020132</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-11-26T17:22:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ldecola</username>
        <id>497276</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* HSE */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">== HSE ==
i am working on a wikibook 'From Data to Insight' that is about the level of HSE, but you don't seem to have a chapter on 'statistics'...any reason why not?&lt;br /&gt;
--[[User:Ldecola|Ldecola]] ([[User talk:Ldecola|discuss]] • [[Special:Contributions/Ldecola|contribs]]) 17:22, 26 November 2011 (UTC)&lt;br /&gt;
----

Love your HSE book!  Hope you update it soon :)

----------

Hey :) I changed your modifications to [[Discrete mathematics]] back, sorry: there  is already a link to intro logic. I'm trying to keep the intro section to have info that will give one the basics of the topics, and the upper level section to be the ideas and concepts that build on the intro topics.

Hope you don't mind :) [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 02:50, 13 Sep 2003 (UTC)

Question for you on [[Talk:HSE Primes]] [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 22:08, 20 Nov 2003 (UTC)

----
Some helpful hints
:&lt;nowiki&gt;x\quad y&lt;/nowiki&gt; = &lt;math&gt;x \quad y&lt;/math&gt;
:&lt;nowiki&gt;x\qquad y&lt;/nowiki&gt; = &lt;math&gt;x\qquad y&lt;/math&gt;
:&lt;nowiki&gt;x^{x^x} \pmod{12}&lt;/nowiki&gt; = &lt;math&gt; x^{x^x} \pmod{12}&lt;/math&gt;
:) [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 07:53, 30 Nov 2003 (UTC)

----

hi xiaodai,

i've been on wikipedia for a while, but only had a look at wikibooks since i need to code [[Basic Polish language course]] into my carbon-based processor/soft-disk ;)

Looks good, and nice to see the HSE stuff you're doing. Say hi to terry gagen for me. :)

[[User:Boud|Boud]] 14:02, 2 Dec 2003 (UTC)

== HSE! ==

Love your HSE book, thanks so much! I usually feel as if I have exactly enough hints to think about something for a few minutes, and then think ''Eureka''! ;)

For the programming section, I think I could help (see my [http://www.livejournal.com/users/r3m0t/ Livejournal]) if you want Lisp/Scheme (go Scheme!). [[w:Haskell|Haskell]] is the only other mathematically-oriented language I can think of - are you planning on using that?

Oh - and aren't Venn diagrams best suited in the logic category? [[User:R3m0t|R3m0t]] 17:35, 5 Dec 2003 (UTC)

----
I'm glad you liked HSE so much! I'm trying my best to do a good job, but as so often is the case in my first drafts, glaring spelling and grammar mistakes seem to plague my work. Lucky you pick them out for me.

I do not know enough about Lisp, Prolog, Scheme (never heard of it) or Haskell to decide whether they are suitable for high school students or not. If you think a coherent course can be taught using one of those languages, then please go ahead! Create a new chapte if you have to. But I was thinking of teaching a more conventional language like Pascal. Anyway we are not just writing about programming, but mathematical programming. Haskell seems to be a good choice, but where can I find a good programming IDE/compiler for it? I simply haven't done the research.

And nice to meet you. How do you do?[[User:Xiaodai|Zhuo Jia Dai]]

: Just being a stickybeak, but
:* If you want Haskell, the Glasgow Haskell Compiler is an excellent Windows/*nix based Haskell interpreter and compiler environment. Some systems may only run the Hugs system. I'm about to go to bed so I can't give you an exact link but I'm sure you can google it :)
:* Haskell is a good choice of language for pure, functional programming. It's not quite the best language for exploring mathematical concepts in since it's a strict functional programming language. You may want to concentrate on looking at programming in common Computer Algebra systems such as Maple and Mathematica (I do know both systems, but Mathematica's better) for stuff like numerical approximations and all that funky jazz. Haskell is nice for exploring recursion, but more conventional looping structures are easier taught in some other language. With teaching Mathematica (You guys should still have it at Sydney, right?) you get the best of both worlds, really.
: HTH :) [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 11:59, 7 Dec 2003 (UTC)

::''Think free. Learn free.'' is the Wikibooks concept, but Mathematica seems to be a commercial thing. I wouldn't encourage people to use a propriety language on Wikibooks. Wikipedia: [[w:Lisp programming language]] [[w:Scheme programming language]] [[w:Haskell programming language]] [[w:Maple computer algebra system]] [[w:Mathematica]] [[w:Maxima]] [[w:Computer algebra system]] [[User:R3m0t|r3m0t]] 19:58, 7 Dec 2003 (UTC)

::: It doesn't mean we can't teach non-free software, at all. And it's not exactly proprietary software either - it's well used. I merely mention this to Xiaodai as an option. In any case, are we to forbid the creation of a Windows guidebook here because it is non-free software? We cannot be bigoted on the forbidding of teaching ''just'' because of its origins now, can we? [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 21:43, 7 Dec 2003 (UTC)

::::A Windows guidebook would be created for users of Windows who wish to (manipulate/configure/whatever) their installation. By teaching Mathematica in a textbook not created ''specifically'' for teaching Mathematica, that is encouraging people to use Mathematica. Lisp, Scheme, Ruby, Haskell seem different to me - it is hard to make any money out of them (plenty of compilers or interpreters are free already) so it's offering a choice of compiler, etc. [[User:R3m0t|r3m0t]] 21:55, 7 Dec 2003 (UTC)

::::: I'm going to reply to this at [[Talk:HSE Mathematical programming]], to stop cluttering up Xiao's talk page [[User:Dysprosia|Dysprosia]] 23:00, 7 Dec 2003 (UTC)
----
Hi, are you from China or Taiwan? Do you speak Chinese? Could you help improve text book [[Chinese]]? Thanks! --[[User:Yacht|Yacht]] 09:12, 13 Dec 2003 (UTC)

: 我的中文不是很好, 好像帮不上什么忙。

: How could he possibly be from Taiwan? His name is in Hanyu Pinyin. --[[User:Menchi|Menchi]] 10:43, 13 Dec 2003 (UTC)

== *waves*jumps up and down* ==

Could we consider showing two or more languages side-by-side for the time being? Also, please read over my beginnings of an introduction. Is it too compicated/too much detail/etc? [[User:R3m0t|r3m0t]] 15:15, 13 Dec 2003 (UTC)


Well I read it, it reads ok, except i think the command line and how to issue command part should be clarified upon. I think it's pretty confusing for someone who is not highly computer-literate.[[User:Xiaodai|Zhuo Jia Dai]]

== HSE is great ==

Your HSE book is great, it's easy enough to read at a reasonable speed and difficult enough to be challenging. I tried to read several real books but those weren't as fun to read because I had to stop regularly to check if I understood everything correctly. So, thanks for the book.[[User:mmartin|mmartin]]

:Thanks, but you may only have read the first chapter, the rest are still horrible. I think they need huge improvements. [[User:Xiaodai|Xiaodai]] 22:40, 19 Jul 2004 (UTC)

:I actually started with the third chapter because I already knew everything in the first one and the second one seemed less interesting. But I agree with you that it can still be improved, although it completly readable for me.(17 year old highschool student)[[User:mmartin|mmartin]] 24 Jul 2004

::Thank you very much for your feedback, much appreciated. [[User:Xiaodai|Xiaodai]] 03:13, 25 Jul 2004 (UTC)

== Attention! Attention! ==

I would like to inform you that I've come up with a alternative solution(actually the final answer is less complex) to question 4 in logic-problem set.
[[Talk:HSE_PS_Logic|Click here to go to the talk page to see the solution]]

And also, Nov 21st is coming soon, and does that means editing work are going to be restarted to full strength soon?

:Yeah, uni holidays starts now and i will do more editing than during the semester. What does &quot;more&quot; mean? I'm uncertainty. See how it goes. [[User:Xiaodai|Xiaodai]] 09:10, 20 Nov 2004 (UTC)

== Concerning logic puzzle item deletion ==

Concerning the 5th question in logic-problem set page...
Yes, I do agree this question is out of ability for most people, but I think may be at least you put it in the logic puzzle page? This way it has a place to rest.
(And consider I spent some good time thinking hard and finally managed to come up with a solution--when I wrote and submitted it, the system kicked me out so the history page didn't log down it was me who submitted the solution)

:Hmmm, i mean this problem is a bit out of reach. Thanks for contribution and i am sorry that i have to take it down. But the question is just so out of left field and you dont necessarily have to use the techniques taught in the chapter to do it properly. So i need to delete it. Congratulations on being able to solve the problem though, it's a tough one, you must be a genius. ^__^ I will put it in puzzle's page then [[User:Xiaodai|Xiaodai]] 12:42, 20 Nov 2004 (UTC)

== Nominated! ==

I'm excited to see that the book &quot;High School Extensions&quot; get nominated for march book of the month. Let's hope we'll win!

Also, I would like to inform you that I've written a starter-a stub, for the discrete probability part. I want to learn some more about it. And I've came up with how to write the starting, so leave that to me as I'm having holiday now and have more free time to do it. Thanks.
--[[User:Lemontea|Lemontea]] 13:10, 5 Feb 2005 (UTC)

:Thanks for that, i didn't know. I am to be nominated, but i feel this book still needs alot of work. Also, i am very much looking forward to your work. [[User:Xiaodai|Xiaodai]] 00:04, 6 Feb 2005 (UTC)

== [[Puzzles/Logic puzzles/5 Houses]] ==

I have just cleaned up the page a bit.  However, the puzzle as it stands is impossible, so obviously you made a mistake/omission in copying it.  Please see [[Talk:5 Houses]] and then make corrections.

Also, the point of puzzle books is to challenge the reader.  By putting the solution on the puzzle page, you are depriving the reader of this challenge, in which case what was the point of giving us the puzzle in the first place?  I have cut and pasted it onto a solution page.  I haven't cleaned the solution up, since I for one would like to have a go at the puzzle once it is complete. -- [[User:Smjg|Smjg]] 17:52, 14 Feb 2005 (UTC)

Well, I'm the one who wrote the solution, and Xiaodai just copied it to the puzzle page, so at most he is responsible for copying it to a wrong place.

As for the content of the solution, I looked at it and remembered that my school's maths club did mentioned this problem on club meeting, and I remember that the detail are different. I quickily find out that the question itself has mistake, and I just searched and choose a random complete version of that question.

Anyway, the task to do now is to find out who wrote the question in the first place, and which version of the question should we use.--[[User:Lemontea|Lemontea]] 12:30, 17 Feb 2005 (UTC)

== Vote too late ==

Hi Xiaodai. I just want to let you know that your vote for the book of the month for Mandarin Chinese was 37 minutes after the deadline, and has not been counted therefore. I encourage you to vote again in the [[Wikibooks:Book of the month/April 2005 voting|current voting for April 2005]], as soon as possible, since early votes seem to have a steering effect. Thanks, --[[User:Andreas Ipp|Andreas]] 13:37, 1 Mar 2005 (UTC)

== Withdrawing adminship request ==

I'm surprised that you withdrew your request for adminship after waiting only five days. You had two votes of support already (you only need four), and they do say that the process could take months. I've been waiting for over a month, and that's not unusual (things move pretty slowly in Wikibooks). ''(''&lt;sub&gt;Donovan&lt;/sub&gt;|[[User:Geocachernemesis|Geocachernemesis]]|&lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:Geocachernemesis|Interact]]&lt;/sup&gt;'')'' 11:26, 16 July 2005 (UTC)

== Template namespace ==

I moved a page out of the Template name space and now I feel bad.  If you wanted the page in that name space I apologize. If you had it there because you wanted to be able to include it here is how you include pages in the main namespace, just put the page name as it apears in curly braces with a preceedin colon as below.  The book is great by the way!
 &lt;nowiki&gt;{{:Page name/as it/appears}}&lt;/nowiki&gt; 
[[User:Msmithma|Msmithma]] 05:35, 17 November 2006 (UTC)
:thanks, i learnerd something. [[User:Xiaodai|Xiaodai]] 10:07, 17 November 2006 (UTC)

== Welcome back ==

Greetings! I noticed your edit summary on your most recent contribution: &quot;i will have the time and energy to start editing again soon. hopefully improve the quality by heaps. so it's more deserving of a recognition.&quot; Currently images without proper licensing and sourcing are being deleted. I noticed that many of yours are without a license or a source. If you would consider licensing them under an appropriate license (GFDL, PD, CC, BSD) and a source (yourself, I assume) I would greatly appreciate it. I noticed that many of your images are still be used! It would be great to be able to keep them.

And don't worry: you don't have to go through every image description page and tag it manually. You may ask an administrator (try [[User:Whiteknight]]) to run a bot to tag them all simultaneously.

Again, thank you very much, and welcome back! --[[User:Iamunknown|Iamunknown]] 03:48, 23 January 2007 (UTC)

== Help! ==

Hi Zhuo Jia Dai]]. 

I'm probably not doing this right, but I can't see any other way.  I'm new to Wikibooks and am just trying to send you a message.

I would like to help with your High School Mathematics Extensions with an addition, or possible follow-up, to your Set Theory and Infinite Processes.  I have read your Chapter and like it (and have a couple of suggestions).

Here is the introduction to a ten-page sample I've written:
&quot;Cantor’s diagonal method is elegant, powerful, and simple.  It has been the source of fundamental and fruitful theorems as well as devastating, and ultimately, fruitful paradoxes.  These proofs and paradoxes are almost always presented using an indirect argument.  They can be presented directly.  The direct approach, I believe, (1) is easier to understand, (2) unifies the proofs and paradoxes by exhibiting a single strategy, (3) shows Russell’s paradox to be the (obvious?) ultimate, set theoretic application of the method, and (4) is extendable to some of the semantic paradoxes.&quot;

If you're interested, please contact me; I just registered with Wikibooks, and maybe that allows you to contact me, but I wouldn't know where to look for your response.  So please email me at TomSchaffter@Mac.Com.

Tom Schaffter
B.S., Colorado State U, Math, '66; M.S., CSU, Math, '68; Ph.D., Berkeley, Logic and the Methodology of Science, '75.
[[User:Tomschaffter|Tomschaffter]] ([[User talk:Tomschaffter|talk]]) 16:21, 16 December 2007 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>qkr9ccf06uxpcz431isy2km50k5i0mw</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Latin/Lesson 11-Translation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1152</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1838853</id>
      <parentid>819175</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-06-10T16:54:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Vubb</username>
        <id>352144</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>moved [[Latin/Lesson 10-Translation]] to [[Latin/Lesson 11-Translation]]: Page was inserted in between 7 and 8</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Latin}}

Lesson 20, as a bit of a reward is a little translation excercise from the Gospel of Saint Luke.

&lt;B&gt;Excercise 1&lt;/B&gt;

&lt;B&gt;Vocabulary&lt;/B&gt;

&lt;I&gt;coming soon, at the moment consult your dictionary&lt;/I&gt;

Respondens Simon dixit: &quot;Aestimo quia is, cui plus donavit&quot;. At ille dixit ei: &quot;Recte iudicasti&quot;. Et conversus ad mulierem, dixit Simoni: &quot;Vides hanc mulierem? Intravi in domum tuam: aquam pedibus meis non dedisti; haec autem lacrimis rigavit pedes meos et capillis suis tersit. Osculum mihi non dedisti haec autem, ex quo intravi non cessavit osculari pedes meos. Oleo caput meum non unxisti; haec autem unguento unxit pedes meos. Propter quod dico tibi: Remissa sunt peccata eius multa, quoniam dilexit multrum: cui autem minus dimittitur, minus diligit.&quot; Dixit autem ad illam: &quot;Remissa sunt peccata tua&quot;. Et coeperunt, qui simul accumbebant, dicere intra se: &quot;quis est hic, qui etiam peccata dimittit?&quot;. Dixit autem ad mulierem: Fides tua te salvam fecit; vade in pace!&quot;.

Et factum est deinceps, et ipse iter faciebat per civitatem et castekkyn oaeducabs et evangelizans regnum Dei, et Duodecim cum illo, et mulieres aliquae, quae erant curatae ab spiritibus malignis et infirmitatibus, Maria, quae vocatur Magdalene, de qua daemonia septem exierant, et Ioanna uxor Chuza procuratoris Herodis, et Sussanna et aliae multae, quae ministrabant eis de facultatibus suis.

[[Category:Latin]]</text>
      <sha1>9k459e1kybdv2tma3i2586ggeks9s9i</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Latin/Lesson 6-Translation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1153</id>
    <revision>
      <id>819210</id>
      <parentid>692912</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-04-04T19:08:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Asv</username>
        <id>55495</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[Latin/Lesson 35]] moved to [[Latin/Lesson 6-Translation]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Latin}}

Congratulations! You have completed the Introductory Latin course! To finish off, you can look at an exciting section from Caesar's Civil Wars Book II stanza 10-12.

&lt;B&gt;Exercise 1&lt;/B&gt;

Skill: Translation from Latin source

&lt;I&gt;Vocabulary&lt;/I&gt;, coming soon

Ubi ex ea turri, quae circum essent opera, tueri se posse confisi sunt, musculum pedes LX longum ex turrim murumque perducerent, facere instituerunt cuius musculi haec erat forma. Duae primum trabes in solo aeque longae distantes inter se pedes IIII collocantur, inque eis columellae pedum in altitudinem V defiguntur. Has inter se capreolis molli fastigio coniungunt, ubi tigna, quae musculi tegendi causa ponant, collocentur. Eo super tigna bipedalia iniciunt eaque laminis clabisque religant. Ad extremum musculi tectum trabesque extremas quadratas regulas IIII patentes digitos difigunt, quae lateres, qui super musculo struantur, contineant. Ita fastigato atque ordinatim structo, ut trabes erant in capreolis collocatae. lateribus lutoque musculus, ut ab igni, qui ex muro iaceretur, tutus esset, contegitus. Super lateres coria inducuuntur, ne canalibus aqua immissa lateres diluere posset. Coria autem, ne rursus igni ac laidibus corrumpantur, centonibus conteguntur. Hoc opus omne tectum vineis ad ipsam turrim perficiunt subitoque inoopinantibus hostibus machinatione navali, phalangis subiectis, ad turrim hostium admovent, ut aedificio iungatur.

Quo malo perterriti subito oppiindani saxa quam maxima possunt vectibus promovent praecipitataque muro in musculum devolvunt. Ictum firmitas materiae sustinet, et quicquid incidit fastigio musculi elabitur. Id ubi vident, mutant consilium: cupas taeda ac pice refertas incendunt easque de muro musculum devolvunt. Involutae labuntur, delapsae ab lateribus longuriis furcisque abopere removentur. Interim sub musculo milites vectibus infima saxa turris hostium, quibus fundamenta continebantur convellunt. Musculus ex turri latericia a nostris telis tormentisque defenditur; hostes ex muro  ac turribus submoventur: non datur libera muro defendendi facultas. Compluribus iam lapidibus ex ea, quae suberat, turri subductis repentina ruina pars eius turrisconcidit, pars reliqua consequens procumbebat: cum hostes urbis direptione perterriti inermes cum infulis se porta foras universi proripiunt, ad legatos atque exercitum supplices manus tendunt.

[[Category:Latin]]</text>
      <sha1>2o24qjkt19c0ehga18lmiv2zgfmzlro</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Latin/Lesson 3-Translation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1154</id>
    <revision>
      <id>819201</id>
      <parentid>518260</parentid>
      <timestamp>2007-04-04T19:06:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Asv</username>
        <id>55495</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[Latin/Lesson 30]] moved to [[Latin/Lesson 3-Translation]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Latin}}

For your pleasure, I present to you a selection of poems from Catullus. 

Tips for translation: soon.

 &lt;B&gt;Excercise 1&lt;/b&gt;

 Skill: Reading Latin poetry
 
 I
 
 Cui dono lepidum novum libellum
 arido modo pumice expolitum?
 Corneli, tibi : namque tu solebas
 meas esse aliquid putare nugas,
 iam tum cum ausus es unus Italorum
 omne aevum tribus explicare chartis
 doctis, Juppiter, et laboriosis.
 quare habe tibi quicquid hoc libelli,
 qualecumque, quod, o patrona virgo,
 plus uno maneat perenne seclo.
 
 &lt;B&gt;Exercise 2&lt;/B&gt;
 
 Skill: Reading Latin poetry
 
 V
 
 Vivamus, mea Lesbia, atque amemus
 rumoresque senum severiorum
 omnes unius aestimemus assis.
 soles occidere et redire possunt.
 nobis, cum semel occidit brevis lux
 nox est perpetua una dormienda.
 da mi basia mille, deinde centum,
 dein mille altera, dein secunda centum
 deinde usque altera mille, deinde centum;
 dein, cum milia multa fecerimus
 conturbabimus illa, ne sciamus,
 aut nequis malus invidere possit,
 cum tantum sciat esse basiorum.
 
 &lt;B&gt;Exercise 3&lt;/B&gt;
 
 Skill: Reading Latin poetry
 
 XVI
 
 Pedicabo ego vos et irrumabo,
 Aureli pathice et cinaede Furi,
 qui me ex versiculis meis putastis,
 quod sunt molliculi, parum pudicum,
 nam castum esse decet pium poetam
 ipsum, versiculos nihil necessest.
 qui tum denique habent salem ac leporem.
 si sunt molliculi ac parum pudici
 et quod pruriat incitare possunt,
 non dico pueris, sed hi s pilosis,
 qui duros nequeunt moveere lumbos.
 vos, quod milia multa basiorum
 legistis, male me marem putatis?
 pedicabo ego vos et irrumabo.
 
 &lt;B&gt;Exercise 4&lt;/B&gt;
 
 Skill: Reading Latin poetry
 
 XCVII
 
 Non (ita me di ament) quicquam referre putavi,
 utrumne os an culum olgacerem Aemilio.
 nilo mundius hoc, niloque immundior ille,
 verum etiam culus mundior et melior,
 nam sine dentibus est: os dentis sesquipedalis,
 gingivas, vero ploxeni habet veteris,
 praeterea rictum qualem diffissus in aestu
 meientis mulae cunnus habere solet.
 hic futuit multas et se facit esse venustum,
 et non pistrino traditur atque asino?
 quem siqua attingit, non illam posse putemus
 aegroti culum lingere carnificis?

[[Category:Latin]]</text>
      <sha1>kxuqobzppm5jtf51iykv1n3zdu2nsf8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:US History/Early Colonial Period</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1166</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1713855</id>
      <parentid>950724</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-02-07T04:11:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adrignola</username>
        <id>169232</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>moved [[Talk:US History/Contents/Early Colonial Period]] to [[Talk:US History/Early Colonial Period]]: Making navigation easier by eliminating &quot;/Contents/&quot; in paths.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">==Aztecs and Incas in the area which is now US???==

:No, but they deserve mention. This chapter is pre-Jamestown, not much is happening in NA. Also you should have a clear idea of what's happening in other areas of the new world and europe, for perspective. There might even be a sub-chapter devoted to european history at this time, because it's so important in the formation of the US. [[User:Etothex|Etothex]] 01:46, 14 Sep 2003 (UTC)

Not much happening! Remember that there were Spanish settlements in New Mexico (often confused with Mexico, but it was occupied by U.S. forces and clained by the U.S. in 1848) by 1598 under the leadership of Don Juan de Oñate, a few years before Jamestown was settled.  Also long before that, the Chaconian culture which lead to the Pueblo Culture was in the Southwest as well.  The Aztec and other cultures of the Valley of Mexico traded with the Chaconians, and they may have lived in the Southwest (Atzlan)  before their journey to the valley of Mexico, but other than that they weren't part of U.S. History.
[[User:Cybergata|Cybergata]]

==Henry VIII and the Church of England==

I am not sure I like the section here.  The Anglican church was intended as a Catholic church that the King rather than Pope controlled. It was not intended to incorporate any of the protestant doctrines around at the time.  I have not edited this as I am unsure as to what extent and when the Anglican church (C of E) became protestant (or viewed itself as such) thereafter.
:Having found out more after I entered the above message I have edited it [[User:Dainamo|Dainamo]] 23:38, 4 Nov 2004 (UTC)

==Colombus is too brief==
One of the great failures of the American education system is to make Colombus, a man who slaughtered the native people of the US out of greed for gold, look like a hero. By not mentioning his habit of massacring natives, this book simply repeats the problem it should seek to solve. After all, is this not supposed to be a NPOV book? -- [[User talk:LGagnon|LGagnon]] 03:06, 4 September 2006 (UTC)

== Review Questions ==

I've just added six questions at the end of the chapter to reinforce the material. I hope they help all prospective readers (and test-takers).

--[[User:Ccny930|Ccny930]] 23:28, 28 October 2006 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>mcfmg810gh8hf41udv8k4lyncmjirct</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>GCSE Science/Parallel and series circuits</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1169</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2611925</id>
      <parentid>2611924</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-02-25T20:59:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>62.255.240.28</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Formula for resistance of two resistors in series */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">[[GCSE Science/Electricity]]
----
You will have already studied series and parallel circuits before, so should be familiar with what a series and parallel circuit is and their basic properties.But in this module we will be looking at them in a little more detail. We will apply Ohm's law to see how we can work out the resistance of a whole circuit that is made up of a large number of components. Before we begin You might want to try some revision questions. Follow the link then come back here when you are finished.
 [[GCSE Science/Parallel and series circuits revision questions]].

==Resistors in Series Circuits==
As we know, 'in a series circuit the current in all parts of the circuit is the same and the current has a one way system'''. The current depends on the applied voltage and the number of and nature of other components in the circuit. 

Consider two resistors in a series circuit with a battery. As you might expect the total resistance in this circuit is higher than the resistance of each resistor, because the battery has to &quot;push&quot; the charge through both resistors one after the other. So the total potential difference of the supply is &quot;shared&quot; between the two resistors.

[[Image:2_resistors_in_series.png]]

Think about what is happening to the current as it flows around the circuit. There are no branches, nowhere for the electric current to escape to, so obviously the same current must flow through both resistors. Let's call this current I.

The total resistance for the whole circuit is very simple. It's just R&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; plus R&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. 

=== Formula for resistance of two resistors in series ===
R&lt;sub&gt;Total&lt;/sub&gt; = R&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; + R&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;

'''The total resistance in a series circuit is the sum of the resistances of all the components.'''

Using this formula we can calculate the voltage across each resistor.
But it could depend on how many resistors there are.

===Example: Calculating voltages in a series circuit===

&lt;u&gt;Question:&lt;/u&gt;

Suppose R&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; = 1&amp;Omega; and R&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;= 4&amp;Omega;. If the battery supplies 2.5 Volts what is the voltage across each resistor.

'''Answer:'''

First use the total resistance of the circuit to work out how much current is flowing through the circuit.

Step 1: Work out the total resistance

*identify formula:         R&lt;sub&gt;Total&lt;/sub&gt; = R&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; + R&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;
*insert numbers and units   R&lt;sub&gt;Total&lt;/sub&gt; = 1&amp;Omega; + 4&amp;Omega; = 5&amp;Omega;

Step 2: Use Ohms's law to calculate the current in the circuit. Decide which resistance to use.

*identify formula(using the triangle):         I = V / R (Ohms's law)
*decide which resistance to use:                Use R&lt;sub&gt;Total&lt;/sub&gt;; so formula becomes I = V / R&lt;sub&gt;Total&lt;/sub&gt;
*insert numbers and units                       I amps = 2.5V / 5&amp;Omega; = 0.5A

Now we know how much current is flowing through both resistors, we can work out the voltage across each resistor.

Step 3: Use Ohm's law to calculate the voltage across '''each''' resistor:

*identify formula(using the triangle):         V = I x R
*insert numbers for resistor 1:                 V&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; volts = 0.5A x 1&amp;Omega; = '''0.5 Volts'''
*insert numbers for resistor 2:                 V&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; volts = 0.5A x 4&amp;Omega; = '''2.0 Volts'''

===Practice questions===
*'''Q1)'''Let R&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; = 2&amp;Omega;, R&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;= 3&amp;Omega;, and V=5V what is the voltage across R&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; and R&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; ?
*'''Q2''')Let R&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; = 3&amp;Omega;, R&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;= 3&amp;Omega;, and V=6V what is the voltage across R&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; and R&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; ?
*'''Q3)'''Let R&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; = 2&amp;Omega;,  V=5V  and I= 1A what is the value of resistor R&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; ?

==Resistors in Parallel Circuits==
[[Image:2_resistors_in_parallel.png ]]

Parallel circuits are a bit more complicated than series circuits, because they contain a branch - the electric current will take more than one route. Look at the diagram. At point X the current splits into 2 paths, and flows through both resistor R&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; and resistor R&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. It may not split in equal amounts.
When several(two or more) components are connected in parallel branches, '''the voltage (potential difference) across each parallel branch is the same'''. And this is the same as the voltage across the battery.

The current through each component is the same as if it were the only component present. '''So the total current flowing through the battery is the sum of the currents flowing through each branch.''' Here is the '''formula for the currents flowing through a parallel circuit.''' 

I&lt;sub&gt;Main&lt;/sub&gt; = I&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; + I&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;

Because the voltage is the same for all branches, the branch with the lowest resistance has the highest current flowing through it.
Because there are more paths for the charge to flow along, '''the total resistance is less than either of the two paths on their own.''' And therefore (with the same battery) the current is bigger.

To find out the resistance of the whole circuit , we can't just add together the resistors as we did in the series circuit, we have to apply Ohm's law to each branch of the circuit.

Imagine we replaced the resistors with bulbs. You should now be able to answer the following questions from your previous knowledge.

*'''Q4)'''You disconnect one of the bulbs, does the other stay lit?
*'''Q5)'''You reconnect the disconnected bulb, does the other dim or brighten?
*'''Q6)'''Would it be reasonable to say &quot;each branch of the circuit behaves as if the other branch weren't there&quot; ?

If you answered the above questions correctly you should find this next section easy!
===Example: Calculating the resistance of several resistors in parallel===
It's best to break the process down into a number of simple steps. Some books may give you a formula to use, but you shouldn't use any formula without understanding where it comes from (otherwise you are likely to remember it incorrectly or apply it inappropriately).By using a simple step by step method instead you can get a feel for why it works, and you will be far less likely to make a mistake in the exam.

'''Step1''' considering each branch on its own, as if the other branch didn't exist use Ohm's law to work out the current flowing through each branch.

'''Step 2''' Add the currents together to find out the total amount of current flowing through the whole circuit.

'''Step 3''' Apply Ohm's law again to work out the total resistance of the circuit.

===Example===
Suppose V=2V R&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; = 1&amp;Omega; and R&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;= 1&amp;Omega;. 

Applying Ohm's law to the branch containing R&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; gives

I&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;=V/R&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; =2/1 =2A 

Applying Ohm's law to the branch containing R&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; gives
I&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;=V/R&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; =2/1 =2A

Total current = I&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;+I&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;  = 4A

Applying Ohm's law again, to the whole circuit.

R&lt;sub&gt;Total&lt;/sub&gt; =V/I&lt;sub&gt;total&lt;/sub&gt; = 2/4 =0.5&amp;Omega;

Notice that the resistance of the whole circuit is ''lower'' than the resistance of either branch!

===Practice questions===
*'''Q7)''' Calculate the resistance of the above pair of resistors ''if'' they had been in ''series'' rather than parallel.
*'''Q8)''' A parallel circuit has two resistors, one is 2&amp;Omega; the other is 3&amp;Omega;. The voltage is 6V. What is the total resistance of the circuit?
*'''Q9)''' Three resistors are in parallel (three separate branches) their resistances are 2&amp;Omega;, 2&amp;Omega; and 3&amp;Omega;. The voltage is 6V. What is the resistance of the circuit?


{| bgcolor=&quot;ffeeaa&quot;
|-
| '''Summary'''
|-
| ''Series Circuits'' The current through each component is the same. To find the total resistance just add the individual ones up. The total voltage is the sum of the voltages across the individual components.
|-
| ''Parallel Circuits'' Each branch acts as if the other branches were not there. The Voltage across each branch is the same. Ohm's law can be applied to each branch separately. The total current, is just the sum of the currents through each branch.
|}


----

[[GCSE Science/Parallel and series circuits answers|Answers]] | [[GCSE Science/Three useful components|Three useful components&gt;&gt;]]

{{BookCat}}</text>
      <sha1>8yj4yeig26oyp7qhripzjz31uxrmf0z</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Spanish/Exercises/Personal Pronouns - Solutions</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1170</id>
    <revision>
      <id>616056</id>
      <parentid>532379</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-10-18T04:14:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Guanabot</username>
        <id>5478</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>User-controlled Bot: table syntax updated</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">Soluciones a los [[Spanish/Exercises/Personal_Pronouns|ejercicios]].&lt;br&gt;
''(Solutions to the [[Spanish/Exercises/Personal_Pronouns|exercises]])''

--------

Pronombres personales.&lt;br&gt;
''(Personal pronouns.)''


Ejercicio 1.&lt;br&gt;
Rellena los espacios en blanco con los pronombres personales correctos en español.

''Exercise 1.''&lt;br&gt;
''Fill the blank spaces with the correct Spanish personal pronous.''



{|  border=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot;
|-
|  
Inglés:                      
|
Español
|-
|
''English:''
|
''Spanish:''
|-
| -- || --
|-
|
'''I'''     am        
|
'''Yo'''         soy 
|-
|
'''You'''   are           
|
'''Tú'''   eres
|-
|
'''He'''    is
|  
'''Él'''   es
|-
|
'''She'''   is
|  
'''Ella'''     es
|-
|
'''We'''    are
|  
'''Nosotros'''    somos
|-
|
'''You'''   are
|  
'''Tú'''    eres (singular)              
'''Vosotros'''    sois (plural)
|-
|
'''They'''  are
|  
'''Ellos'''       son
|}


Ejercicio 2.&lt;br&gt;
Rellena los espacios en blanco con los pronombres personales correctos en español.

''Exercise 2.''&lt;br&gt;
''Fill the blank spaces with the correct Spanish personal pronouns.''




{|  border=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot;
|-
|  
Inglés:                      
|
Español
|-
|
''English:''
|
''Spanish:''
|-
| -- || --
|-
|
'''You'''  are                   
|
'''Vosotros'''    estáis
|-
|
'''He'''   is                   
|
'''Él'''     está
|-
|
'''You'''  are                   
|  
'''Tú'''         estás
|-
|
'''I'''    am 	           
|  
'''Yo'''      estoy
|-
|
'''They''' are                   
|  
'''Ellos'''     están
|-
|
'''We'''   are                   
|  
'''Nosotros'''     estamos
|-
|
'''She'''  is                    
|  
'''Ella'''    está
|}

----------------------------------------
[[Spanish/Exercises/Personal_Pronouns|Enlace a los Ejercicios]] ''Link to exercises''


[[Spanish/Lesson_1|Enlace a la lección 1]] ''Link to Lesson 1.''

[[Category:Spanish]]</text>
      <sha1>jz6sq78vcla7jtk8lal60vhalhwa7g9</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>